本字幕由志愿者义务贡献，采用许可协议
知识共享 署名-非商业性使用-相同方式共享 3.0 美国
Stanford University. >> All right,
>> 斯坦福大学 >> 好
well, welcome to lecture number 14 of Stanford CS193P,
欢迎来到斯坦福 CS193P 的第十四节课
fall of 2017, 18. So, I'm going to finish off the thing
现在是 2017-18 年秋季学期
we had about the documents last time, I was hoping to
have finished that last time. So we're kind of rushed for
time this time, especially since we're gonna get kicked
out again for a midterm right after. And then I'm gonna
launch into a long demo that's gonna basically demonstrate
all of the stuff we talked about on Monday.
All right, so we did all that stuff on Monday so that we
could easily take whatever our document-based app is,
and store it in a document. We went all the way through
having UIDocument write things out to the file system.
Now we're gonna add a really cool layer of UI in the front
of that, so that users can pick the documents they want.
Rename them, move them around, all that right inside your
app. And the UI for this, as you can see the screenshot of,
looks a lot like the files app in iOS 11. In fact,
the files app in iOS 11 is probably just a very thin
layer on top of this UI, or this API,
the UIDocumentBrowserViewControl-
ler. So how does this thing work,
this view controller? Well, the most important thing to
understand is that it's just a view controller, but
it's always the root view controller of
your application. So in other words, in your storyboard,
it's always got the little arrow that points to it. And
when you run your app,
it's gonna be the view controller users see first.
Then they'll pick whatever document they want, and
then your UI will take over.
Your view controller will come up in front of this one,
do whatever it does to show your document. All right, so
that's the fundamental architecture of this thing.
And one thing that's important to tell this little document
browser view controller is what types of files you open,
and you do that on your project settings. So
if you go to project settings underneath the info tab,
you gotta select your target, not the project, but
the target. Go to the info tab, and then inside there,
there's a little section there called document types.
Well, that's the types of documents you open, and
you just fill out this.
You can have multiple types when you fill out this little
form, like that one. In here, for example,
I've shown how to have JSON files be a kind of file that
you open, and it's pretty straightforward there.
The little things at the bottom there, the BundleType
and the HandleRank, are basically just saying, well,
is this like a primary type of file that you open?
Are you the owner of this type of file, or is it just some
other type that you can, that you know how to open,
etc. Now, you can have your own document type,
for example, for emojiart,
I'm not gonna get to it today because of time constraints.
But emojiart really wants to have its own document type,
.emojiart or something like that. And you set that up in
the section right below the document types,
called exported UTIs, UTI stands for Universal Type and
Identifier. And you can invent your own UTI,
as long as it's a nice, unique name.
Like here, I've used the name edu.stanford.cs193p.emojiart,
that's very likely to be a unique type identifier.
I just have to specify a couple of things,
most notably at the bottom there,
the file name extension that goes with an emoji art,
I picked emojiart, .emojiart. And then once you set this up,
you can go back up to the document types one at the top,
and add this as a document type that you open.
Just like that, and yeah, and I explained the UTI there.
Now we, you know, from the start of this class,
we always picked single view app as the type of app that we
opened. But we're actually, for document based apps,
we're going to use an Xcode template.
It doesn't really give us much in that template,
but it gives enough that it's worth doing.
So if you're gonna do a document based app,
I recommend going back and creating a new app,
a new project, using this as the template. And in fact,
I'm gonna do that in the demo, even though we're, you know,
80% of the way through emojiart,
I'm still gonna go back and
create a new emojiart with this, and
then just move my files over.
Because I want the things that come with the template, and
let's talk about what's in that template.
One thing is that it stubs out that
document types, and it doesn't do JSON files.
It does image files, but you can change it to JSON files or
add more types. It also puts an entry in your
Info.plist which is very important,
called Supports Document Browser. And that's basically
just saying that the documents that are stored inside
your app sandbox are like real documents that people would
wanna open with like the files app or something like that. So
that's an important entry to put in your Info.plist,
we're actually going to put that into the demo manually,
just to emphasize it.
It has one method in AppDelegate, you know,
AppDelegate's that file that we're always moving out of
the way, into supporting files. So it has one method in
there that allows other apps, like the files app,
to ask your app to open your documents. And it's a very
simple little method, we're not really gonna look at it
today, but this template does throw that in there for you.
It also stubs out a subclass of UIDocument, which you
usually don't need, cuz you've already created that yourself.
And it also stubs out an MVC to show the document,
just this really dumb MVC. And you don't need that, usually,
either, because you obviously have an MVC that shows your
document, or you wouldn't be writing this app. And finally,
it gives a subclass of UIDocumentBrowserViewControl-
ler, which serves as its own delegate.
It just has like five methods in it that are really simple,
and we're gonna go over those in detail. So
after you create a project with this template,
what do you need to do to get your app working? Well, one,
you've gotta have your own UIDocument subclass, of
course. Two, you've gotta have your own document-viewing MVC,
right? Like EmojiArtViewController,
or your ImageGalleryViewController,
whatever from your homework. Then you have to add
a little bit of code to this UIDocumentBrowserViewContro-
ller subclass that comes with the template. In its
viewDidLoad, you're gonna configure it a little bit,
it has a couple of bars you can set,
we'll talk about that. You're also going to have to provide
the URL of a blank document. And
this is so that when the user goes into the UI and
says, create a new document, you've got, it's gotta
copy some template, some blank version of your document,
to be that new document. So you just have to give the URL
of a blank document, so that you support document creation.
And then finally, the code you have to put in there is,
when someone wants to open one of your documents, you have to
write the code to put in MVC onscreen. And you don't do it
with segueing, so we're gonna learn a little bit new way to
put an MVC on screen that does not involve segues. And
the last thing you wanna do to the template, of course,
is update those types, the document types to be,
not be imaged, but to be JSON or emojiart type or
image gallery type for your homework, or whatever. So
those are the only four things you do, once you do those four
simple things, you'll get this full UI. So steps one and
two, you've probably already done in your app.
Step three looks like this, this is viewDidLoad of
the UIDocumentBrowser ViewController's subclass.
And you really have to the first thing,
which is set it as its own delegate.
Because it actually implements a lot of these opening
file methods and stuff using its own delegate methods.
Then you can have some things like, allowsDocumentCreation =
true. Do you allow people to create documents in your app,
or are you just a document viewer? Do you allow multiple
items to be picked, in other words, can the user go in and
like Shift + click, or whatever the equivalent is,
with the touch interface, to choose multiple items and
open them at once? Like Emoji Art can't do that,
it can only show one document at a time.
Then you can also tweak the look of the UI a little bit.
Change the colors, tint colors,
things like that, to try and match your document controller
when it comes up to have the same kinda look.
So that's it, that's how you configure it in viewDidLoad,
that's mostly the settings that you can set.
And then you have to provide this template URL, you do it
kind in a weird way. There's this method, DocumentBrowser
didRequestDocumentCreationWit- hHandler. That's the method
that's saying, somebody wants to create a document of your
type in your app. What do you got to give me is a URL
to a template, to a blank. And the way it makes you
do that is it hands you a little function called
the importHandler. There it's called,
I guess I called it Handler to make it shorter.
But it's actually called importHandler and
it just takes a URL which is the URL of a blank document.
And then the import mode which is either copy this or
move it to create a new document. So, it would be move
if you created this thing every time this got called.
It's copy if you create it once and then you hand it
out every time someone says new document.
And that's it, all you have to do is call that handler,
super simple, you'll see that in the demo. Next, you have to
present your document MVC, so we have to take a little time
out and go to an aside and learn something different
which is how to put MVC on screen without segueing. So
how do we do that? It's quite easy. There's a method
in UIViewController called present animated.
You send it to yourself, if you're a ViewController, and
you give it an argument of another MVC, and it
presents it animated. And it presents it on screen modally,
which means it takes over the entire screen. Okay and
just owns the entire screen until it dismisses itself,
then it's back to you. Which is exactly what we want here.
So, the trick here though is how do I get a new MVC
I told you actually earlier that iOS has a few MVCs like
to present? And
the camera take, picture taking MVC and somethings.
So it has some, but what if you have one of your own?
Okay well, it's really easy actually. You just put it in
your storyboard, it won't have any segues drawn to it,
but what you're going to do is name it. You're just going to
select it, go to your identity inspector, there's a little
storyboard ID in there, you give it a name and
then you use that name in your code like this. You get
an instance of your storyboard which you get by saying
UIStoryboard name. You that our storyboard has always been
called Main.storyboard. But we haven't talked about the fact
that you can actually have multiple storyboards,
probably legal. We always just have that main. And
bundle is almost nil there, cuz you got your main bundle,
and nil means your main bundle. So
you get the storyboard, and then you ask
the storyboard to make you an MVC with that name by saying
instantiateViewControllerWith- Identifer.
And that foo that you have there is the thing
that's in my identity inspector for that MVC for
the controller, top level controller of that MVC. And
that's it, now you just prepared that thing.
In this case, you know by setting its document and
then you just present it. So it's really, really easy and
instantiateViewControllerWith- Identifier is the key method
that you need without a storyboard.
All right, so back to our present. So we need to be able
to write a function that presents it. And it's really
simple, we're just gonna get our storyboard, we're gonna
instantiate our ViewController from the storyboard.
Now, really importantly we're gonna set the document
of the document showing MVC that we just got
out of the storyboard, we're gonna set it to be a new
document with URL that's passed to us, because it's
presentDocument at url. Now this might be a new document,
it just created by copying that template or
it might be some document we're opening
that was created in the past. You don't know and
you don't care here. And then you just called present
of that document MVC. That's it,
if you do all that, then it just will all work. Of course,
you wanna set the types that you do, JSON, Emoji Art,
whatever. And we're gonna see all of this happening
in Emoji Art. So let's jump right into the demo and
do this in Emoji Art. Now, Emoji Art is an obvious app
to want to turn into a document based app. Because
building these beautiful works of art with emoji, right?
And we certainly might want to do multiple of them, not just
have to constantly be working on the same one. So there's
something about our MVC, our EmojiArtViewController.
The view controller that shows our Emoji Art document.
It has no model, right? We have no model in this thing.
It's just all view. All the EmojiArtView especially. So
I'm going to add another section here at the top
to put my model. I'm going to put this in my Model section
right here. Everyone remember that these marks that you put,
that causes it so
that when you go up here to the top, you can,
these are like in sections. You see the sections there?
So I've added a new one up here, Model. And
you can click on them to jump to the different sections. So
my Model, it wants to be some sort of var, I'll call it
emojiArt. And it's gonna be of some type, like EmojiArt.
This type doesn't exist, but that's kind of what my model
wants to be. So, let's invent a struct here, or class or
struct, that represents an Emoji Art document.
Well, what's in an Emoji Art document?
There's the URL in the background and
then there's all those emojis, what they are, and
where they are, and how big they are, right?
That's what an Emoji Art document looks like. So,
let's go create a model to do exactly that.
So I'm going to create a new file, just a model file.
So we're over here in Swift, not over here at Cocoa Touch,
we're over here with Swift File. I'm going to call it
Emoji Art. Makes perfect sense to call it that. Here it is,
I'm going to type it in really fast. There it is.
And so here it is. Makes perfect sense what it is,
right? URL, that's for the background, then an array
of these EmojiInfos which is this thing. And each EmojiInfo
is its position, x and y, the text that's like a bike or
the bee, or whatever the string is, and then the size,
which I'm gonna have be the font size. Notice I've made
these Ints instead of CG floats or whatever because
this is a model okay this is not a UI thing, it's our
model. So these could be Ints or they could be doubles but
I decided I want Ints because I want my JSON to look nice
and not have a lot of fractional numbers and
all that stuff, so I decided to make them into Ints.
And that's it, this fully represents an Emoji Art
document this is just initializer that initializes
those two things. Nothing else to it but this, all right.
Now let's think about our EmojiArtViewController back
here. What does it need to be able to interact with
the model? Well, it needs all those little UI labels that
are in its EmojiArtView. No problem. We can get those.
We're the controller. We can talk to our view and
get anything we want from it. But it also needs the URL and
currently we actually don't keep the URL for
the background image.
Let's go scroll down to where we get that image,
it's right at the bottom here. When we drop an image, and
you can see our image fetcher goes off and fetches
that url and image. But then we only use the image.
We don't use the URL. So, we're gonna start doing that.
And I'm gonna do it in a way just to show you
a little bit more kind of Swift program, which is
I'm gonna make this var, which is currently a UIImage,
be a tuple. And why would I make this a tuple? Well,
I'm gonna make it a tuple because I want the URL and
the image to always be set together. I would never want
to accidentally set the image and have the URL be different.
So I'm gonna always set them together. So I'm gonna change
this from being a UIImage to being a tuple.
So let's go find out where it's declared,
here it is. It's currently a UIImage,
I'm gonna change it to be a tuple that has a URL and
an image as part of the tuple. And of course,
changing this thing's type is gonna require me to change its
implementation a little bit. Like all these new values down
here aren't UIImages anymore, they're this tuple, so
we gotta say newValue.image when I want the image. And of
course when I'm returning it I can't just return the image
here I after return the tuple with some URL of some sort and
that UIImage and what URL am I gonna return. Well,
I'm gonna actually have to store that,
so I'm gonna make a little private var.
I'm gonna call emojiArtBackgroundImageURL,
which is gonna be URL. And I'm gonna store it in there. Now,
I'm not gonna wanna set it from here,
I'm gonna always want to set it from here,
but I'm just gonna be using this as storage.
Some people might put an under bar in front of this here to
kind of emphasize, that this is background storage.
We're not gonna ever set this directly.
We set the URL here, so it's always set The same so
I'm gonna leave it under bar there too.
So this URL here then is this one.
So I'm just gonna return this URL. And of course when I set,
I need to set the URL to be this new values URL. Okay so
now I'm capturing the URL all the time,
I always have the URL anytime I have an image. That's good,
I need it for my model. Now let's talk about the model
here, we could have this model just stored like this and
then have some other functions that like go and
look at all of our UI labels and grab the URL and
build an emojiArt, but you know,
I'm gonna do something fun. Watch this,
I'm gonna make this
a computed property
be a perfect match
with my UI. And that is a really
good thing to have in a controller is the model and
the UI always in sync. So, that's why I'm gonna do this.
And I think it'll work out nicely here. All right, so
what do I need to do get my model? I gotta return the URL,
and I gotta return all those little emoji infos, right?
I'm eventually gonna have to return some emoji art by
calling its initializer, url with some url, and the emojis
with some emojis. So we need these two vars to be created.
Well, the URL is really easy,
I'm just gonna say if I get let url = my
emojiArtBackgroundImage. URL that's it's URL.
If I can do that then I'm ready to return something
here. By the way if I can't do that then I'm going to return
Nil because for me my emoji art is not really
well defined if it doesn't have a background. It doesn't
really make sense to have emoji art where there's like
a bee and a bike on a plain background,
we don't really support that. So I'm just going to say,
if you ask for my model and I don't have a URL yet,
then I'm just going to say I don't have a model yet.
I'm not been created enough to say that I have one. So
that fixes the URL. How about this emojis thing right here?
We have to set this emojis var right here, so I'm just gonna
say, let emojis =. And essentially what I wanna do
here is go ask my emojiArtView for all its subviews.
But I really don't want all of them, I just want the ones
that I can get as a UILabel. I'm using map here, you
all know map. So this returned in array fo UI labels.
The only thing about this is, this might return nil. So
I actually want to use a different map called flat Map.
So flat Map is just like map, is just if the little function
returns nil it ignores it. So it flats it down not to have
the nil ones, all right. So now I have all my UI labels.
Now I need to turn this into an array of these
emojiinfos. All right because that's what I'm doing, I'm
returning my model. So how the heck am I going to do that?
I'm definitely going to need a function that takes a UI label
and returns one of these emojiinfos.
You know what I'm gonna do,
I'm actually gonna do that by writing an extension
to this struck. And I'm gonna put that extension
over here in my controller because that extension
is gonna take a UI label as an argument and
return an emoji info as the value.
And that UI label is a UI thing so that can not be in my
model. But it can be in my controller, and
this is my controller. And some people say, well,
wait a second. If you put an extension here to EmojiInfo,
you've just added UI to your model.
No, this is my controller. Not my model,
the fact that my controller is implementing this with makes
extension, this extension lives in my controller so
that is perfectly legal to do and you'll see IOS do that
where you have something like NS attributed string,
which is actually in foundation, I think.
But, when you start adding attributes like fonts and so
like that now becomes UI thing,
all that stuff is implemented the UI kit. By extension,
in NSAttributeString. We're doing the same thing here. So
I decided to do this, instead of with a function,
I actually add an extension that adds a new initializer
to EmojiInfo. Initializes it with a label, and if I can
get the attributedText out of there and get its font,
then I can make myself an EmojiInfo. If I can't,
I'm gonna return nil, so this is failable initializer,
this is how you fail out of a failable initializer. So,
now that I can do that so easily,
I'm just gonna take this array of UI labels right here, and
I'm going to flat map that. And the thing here I'm gonna
say is return an EmojiArt.EmoliInfo
using my nice new label initializer. And
remember that $0 right here is these UI labels. You got that?
It's kinda cool. All right, so that's our emoji has.
That is creating out EmojiArt, that's it. That's all we need
to do to get our model. How about the set side of it?
Well ,the first thing I wanna do when someone sets a new
EmojiArt is clear out what I've already got in there.
So I'm gonna set my EmojiArt Background image to nil,
it's a tuple, remember? And
I'm gonna set all of my emojiArtview.subviews, but
actually only the ones that are labels.
I'm gonna send a message to all of them for
each to remove themselves from their Superview.
Okay so I'm just taking all the labels in there and
removing them because somebody set a new model so I'm
clearing everything out here. As question mark, there we go.
So now I cleared everything out, now I need to put
this new thing in. Well, to put the URL in,
I'm gonna need to fetch it. So let's fetch it,
here is how I fetch right, here is my image fetcher,
doing the same thing, I did when some thing was dropped.
I'm gonna do this back on the main cube because now I'm
gonna update my UI with this URL when it came back. So
what am I gonna do when this thing comes back?
First of all, I got to set my background image. So
I'm gonna set my image, oops, my emoji Emoji art
image background equal to the URL and image that came back,
again this is a tuple. I'm setting it from here, coming
back from the ImageFetcher. And now I need to
add all those labels for all the emoji, right. The bees and
the bikes and everything that I've dragged down,
I've got to put all of those in there, so let's do that.
Probably the easiest way to do that, kinda conceptually,
I'm gonna take this new value of the emoji art,
and look through all of its emojis.
And for each of them, I kinda wanna just ask my
emojiArtView, to add a label
with the right arguments, whatever for each one, right?
This is conceptually what I wanna do. Well, actually,
I have add label in my emoji art view, but I made it
private. So I'm gonna go over to my emoji art view and make
that public. And remember that I'm the controller over there.
I can call anything I want in my view. My view can't call
anything at me without that blind structure communication,
but I can call anything I want in it.
So in here, we have label and
it looks like it wants an attributed string and
the point. That makes sense, so let's go back over here and
do that. So, the attributed Text,
is that what they called it? We want some attributed, no,
it's just with, I think, with attributed,
yeah. Attributed text, and centeredAt, actually,
I already know centeredAt. centeredAt is just a CG
point with the X being this $0.x.
And the y is this $0.y.
Because $0 is each of these emojis, so it's in EmojiInfo.
EmojiInfo, just to remind you, is this thing, so
the x and y, this is the x and y position. Now I need to deal
with the text and the size, so let's do that.
And we do that by letting that attributedText argument equals
the text converted to an attributed string. I actually
have this nice little function I wrote in utilities called
attributedString(withTextSty- le). And so
I'm gonna make it .body font, of a certain size,
which is a CGFloat of the $0's size. So there we've set and
if now someone sets our model, boom! We've set everything.
Our UIs should match. Now we're in great shape,
because we've got an MVC here. Which has a model that we can
set and get that makes our UI work and all we need to do is
make it persistent. Make it store on disk. And we're gonna
make it persistent by having this EmojiArt thing here
become codable, and be able to turn itself into a JSON.
And then we're gonna use JSON as our file format. So
let's go back to EmojiArt over here, and
make this thing generate JSON. And
we're gonna do that by just saying that it is Codable. And
when we put Codable on there, and we recompile.
We're gonna see if there's any problems with this and
see whether it is codable or not. So let's find out, and
it says it's not. It says it doesn't implement decodable
and encodable, which are the two protocols in this Codable
protocol, why not? This is codable, an array is codable,
no, this type is not codable, well,
no problem, colon, Codable. We made that Codable, and now,
we'll let this thing recompile, and the error went
away, look at that, we just made EmojiArt codable.
And this is what I was telling you about, this codable stuff,
the new kind of archiving is so easy.
Because you don't need to do all of that inits, and decode,
and encode, and all of that stuff. For 90% of all structs,
it'll just do it for you. Now, again,
our JSON keys are gonna be the same as our variable names.
When we do the JSON, which is good, in this case,
cuz they're all nice enough. But
we could change it by adding that private enum coding keys,
colon string, remember that?
So I, we're not going to, but, but we could do that.
All right, now, how about the JSON?
How do we get the JSON version of this? Well,
I'm actually gonna add a var to this EmojiArt called json.
And it returns a Data, optional, it's possible,
I guess, we might not be able to turn ourselves into JSON.
But I think 100% we would, but
I'll make it a Data just be clear. And I'm just going to
create a JSON out of myself by returning, trying
to use a JSONEncoder to encode my, self, and that's it.
That's either gonna return a data of myself, a JSON, or
nil if it couldn't do it, now this is never gonna
fail. I'm so confident this is never gonna fail, I could even
do try exclamation point right there and
not make that an optional.
Cuz these types are all 100% encodable. But
I'll do this just to kind of be correct programming.
So now we have a way to turn this thing into EmojiArt.
So let's add a little bit of UI to our EmojiArt to have
a button I'm gonna call save. Which you press save, and
it's going to eventually save this JSON,
this EmojiArt document to disk as JSON.
But first, we'll just have it print the JSON out on
the console, so we can just see what's going on here.
So let's do that, let's go to our storyboard and add a save
button here. Now if we look in our storyboard, look,
we've got a lot of junk in here. This is that table view
that we put to try and have our documents in a table view.
Hm, well, we're gonna have a significant upgrade here,
because we're gonna use that nice files app thing.
So I'm just going to delete this junk.
Get rid of all that, and I want to now put a save button
somewhere here in this UI. You know what I'm gonna do?
I'm gonna Embed this into Navigation Controller, so
that I get the little title bar at the top,
you see this little title bar that comes at the top?
Cuz that's a good place I could put a little save button
too. So throwing things in Navigation Controller,
you get that title bar, it's actually quite common and
a quite nice feature. So let's go down here and search for
Bar Button, Bar Button, here it is.
We always use bar buttons in these bars, not regular
buttons. And I'm going to inspect that bar button and
make it be a Save, a standard button called Save,
there it is. Let's wire it up, target action,
into our controller here. So, control drag, down here, it's
going to be an action, I'm going to call it save. That's
going to be a bar button item as its argument, there we go,
here it is. Let's go back to full screen so we can get the,
oops, get the full width here to do our save.
So this save, I just wanted to print my model out as JSON on
the console. So, to do that, I'm just gonna say,
if I can let json = my model, if I have one,
it's json. Now I have the json, it's a data, though.
And I want to print it out, obviously, as a string. And
when you have a data and you want to print it as a string,
you have to tell the system what the encoding is like,
is it ASCII? Or Unicode, some sort of Unicode thing?
Well, JSON is always UTF8, which is Unicode encoding,
eight bit encoding.
So, we're just going to let, if let jsonString = String,
constructor, with taking that json that I have.
And telling it what the encoding is, which is dot,
you can see there is a lot of different kinds of isoLatin1
and shiftJIS. And all these things, ascii right there, but
we're gonna do utf8. So if we're able to do that,
then I'm just gonna print it, print(jsonString). So,
now we're our save button is gonna print it out,
so let's go ahead and give this a try.
You see a little bit of warnings over there.
That's just because of that, yes that warning is
a good warning. Let's go look at this warning right here,
it says, unreachable part of our storyboard.
And indeed if we go look our storyboard over here,
here it is. We have no entry point to our storyboard, cuz,
remember, I deleted all of that junk?
Well, I deleted the entry point with it. So let's select
this Navigation Controller, and go over and inspect it,
and say, this is our initial View Controller. So you've got
to pay attentions to your warnings over here, right?
So let's bring our console back up,
make this as wide as possible, run, go back and
take a look here. All right, this time it's running.
So here's our EmojiArt right here, let's go ahead and
make a nice EmojiArt document. How about with this thing
right here, and let's put a little bicycle on the road,
right there. Now I'm going to hit save, and
let's watch our console over there. Oops, save, look,
there it is. Here is our emoji, it's got the URL,
which is this really, really long Google image emoji.
And then it's got the emojis,
which is an array, that only has one thing, the bike in it.
So let's add another thing, my second favorite thing to add,
which is a bee, and save. And now JSON has the bee in it as
well. So with very little work here,
just by making that thing codeable, we have made it so
we can save our document in JSON format. So
now let's add the file system code to actually write it out
to disk. And that's gonna be our next step here, so
let's go do that. Go back to our controller here.
So instead of printing this thing out as a JSON,
we're just going to write this to disk.
Now this is of type data, right? It's a data. So
I can just write it to disk with json.write[to: url].
Now, couple of things, one we have to say what url are we
gonna write it to. And of course this throws.
So you're gonna have to do both of those things. First,
let's talk about what url we're gonna write it to. Well,
any time you talk about the file system, what's the number
one thing you have to do when you're creating your url?
Find a directory in the sandbox to start.
Always do this. 100.0 percent at a time, you're going
to write something to the file system or read something from
the file system. You gotta figure out which sandbox
directory you're gonna start in. So this is a document, so
I'm gonna put it in my document directory. So, I,
let's type this in here. This is how we look up a sandbox
directory here, this default FileManager.default method
url. So we're looking for the document directory.
We always do userDomainMask. We're not replacing a file so
we don't care about that. And we want to create
the documents directory if it hasn't. And then I'm gonna
append the name of my file unto that URL for the document
directory. untitled.json, I'm gonna call it. So
now I have the URL. I can put this in here and write it.
Now I just have to deal with the fact that this throws.
So it means I have to put try in front of it. And
I'm going to actually catch errors in this.
Catch, oops, catch let error. And here if I get an error I'm
gonna say print("couldn't"), oops, couldn't.
Save, and we'll put the error right in there, so
we can see what it is. But, if it doesn't fail,
then I'm gonna say saved successfully.
So, now when we run on our console, we should see,
either, saved successfully, or couldn't save.
So, let's go try this. Put all the code on here at the same
time so you can see it. Run again. Let's go out here,
see that. So one thing about our app, of course,
every time it starts, we, it doesn't load up the document.
So, it's always blank.
So we'll always have to start again. So here let's start
again with this one. Let's put an apple in the sky up here.
And I'm gonna hit save now and hopefully it will say saved
successfully in our console, ready? Woo hoo,
saved successfully! Let's add another one, some coffee.
Saved successfully, it's working. But, this is not very
satisfying because, it's just saying saved successfully.
And you're like, yeah, sure, well you say it's saved. But
did it really save? But actually, we can go look and
see if it saved and go find this document. Because
we have the iOS 11 files app, which let's us look at
documents in apps that opt in. Now,
the key there is apps that opt in. So we have to actually put
that little info.plist thing I was talking about that says we
are an app where you can look in our document directory and
see our document. So let's go do that.
We're just gonna jump over to our info.plist here. I'm gonna
do the same kind of thing that we did in your homework where
you added a row, remember that, to do the HTTP URL. So
I'm gonna add a row, Support Document Browser,
there it is. Supports Document Browser, and
I'm gonna set that to yes. And that tells the system, okay,
you can look in my documents directory and
see my documents. So I have to run again because we have to
transfer the app back over to the iPad, so
it'll look at this info.plist over there. But actually,
I don't even need to create that untitled JSON again,
it's already there. So I swiped up from the bottom to
get this little thing to appear on the bottom here.
And I'm gonna click or
touch on this app right here. That is the files app.
And you're gonna see the UI here for files.
This is a lot what your UI is gonna look like in your app.
So it's got all these nice folders right here.
You can arrange them by date, and tags, and
name. You can go put things on your iCloud Drive. You can put
things on you iPad. And here, I'm clicking iPad. Emoji Art
is the only app On my iPad currently that has a documents
directory, with documents that file is allowed to look at.
That's because this iPad is pretty much fresh install.
But here it is, my app. And if I click on this notice it puts
my app icon in, that's kinda nice. If I click on it,
woohoo, it's untitled.json. And I can long press on it,
and say info. And it'll even tell me look, this is the kind
of file, it's a*.json file. It has 656 bytes, that sounds
about right. That's about how many things we had in there.
And I can even click on it to view it. However,
look where it views it. In some sort of JSON,
viewing app of some sort.
Not in our app, so that's kinda weird.
Why is that? Well, because we're not a JSON viewing app,
we're an emoji art app. So the files app doesn't
know that we are the one to open there. And we can fix
that a little bit later. We're probably not gonna have time
to do it today with the demo.
But I will certainly do it in the code I post and show you.
And the fix to that is to define a new file type called
emoji art. And then the files app will know,
that's an emoji art thing.
But right now, it looks at extension json and says well,
I'm gonna do the json thing.
And you can tell, see it's right though.
It's got the apple, it's got the coffee in there.
It's really small but you can see it. So, that's great. So,
we know it's actually saving. So let's go to the next step,
which is reading this document. So,
let's have our app, every time it puts its view controller
up, view will appear we'll do it in, it looks for
untitled.json, and loads it up.
That way, every time we run our app, it won't be blank
every time. It'll just load the last document we were
working on untitled.json that we were working on. Okay, so
let's do that. Go back to our controller.
Here's our view controller right here. So we're gonna do
that in viewWillAppear. super.viewWillAppear(animat-
ed). So, what do we need to do in here in viewWillAppear,
to get this to appear? It's pretty straightforward.
We just need to get that URL for the untitled.json. And
then look at the data and turn it back into an emoji art and
set that as our model.
Got that, so let's do that. Of course I need that URL.
So I'm gonna do the same thing that I did before.
What did I call that, let url, yeah. So
here's where I go get my document directory and
append the path component on untitled.json.
This is exactly what I did up here, no different cuz I want
the exact same url. But here, I'm going to say if I can let
jsonData equal trying to have Data contentsOf,
exactly the same thing. This Data contentsOf is exactly
what we did to get image urls over http, right?
So, contents of the file url, which is
this untitled json file in our documents directory.
That's what this url is. So if I'm able to create a data out
of that file, now I need to create an emojiArt out of it,
and set that as my model. So emojiArt is my model,
let me say equal to. I need to create an EmojiArt from
some jsonData. Well, we don't have an initializer for
EmojiArt that creates an EmojiArt from jsonData.
But we can really easily write one.
Let's go back to EmojiArt over here.
And just like we wrote this to get the JSON,
we can certainly write an initializer,
which I'm also gonna have be failable,
that takes some JSON, which is a Data. And, Initializes and,
if I can't initialize it, then I'm going to fail and
return nil. So what does it look like to do this? Again,
really easy. I'm just gonna say, if I can let new value,
that's gonna be my new value that I pull out of there,
equal try to JSONDecoder.
And what am I trying to decode out of that data?
I'm trying to decode an EmojiArt object.
And from what data? The JSON that you passed in.
So if I'm able to do that,
if I'm able to decode it out of there, now I have it.
The new thing in new value, and so I'm just gonna say,
self = newValue, right? I mean, an initializer here. So,
I'm just going to initialize myself, and I'm gonna fail
otherwise by returning nil. Now, this ones much more
likely to fail, because you could imagine corrupted JSON,
just playing the wrong JSON file. An empty JSON file, all
of these things would cause this to fail, and that's fine.
It's just this will not initialize,
this is only gonna initialize. If this is valid about JSON
encoded, something from this basically that's the only way
it will succeed. So now our code will work over here,
right? We've got this implemented, so
now when we quit and go back our document should be there.
So let's do that let's run and
then show it to you. Here it is and
sure enough look at that, it already picked up that
untitled.json and if I add a dog to this and hit Save.
Then quit and run again,
comes back with the dog. So we're both saving it,
with the Save button, and view will appear,
we are loading it up. So this is excellent.
We are really making a lot of progress here.
But now it is time to take this to the next level,
which is to be able to do that files app kind of UI. And
to do that, to make that easy, and to simplify our existing
code actually, we need to use UIDocument. UIDocument
encapsulates a document in just this really beautiful
way, really nice API. And that's what we need to do.
Now we could just do that here.
All you have to do is create a UIDocument subclass,
and implement the two methods I talked about in lectureon
Monday. But this where we're gonna step in and
use that template. We're gonna throw that template in here
for document base. So I'm gonna stop my app right here.
And I'm going to rename my existing EmojiArt.
I'm just gonna call it EmojiArtOLD. And then I'm
gonna go back to Xcode and create a new project. On this
two project I'm gonna use this Document Based App right here.
I'm wanna call this still EmojiArt,
basically this gonna be the same app which gonna have
this build on this template. I'm gonna put the same place,
I put everything else, here it is.
Let's quickly look at the things this created.
It's just a normal kind of Xcode app, of course,
it has assets, a launch screen, an app delegate.
And so I'm gonna put these three things in a little
supporting file like I always do. However, I'm gonna
take a moment to first take a look at the AppDelegate.
Because the AppDelegate is not just a bunch of
empty methods with just comments only,
it also now has this actual method.
This method is called open inputURL. This is sent
to your application by other applications,
like files, that say, I wanna open up one of your documents.
Now, this is only gonna get called if we have an EmojiArt
document, not a JSON document, cuz we're not an,
JSON opening app. But this is how that happened.
It's pretty simple code, I'm not gonna go through it, but
this is where that's going on. And we're gonna talk all about
AppDelegate, all this stuff, next week, all right.
So we got supporting files. What else came over there?
Well, we have this UIDocument subclass
called Document. Well,
this is going to eventually be our EmojiArtDocument.
EmojiArt, so you can rename the name of the file to be
EmojiArt. So this has got those two functions, right?
The one that converts from out model to a data,
and from a data to a model, back and forth.
That's all we have to implement to make this work.
So we'll do that in a little bit.
Then there's this, DocumentViewController,
is basically like EmojiArtViewController, right?
It's just the stub for a DocumentViewController.
And, of course, we have EmojiArtViewController so
we don't need this.
So I am just going to right-click on it and
delete it. So I'm gonna delete this DocumentViewController.
I don't need it, I have my EmojiArtViewController. And
then there's this DocumentBrowserViewController
thing right here. This is the subclass
UIDocumentBrowserViewControl- ler. Here's that viewDidLoad I
was telling you we were gonna configure it. Here's the place
where we're gonna call this import handler to copy
a template. Here's some other methods that we are not even
going to have to touch,
they just get's called when it's time to open
a document. And then there's this one down here
presentDocument, which I'm gonna delete most of.
This is just an internal method that's called from all
those other things that says, present your MVC for this
document at this URL. So we'll be implementing that soon.
And then, of course we've got our story board.
Let's see what's in our story board.
I'm gonna make our story board look like more like an iPad.
It's a little more familiar to us. Although,
our app will work on iPhone, by the way.
After all this I will show you that hopefully,
if we have time. So there's only two view controllers
here in this storyboard, one is this one.
That's the DocumentBrowserViewController.
That's the thing that looks like the files app. And
notice that's where we come in.
We arrive into this app there. Then there's this,
this is going to be our EmojiArtViewController.
In fact, I'm going to delete the one that comes in here,
cuz it's just a little place holder.
And I'm gonna put my EmojiArtViewController here,
and lets go do it right now.
In fact, I'm gonna go back to EmojiArt.old here.
I'm gonna go to its storyboard.
And one thing that's really cool about storyboards is that
you can copy and paste from one storyboard to another,
because all the connections to the code are made by name.
It's only just the names, so
as long as the names are the same in both ways,
places it works. So I'm just gonna select all of this and
hit copy. Then go back to my new one here and
hit paste. Zoom out a little bit, so I can see it all.
Go to our document outline, make this look nice here.
Now, one thing to notice,
I know this is a little hard to see on this screen, so
I'll try and zoom in more.
But you notice there's no segue between here, right?
These live on their own, this one lives on its own. And
that's why we have to do this manual presenting. The other
thing I'm gonna do for now is I'm gonna have the entry point
be our existing view controller. We'll add this one
in once we get the UIDocument stuff working, cuz we have to
have UIDocument working before we can really leverage this.
So we're just going to have our old UI for now.
And I'm gonna try and get our existing app as we had it
before working with UIDocument.
So it's gonna be the exact same thing, but
just working with UIDocument instead of directly accessing
the file system there. So of course we also need to have
all of our files from the old one. So let's go back to old
EmojiArt here. And get all of our stuff out of there, oops!
This, getting these two things on the screen at the same time
on this very small screen can be a challenge, all right.
So I'm going to bring over my controller, my model, my view.
Some of the supporting files like the cells,
the gesture recognizer stuff. The utilities,
the stuff I did, I'm not bringing over the AppDelegate,
because that came with the template. So I don't wanna do
that and I'm not bringing over my TableViewController either.
That's what under junk here, that's the TableViewController
that was suppose to be the documents thing, but
we said forget that, we're using this new files thing So
I'm just gonna drag these over here. Copy them all in and
one other thing I wanna bring over actually from here is my
app icon. I got this nice app icon, I don't wanna lose that.
So I'm gonna go over here to my assets and my new one and
get rid of the blank app icon and just drag this app icon
over here. So that's it. So I've essentially brought over
everything from my old emoji art to the new emoji art. But
what we're gonna do first is go and
make this emoji art document business work.
So let's go do that. Where's our emoji art document?
It's right here. This is the thing I just renamed.
And there is only these two methods that are doing stuff,
we know exactly how to do it,
we were just doing this. One thing about this is,
is you notice the contents returns an Any not a Data,
that's because this Any could be a file wrapper. A directory
full of files is a way to represent a document just like
is a data is. But usually this is going to return a Data.
In fact, look, the default returns a blank Data. So here,
to do either of these,
we actually need that model passed to us in the document.
So, I'm gonna have a var emojiArt over here as well
which is going to be an EmojiArt. And
any time I wanna save my model from my controller, I just
take my controller's model and put it in the document and
then the document knows what to do from there.
So let's go ahead and return this emojiArt.json and
if it doesn't have JSON representation,
then we'll return Data, which is a blank document.
Empty document and we know how to deal with that,
because our documents always come up empty.
And then this is the other way around, here we're having one
passed to us. A data pass to us and we want to turn it into
an emoji art. So I'm going to say if I can let the json =,
the contents that were passed to me as a data,
because I don't deal with file wrappers.
If this were a file wrapper, I don't deal with that.
Then I'm gonna set my emojiArt equal to, again,
using that constructor that I did to take the data and
turn it into an EmojiArt.
And this might fail and that's fine. And this will be nil and
then it won't save the document. It can't save a nil
document. And, I talked about this ofType in both these
cases. This is a UTI. Like public.json is a UTI or
edu.stanford.cs193.emojiart could be a UTI.
A unique identifier of the type.
Now we don't really care because we only open one thing
or anything we open, JSON or an emojiArt or whatever,
is all just a JSON data anyway to us. So we don't care about
the type, but some apps might open multiple different types.
They might need to know what type it is in order to
successfully open it or save it. And that's it, this is all
we need to do to do an emojiArt document. We're done,
now we can use all the API of UIDocument like, let's say,
synchronous opening and saving, working over iCloud,
automatics, auto saving, all that stuff just all work for
free as long as we implement these things.
So let's use all those things back in our emojiArt
view controller here to replace the places where we're
actually accessing the file system directly here. So
we want to get rid of this, so let's delete all that. And
let's delete all this. And
we're gonna replace this with stuff from using the same
primitives, but using the document. Now, to do this,
we obviously need to have a var which is the document
cos we have to be able to talk to our own document.
And so we're just gonna have a var called
document which is a type EmojiArtDocument. This is
going to be set in that code from the file chooser, right?
When the file chooser chooses a file,
we're gonna set our document in our new MVC and
then it's just gonna magically show its stuff using all
the document API. So let's talk about,
view will appear first. When our first document first
appears, we need to open our document.
So we do that by just saying, document?.open. And that's all
we have to say. It does come with a completion handler
that will tell you whether it was successful doing that.
And we usually want to check this, and say, if we're,
there were success, then we're going to do some stuff.
What might we want to do here, maybe want to set
our title equal to the documents localized name. This
localized name just come from the URL, it's like the last
part of the URL without the file extension put in there,
so that's nice. We need self in there of course to
insert a closure. But the most important thing we wanna
do if we successfully open the document is to set our model
to the model that the document was able to get by
opening that file. So the document has an emoji art that
it got from the file. We have our model. We want to get it.
So that's the main thing we are doing in all of these
document things, is for setting, getting our model.
Now what about save? Well,
we actually don't really do save, we do autosave.
So how do we do autosave? The only thing that's important
with autosave is that you tell the UIDocument that something
has changed. Otherwise, it's not going to waste its time
autosaving something that hasn't changed. And
you do that by first telling the document to look
at your model, so we wanna set it to our model.
And then you tell the document that a change has happened.
So you update the change count and you say that that change
is done. By the way, this done can be undo, redo or done.
So we're not talking about the undo manager, so
I can't really show you that. But the other option is done,
because meaning the change is done.
And by the way, I'm only going to do this is the document's
emojiArt is not nil. Okay, if we haven't actually started up
a document, it's useless to be updating its change count
there. Now this is strange, because we are saying and
noting that our document changed,
because the user pressed the save button. That is weird.
Really, we should notice change when anything changes.
Someone dragged out another emoji, they resized it,
they put a different background URL. That's when
we should "save". And really, this method shouldn't even be
called save, it should be called document change.
Well, unfortunately, the time, one of the number one thing
it's gonna cut off that I can't get done,
because of this midterm coming in here,
is putting that saving, or the document change tracking in.
And why is that an interesting thing?
Well, because that's being tracked in our view, right?
Our view is what knows when we've resized something or
dragged something in.
So our view needs to talk back to our controller and say,
hey, something changed. Well, it can't talk back to our
controller, except for blind and structured, right? So
how would we, any of you here, how would you suggest that we
talk from our view back to our controller to tell it, hey,
this document has changed, this document has changed.
What would you suggest, mechanism?
So one suggestion is, let's have a variable in our
view that's a reference to our controller. And
that's not allowed by MVC, right? View can't talk
to its controller that way. So let's try delegation.
The same way a table view talks back to its controller,
it's a delegation, scroll view it uses delegation,
that's how we would have to do. So we are going to set up
our own delegation where we have an emojiArt view
delegate. That's what we would do. Unfortunately,
I don't have time to do that, but that's what we would do.
So I don't want you to get the idea here that you should
have save buttons in document apps.
You should never have a save button.
It should know when things change and
just call this updateChangCount.
But since we don't have that, we will have our save button,
we will just tell it when it saves. All right? What else do
we have to do here? How about closing our document.
Right now we only have one document, untitled.json, but
we're just about to ask, add a file chooser that's gonna let
us choose lots of different documents. So
we need a way to close this document so
we can open another document.
So I'm gonna go back and add a close button to our UI.
I'm gonna put it right here on the other side from save
over there. We're gonna go in here. Bar Button again,
Bar Button up here. There's actually a standard one for
that. It's actually called Done,
cuz you're done with this document, right there. And
we are then going to control-drag, and
I'll put it right in here. And I'm gonna have an action here.
I'm gonna call it close, I could call it done, but
I'll call it close. And now let's go back
to full width here, go back over to here. All right,
so what are we gonna do in our close? Well, for a document
app, it's easy. You're just gonna say document?.close().
Now, it also has a success completion handler, but
I don't really care because I'm not gonna do anything.
Whether it's successful or not,
I'm just going to try to close it, and hope it will be, and
99% of the time it's going to be. I could, you know,
catch your errors and stuff like that. Having problems for
some reason, the closing and having problems, but
the best we can really do is just try to close and
see what happens. The other thing I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna save() right before, now because I don't have automatic
change tracking, I wanna save before I close. If I had
automatic change tracking, I wouldn't do save here. I would
delete this line of code. And in fact I am going to delete
this line of code when I post this code after lecture,
because I'm going to have that change tracking in there.
Now notice I did save with no argument,
because save takes a bar
button item and I don't have one. Here's a cool trick.
I'm gonna make this an optional and
have it default to nil. By doing that, now I can call
save with nothing and it defaults to nil and
I don't use this bar button item in here so,
all is well. Everybody got all that? Okay, now,
to test all of this, this is it. See how we've replaced all
that stuff in our, that was file system now with all this
nice code that is very understandable and readable?
Open our document, close our document, update the document.
I'm going to, in my view did load, set my document
to be Untitled.json. Eventually, it's going to be
that chooser thing, but for now it's going to be that.
So in viewDidLoad, just a, this is just as a test.
I'm going to take this right out of here,
right after we do this test. And
all I'm going to do here is get that,
that json url again. You can see why I put that in,
those codes in there, because I have to type it so
many times. And all I'm going to do here is just
set my document, right?
That's this bar right here. It has to be an EmojiArtDocument,
I'm going to set that equal to an EmojiArt,
well we're running out of battery there. Document, and
remember that UIDocuments only have one initializer,
it's the URL. So this is fileURL,
the URL. Make sense there?
Have my close, curly braces, there we go. So that's it.
So I'm only doing that just as a test. So now,
when we launch our app, it should load that Untitled.json
up because we're immediately setting that as our document,
and the document just does its thing.
So let's go ahead and take a look at that here.
Run, and let you see what's going on.
Okay, look, it loaded up Untitled.json. And
let's put a little airplane flying across there, and
I'm gonna hit Save to let it know that there was a change
to the document, and then hit Done. Now if I quit and
run again. Hopefully, we'll see
the airplane there and we did. Okay, so UIDocument is doing
all of the things the file system stuff was doing for
us. But now that we have UIDocument,
we can have our app launch instead
of launch and show this, launch and
show that file choosing thing, the document browser thing,
like the files app. So let's go put that piece of
the puzzle in here. Before I do anything,
I'm going to make sure I remove this viewDidLoad.
I'm going to take that away because I'm not gonna be
setting my document to this Untitled.json, I'm going to be
setting it to whatever the document view browser
wants me to have it be. All right, so here we are.
This is the document browser view controller,
this is thing where all the magic happens, here.
One thing we have to do to get this guy in the loop is to go
back to our storyboard and have the entry point no longer
be our MVC. Instead it's going to be this. And we're gonna be
responsible from getting from here to presenting this on top
of this to show our documents. So, let's see how we do that.
All right, so let's do all the parts I talked about in
the slides here. Let's do viewDidLoad. Let's configure.
So, of course, we want or delegate = self, we need that.
Also, we are not going to allow picking of multiple
items, cuz we only know how to show one EmojiArtDocument
at a time. Allows documentation to be true, hm,
yeah for now. And then here is things, tint color,
I'm not gonna change the color or the look of it.
You can play around with that, see what you like there.
So, we're gonna come back to viewDidLoad and
address this in just a moment.
But now let's go down here to didRequestDocumentCreationWit-
hHandler. This is where it's saying, give me the URL of
a blank document, because someone wants to create one.
And I'm gonna make this really easy on us here.
I'm gonna delete all of that in there, and
just call this importHandler that it gave me.
See, it's giving me this importHandler? It takes a URL,
and either copy or move. And I'm gonna copy,
call it with a template, which is gonna be a URL, and .copy.
And all I have to do is make a URL, var template: URL.
Make this template point to some blank document.
And I'm gonna do that in viewDidLoad right here. And
I type that over here. And
to do that I'm just going to get a URL.
This time not into my documents directory because
this is the blank document I'm copying all the time. I don't
want it to appear in the documents when the guy goes
and looks there. So I'm gonna put it in applicationSupport.
So, applicationSupport's a great place to put things that
are kind of behind the scenes. But they're permanent.
I want this template to stick around.
I don't want it to be in the caches and get deleted,
although I probably could put it in caches cuz
I can always recreate it here in viewDidLoad.
But anyway, so this is the URL.
I'm going to call it Untitled.json, just for
old time's sake.
I'm putting it in my applicationSupportDirectory.
And all I wanna do here, though, is make sure I create
this file. So I've got the URL to it. So to create it,
I'm gonna say, if the template is not nil. In other words,
I was able to create the URL, which I should be able to.
I'm gonna now set allowDocumentCreation.
This var up here, instead of it being true.
I am going to set it to be the result of asking
the FileManager, the default FileManager,
to create that file. So it has a method called createFile,
give it the path to the file, the template's path, and
you create it with some contents.
I'm gonna make it empty cuz it's just a blank document, or
an empty document, and I don't even need any file attribute,
so let's get rid of that. Now createFile is a nice way to
create a file because it doesn't throw or
anything like that, and it returns a Boolean whether that
file either got created or already exists,
which is exactly what I want here.
And if it's true, then I will allow document creation.
Otherwise, I'm not gonna allow it,
cuz I couldn't create the template. See why I'm doing
that right there? So that's a nice little trick to kinda do.
When you're creating your template,
if you fail to create it for some reason, you can do that.
So now this importHandler will just work. I'm passing it to
this template that I created up here, and having it copy
out of application support into the documents directory.
These other things over here we don't need to even touch.
These are the things that get called when people click on
documents, didPickDocumentURLs.
didImportDocument is when some other app, like the files app,
asks you to open up one of your documents.
And notice that they are both doing the same one liner,
which is, please present the document at that URL.
That means, put up your ViewController to show it.
Okay, so we, and there's a, by the way, an error one here,
see, failedToImportDocumentAt.
You really should put up an alert here, but
I haven't shown you how to put up alerts.
I'm gonna show you next week,
so you can't do it. But that, you really should put an alert
that says, couldn't load document, or
couldn't open document, or whatever. All right, so
here's presentDocument, that's going to present it. And
I'm gonna basically do what I showed you in the slides right
here, which is, I'm gonna get my storyBoard.
There was already code to get the storyBoard in here
from that template. And I'm going to use the storyBoard to
get the ViewController that I want to present.
Now, it's a little tricky here,
the ViewController that I want to present is actually not
my emoji art ViewController. It's the navigation controller
it's in, does everyone understand that? So
I have to somehow instantiate this navigation controller,
which will also bring this in.
So I need to give this guy a name, so I'm just going to
select it, go to the Identity Inspector and give it a name.
I'm gonna call it, my DocumentMVC. It could be any
name we want, but DocumentMVC is kind of what that is,
at the top of my DocumentMVC mechanism.
So now that I have this name, I can go back here and say-
Let my documentVC
= the storyBoard.instantiateViewCon-
troller(withIdentifier: "DocumentMVC").
So now we have our DocumentMVC.
And now I'm just going to configure it, and then I'm
going to present it by saying present the (documentMVC),
VC rather. And animated: true, I want animated: true in case
someone clicked on it in the file, we want it to slide up,
right? We don't just want it to just appear,
we want it to slide up from the bottom.
There's even a way to make this like grow out of the icon
in the files thing, which is really cool.
It's not even that hard, but
unfortunately I don't have time to show it to you, but
just know that there's a way to do it. This is gonna be
the normal slide up from the bottom presentation. But
this DocumentMVC has an emojiViewController in it that
we need to set the document of. So
I'm going to do the same kind of thing we do in a prepare.
I'm going to say, if I can let my emojiViewController
= the documentViewController, its contents.
Remember that contents, I showed you that before, let's
go look at it just to remind you, I have this in Utilities.
The contents is a UI ViewController method right
here, that just says, if I'm a navigation controller, return
my contents. Otherwise, if I'm not a navigation controller,
just return myself. So this will make it so
that this code that I just wrote will work,
whether it's wrapped in a navigation controller or not.
So get the contents as an EmojiArtViewController.
So, if I can get the EmojiArtViewController,
I guess I should call this EmojiArtViewController just to
be nice there. Then I can set its document,
EmojiArtViewController.docu- ment = and
what does the document equals? It means,
= a new EmojiArtDocument, which we know
the constructor is fileURL, and what's the URL?
It's the URL they want us to present, documentURL.
This is saying Instance member, capital E,
there we go. I thought it wanted a static method there.
One other thing we need to do is the types. Right now,
if we go look at our project settings right here,
I'm gonna go over and look at our project settings.
And we look at the info here,
the Document Types that we can open are images. And
we don't open images, we open JSON files. public.JSON.
And, like I say, when I post the code after lecture,
I'll also do this Exported UTIs down here. And
make a new type of emoji art, and then put that as our type.
But, for now, we'll say that we do JSON files.
Okay, so if I haven't forgotten anything here,
it should work. Okay, look at that,
already you can see that our app is quite different.
It is showing us a UI that looks just like the files app,
right? It's got the folders and all that stuff,
we can even go over here to iCloud Drive.
We can go on my iPad, there it is, EmojiArt, let's look
inside. Okay, there is our Untitled.JSON, let's open it.
Woo, it works! Let's close this one, it doesn't close,
look, I'm pressing Done, it doesn't close.
When our MVC comes up, it takes over the whole screen,
because we presented it right here,
how do we make it go away? How do we dismiss it, essentially?
Well, we do that in the ViewController itself, or
the ViewController that wants to dismiss itself.
And the way we're gonna do that is in close,
when you hit that Done button right there.
And we're going to save, but
then we're going to say dismiss(animated). So
dismiss(animated: true) is how you dismiss yourself.
If you've been presented, you can dismiss yourself.
This also has a completion handler, and
in that completion handler, I'm going to close. So
I'm gonna wait until I've been dismissed. The animation has
happened, then I'll close my document. And, of course,
now I'm in a closure, so I can say, self. So let's try that.
So here I'm gonna open Untitled again.
Now I'm gonna close it and I'm back here,
now I'm gonna create a document, ready?
Create, it copies that template, it's blank.
Now I'm gonna drag a document in here,
let's see if we can find something good here,
something like that. Put an apple on the tree, I'd say,
like that. Now, I'm going to, I'll save just to note that it
has changed, again, we should do that automatically. And
then I'm going to say Done. And now I have two documents,
and now I can go back to the other one, right?
Click there, go to this one, put that one, now,
what if want to put these things on iCloud Drive?
Watch what happens when I go to iCloud Drive for emoji art,
Create Document, see, look.
I can create a document on iCloud Drive.
So this is actually created on the network, I'll be able to
see on all my devices, so make another one here,
something like this. Put a bee out there, a big bee, and
mark saved, and then Done. And now we have this document
Untitled right here that you see is on iCloud Drive.
Se still have the Untitled ones on our device, and
we have the one here on iCloud Drive. So, we click on it and
we get to see it. Now,
the next thing I'm gonna do is make it so that this UI looks
a lot better. Because look at the icons there. I mean,
is that the world's ugliest looking icons? We're gonna
go from the world's ugliest looking icons to the world's
best looking icons. Because with UI document,
you can have each document have it's own icon. And
I'm gonna set the icon to be miniature version of
the document, a thumbnail image of the document. That
way I can easily see which one was the one with the apple and
which one had the bee. It'll be,
I'll be able to see it right in here.
So let's do that. That turned out to be super simple to do
in the UI document. So I'm gonna go back to my Emoji Art
document here. This simple guy. And
I'm just gonna add one method, which I'm gonna override.
Called file attributes to right. And this is essentially
just returning a dictionary of the file attribute,
like is this file hidden, those kind of things. So
I'm gonna get those attributes from my super class,
cuz I'm overriding this.
So when you get this and then I'm gonna add one attribute
which is this kinda complicated thing called
a thumbnailDictionaryKey. Actually the value is another
dictionary. And you put this other key here,
Thumbnail1024x1024SizeKey. Don't let that fool you.
It can be any size you want. Although if it's too small,
it'll use the document icon again. So
make sure it's big enough to actually being an improvement
on that. And I need to put a thumbnail in there.
So I am gonna add a var to be that thumbnail.
UIImage. Thumbnail's just a UIImage. And
now I'm gonna set this thumbnail image in my document
every time I close. So
when I close I am just gonna make another snapshot of it.
So let's go do that to my controller.
Here's where I close, right after I save. I'm gonna say
that my documents.thumbnail =
myemojiArtview.snapshot. So
snapshot is a little var that I wrote, I put in utilities.
You can go a look at it. It's only three or four lines of
code that just takes the view and snapshots it, grabs it as
a UI image. And I'm only gonna do this by the way if,
again, if my documents emojiArt is not nill.
Cuz I don't wanna snapshot a blank document.
But what I should do here is do the snapshot and
then if this thing is nil, I should come up with some other
nice thumbnail for it. But I'm not doing that. So
let's make sure it rebuilds everything here. So
let's run again. Go over here, see what this looks like.
It actually ran even though it said it had an error there,
but it did run successfully. All right, so
let's open one of our documents.
Remember we set our thumbnails when we close,
so here's one. Let's go ahead and close it. And
look, we get this beautiful thumbnail of it.
How about this other one over here?
This guy? Let's close that one. And this even works on
the iCloud drive. It might be a little delayed on the iCloud
drive because it has to upload it, but let's try.
Let's see how fast, pretty quick network right here.
I don't know if you can see in the iCloud drive,
it actually had the little cloud symbol there briefly as
it was downloading it back from
the clouds which is kind of cool.
In this UI that you see here, is all the full files UI.
So not only can you do things like I did before we check
the info, but you could move it,
like I could move this from my iCloud back to my local device
or copy here I guess. And it's asking here if I wanna
keep both or replace it cuz they're both called Untitled,
so I'll keep both. So now if I go back to my iPad here, now I
have three items, including this one here. And again,
sometimes you get a delay when you move things from iCloud,
getting the thumbnails,
cuz the thumbnails can be kind of big at times. And so
slogging them around can take a little bit of time here and
there. You can also rename your files, so
you know, this is apple in the sky. So let's rename it,
let's call it Sky Apple. So you can rename your files,
all that stuff. And the user can do it in here without
having to go over to the files app to do that.
I have a couple minutes left so I'm
gonna show you one other thing which is running this on
iPhone. So let's go run this on the iPhone.
I'm just gonna go run it in the simulator, iPhone X,
let's see what this looks like in the iPhone X. So
this whole document view browser, it all works just as
well in the iPhone, as it does on the iPad. There's only
a couple of things we have to think about when we try and
make this app work on the iPhone, as you'll see here.
Once this gets fired up. So there it is. See, you can,
we can look on iCloud Drive here.
We can even see that document, a document that we've created
before on iCloud Drive. And in open end, we can open stuff
off of iCloud Drive. So I can open it. Now On iPhone, I'd
really like to still be able to drag some emojis in and
work on this document, right. One thing I can't do, though,
is create a new document. Do you see why? Because on
iPhone, you can't drag from Safari to drag in new things.
So it's really misleading that it says Create Document here.
Because if I hit Create Document,
I can't really create an actual document,
because I can't drag anything in. So I really don't want it
to say Create Document on iPhone. The other thing is,
I want my collection view to work. I can't drag. I'm trying
to push down and drag. Why does drag not work? Well,
drag doesn't work because collection view by default
on iPhone does not allow dragging. But we can turn it
on. So let's go fix both of those things in our code.
We're gonna fix the problem with
the misleading create by just, this part here where we go and
create the template. I'm just not gonna do that on iPhone.
So I'm, that's gonna leave this to be false, and
So how do I check my code to see if I'm on an iPad? And
it's not do it.
you do that this way. You say if UIDevice.current,
that's my current device,
has a userInterfaceIdiom
of .pad. And the other option is
.phone so I'm only gonna do this template thing, which is
the only thing that can set this to true on the iPad.
So I'm never gonna have create document on the iPhone.
That's good.
Now, what about the dragging of the Collection View?
Well, that's in my controller. I'm gonna go down here
to where I create my Collection View. This is my
Collection View outlets that are here. And I'm gonna set
this thing in Collection View called draginteractionenabled.
Now this is true by default on iPad. And false by default on
my iPhone. But if I set it to true everywhere,
now it will make it so
I can drag in my collection vew on the iPhone, as well.
So when we go here, we won't see the create button and
we also will be able to work on our document.
So let's open this document right here. Here it is.
Now look, I can drag. Drag around my Collection View and
I can also pull things out of here and
into my picture. I can either mark it as saved and done, and
if I want it back to my iPad, I'll be able to see it over
there. So the only two things I'm gonna do post lecture
here that you're not gonna be able to watch me do
is the delegation thing. So that we don't have to
have that save button anymore cuz we hate that and
also adding the new type emoji art. Which really is only two
things I'm gonna change. I'm gonna add the emoji art thing
in that settings that I was telling you about.
And then I'm gonna change this right here,
my empty template to be untitled dot emoji art. That's
only change I'm gonna make to make it be using the emoji art
documents instead of JSON. All right. That is it. I
will see you all next Monday. >> For
more, please visit us at stanford.edu
>> 更多课程详见 stanford.edu