本字幕由志愿者义务贡献，采用许可协议
知识共享 署名-非商业性使用-相同方式共享 3.0 美国
Stanford University. >> Welcome to Stanford CS193P,
欢迎参加斯坦福 CS193P 课程
Developing Applications for iOS. This is Lecture Number 2,
iOS 应用程序开发。今天是 2017 年秋季学期
fall of 2017. So today, I'm gonna spend the first 15 or
的第二节课。今天我要先花十五到
20 minutes talking about Model-View-Controller,
二十分钟的时间讲 Model-View-Controller
this design paradigm that I told you we always have to do
这个设计模式，我说的我们总是需要
when we develop for iOS. And then, we're gonna apply
在开发 iOS 时用的设计模式。然后我们把
Model-View-Controller to our Concentration app, so
模型-视图-控制器 运用到翻牌游戏里
you're gonna get to see the kinda the concepts first,
你会先了解下这个概念
then we get to see it in action. All right,
然后我们看实际的应用。那么
Model-View-Controller, what is it? It's essentially a way
模型-视图-控制器 究竟是什么呢？它是一种
we're gonna divide up all the objects in our system into
在我们的系统里把对象分类的方法
three camps. one camp, this blue camp, is the Model camp.
分成三个阵营。一个是这个蓝色的 Model，模型
That's a UI independent set of objects that is
这是不依赖于 UI 的一系列对象，这代表了
the what of your app? So for our Concentration game, it's
你的程序究竟能做什么。对于我们的翻牌游戏
the part of our app that knows how to play Concentration.
就是程序里知道翻牌游戏规则的那部分
It knows how to match cards, take them away,
它知道怎么匹配卡片，移走
it knows when to flip cards, it knows all that stuff.
知道什么时候翻牌，知道所有这些
It's all the kind of knowledge about the Concentration
它知道所有翻牌游戏相关的的信息和规则
game but nothing about how it appears on screen. That
但是并不知道这是怎么显示在屏幕上的
is all part of the Controller camp's responsibility.
那个就属于 Controller，控制器的职责了
So the Controller camp is the how
控制器阵营的是负责
your Concentration game appears on screen.
你的翻牌游戏如何显示到屏幕上
So Model is what is your app about, and
所以模型是代表程序是做什么的
the Controller is how it shows up on screen.
控制器是程序是怎么显示到屏幕上的
And the View camp is your Controller's minions.
然后 View，视图阵营就是控制器的下属
These are very generic UI elements, like UI button,
他们是通用的 UI 组件，比如 UIButton
the UI view controller even UI label.
甚至 UIViewController，还有 UILabel
All those kind of generic things, UI things,
所有这些通用的 UI 组件
that the Controller has to communicate with the Model to
在控制器与模型交流过后
get your game, whatever is going on your app onto the UI.
得到了游戏一类的信息，就会用视图显示出来
So the View is generic minions of the Controller. So
所以视图是通用的，控制器的下属
those are the three camps. Now, MVC is really all about
这就是模型-视图-控制器三个阵营，简称 MVC
managing the communication between these camps, right?
但最重要的是规范这三个阵营之间的通讯
You put the objects in these camps, and
你把对象分到这三个阵营里了
they have to kind of obey certain rules when they talk
那他们之间交谈就要遵守一定的规则
to each other. So, I've drawn road signs up here.
所以我这里用道路交通标线来表明
You see the little road signs that are kind of approximating
看到这个道路交通标线了吗？它们表示了
what kind of communication is allowed between the various
这几个阵营之间被允许的沟通
camps. And let's look at it all in detail. So
让我们来仔细看看
the Controller, talking to the Model,
所以这个控制器可以访问模型
that's a fully dashed white line going in that direction.
向这个方向的是一条白色的虚线
You can cross over anytime you want, big green arrow.
任何时候都可以穿过去，我用绿色箭头表示
The Controller can talk to the Model all it wants.
这个控制器可以随便和模型交流
It has to be able to because it is the Controller's job to
它必须要能这样做，因为这是控制器的工作
present this what the thing is to the user, so it has to be
就是把模型展示给用户，所以必须要
able to access the Model. So that's a big old green arrow,
能够访问模型，所以这是个肯定可以的绿色箭头
and this is the Controller talking to the Model.
控制器是可以访问模型的
Pretty much unlimited communication to the Model's
访问模型基本没有限制
publicly available functionality. What about this
只要是公开可用的功能都行。那这边呢？
direction? Well, similarly here, its minions,
这边也是类似的，视图是下属
the Controller has to be able to control its minions, so
控制器需要能控制它的下属，所以
it's a pretty much a wide open green arrow that way as well,
这也是可以的，我这个方向也用绿色箭头表示
and you've already seen a green arrow from
而且你已经看到了这样的“绿色通道”了
the Controller to the View in our Concentration.
在翻牌游戏里，从控制器到视图
It was called an outlet. We had an outlet to the flip
就是我们的出口（outlet），我们有一个到
count label, and of course we can talk to the flip count
flipCountLabel 的出口，当然我们可以告诉 flipCountLabel
label and say anything we want to it to get it to say what we
说我们想要让他在 UI 上显示
want in the UI. That is the Controller's prerogative.
我们想要的内容。这就是控制器的特权
So you can see the controller can talk to everybody
你看到了，所以控制器能和所有人交谈
pretty much all at once. What about some of the other kind
基本都可以。那这些其他之间的
of communication? What about the Model talking
通讯呢？比如模型
directly to the View? Okay, that's pretty much impossible.
直接访问视图呢？好吧，这个基本是不可能的
Why is that impossible? Two reasons.
为什么不可能呢？有两个理由
One, the Model is UI independent, and the View only
其一，模型是和 UI 无关的，而视图
has UI things in it, so there's absolutely no way a UI
只负责显示 UI。所以没有可能一个
independent thing could talk to such UI dependent things
无关 UI 的阵营去访问这个只是 UI
like the View. Another reason is that these View things
的视图。另一个原因是视图
are generic objects, like a button or a slider. How could
都是通用的，比如按钮或是滑杆
a button have any idea what a Concentration game is about?
一个按钮怎么可能知道翻牌游戏是干什么的？
No way. There's just no way it would know that, it's generic.
不可能。按钮是通用的，它不可能知道翻牌这个游戏
So there's never any communication between these
所以这两个之间是不可能沟通的
two, I never wanna see you having any communication
我不希望看到你在作业里面
between these camps in any of your homeworks or whatever.
让这两个阵营之间沟通
That's why it's a double yellow line there.
这就是为什么这里是双黄线
No crossing over. All right, that's an easy one. What about
不能跨过去。好，这个简单
the View talking back to the Controller? This is probably
那视图翻过去通知控制器呢？这个可能
the most interesting of the communication pathways here.
是最有趣的交流的方法了
The View can speak to its Controller, of course it,
视图是肯定可以通知控制器的
it kind of has to, like when a button is clicked or whatever,
某种意义上这是必须的，比如按钮被按下一类的
but when it communicates,
但是他们要交流的话
this communication has to be blind and structured. It
这种交流必须要是某种标准化的匿名通讯机制
has to be blind because these are generic view objects.
说它是“匿名的”是因为视图是通用的对象
The UI Button doesn't know anything about a Concentration
UIButton 不知道有关翻牌
game controller, so when it's talking to the Controller,
这个游戏的控制器，所以当它通知控制器的时候
it doesn't really know that it's a Concentration game
它是不知道那是翻牌游戏的
controller and it's structured in that
控制器。说它是有标准的
since we're gonna have this communication going on,
是因为我们要让这个通讯成立
a generic object has to think a little bit ahead about how
一个通用的对象要提前考虑好
it might wanna communicate with this Controller object.
要如何和控制器对象沟通
So, you already know one structured, blind way for
你们已经见过了一个视图使用的
your View to communicate, and that's target action.
标准化的匿名通讯，那就是 target action
When we Ctrl dragged and created the method touchCard.
当我们按住 control 拖拽，创建了一个方法 touchCard
That's target action. And all the Controller has to do is
这就是目标对象操作。而控制器所要做的
kinda hang a target on itself. That's to say, it creates
就是把自己设为目标对象，也就是创建
a method like touchCard. And then UI button and
一个 touchCard 这样的方法，然后 UIButton
other things, they can get this action, and
一类的控件就能得到操作这个方法的存根
every time the button is pressed,
然后每次按下按钮
they just call the target. This is a very,
按钮就调用目标对象的方法。这是一种非常
very simple kind of blind structure communication. But
非常简单的标准化匿名通讯
sometimes you need more complicated communication,
但有的时候你需要更复杂的通讯
like you have a more complicated generic view
比如你有更复杂的通用 UI 组件
item like, let's say a scroll view. A scroll view is
比如一个 scroll view，滚动视图能够
scrolling around on some image or something like that, and
四处移动来查看一张图片一类的
it might need to tell the Controller,
它可能需要告诉控制器
I scrolled to the end. Am I allowed to scroll down here?
我滚动到最底部了，我还能继续往下么？
Can I scroll vertically or horizontally?
我移动的方向是竖着还是横着？
It kinda wants to talk to Controller as it's
他会想要在完成任务期间
working to do its job. And we do that with these kind of
和控制器保持沟通。为了实现这个，我们会用
predefined methods that the scroll view defines as part of
滚动视图规定好的一些方法，这些方法
what's called its delegate. So its delegate is just a var in
属于 delegate，代理的一部分。代理就是一个变量
scroll view that, and this var will have some object in it.
滚动视图里的一个变量，这个变量存储了一个对象
And all we know about this object is that it responds to
对于这个对象，我们所知道的只有
a certain number of messages. Most of these messages
它能够响应一定数量的某些方法。大部分这些方法
start with the words will, should, or did.
都会以 will, should 或 did 开头
Like, I will scroll to here, should I scroll over here? I
比如我将要（will）滚动到这里，是否能够（should）滚动到那里？
did scroll down to here. Those are classic delegate methods.
我已经（did）滚动到这里了，这些就是典型的代理的方法
And the Controller, using a mechanism called protocols,
然后控制器通过 protocol，协议
which we'll talk about next week,
这个我们下周讲
is able to tell the scroll view,
就能告诉滚动视图
I'm your delegate, and all the scroll view will know
我是你的代理，然而滚动视图只知道
is that it implements these will, should, and did.
我实现了这些 will，should，did 方法
It doesn't know anything about it. It doesn't know its class,
滚动视图不知道其他我的信息，不知道究竟是哪个类
doesn't know that it's has to do with Concentration game
不知道是否是我们的翻牌游戏
obviously, it knows nothing. It just knows that
显然什么也不知道，只知道
the Controller will implement that. So
这个控制器实现了代理方法
we'll see delegation in about two weeks when we start using
我们会在大约两周之后看到代理模式，就是当我们
more complicated UI objects. Now, another important thing
开始使用更加复杂的 UI 对象的时候。另外一个重要的是
to remember in the MVC model is that views,
记住在 MVC 模式里，视图
these generic things,
这些通用的视图
cannot own the data they're displaying. In other words,
不能自己提供他们显示的数据，也就是说
they're not going to have the data they're displaying as
他们不能写死显示的数据，然后作为
part of their instance variables. Now why is this?
实例变量的一部分（伴随每个对象）。为什么呢？
Well, imagine that the View is showing your entire iPod music
让我们现象一下你展示整个 iPod 音乐库
library. And let's say you have 50,000 songs in there.
比如说我们里面有五万首歌
There's no way, it would make absolutely no sense to have
我们不可能，而且也根本没有理由
a list view or something, some generic view that lists
让某个列表视图，某种展示某个列表的通用视图
things, to bring all 50,000 of those things in there. So
存储五万首歌在里面
instead, it uses this same kind of protocol mechanism to
取而代之，应该使用类似的某种协议
have another set of special messages,
让另一些特殊的方法
and they are messages like data, give me the data at, or
这些方法包括给我在这个地方的数据
how many items are there? And the Controller implements that
或者是一共有多少个项目要显示，然后控制器实现这些方法
so we can talk to the Model and get the data for the View.
控制器通过访问模型来获取视图需要的数据
So, for example, table view, which is a big scrolling list
比如列表视图（table view），就是个很长的滚动列表
kind of generic view item, that's in iOS.
这个是 iOS 提供的通用视图组件
When it's scrolling around on all your iPad music things,
当你在来回滑动查看 iPad 音乐库内容的时候
it's just asking for the ones it's currently showing. Right,
它就会去请求正在显示的那些歌曲
there's 50,000. It's only scrolling around to
一共有五万首，来回滑动的话
showing maybe 10 at a time. And so it's just asking
每次大概只会显示十首，它就是去让
the controller give me the next ten,
控制器给它接下来的十首
give me the ten here, and
给我这里的十首歌，然后
the controller turns around to the model,
控制器就转过去问模型
which is probably a nice fast SQL database or something, and
可能是很快的 SQL 数据库一类的
grabbing the data, and handing it off to the view. Okay, and
抓取这些数据，然后传递给视图
this uses the same mechanism where the table view again
这种方法同样的，列表视图
doesn't know anything about this as being an iPod
也是不知道这些数据来源，不知道是不是 iPod
music app, it just knows that it's the data provider, and
音乐程序，只知道它能提供数据
we call this kind of delegate the data source. All right, so
我们叫这种代理 data source，数据源
you'll see that as well, and both data source and delegate,
之后你也会看到。数据源和代理
very similar it's just kind of a different set of methods,
这两个很类似，只是是两套不同的方法
and these methods are of course dependent on the kind
当然这些方法取决于具体的
of UI element, they're not a preset list, depends on what's
UI 组件，并不是固定的，取决于
going on in that UI element. So that's the kind of
那个 UI 组件是干什么的。所以这就是
communication the view can have with the controller,
视图到控制器的通讯
it's structured, it's kind of predefined, things like that.
它是有标准的，提前制定好的
Because of all this communication going on in this
因为这个方向的所有这些通讯
direction we say the controller's job in an MVC is
我们说控制器在 MVC 里的作用
to interpret and format the models information for
是把模型的信息翻译成某种格式
the view. That's its primary purpose.
提供给视图，这就是它主要的目的
It kind of also goes the other way,
反方向它也要处理
It interprets user interaction in the view for the model.
把视图里的用户交互翻译成模型里的数据
It's the interpreter back and forth.
它负责当来回通讯的翻译
It's the center of all communication here.
是所有交流的中心
What about the model? Can the model talk to its controller?
那模型呢？模型能通知控制器吗？
Obviously not directly. Because the model is UI
肯定不是直接的，因为模型是与 UI
independent and the controller is fundamentally UI dependant,
无关的，而控制器根本上讲是取决于 UI 的
so it can't do it directly. But there is a mechanism for
所以不能直接沟通。但是有一种方法
the model to communicate, for example, if some data changes
让模型能够在比如数据发生改变的时候发出通知
and it wants any UIs that are interested out there
好让任何其他对此感兴趣的 UI
to update. And the way it does that is with a model that I
更新，它实现的这种方法我
call radio station model, and the model essentially
把它叫做电台模式。基本上就是模型
starts broadcasting on a certain known radio station.
在某个已知的电台上开始广播
And the controller up there it's just going to tune in and
而上面的控制器就会收听这个电台
when it hears oh something's changed on the models radio
然后听到模型电台说，发生改变的时候
station then it's gonna use its big green arrow,
那控制器就用它的“绿色通道”
to go talk to the model and get the date of the change, or
来访问模型，然后获得改变了的数据
whatever. So this is a radio station model. In iOS
之类的。所以它用的是类似于电台的机制。iOS 里
it's called notifications, or KVO, Key Value Observing, and
这叫做 notification，通知。或者 KVO，键值监听，Key Value Observing
we'll talk about those in a few weeks as well. So there is
这个我们几周之后也会讲。所以我们有
a way from the model to kind of broadcast, wow things
一种方法让模型来广播说
are changing. Now, some people have asked can a view tune in
这些发生了改变。有些人问视图能够收听
to a radio station? A View could only really tune into
某个电台吗？真要说的话，视图只能收听
a controller radio station like another UI thing, cuz
控制器的电台，或者某种 UI 相关的东西
a view is fundamental of UI, but even that's pretty rare.
因为视图是 UI 的基础，但即使有的话也是很罕见
Usually the radio stations are pretty much for
通常电台是用来让
the model to communicate hey something's happening in your
模型用来交流说你的数据发生了变动
data or whatever. This, MVC, a collection of MVC, is
这类的。这个 MVC，这个模型，视图，控制器的集合
generally only used to control one screen on the iPhone, or
一般只会用来控制 iPhone 上的一个界面
on the iPad. Maybe it can control little sub-place,
或者 iPad 上的一个界面。可能可以控制某个附属的界面
like maybe on an iPad, maybe one MVC controls one space,
比如像在 iPad 上，可能一个 MVC 控制一个界面
and another MVC controls another place, and
另一个 MVC 控制另一个界面
possibly a third MVC controls another space, but
然后可能第三个控制另一个界面，但是
you would never have more than one screen, in an iPhone,
但是在 iPhone 上你不会有多个界面
controlled by a single MVC. So the MVC kind of goes with
是由一个 MVC 同时控制的。所以 MVC 还会
a grouping of UI. Usually one screen, one iPhone screen
把 UI 分组，通常是一个界面，一个 iPhone
size worth of stuff. So most apps have tons of screens.
屏幕那么多的内容 。所以大部分程序都有很多个界面
You got your settings, you got all the different features in
你有设置界面，不同的功能
your app, tons and tons of screens going on. So
你的程序里有很多很多的界面
how do we build an app out of multiple MVCs?
那我们如何用多个 MVC 来构建一个程序呢？
Multiple MVC apps look like this. I have a bunch of MVCs
多个 MVC 的程序看起来是这样的。我有很多个 MVC
upright. All those purple things
所有这些紫色的
are all the controllers, and when one MVC wants to interact
是所有的控制器。当一个 MVC 想要和
with another MVC like right here, you see this right here,
另一个 MVC 交互的话，比如，你看这里这个
it always treats those other MVCs as part of its view. So
它总是把那个 MVC 当作是它的视图
these three MVCs down here are part of the view of this MVC.
所以下面这三个 MVC 是这个 MVC 的视图
So it has to talk to them in a blind and structured way.
所以它需要用标准化的匿名方式交流
These kind of act like generic, reusable components,
这些就像是通用的，可重用的组件
and we're gonna see how that works when we
我们将会看到这个是怎么运作的
start talking about multiple MVC apps, a week from Monday.
周一之后过了一周我们就会开始讲多个 MVC 的程序
Now the main thing that we wanna do here is not build our
注意我们讲主要的目的是让你不要编写
multiple MVC apps like this, where there's just green
一个像这样的多个 MVC 的程序
arrows talking everywhere, and the reason we don't want this,
绿色箭头到处都是。我们不想要这个的原因是
it is impossible to debug and find out what is going on
我们不可能调试这个，然后找出问题所在
inside our app, because if something changes in the UI,
在我们的程序里，如果 UI 发生了改变
we don't know which controller was doing it, or
我们不知道是哪个控制器干的
what model gave the data. We're just totally lost. So by
或者是哪个模型提供的数据。我们会毫无头绪
grouping them into these nice MVCs each screen on the phone
所以通过把他们分组成为很好的 MVC，每个手机上的界面
is very well contained and understandable, debugable,
都是隔离开的，而且方便理解和调试
manageable. Everybody got all that? So we're
是可管理的。大家都清楚了吧？所以我们
not gonna do things this way. This is do not do it this way.
不会先这样随意交流，千万不要这样做
Okay so the demo that I'm gonna do.
所以我要演示的是
We're going to do our concentration game.
我们会接着完成翻牌游戏
I'm just gonna create the model and
我会创建一个模型，然后
we're gonna hook the model up into it.
把模型整合进来
Along the way we're gonna learn all these other things.
同时我们会学习其他这些知识点
Again, this is a slide you go look at after the demo to make
同样的，这张幻灯片是给你们之后看的
sure you learn these things.
用来确认你收否学习到了这些
I won't get back to the slides. So once again,
我不会再回来讲幻灯片。那么
what's coming up, don't forget that Friday section at 11:30,
之后的安排，不要忘了周五的课是十一点半
on Friday, about Xcode and debugging, and then next week
星期五是关于 Xcode 和调试，然后接下来一周
we're gonna talk about Swift and some other iOS things, and
我们会讲 Swift 和其他一些 iOS 的内容
we're gonna do it all in with the Concentration app as
我们都会用翻牌游戏
a little bit like our demo land.
把它作为做演示的地方
I'll show you, talk to you about something, some slides,
我会讲解某些内容，给你看些幻灯片
and then we'll go to Concentration.
然后我们到翻牌游戏里
I'll show you how it actually looks. All right, here we are,
我给你看看实际上是什么样的。好，我们到 Xcode 里
back exactly where we were at the end of Monday. We've got
回到我们星期一下课的时候所在的地方。我们有
our view controller here. We're all ready along the way
我们的视图控制器，我们已经在运用
of MVC. Right here, in this story board, that's our V,
MVC 的路上了。这里我们的 storyboard 就是 V(iew)
our view, and right here, this is our C our controller. Okay,
我们的视图。然后这里就是我们的 C(ontroller)，控制器
so this is our controller, and this is our view.
所以这是我们的控制器，这是我们的视图
So we need the M. So let's go make the M right now. So
我们需要 M(odel)，那我们现在就创建这个模型
how do we make a new class or whatever in Xcode.
那在 Xcode 里我们如何创建一个新的类呢？
We go to file > new > file. That's how you create a new
我们的菜单栏的 File > New > File...，这就是
Swift file, or whatever, and when you do that, it's gonna
我们创建类似于新 Swift 文件的方法。当你点击之后，他会
offer you a lot of different kinds of iOS files you want,
提供很多种你可能想要的，有关 iOS 的不同种类的文件
but really these are the two that are most interesting.
但我们最关心的是这两个
This is if you wanna create a subclass of
这个是如果你想创建一个子类
a Coco Touch class, of an iOS class, like a subclass of
继承自 iOS 的 Cocoa Touch 框架的某个类
another view controller or something like that.
比如创建一个继承 UIViewController 的子类
But here we're talking about the model, non-UI, so
但我们现在是要模型，和 UI 无关，所以
we're going to pick a blank, totally blank Swift file.
我们选择空白的，完全空的 Swift 文件
This is asking the name, we always name the files that we
这里问文件的名字，我们总是把文件
are creating in Swift. We name it after the most
创建的 Swift 文件，依据
important class that's gonna be in that file. Now I'm gonna
文件里最重要的类命名。那我要
call my model, my main model class, Concentration,
把我的模型，主要的模型类叫做 Concentration
because it is the thing that implements the game
因为模型实现了游戏
Concentration, so it deserves the name Concentration, so
翻牌，所以应该用游戏英文名 Concentration 命名
that's what I'm gonna call it. By the way, I'm not gonna
所以这就是我给它的名字。顺便一提，我不会
put it, you see this group, this is the top level project,
把它，你看这里有个 Group，现在是项目的最顶层
you really wanna put it in the folder one level down.
你应该把它放在下一层的文件夹里
It's the same folder where your view controller it's
和你的视图控制器放在同一个文件夹里
a better place to put it than at the top level.
放那里比放项目最顶层要好
It'll work if you put it in the top level, but
放在最顶层也是可以的
it just looks nicer to put it down here. All right so
但是放在这下面会好看些。好
I'm gonna create this Swift file, it creates it for us.
我点 Create 创建这个 Swift 文件，Xcode 已经创建好了
To make it full screen here. Notice that all it says is
我把它全屏显示。注意这里唯一的代码是
import Foundation. Not import UI kit. This is not a UI file.
import Foundation 而不是 UIKit，因为只是和 UI 无关的文件
This is a model totally UI independent.
这个模型是和 UI 不沾边的
So I'm gonna make my class here.
我要在这里定义我的类
I'm gonna call it Concentration. Concentration.
我要把它叫做 Concentration
Okay, is my class, and when ever I build a new class,
好，这是我的类。每当我定义了一个新的类
I always wanna think about what its public API is.
我总是要考虑它的 public API，公开的应用程序接口
How many people know what the phrase API mean?
有多少人知道 API 是什么意思？
Well, almost nobody, okay. So, API stands for
好吧，基本没人知道。所以 API 是
Application Programing Interface. It's just a list of
Application Programing Interface 的缩写，其实就是
all the methods and instance variables in that class and
这个类所有的方法和实例变量的列表
the public API is all the instance variables and methods
而公有的应用程序接口就是所有实例变量和方法
that you're going to allow other classes to call. So it's
你允许其他类访问的那部分。所以
basically how you use this class, and next week we'll
基本上就是你能如何使用这个类，然后下一周我们
talk about how you actually make things private and
会讲如何让这些接口变为私有（private）的
public, but today we're not going to worry about that, but
或是公开（public）的，但我们今天不操心这个
I'm going to basically design my public API.
但我会先设计我的公开的应用程序接口
Now why, when I kind of design my vars and funcs right off
那为什么我要在一开始就设计我的变量和方法呢？
the bat here, And the reason is because to do that I have
原因是要能够设计 API 的话，我需要
to get the essentials of what is it that this thing does and
理解这个东西本质上能做什么，以及
how are people gonna use it. And
人们如何使用它。这样
that makes me think clearly as I go in to my design here. So
我设计的时候就能思路清晰。因此
I recommend doing this for
我建议你这样做
any class that you design. So a concentration game.
在设计任何类的时候都这样。那对于翻牌游戏
Remember, we had it up here? What are the essentials of it?
就是我们摆在这里的这个，它的本质是什么？
Well, one essential is it has some cards. That card,
它最基本的就是有一些卡片
those cards are arrays of cards or something,
那些卡片可以用一个卡片的数组来表示
not quite sure what, some kind of arrays of card. So,
我还不是很确定，某种类似于存放卡片的数组
that's a fundamental part of the Concentration game for
这就是翻牌游戏的基础
sure. What about, what can you do in the Concentration game?
那么你可以在翻牌游戏里做什么？
The only thing that you're allowed to do as a user is
玩家唯一能做的一件事就是
flip the cards over, right, choose cards. That's all you
把一张卡翻过来，对吧？选择一张卡翻面
can really choose cards. All the matching and
你能做的就是翻牌。对于配对
all that stuff is kind of internal implementation of
这些都是我们内部的实现
the Concentration game. From user's perspective,
翻牌游戏自己处理的。对于玩家而言
you're just touching on it. So I'm gonna need some func
你只是点一张卡片。所以我需要某个方法
that let's me choose a card. Okay, and
能让我选择一张卡片
the argument to this could be either a card, one of whatever
这个方法的参数，要么是张卡片，某个
this thing is which we're gonna define in a second, but
这个类的实例，Card 这个类我们等会儿定义
I'm actually gonna make it be a little more flexible,
但我实际会让它更灵活
I'm gonna make it be the index into this array. So when you
我接受这张卡在这个数组里的索引
choose a card, I'm gonna let you choose it by index
所以当你选择一张卡，我会让你选择它的索引
and that's just to be a little more flexible to different
这样可以更灵活地让不同的
kinds of UI's that might want to do this.
用户界面来实现这个功能
They might be index based. It's really not that big of
这些 UI 可能是基于索引的。这其实影响不大
a deal cuz you could always just look up the index in this
因为你总是可以通过索引查找
array all the time.
数组里的元素
But it's a little easier to subscript an array and
但确实把索引作为下标（subscript）访问数组元素
find something than to go the other way around,
比在数组中找到某个元素要简单点
do index of like we did last time. So that's it actually.
要比用上次的 index(of:) 简单。好了，这就完了
This is all, this is the entirety of the public API
这就是所有的，我们全部公开的应用程序接口
of my Concentration game. Could not be simpler.
我的翻牌游戏就这样，不能再简单了
Now the only thing here is we gotta define Mr.Card. So
但现在我们要做的就是定义 Card 这个代表卡片的类
we're gonna go file>new>file and create another Swift file.
我们还是 File > New > File... 创建另一个 Swift 文件
This one I'm gonna call card. Okay,
这个我把它叫做 Card
put it in the same place as everything else there.
把它和其他的放在一起
All right, again, this is not a UI thing.
好，同样这不是 UI 相关的
This is part of my model. So I have two things in my model.
这也是我模型的一部分。所以我的模型有两个部分
The Concentration game and this card. What's really
一个是翻牌游戏，一个是卡牌
interesting here is I'm going to make card to be a struct.
很有趣的是我要用 struct 关键字定义 Card
Not a class. Now what's the difference
而不是 class。那有什么区别？
between a struct and a class? Let's go ahead and
struct 和 class 有什么区别？让我们
get the concentration up here in the same time.
把 Concentration 类也同时显示出来
Can use my manual thing here. We've got card on the left and
我能够用 Manual 手动选择它。我们 Card 在左边
structure on the right. One's a class, one's a struct. Now
然后 Concentration 在右边。右边的是 class，左边是 struct
in a lot of other languages like C, a struct is just kinda
在很多像 C 语言一类的语言，struct，结构体
this little thing that holds a little bit of data.
就是某种存储少量数据的类型
It's nothing really that big a deal, but in Swift,
不是什么重要的东西。但 Swift 里
structs and classes are almost exactly the same.
结构体和类基本是一样的
They have methods, they have vars, very very similar. So
他们都可以有方法，有变量，非常相似
what is the difference between the two?
那这两个之间的区别是什么？
There's two major differences. There's some minor
主要有两个区别。有些小的
differences we'll run across as we going over this, but
区别我们等会儿会过一遍
there's two major differences between a struct and a class.
但是结构体和类两个最主要的区别
This is very important to understand this.
理解这个是非常总要的
Number one, struct, no inheritance.
第一，结构体没有继承
So you have no inheritance in struct that makes structs
所以结构体不能继承。这让结构体
a little simpler. Because if you have inheritance, you have
稍微简单了些。因为如果有继承
to kind of worry about all the things you're inheriting and
你必须要考虑继承的那些东西
what that might mean for you. The struct has no inheritance
考虑那对你来说意味着什么。结构体没有继承
so it's a little simpler than a class. Number two, and
所以它比类稍微简单些。第二
the most important difference, is that structs are value
也是最重要的区别，结构体是值类型
types and classes are reference types.
而类是引用类型
What does that mean? A value type,
那是什么意思？值类型
when you pass it as an argument, put it in an array,
当你把它作为参数传入函数，把它放进数组
even assign it to another variable, it gets copied.
甚至把它赋值给另一个变量，他都会被拷贝
This is very important to understand. It gets copied.
理解这个是非常重要的。他会被拷贝
And why is it so important that you understand this?
为什么你理解这个是非常重要的呢？
Why don't you just avoid structs?
那你为什么不干脆避免使用结构体呢？
Because you can't avoid structs in iOS.
因为你开发 iOS 是没法避免结构体的
Arrays are structs, ints are structs, strings are structs,
数组是结构体，Int 整数是结构体，String 字符串是结构体
dictionaries are structs, these are all structs.
Dictionary 字典是结构体，这些都是结构体
When you pass them around in your code,
当你把他们在代码之间传递的时候
they're getting constantly copied.
他们总是会被复制
Now you might be kinda like, whoa wait a second,
那你现在可能会想，等等
that is gonna be incredibly inefficient. No, because Swift
那会非常低效率。并不会，因为 Swift
is super smart about when it passes these things around.
非常聪明，在把这些结构体四处传递的时候
It doesn't copy all the bits of all the things of
它不会把所有这些的每个比特都复制
the array when you pass it. It passes it in a way so that it
当你把数组传入的时候并不会这样。它传递的方法是
only has to make copies, actual copies, when someone
只会在需要实际进行拷贝，也就是有人
modifies it. That's called a copy-on-write semantics, and
修改了它的值才拷贝。这叫做 Copy-On-Write，写时复制
that's the way Swift implements these value types.
这是 Swift 实现这些值类型的方法
So structs are value types. Classes are reference types.
所以结构体是值类型，类是引用类型
What's a reference type?
那什么是引用类型？
That's what you're used to in other languages.
那是你在其他语言里熟悉的
The thing lives in the heap. You got pointers to it. When
他们被存储在堆（heap）中，你保留指向它的指针
you pass it around, you're not passing the thing around.
当你传递它的时候，你不会把对象四处传递
You're just passing pointers to it.
你传递的是那个指针
And so you might have a whole bunch of code that
所以你可能有很多代码
has pointers to the same object. So
都拥有指向统一个对象的指针
you see the difference there?
你看出区别了吗？
So, structs are gonna take some getting used to because
确实要花些时间才能适应结构体
you're not used to when you pass things,
因为你还不适应，在传递的时候
it makes a copy. But you're going to see
他会拷贝这种机制。但你会看到
it provides an awesome semantic that you can really
它提供的这种很好的机制，你其实可以
use to your advantage. We're even gonna see that here
让它为你服务。我们甚至能够在这里看到
in a small way in our example, but you'll definitely start
在这个程序里它的体现。但写时复制，你肯定会
seeing it when you start using arrays and dictionaries and,
在开始使用数组和字典的时候看到
such, stuff like that. Okay, structs, card here,
或者使用类似的东西的时候。好，Card 结构体
what does a card need?
它需要什么？
Well same thing, let's think about its essentials.
同样的，让我们来考虑他的本质是什么
Certainly, a card can either be face up or not, so and
肯定有记录一张卡是否是面朝上的
it probably always starts face down, let's say.
多半不是，我们决定开始的时候是面朝下的
A card can be matched or not, probably starts out definitely
unmatched. You know a card also needs a unique identity.
Because we're playing a matching game and if we can't
tell the identity of the card, we can't match it against
another card. So we need some kind of identifier or
something, which really could be any type.
It could be a string or whatever. I'm gonna make
an Int because it's really easy to make a unique Int.
So, we definitely need that. Now,
some of you might thinking, oh,
okay a card also needs the emoji that's on it.
Like the pumpkin or the ghost. And very importantly,
no it doesn't. This card is UI independent.
So there's no way it can have emojis or jpeg images or
anything like that, that's all how you display the cards.
This is just how the cards behave, how the game works. So
you would never have an emoji in here, in this model. We're
in the model here not the UI. Very important to understand.
All right, so now we've got basically all of our API and
our model here. Let's get rid of some these errors. You see
that we still have this error class concentration has no
initializers, a very common error that we're used to.
That's because this var is never initialized, so
how do we create an array of cards, okay?
So this is now you're learning how to create an instance
of a struct or of a class. It's exactly the same.
And the way we do that is I'm just gonna say equals
open parentheses, close parentheses.
So this is just a type. It could be int or string.
It happens to be an array of cards. And I'm just putting
open parentheses, close parentheses after it. And
I could actually be putting various arguments in here. And
these correspond to those in ints I was telling you
about. Remember last time, I said class could have
an initializer, it's a special method called in it,
it can have whatever arguments you want.
You could have multiple in its. Array has an in it with
no arguments and what it does is it creates an empty array.
So the array exists, but there's no cards in it.
There's nothing in it. There are other, and you can go look
in the documentation, for other inlets that array has.
It has an it, for example, let's you reserve capacity for
a certain amount for performance reasons if you're
pretty sure you know how big there's going to be array.
You can create an array from another array and
it'll copy over the items from that other array,
so there are other in its, but the most common array in it
is this one where you just do nothing.
Now by the way, we're using this kind of easier to
understand syntax, but we would almost certainly use
this syntax. Array of Card. So I showed you last time.
So I've got an empty array of cards to work with right here.
I've got no warnings. So now, it's time to go
back to our controller and try to start using this model. So
were doing NBC were going back to our control. So
I'm gonna back over here. I'm gonna go to my ViewController.
let's have the Concentration on at the same time here. So
Actually, let's go,
we've got Concentration,
I'll make it small, there it is, and our ViewController,
so how am I gonna use my model in this controller? Well,
the first thing I wanna do is make that big green arrow,
the green arrow that points from my controller to my
model. And I'm gonna do that by creating a var
in my controller, and call it game. And it's gonna be of
type Concentration. There's my big green arrow. I can send
any messages I want to game, like, I can get at its cards.
I can choose a card, whatever. and I'm ready to go.
Now, look at the error I get, our favorite error,
Class ViewController has no initializers, because this
is not initialized. How are we gonna initialize this?
Let's see, we wanna do something similar to what we
did with this array over here. Let's try that, let's do
Concentration,this is probably not gonna work, right?
Because we didn't create an init with no arguments for
Concentration. But it did work!
How could this possibly work? The answer here is classes,
and Concentration is a class, get a free init with no
arguments as long as all of their vars are initialized.
And this only has one var, it's initialized, so
Concentration got a free init. We're initialized.
We don't actually need this type. Remember why?
Type inference, obviously Swift can figure out from that
line of code the game is of type Concentration, we don't
need to put that in there. But this was fun and nice that we
got this free initializer, but actually, it's no good.
It's not good enough. Because when we create a Concentration
game, we gotta think how many cards there are. Because
the Concentration game has to kinda load up this array over
here with all the cards that it's gonna use,
and we can't assume that a Concentration game only has 12
cards like we had on the board. Or only has four cards,
like our current UI here has. We actually need to create our
own init. So let's go, again, make some more space over
here. And add an init to our Concentration class.
Init. Now again, we get to have any arguments we want.
And what we need to create our game is we need to know
the number of pairs of cards. And that's gonna be an Int.
So this is the initializer that people are gonna
have to use to create a Concentration game.
Cuz we need this. So how are we gonna implement this init?
We need to create this many pairs of cards and
put them in here. Let's try and create one card.
Let card =, maybe we'll get lucky and
we can just say card. We got, that worked for
Concentration. Didn't work. Why didn't that work?
Because if you look over here to our card.
Let's bring up Mr. Card here. The card,
it has something that has to be initialized there.
Card is a struct. Now, structs get a free initializer
as well, but it's different than a class.
So this is another difference between structs and classes.
Struct, the free initializer they get, initializes all of
their vars, even if they're already pre-initialized,
like isFaceUp and isMatched. Watch this, okay,
I'm gonna just type card. Open parenthesis,
I'm gonna let Xcode show me the initializer, and
you can see that it just initializes every single one.
So I could do isFaceUp false, isMatched false,
the identifier, I guess I'm gonna have to make up some
identifier for this thing to do it.
So I could initialize a card like that, cuz I get a free
initializer. Classes never get this kind of free initializer.
They don't get the free initializer where they,
you can initialize all their vars.
That's purely a struct thing. But this is bogus, because
these are, start out false, so why, when I'm initializing,
do I have to say again they're false? If I want to get rid of
those, and to get rid of those, I have to add
an initializer here. So I'm gonna have an initializer that
just takes the identifier, which is an Int.
And then I wanna set this identifier right here equal to
this identifier right here. We've
got a couple of problems with that, with trying to do that.
One is this certainly can't be right. Identifier equals
identifier? That, that's just weird. One thing also notice
that in both of my inits, I didn't do an external name and
an internal name. You notice that?
I only did one, which means both the external name and
the internal name is the same. So one thing I could do to fix
that is make the internal name be different, like i.
And then I could say identifier = i.
You see? This is the external name,
I'm using it here when I call this init.
And this is the internal name, which I'm using inside here.
And now it knows that this identifier means that one. But
you know what? This is kinda gross. First of all,
I hate variable names like i. i is a bad variable name.
I just don't wanna have it here. But I can't really think
of another one here that's any better than identifier.
That's, identifier is a good name there. So
I actually want it to be same internal name and
external name. Now, inits are the one method that
usually has the same internal name and external name. Most
functions don't, but inits tend to. They don't have to,
but they tend to. So, now I'm back to saying this, but
it's not, I can't really distinguish between these two,
so how can I distinguish between two, these two?
This is the parameter. This is my identifier on myself.
Well, I can say, self. So, self., means my identifier.
This card's identifier. So now it knows we want this one,
and so this one is this one. That's kinda cool.
We got out of having that going on. All right, so
let's go back over here again.
We're able to create one card, great, worked good.
But we have to specify the identifier for the card. So
this really doesn't matter what the identifier is,
as long as it's unique. So I'm gonna create a for loop. So
pay attention, here's how you create a for loop in Swift.
It's a little different than other languages. It starts out
the same. For identifier, this is just for some variable. But
you don't say equals zero, less than 20, i plus plus,
we don't do any of that. Instead we use the word, in,
and then this right here can be anything in Swift that is
a sequence. And a sequence in Swift means anything where you
can start somewhere and go to the next one, go to next one,
go to the next one, and that's what a for loop does.
It starts somewhere, and it goes to the next one, and
goes to the next one, goes to the next one. So
what are some examples of sequences in Swift?
Arrays? Okay, obviously array, you could start at the first
element, and go to the next one, go to the next one,
till you get to the end.
String, a string is a sequence. First character,
go to the next character, go to the next character,
next character. The one I'm gonna use here is a really
cool sequence called a countable range. So
a countable range is a range, in other words, it has a start
and an end, and it's countable. In other words,
it knows how to count through it and go to the next space.
And there's special syntax in Swift because it's so
common to wanna make a countable range. And
it goes like this. The start of the countable range,
..<, which means from 0 up to and
not including the number of pairs of cards.
So this is a for loop that is going to go through,
why is that not cutting? I didn't select it,
I guess? Cut, there we go, paste. It's gonna go through
the number of pairs of cards. Now, there's another kind of
countable range creator here, which is .. Dot,
that means zero to here, including this one.
So, here, if I wanted to use that one, I would say one dot,
dot, dot cuz I only want this many cards. So, that makes
a countable range. In fact, if you look at this thing's type,
it'll be countable range. Okay, so now I'm going through
and creating a card here, but I need another card.
So I could say matchingCard = the same thing, right?
Create another card with the same identifier. Makes sense,
right? Now I have two cards that match that I can add to
my bunch of cards up here.
I always need two cards that match,
but you know what's amazing is I actually don't even need to
do this right here. I can just do this,
because when you assign a struct, which card is
a struct, to another variable, it copies it. So
matchingCard is a copy of card. Just by assigning it,
it makes it a copy. Now I have a card and a copy of it. So
I can say cards.append,
that's how you add something to an array, append the card,
and then cards.append the matching card, matchingCard.
So now I've added these two matching cards to my array.
And I'm going to do that number of pairs of cards
times. I've got my cards,
however I don't even need this matching card.
I can get rid of that, and instead just say append(card).
Because putting things in an array or taking them out also
copies the card. There are actually three cards involved
here. This one I create, the copy that gets put in here,
and another different copy that gets put here. So
understand that when you pass these structs around,
you are copying them.
Now later when we turn one of these cards face up,
the copy will actually be a real copy and
only one of them so it's not a pointer to the same card and
memory, it's actually two different cards. By the way,
another cool way we can do this different syntax is I can
say cards, which is an array of cards,
+= another array of cards, with those two cards.
Plus equals works with arrays. You can add arrays together
and this, putting this card in this array and
this card in this array copies it. And then we put it in
there, and in effect this array also gets copied
cuz array is a struct. All right, so we got that,
this is all going quite well. The only thing I don't really
like about this is it doesn't really seem right to me that
the concentration game has to pick the identifiers for
the cards, because the concentration game does not
care what the identifiers are.
All it cares is that they're unique. So really,
I don't wanna do this. I want to get this out of here, and
have the card figure out its own unique identifier. There's
no reason the card could just like pick 1 billion and 7.
And that's its, as long as that's unique and
it never gives out another card with 1 billion and 7,
then it should be unique. That's what I do.
I want this init to not have to take this identifier. But
if this init over here doesn't take the identifier, then we
gotta figure out how to create a unique identifier here. So
how are we gonna do that? Well, I'm going to teach you
another cool Swift thing, which is I'm going to create
a special kind of method. It's a static method.
It's a same syntax func but it has static before it, and
it's going to get a unique identifier. It's gonna return
an int that's gonna be unique. And every time I call it,
it's gonna return me another unique identifier.
It's just gonna return some unique identifier.
We're gonna have to make it work. Now, what is a static
function all about? A static function is a function,
even though it's in the card class, you can't send it
to a card. A card does not understand this message.
What understands this message is the type card.
You send it to the type itself.
So you can think of it kind of like a global function,
a utility function or something that's just tied to
the type. Does it make sense? You don't send it to a card.
You can't ask a card for a unique identifier.
You ask the card type. So, and that's what static means.
So here when I want to call this function,
I send it to the type card.getUniqueIdentifier.
That's getting it from the card type. Now how am I gonna
implement this get unique identifier? Well,
I'm gonna have a static var, cuz you can have those too.
So that's a variable that's stored with the type,
not with each individual card. These are scored with
each individual card, this is stored with the type.
And I'm gonna call this my identifierFactory,
I'm just gonna start out with = 0. And then in here,
what I'm going to say is Card.identifierFactory += 1 to
make it a new unique identifier. And then I'm gonna
return Card.identifierFactory. So now I'm returning a unique,
every time you call this, it makes a unique int,
cuz it starts at zero and makes a unique int each time.
Now, what's interesting is I don't really seen to say Card
dot because I'm in a static method, so I can access my
static vars without the Card. So that's kinda cool.
So I just want to take this little detour to show you how
you can do these nice utility methods or whatever,
utility vars on a type. So now let's go back over to
our concentration, over here cuz it's got a warning, let's
see what this warning is all about. It says immutable value
identifier, this, was never used.
It says consider replacing with underbar or removing it.
Well, we can't remove it because it's the control
variable of our for loop. But we can replace it with
underbar. Underbar in Swift means kind of ignore this or
I don't really care what this is cuz I'm not gonna use it.
And we've actually used this before, do you remember?
Back over here in our ViewController, touchCard,
it's external name was underbar. Which means don't
give an external name when you call this because remember
touchCard's kind of an Objective-C thing.
This target action, and so it didn't have external name and
so we just said, hey,
I don't want an external name. Similar kind of thing here in
Concentration, we're doing a for loop, we still want to do
this, this many times. But we don't care what identifier is
cuz we don't use it in here anymore. Got that? Okay,
the last thing we need to do here when we're initializing,
it's kind of left to do, is to shuffle the cards. cuz if we
don't shuffle the cards, then they're always going to be in
the same order all the time. It would be really easy to
play the game. I'm gonna leave that for your homework.
Your job is gonna be shuffle the cards there. It's gonna
require you to understand, again, this value type arrays,
or value types, etc. It's a pretty good exercise to
do that, so I'm gonna leave that for
you. We've solved the whole initialization problem. So
now we can go back over to our view controller over here. And
find it. There it is. And Concentration
right here needs to specify the number of pairs of cards.
numberOfPairsOfCards, and what number do we put here?
Right, I guess we could put four.
We know we have four cards in our UI.
But what if I wanted to add more buttons?
Now I gotta come back here and change this four?
Why don't we just count the number of card buttons,
remember? Card buttons, all those buttons are in there,
cardButtons.count. That's how many cards there are, and
we'll just divide by two. All right, make sense?
Let's so you can see this a little better.
I'm just gonna take the card buttons and divide by two. So
if I have four card buttons, that's two pairs, obviously.
Actually I should be a little careful.
If I had an odd number of cards,
I probably wanna round up. So if I had three cards I'd need
two pairs so I have four total cards.
I'll never be able to match that third card but
at least the game will have enough. Now, this is the right
thing to do but I got a very serious error here. Okay,
let's look at it. It says, cannot use Instance member
card buttons, right here, within a property initializer.
Oh yeah, look, var game that's a property and
I'm initializing it, that's a property initializer.
It says property initializers run before self is available.
Oh, remember I told you that in Swift you have to
completely initialize something before you can use
anything in it, before you can access any of its bars,
call any of its functions, anything.
Well that obviously we're not fully initialized yet
because we're in the process of initializing game. And
game is the one that's initialized so
we got a catch-22 here. How the heck are we gonna do this,
where one depends on the other? Where one var depends
on another. There's a couple of ways to address this.
But I'm gonna show you kind
of a cool one which is lazy. If you make a var lazy,
that means it doesn't actually initialize until someone grabs
it. Until someone tries to use it. As soon as someone tries
to use game, then it's going to initialize it.
Now by definition, because of that very same catch 22, no
one can try and use game until this is fully initialized.
So we win, it works perfectly. And lazy count as,
this var initialized. Counting that game of getting going
this way, so it's awesome. There is one restriction
about lazy though, that's not so nice.
Which is, it can not have a didSet. If you try
to add a didSet to it, like we did here with flipCount,
remember that? It's, you're gonna get an error here,
this is clash declaration blah blah blah, but basically what
it's saying here is you can't use property observers with
a lazy var. So if you need to use a property observer there,
you need to find out every time the game changes,
you're going to have to do a different way.
What are the other ways you can do it, by the way?
Well, you're going to
learn next week that there are methods that are called after
all these outlets get fired up. The system will call
a method and in there you can initialize your game.
And maybe in the mean time you make it an optional or
maybe even an implicitly unwrapped optional.
A little hint to you there. But you won't need that for
your homework though. You'll be able to do this for
your homework. Okay, so it's good. Now we have the game,
the big green arrow. There our controller is talking to our
model. What do we need to do next?
Let's go back and look at our Concentration API again, see
what we need to do. It seems like there is two things,
we have used this part of the API. We got these two left, so
let's do this one, chooseCard. We got to tell
the concentration model when our card is chosen.
And we know exactly when that is in our controller.
It's right here in touch card. Whenever a button calls touch
card, we know a card's being touched.
And instead of doing all this flip card with emoji choices
thing right here, I'm just gonna tell my game hey,
choose this card. Okay?
So instead of handling it myself, I'm letting the model
handle it. So, it's the one that's figuring it out.
But there's something interesting to note here,
is that when I tell the model choose this card,
it might change the game might change. And in fact, I hope it
does change cuz it's supposed to be doing matching and
all kinds of stuff. So it's gonna change. So now,
we have to update our view from the model, okay?
Our view is now a little bit out of sync with the model,
because when we chose this card,
that could have caused the game to change.
So we need a method like updateViewFromModel or
something like that. Some kind of func down here,
func updateViewFromModel. And what's that gonna do?
That's gonna use the other part of this API right here.
It's gonna look at all the cards and
make sure all our card buttons match, right?
Whether they're face up, whether they're matched,
all that business. We look in the game,
find out, and make sure our card doesn't match. All right,
so how to we implement this updateViewFromModel?
Well I wanna go through all the card buttons and
look at the game and set it up appropriately. So I could do
another for loop where I say for button in my cardButtons,
okay? And just go through and now each button will be if we
look at the type of this it's going to be a UI button. See?
Because this is a sequence of buttons. Isn't that cool?
All right? But I'm actually not gonna do that.
I'm gonna do something else because I need to look up this
button's index in this card thing so I'm gonna do my for
loop by index. In the card buttons array which I could do
with 0 dot dot less than cardButtons.count, okay.
Everybody understand this counter range right here, but
I'm not gonna do that either I'm gonna show you another
way, cardButtons.indicies, okay. cardButton.indicies
Indices is a method in array. Okay, that returs
you a countable range of all the indexes into the array.
In fact, if I option click on Indices, look at it's type,
Countable range of int. Okay? So,
that's a kind of a cool way to go through all the indices.
And now that I have the Indices,
I can say let button equal our cardButtons at that index.
And let the card equal the game's cards
at that index. So this is awesome. I've got the button.
I've got the card. I just have to make them match up.
So I'm going to say, if the card is faced up,
then I'm gonna do my face up UI, which is what,
that's this one. With the white background there.
So let's do that. Otherwise else, if it's faced down,
I want the orange background thing right here, that there.
And now I don't even need flip card,
let's get rid of flip card. Everybody,
see what I did ther? I just made it so
that the button matches the card. There's one other thing,
by the way, cards can be matched. They have is matched.
Remember, when we put that in the card, is matched. So
I need to handle that. And the way I'm gonna do that,
is I'm gonna make matched, cards, so
that I can see them. If the card is matched,
I'm just gonna take it out of the UI by making it background
be clear instead of orange, when it's matched and
face down. If it matches and still faced up, I don't want
it to be clear, I want people to see you gotta a match.
But once it turns back face down in Match I don't want it
to show. So the way I'm gonna do that is by doing this,
card.isMatched. Matched. Question mark.
Either this thing or this. Does everyone know this
question mark colon? We have it in C and other languages as
well. So here instead of orange I want it to be clear.
How do you get clear? Well if you go to any color
chooser, if you look at the bottom it says opacity. That's
how transparent the color is. So that's fully opaque, fully
transparent. In other words, clear. So if the cards match,
I'm gonna make it clear. Now, there's one other error here.
It's this, emoji. Now, this emoji used to be something we
grabbed out of this emoji choices based on the index and
all that. I'm gonna postpone implementing that here by,
it's calling a function emoji for card. And
this is gonna be a function I'm gonna do down here.
Let's scoot this up a little bit so
you can see it, func emoji for card which is a type card, is
gonna return an emoji and I'm gonna return question mark for
now. We just returned question mark,
we're gonna deal with taking these emoji choices up here.
We're gonna put these emoji choices and eventually,
we're going to pick one of these emojis. Randomly,
and put it on the card, and actually I have a few more
emojis here, little more Halloween emojis.
So we're gonna pick one of these many emojis right here,
and put it on the card, but for
now, I'm just gonna do question marks. Cuz I really
wanna get back to my UI and make sure I haven't broken
anything with all this MVC machinations. Let's go back
to our model and do something when a card is chosen. So
all I'm gonna do, eventually we gotta make it match. But
all I'm gonna do now is have the model flip the card over.
The model's just gonna flip the card over for now, so
here we are in chooseCard in our model. And so
I'm gonna say, if the card at that index is face up,
then I'm going to set the card at that index to
be isFaceUp = false, and else, I'm going to make this true.
True, so I'm just gonna flip the card over, everyone
believe me that that flips the card over? Yes, just gonna,
if it's face up, it goes face down, if it's face down,
face up, so that's it. So now when we run our app,
there's no emoji, everything's gonna be a question mark, but
the card should flip over. And this is the entirety of our
UI, here's our controller, that's all there is.
And here's our model over here, plus we have the card,
which is just keeping track of isMatched and
doing that identifier. So let's take a look,
let's run this, make sure we haven't broken anything.
It's always nice when you make MVC and you divide it up,
try to make your model to just do something simple.
Just so you can make sure that your MVC is actually working.
Here we go, sure enough, it appears to be flipping these
cards over. Okay, excellent, so all we need,
we have two things left to do. One, get emoji on these cards,
two, make it actually match, make it be a real game.
One thing is a controller thing, the emoji,
another thing is the model. So let's go to our controller
right here, and do this emoji thing. Now in teaching you and
showing you this emoji thing, I'm gonna show you and
teach you how to use a dictionary. A dictionary,
it's very important to cloud,
does everybody know what a dictionary is?
Like a hash table, it's just a data structure where you can
look something up and get a value for a certain thing.
So we're gonna use a dictionary,
and our dictionary looks like this, I'm gonna call it emoji,
and its type is gonna be a dictionary.
Now, dictionary is also a generic type like array, but
you specify the type both of the key, which I'm gonna
have be a int, cuz it's gonna be a card identifier, and
the value, which is a string, an emoji.
So this emoji dictionary, I'm going to look up the card
identifiers to get the emoji that goes on that card.
Everybody got that, gotta understand that before we move
on here. So how do I create one of these dictionaries,
exactly the same as I did with array.
I'm just gonna do open parentheses,
close parentheses, which creates an empty dictionary.
So this is a dictionary of ints mapped to strings, but
it's empty. Now down here in emoji for
card I'm just gonna look in this dictionary and
get a card. So let's say let chosen emoji equal, and
here's how you look something up in a dictionary. You say
the name of the dictionary, open square bracket,
the thing you wanna look up. And this had better be an int,
because this is a dictionary that looks up
ints and gives you back strings, and this is gonna be
a string. If I alt-click, option-click on this,
is that going to be a string, obviously not, or I wouldn't
be asking that question. Let's see what this chosen emoji is,
you think it would be a string, oh, what is that? What
type is that, anyone want to venture, I heard it out there
whispered, an optional. It returns an optional, why is it
returning an optional instead of returning a string? Well of
course, because when we look something up in a dictionary,
it might not be in there.
The thing we looked up isn't necessarily in there, and
if it's not there, we're gonna get back not set,
the optional not set. If it is in there, we're gonna get
the optional set, and it's going to be a string as its
associated value, because of course, a string is what's in
the dictionary. Everyone, understand that looking
something up in the dictionary returns an optional.
By the way, see this kind of thing,
you know how we have that special array syntax,
open square bracket, type, bits in the array.
We have the same thing for dictionary,
it looks like this, open square bracket.
Open square bracket, the key,
colon, the value type. So that's,
dictionaries and strings are the most common things we're,
data structures we're using. So we have special syntax for
both of them, so that's what declaration of a dictionary.
That's exactly the same as the thing I just blanked out,
dictionary, int, string.
So we could, since we know this returns,
this thing is an optional, we could do if let here. But
I'm gonna show you a different way to deal with optional. So
you know how to do exclamation point, which we definitely
don't wanna do here. Because, for example,
this dictionary starts out empty, so if we do exclamation
point here, it's gonna crash every time, so that's no good.
And we could do if let, that would be safe, but I'm gonna
show you another way that we often deal with something that
might be optional. Is that we just check to see,
if this thing does not equal nil, then we can exclamation
point it. I can return this thing exclamation point, and
it's safe because I checked to make sure it's not nil first.
So that's another way to deal with optionals, just check and
make sure it's not nil, and
then you can exclamation point it. And then the else,
I guess if we can't find the emoji in the dictionary, we'll
just return question mark, so we'll kinda give up and
just show question marks. Now, this code is so common to want
to get something that's an optional, and
if it's not, if it's set, then use it. But if it's not set,
do some other well-defined thing like this, but you can
write this with a special operator, looks like this.
Return, return, this thing right here.
But if it's nil, question mark, question mark,
return a different thing. So this is return this, but
if it's nil return this. Very common,
that's exactly the same code as this, exactly the same. So
we do not need that, everyone got that syntax,
it's very common to do this. So we're awesomely looking
up the card identifier in our emoji dictionary and
returning emoji, hopefully. But we never put anything
in that dictionary, so it's always gonna return a question
mark, so how do we put something in the dictionary?
Well, I'm gonna put them in the dictionary on demand,
as they are used. So every time someone asks me for
the emoji in a card, I'm gonna check and
see. If this emoji for that card is currently nil,
then I'm gonna put an emoji in the dictionary for that card.
So I'm kind of just in time loading up of this dictionary,
now, how am I gonna do that? I'm going to take one of these
at random, and put it in this dictionary, so let's get
a random index. I'm gonna let randomIndex equal something,
I'm gonna use this nice Swift function called
arc4rando_uniform.
So arc4rando_uniform is a pseudo-random number
generator, and it generates a random number between 0 and
this upper bound. Do you see it says_uppe_bound,
which is an unsigned int, 32 bit integer.
It will generate a random number between 0 and that,
not inclusive of that number. Which is exactly what I want,
where the upper bound is, how many things are in this array?
Cause I want an index into this array between zero and
however many things are in the array minus one. So here,
the upper bound,
I'm just gonna say emojiChoices.count.
Now this is great, but it doesn't work. I get an error,
and what does the error say? It says cannot convert value
of type int to unexpected argument type unsigned 32 bit
int. Our for random totally works only with unsigned ints.
Whereas this array's count is an int. Not an unsigned int.
And Swift never does automatic type conversion never.
It does never automatically converts from into an unsigned
enter from into a double. You have to explicitly convert it.
And so how do you convert types in Swift?
This is why I'm showing you this so
that you'll know how to convert types in Swift
you have to create a new thing and
use the initializer of that new thing to create one. So
here, I wanna create A uint32, an unsigned int 32. So I have
to call uint32 initializer to create a uint32. Luckily,
uint32, which is a struct, by the way, just like INT,
just like string, just like array, just like dictionary,
just like card. These are all structs.
It has an initializer that takes an int.
Exactly what I want, okay? So I can create a UInt32 by
passing it an int emojiChoices.
That's why it's suggesting this fix right here.
So I'm gonna do that, fix. You see what it did? UInt32,
open parentheses. The argument to its init is an Int.
It knows how to do that. Now we're not there yet.
Because look at the return value here, randomIndex.
It's also an unsigned integer, and that's no good.
Because I want to use it as an index into this array. And
we know that indexes are not unsigned ints,
although they probably should be. They are ints. Okay,
just for mostly for backwards compatibility issues.
So I need to convert this whole thing to an int, luckily
int Has an initializer that will take an unsigned int and
turn it into an int. Okay, so now I have random index here.
It's an int, it's suitable for indexing into this array.
It's a random index in there. So to get it, I can say emoji
sub card.identifier. Now to put something in A dictionary.
You just say equals and the thing you want. Emoji,
choices, sub, random, index. But I'm not, this is not quite
what I'm gonna do. This would work kind of.
The only problem with this is, I could get two identifiers
that use the same emoji. So instead of just grabbing
something out here, I'm gonna remove it. Okay, when I use
one of these emojis, I'm going to remove it out of here so
I never use it again. So to do that, I'm going to use
a different method in array than subscripting called
remove at. And I'm just gonna remove at the random index.
So remove at returns the thing it removed. And so it's gonna
pick one of these emojis out of here and return it.
And I'm gonna put it in the dictionary. Everybody got
that? Now there's only one other thing here,
which is what if emojiChoices.count is zero.
In other words, what if I've used all the emoji
in emojiChoices, I've pulled them all out of there?
That's going to cause a problem. ran, arc4random can't
take zero because it goes from zero To that number minus 1.
And it's an unsigned int, so it can't be a minus number.
So we're gonna have to protect against that case.
So I'm gonna say if emojichoices.count
is greater than 0, then I can grab
an emoji out of there and use it. But if
it's less than that, if it's equal 0 then I can't do this.
And then I'm stuck with question mark down here. By
the way cool thing in Swift, you see how we have back to
back ifs here. You can put back to back ifs on the same
line by just separating them with comma, okay,
then you don't need the embedded ifs right there.
And it's nice especially when things are related, like look
at how this cut line of code reads. If the emoji for
this card identifier is not set and
if we have emojiChoices, then go get one, All right?
Okay, so let's see if this works. Let's go and run and
see if we're grabbing a random emoji out of there and putting
them in one of our four cards. It's pseudorandom by the way,
so you're gonna see that it's not super random.
But anyway, all right, so let's look.
Oh yeah, look, we got a random emoji. Oh there's another one,
little candy, hopefully these two are the same, yay!. Okay
so it's working. Okay it's looking it up by identifier,
picking emoji and using that emoji for that identifier
on all cards. And hopefully it's random. Let's stop again.
So we've got the devil guy, and the candy here.
Cross your fingers that pseudo random generator does it,
let's see. Uh oh, devil guy, oh we got the cat,
the scared cat or whatever that is, the screaming cat. So
we're getting random, this looks like it's working.
So we've got our UI fully functional here.
So the only thing that's left to do now
is make this thing play Concentration and
that's purely a model thing. So to make
that work I'm going to bring up my model. And
I'm only going to put code here in my model.
Right now it flips cards over. We'll stop that.
Instead we're gonna have it play the game. And
as part of implementing this, I'm gonna use an optional.
Because I know you're all still except for
this guy who asked this great question. You're all still not
quite sure I understand the optional thing.
So here's a chance, case where I'm gonna use an optional
as part of my Fundamental semantic implementation
of this method. So here we go.
The first thing I'm gonna do when a card is chosen is
I'm gonna ignore a card that's already been matched. So
if you choose a card that's on the board that's already been
matched to another card, I'm just gonna ignore it. So
I'm gonna say if the card that you chose, card of the index,
isMatched. Then I'm not gonna do this, so
I'm gonna say if it's not Matched then do it,
if it is Matched then don't do this. This notch,
just like any other language means not, the opposite of
this Bool. I'm gonna ignore all Matched cards.
Now what am I gonna do? There's three cases here
that can happen. One, no cards are face up. If no cards
are face up when I choose a card it just flips it over.
That's all it does. Another option is two cards are face
up, either matching or not matching. If that's true,
when I choose another card it needs to flip those cards face
down cuz I'm starting a new match now. The third option is
there's one card face up and I choose some other card.
Now I need to match. I need to see if they match.
So those are the three options. So I want to
really keep track of the option where there's one card
face up because that's where I really have to do the work.
I have to try and see if they match. So
I'm going to create a var to keep track if there is one and
only one card face up.
I'm going to call it indexOfOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
and of course its an index so its going to be an int.
Now whats the value of the indexOfOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard if
no cards are face up? What's the value of that if two
cards are face up? Ah, interesting.
I think this wants to be optional. You see why, because
in those cases where there's not one index of a one and
only face card, then this going to be not set,
cause there is not one and only face card. So this
is a great use of optionals right here. So all the time in
my game, when there's one and only one face up card, this
going to tell me the index of it so I can match against it.
And all the other times this is gonna be nill and
I'm gonna know I don't have to do any work. I don't have to
do any matching because there's no card to match
against. So what does the code look like to use this?
I'm going to say if I can let a match index,
which is a local variable, equal this index of one and
only face up card right here, then I have something to
match. By the way, I wanna make sure that that match
index of that thing is not equal to the card you chose.
If there's only, only, if there's one and
only one face of card and you chose that,
it's going to ignore that. You have to choose a different
card. This inside this curly brace right here is, you know,
check if cards match. And then outside right here is what?
Either no cards or
two cards are face up, so I can't match. So
in that case I'm gonna need to turn the cards face down and
have the card you chose be the only face up card.
And then I'm gonna set it to be the index of the one and
only face up card.
Let's do all that. Let's check if the cards match,
really easy if the cards match index its identifier
equals the cards of the index you chose. This is choose card
at index. If they match, then I'm gonna mark them matched.
Cards of match index is matched and
the cards that you chose is matched.
So I matched them, excellent. Now, even if they don't match,
what happens when I chose that second card right there? Two
things happen, one, I gotta flip up the card you chose.
Cuz you chose a card that was face down, right there so
I'm gonna say cards sub index is...
Is face up is true, cuz you chose a card,
I'm flipping it up of course. And number two and
most importantly the index of the one and only face up card
equals nil. Because now there are two matched cards,
two, matched or unmatched, two face up cards. So
there is not a one and only face up card. So it's nil, so
it's perfectly legal to to set an optional to nil. So that's
what we do if the cards match, that's all we have to do.
Now here we either have no cards or
two cards are face up. In this case,
I'm gonna turn all cards face down. Now they might already
all be face down but so it's a little of wasted work.
I'm just gonna go for flip down index in, what?
In my cards' indices. Cards.indices,
that's all, that's a countable range. Remember,
this is a countable range right here, of all the indexes
of the flip, in my cards. So for each one of the cards,
I'm gonna say card at the flipDownIndex.isFaceup= false.
I just turned every single card on the board face down.
But now you've chose a card, so I'm gonna turn that card
that you just chose back to face up. .isFaceUp = true and
of course since I just turned all the cards face down and
turned one card faced up, what is the index of the one and
only face up card? It's this index. I just turned it
faced up so, by definition it's the only card.
And this ladies and gentlemen what do we got here? Oh this
is cardsindex.identifier got to compare the identifiers.
This is the entirety of the concentration game logic,
that's it, that's all that's necessary.
And can you see how having this optional
right here kinda made it very simple and straightforward?
Because it's easy for me to track the card I want it to
match against all the time. And it was easy for
me to tell whether there was one to match it against or
not, all contained in one little variable that had a lot
of information it it. That's it, let's go see if our
app is working. It should just work, I mean once you make
the model, do what its suppose to do the UI doesn't care.
It's just presenting what the model has, so
it should just work. So let's try it here. All right,
we've got this, the cat, oh, there's the screaming face.
Now what should happen when I click another card?
It should flip them all face down.
It didn't match, this didn't match, so
it should flip these all face down. Turn the new one face
up, and now that optional's gonna be set. So
let's try it. Sure enough it turned them all face down and
turned this one up. Now what happens if I choose a match?
Now they've both been marked matched. Now the next time I
click on a card, it's gonna turn them face down.
They're gonna be both face down and matched, so
they're gonna get a clear background and
we're not gonna be able to see them, watch.
Now that the game is done. Now in your homework you're gonna
add a new game button which is what you would press at this
point. I won't play another game. Last thing
to do here and we have time luckily is to add more cards.
Because four cards is kind of a boring game so
let's go here to our UI. We've got our UI. I made my
buttons here be 80 points wide which I kinda recommend you do
for your homework. Because 80 points wide,
they fit really nice four across okay? Let's put them
up,now I'm gonna use the little blue lines to help me
place them here. If you use the blue lines look,
four of them at 80 points each fit right across. And
then I'm gonna make some more. I'm gonna select them and
copy paste. Use the blinds, the blue lines paste some
more, let's have 12 of them here.
And I need to make sure that everything is connected so
let's look at like touch card. Hey, they're all sending touch
card, great. How about card buttons? When we copy and
paste it doesn't put them into that card buttons outlet
array of buttons, so we need to do that.
So I'm just going to do ctrl+drag.
Now if you really had 12 cards or more than 12 cards, in real
life you'd probably wouldn't use an outlet collection.
You would probably go in your code and go find all these
things, you could probably do it all in one or
two lines of code actually. But you really haven't learned
enough from me about how the view hierarchy works and
all these things to do that. So for your homework
you're just gonna have to be doing some control dragging
like I am to hook them all up. They're all hooked up,
they're all hooked up. Our flip count label's hooked up.
Our UI looks all set. I haven't changed anything but
that. I didn't go change any code anywhere. Okay, I just
put more buttons in my UI. And because I built this nice,
flexible UI that can really handle any number of cards,
this should just work. Here we go,
let's try. We got candy, apple,
no match. I have bat, no match.
How about pumpkin? Oh candy I think I remember candy,
was it maybe right here? Yes,
woo ho we found the candy it was right next to each other.
Let's try something else. Okay how about this one, apple,
no.,no match. Oh, apple oh, this is a pretty easy game.
I don't know why everyone thinks Concentration's so
hard, look at that. Okay,
all done. Okay so why is this game so easy?
Well, because you guys have not done your homework yet,
which if you remember back here Concentration we have
this little to do. To do by the way is a special comment.
If you look at the top line of your thing right here, which
shows you which file you're choosing. It also shows you
within that file with all your methods and properties and
if you put //to do, it shows up. See shuffle the cards.
All right, see you on Monday. >> For
more, please visit us at Stanford.edu.
>> 更多课程详见 stanford.edu