本字幕由志愿者义务贡献，采用许可协议
知识共享 署名-非商业性使用-相同方式共享 3.0 美国
Stanford University. >> Okay,
斯坦福大学
well welcome to lecture number three of Stanford CS193P,
欢迎参加斯坦福 CS193P 课程
fall of 2017 and 18 academic year.
2017 至 18 学年的第三节课
Today mostly, we're gonna talk about some Swift stuff.
Now, you've hopefully done your homework for the reading,
so some of the stuff will be kinda summary, but
some of this is really not covered in the reading.
So I'm trying to give you the full picture of stuff,
that reading is really great but it is great concise.
I know you probably feel like well,
that was a lot of reading for something that's concise, but
it is quite concise. So I'm gonna try and
cover some of the other stuff. But before I do all that,
I'm gonna do a little, what I call a teaser demo of
auto-layout where I'm gonna show you how we can make
our UI in concentration look good when we rotate the phone,
or when we a run on little bit different sized iPhone, or
whatever. I call it a teaser because I don't intend to
teach you auto layout which is the feature that allows
us to do that. It's just to show you what's possible.
We'll actually have a whole lecture on auto
layout in about three weeks I think. But then,
after I do that little demo, I'll be back. I'm first gonna
take just one minute to review what you should have
learned by what we did last week and I'm literally just
gonna read it off a list with quick examples. And you can
kind of say in your head, oh yeah, yeah I got that,
I got that or oh wait, I did not really understand that and
that's a prompt to go back and look at it.
Then we'll dive into this long list that you see up here,
of various Swift things. So let's start with this demo I
was talking about, this auto-layout demo.
What we're gonna do here, and I apologize for any technical
problems we have here because, actually, my computer died,
and I had to put it. This is all brand new computer, so
I hope everything's installed properly. But here's the code,
I think, that we had at the end of the last lecture.
And the UI looks pretty good. We laid it out.
But I just did this by dragging these things and
using the little dash blue lines to put them
in position. And when we run this thing, it looks okay but
only on an iPhone X and
only in portrait mode like this. If I were to for
example, rotate this iPhone to the side which I can do
in a simulator by going, Hardware, rotate left or
right, you can see that my UI looks like this. My buttons
are kind of all jammed in the corner here. I've lost flips,
it's down here somewhere. I can't even see it.
Still works, but it's kind of off in the middle of nowhere.
What we really want is for this UI to spread itself
out and fill the whole space that's involved. By the way,
you can also rotate your device with Command and
the arrows. Kind of a cool way to flip back and
forth. All right, so how are we gonna do that?
How are we gonna make our UI expand? Let's go ahead and
open up here, give ourselves some more space.
And also I'm gonna zoom in a little so
you can see. Another thing I'm gonna do is we're gonna be
using these blue lines, the dashed blue
line that appears as you move things around as part of this.
So I'm gonna change my background from black
to back to white temporarily, just so
that we can see that those blue lines and
stuff a little bit better. So I'm just gonna go to white.
When we come to run, I'll turn it back to black.
So this is purely for dealing development issues here. So
it's really kinda two things I need to do to make this work.
One is, I need to kinda take all those buttons and
make them stick to the edges, right?
So that when they rotate and
the edges get longer and skinnier, they stick.
Right now, everything's stuck to the upper left corner.
The upper left corner, you're gonna find out next week,
is the origin of drawing. In IOS where everything is kinda
stuck up to the upper left and then just, so
when we rotate it all, it just goes off the bottom,
we can't see it. So that's really what we need to do, but
to stick them to the edges,
we also kind of need to group them together. Because when
the edges pull this group of 12 buttons apart,
they all need to kinda share that space.
So there's two things we have to do.
One is group them together, one is pin them to the edges.
So we're gonna do that with two different features in IOS.
One, the grouping things together,
we're gonna do with stack view. Okay, so UI stack view
is just another class in IOS like UI Button is a class and
UI label is just another view in fact. And
what it does is it will take other views, like let's
say these four buttons and it will stack them together.
Now, it only knows how to stack horizontally or
vertically. It can't stack 12 of these things in two
dimensions like this. So I'm gonna have to make three
horizontal stacks out of this group, out of this group, and
out of this group. But then I'll take those three stacks
and stack them vertically. Cuz it's perfectly fine to put
stacks inside stacks, all right? And once I do that,
I'll have all 12 of these kinda stocked together. And
then I can pin it to the edges and they'll stretch out. So
how do we make this stack use?
Super simple, you just select it here. Let me zoom in so
we can really see what's going on here. We only need the top
part for now. So I deselected these four things.
I'm going down to this button right here.
You see this button, embed and stack?
Well, that's what it does. It embeds in stack.
And it embedded it. Now, couple of things.
One is, it made the buttons as small as it could when you put
in the stack. It has 50 point font, remember, for
those emojis. So that's just as small as they'll go.
It also has no spacing between. But I can put spacing
in-between by just selecting it. It was left selected after
I stacked. And going over here to the inspector because this
stack view, just like a button, can be inspected,
right? And you can see it made it horizontal,
it kinda noticed my buttons were mostly horizontal. So
it picked horizontal. And so here's how I set the spacing.
I go down here. I'm gonna use a standard spacing.
There's a lot of places when you're doing UI design where
you can pick an UI standard value and
it'll pick a standard spacing.
This is a standard spacing between buttons.
And you wanna use that pretty much as much as possible.
That way, your UI will be spaced like other UI and
you will feel like rolling on the same page as
UI designers across all these apps. Also I wanna make sure
that these four buttons get equal amount of space. Okay,
whatever space I am given here gets equally distributed and
I do that with this distribution thing here,
I say fill equally. Alignment just means I fill the whole
space, I could have these things being centered or
kinda pushed up to the top of the stack but
I'm gonna have it fill the whole space. So that's it.
So I'm just gonna do the same thing with these two rows.
So this one go down here, embed in stack,
this group right here embed in stack. Oops,
I did it twice there. Now I'm gonna select both of these.
Make them fill equally and standard value spacing. So
now I've got three horizontal stacks. I'm gonna stack these
together, I'm gonna select them. By the way,
dragging to select is really an awesome way to select.
I highly recommend you do that rather than trying to click on
things. Because by the way, let's say I try to click on
here to select this row. Oops, I selected the button inside.
I didn't want that, I wanted the whole row. But
if I just drag, not control drag but regular drag here,
it selects the thing that I intercepted with my drag.
Anyway, so I'm gonna select all three of these with drag.
And I'm gonna go embed in stack. You put them in
a vertical stack. You notice this time it's vertical,
cuz it noticed those three things are vertical.
If your things are random,
it'll pick the one that it thinks is the most likely.
You can always change it by going here and
changing it to the other one. So we have vertical,
we also wanna fill equally, top to bottom here, and
we also want standard spacing. So
it's great. We got our buttons in this nice grid.
They're all Perfectly laid out in this rectangle. Now,
we want to pin this rectangle to the edges. Okay, so
that when the device rotates, or if the device was bigger,
like if it was an iPhone 8 Plus, or
something like that and it was wider, so
that it would all just stretch out. So, the way we do
that is first I'm going to use those dash blue lines.
I picked up this thing. Again, picking it up,
you wanna select it first, then pick it up.
If you don't select it first and try to pick it up, oops,
you might try and pull one of these things out of there.
Okay? So, be careful about that. All right.
So, I'm gonna use the blue lines. I'm gonna
put this where it kinda suggests for
the upper left hand corner.
You see that? That's pretty much where the blue line,
that would be the standard spacing from the edges.
That's what the blue lines are telling you.
This is a standard place to put this. Now,
I need to pin it and the way we make relationships between
views and the UI like pinning them to each other and
stuff is with control drag. Exact same way that we made
a relationship between our UI and our code,
by dragging the code, we do the same thing between views.
So, I'm gonna control drag from this already selected
box here to the top. Okay, so I'm just dragging up towards
the top, and when I let go it's going to say, okay,
what relationship do you want between that view and
the top. And there's various relationships you can have,
like I said, in three weeks we're going to have
a whole lecture on these relationships, but
at the very top is the one Top Space to Safe Area.
You see that Top Space to Space Area? The safe area
is a safe edge around the screen where you can
safely draw without overlapping some other UI.
So, here it's putting it right under the place where all
the cameras and face recognition stuff is all in
here. So, it's to keeping it below that. Now, if I had
other UI on this, like tab bars, or title bars, or
whatever, then the safety area would be inside those. So,
we wouldn't overlap our titles and stuff. It's really cool.
So, I'm gonna put this top space little pin, so
I'm kinda connected it and you can see this blue line appears
right here. Okay? This blue line here, long blue line.
It represents that pinning and I can even click on it. Okay,
and when I click on it, look, it's inspectable in the top
half here. Okay? And it's just telling me that un-pinned
from the safe area top to the top of that stack view. And
we're zero points away from it.
We wanna be right up against that safe edge.
That's where the blue dashed lines told me to put it, so
that's where I'm gonna put it. Now, we can do the same thing
to the left edge over here, so I'm gonna control drag over.
This time it says, Leading Space to Safe Area.
Now, why do you think that says leading instead of left?
Anyone wanna guess? It says leading instead of left,
because some languages Hebrew, Arabic, they go right to
left. The letters come from the right, and they flow
out towards the left. In those cases, you want pretty much
your whole UI flipped over. So, you would want these
buttons pinned to the other side, because the text on
the buttons is gonna be coming from the right. Okay?
Now, it doesn't matter with our emojis, but
that's why we do leading and trailing instead of left and
right. Okay? So, I'm gonna click this Leading Space to
Save Area right here. Connect it, I get another little blue
thing right here. You see this one? If I click on it,
it looks like a little eyebeam,
it's pinning these 2 and it's pinned it with 16 points.
You see 16 points, evidently the blue lines think from
the left edge, or the leading edge you want 16 points.
Okay, I'll take that. And then, of course,
I could pin to the other side. Ctrl+drag over here.
And now, here I didn't use the blue line for that edge.
So, here if I say trailing space to safe area.
I get an eyebeam, this huge, okay.
So, it goes all the way across like that.
And I don't want that, I want it to be the same as the other
side, 16 points. So, in my inspector right here,
this distance is this constant right here, 215 points.
So, I'm gonna change that to be 16,
so it matches the other side. Oh, and look what happened, it
pinned the edge of my buttons and they spread out, equally,
filling equally, because we told we want to fill equally.
Okay, so that's pretty cool, now we have the bottom.
So, the bottom is a little trickier, because we've got
flips down here. So, we want flips to be on the bottom, and
we want this thing to be above flips. So,
let's work on flips first, let's just get it, so
that flips is on the bottom and we're gonna do exact same
thing. So, I'm gonna grab flips and use the blue lines,
okay, put it in the center on the bottom.
And then a controlled drag to the bottom,
and say that I want the bottom space to be pinned to the safe
area. So, that's good. Now, when I did that,
look I got this yellow and red lines and
I got a warning up here. See a warning this warning,
this means there is a warning and it can be red if you have
an error. And if you click on it it will tell you what all
your warnings are kind of a quick summary there, and
here it says horizontal position is ambiguous for
your flip count label. In fact, it is ambiguous.
I never told it where it horizontally,
I pinned it to the bottom, but
I didn't say it was in the middle, or left, or
right now I dragged it there with a blue lines, but
starting with blue lines, it doesn't pin it there. So
really what I want with flips is,
I want it to be in the center. Okay, I want it to be in
center. Just to show you something a little different.
And to do that, again, I Control+drag from flips right
here, to the thing I wanted to be in the center of,
which is this background here. So,
I'm just gonna Control+drag to the background. And
another option is center this horizontally in the safe area.
So, I'm gonna do that. Now, it, it puts it in the middle.
It's still yellow here. So, what does this yellow say?
It says the frame for the Flip Count Label will be different
at run time. That's, because I have not constrained the size
of this Flip Count Label. I've let it be any size it wants.
And since it can be any size it wants,
it's gonna want to be its natural size,
whatever size fits it.
Now, I can fix this warning down here in this button right
here. This is where all your constraints.
All this pinning things to edges is called constraints
we're constraining these views to be in a certain place,
that we can just, um, actually we don't fix it there,
but we're gonna fix that over here.
So, remember, our document outline that we had over here
this little thing we hide. If you unhide that and
look in the upper right, if there are any of these little
warnings you have this little button, if you click on it,
it will tell you all the problems. So,
this one is a misplaced view, cuz this flip is too big. For
what it should be. So, again, if you click on this little
triangle, it'll offer, hey, you wanna fix this? And
you can fix it by updating the frames, which we want,
cuz we don't care what the frame this is, the rectangle
that encloses it. It could be anything as long as it's
pinned to the bottom and in the center. And we can
do other things too, we'll talk about a couple of weeks.
So, I am just gonna update frame drive here fix
missplacement. Look at moved flips down,
it made the frame around it just barely contain it.
Okay, and now they frame around that flip zero is it's
natural size. If I run this and do a hundred flips, so
that it has to be bigger it will naturally get bigger.
Because it's size is not constrained.
It's not pinned to anything, only its location. So,
its size will get as big, or small it needs to to contain
its stuff. And now, we see we have no auto layout issues.
We have no warning up here, all is well. One last thing we
need to do is the relationship between the top of the flips,
and the bottom of this. Now, I could just take this thing up
here and control drag between that and the flips, right?,
that's a good idea. And we could, for example,
constrain the vertical spacing between the two, so I'm gonna
click Vertical Spacing, there it is. It's this huge bar.
I could go over here and change it from 454 to 0, and
use all the space here. But that didn't look very good.
I don't really like tall thin buttons like that.
So I'm gonna leave this constraint in here. But I'm
gonna change it from equal, where it has to be equal,
to 0 with the flips. Also I probably don't want 0, I want
a standard value here so I'm gonna change to standard value
difference, okay, this, this, this distance.
And I don't it to be equal, I want it to be greater than or
equal. So I just wanna make sure that these things on
the top are always above the flips, greater than or equal.
But it doesn't have to be right above it like that. So
you don't have to always have these constraints be equal.
They can be greater than or equal, less than or
equal kind of relative constraints. You see all this?
Now, we can run the app and this should all work.
Everything is kind of constrained to each other.
We can actually kinda take a look at it here in interface
builder. Right, remember this button down here that showed
us all these phones? We can say, okay, what's this thing
gonna look like on an iPhone 8? Here's iPhone 8,
we click on it, and sometimes when it does it,
you can kind of zoom in and out to get it to redraw.
So this is what it's gonna look like on iPhone 8.
We can look at, back on iPhone X, but rotate it.
So here's what it's gonna look like rotated on iPhone X,
that looks like that's gonna look okay. So
we can kind of preview a little bit what's going on
here in interface builder, but there's no substitute for
running it. So let's just run it on our simulator and
see if it looks like what we expect.
Right here it is, app seems to be working. Oh,
let's go make our background black again. So go back here,
background black, keep our Halloween theme intact.
Right now here, okay, so this thing is working we can still
match things, etc. But now when we rotate,
remember Command+Arrow, look, it re-lays out the entire UI
to fit the space. And it's doing this, it's relaying
it out because of those constraints we put it.
We constrained this edge to be stuck to here,
we constrained this edge to be stuck up here.
We constrained this distance to be
greater than or equal to a standard distance.
We constrained the bottom of this to be a distance down
here. We constrained the x position of this to be in
the center. We put those constraints on here, and so
that when we flip this thing around, it's living with those
constraints. Got it? So like I said, this is just a teaser
of this constraint stuff. It's a very powerful system for
doing these constraints and we'll talk all about that,
like I said, in about three weeks. Okay,
back to the slides. All right, so
here's your brief review of week 1, okay,
hyperspeed review. Of course you know about target action,
outlet out to out collection, outlet collections.
The card buttons, your flip count label. The touch card,
you know about that. You learned all about methods and
properties, what their syntax was for all of those things.
Properties like flip count and tons of methods all the ones
in concentration in card and view controller. You learned
about property observing right when the flip count changed,
we have that didSet that would cause the UI to change as
well. You obviously learned about arrays,
how to put things in arrays, how to declare an array.
You'll learned a ton about model view controller.
We went and made the Concentration game have
a model like concentration on the card.
You learned about value types versus reference types, right?
The card, which is a struct, a value type that gets copied
when you throw it around. So when we put them in the array
there, we made the copy by just putting it in twice.
And they copied it each time you put it in there,
remember that? You learned about initializers,
we had initializers both for
for concentration, they each did different things to get
card and
themselves an initializer. We didn't initializer for
our UI view controller and we probably never will.
UI view controllers initialization is messy. Okay,
so we try at all possible not to use init for our view
controller. And I explained that in your homework
that's going out today, you can read about it. You learned
about static methods like get unique identifier, static
vars like the identifier factory that we've created
there. You learned about lazy properties like game, which
depended on another property, and so it couldn't initialize.
We just made it lazy so that it wouldn't actually
initialize until someone asked for it,
which would of course be after the thing is all initialized.
You learned about for in loops, which in Swift only
work by iterating over what's called a sequence.
And we learned that countable range is a sequence, right?
0..< than whatever is a countable range,
that's a sequence. But also array is a sequence,
and string is a sequence of characters.
A lot of things are sequences, you can for in over them.
We're gonna talk about what it means to be a sequence
little later, probably on Wednesday. You learned about
dictionary. Of course our emoji were in a dictionary.
We learned about type conversion.
We convert types by creating a new thing. And using an init
with the old thing like uint 32 of an int makes a uint,
convert into a uint 32. And of course, you learned a lot
about optionals which I'm sure are all still new to you and
I'm gonna talk a lot today about optionals and how they
really work. And what's really going on with optionals, okay?
So that's your review of week one.
If for some of these, if you don't feel like you understand
these, probably haven't done your homework yet, then you
won't understand this, very important. Okay, the first two
things I'm gonna talk about here are just a little quick
minor things, asides. I mentioned doing a for
loop over floats. So this for i = 0.5, i < 15.25 whatever,
that's something you might see in C. You can't do that
in Swift, okay? Swift doesn't have, it only has for in,
that's all it has. But how do we create a countable range or
some kind of sequence of those floats because 0.5...15.25,
that's actually legal to say, but
that's only a range in Swift not a countable range. And
that's because we don't know what to count by there,
so it can't create a countable range. So
the way we do that is using a global function called stride.
Stride has form, through or from and
to depending on whether you are gonna include the last
thing, and a by tells you what it strides by. Stride is
function that creates a countable range. Countable
range is a generic type like array is a generic type.
It can count over not just ints,
it could count over floats, it could even count over indexes
into a string, all kinds of things it can count over.
And this stride knows how to create a countable range,
in this case a closed countable range because I did
through 15.25, not to 15.25.
It creates one that goes over floats and knows to step by
three, 0.3 there. So that's how you do floating point.
And you don't have to do that for your homework or anything,
but I just wanted to be complete about how we do
a countable range for floats. All right, tuples.
I try to fit everything into Concentration that I can,
an example of everything. But I couldn't figure out
how to fit a tuple in even though tuple is a very simple
little data structure. And all that tuple is, essentially,,
like a mini struct that has no methods or vars or anything.
Just has values in it. So it's kind of like struct in other
languages, like C structs. They don't have methods or
vars or anything, or they kind of have vars,
they have the data stores and that's it.
So but the tuple is super lightweight and
you kinda define everything in line.
So here's what a tuple looks like. Here's a tuple x. x,
is up here, is of type tuple. And this tuple has three
things in it. A string, an int, and a double. And
I set its value by just saying equals parentheses,
the three things, okay, the three values. Now, what's
kinda cool about a tuple, as a lightweight struct kinda
thing, is that the names of the elements is very flexible.
You can define the names when you get the values, like this,
let parentheses word number value equal x. And
that actually assigns each of the values of x to the three
variables word, number and value. Okay? So I'm kind of
giving these struct elements names as I grab them out, or
we can do the other way around. When I define x,
I can say x is a tuple that has a string and
Internet double called winv. Then,
when I have x in my hands, I can get w,
i and v with using, using this dot notation,
kind of like it's a var almost in a struct, x.w, x.i, x.v.
See, so now I'm declaring the names when I declare
the thing. But, and even if you do this, you can still
redeclare the names to be something else by saying, let
word num val = x, it'll crate those three local variables so
super flexible on the naming of those three things.
Usually when we crate a tuple we want to use the second way
the x : i : v way although we probably would not use x,
i and v those are terrible names that is just my
slide only has so much space.
Horizontally, probably word, number or
value would have been better names. Usually we do that, and
that's mostly because of documentation,
we want people to know what those three things are. If we
just declare it like x at the very top there, string, int,
double, people are like, hm, what are those three things?
So, what's a tuple good for? Well,
it's good any time you wanna group some stuff together
that's really lightweight, it doesn't have any methods or
anything associated with it. It's also very good for
returning multiple values from a function. A function of
Swift can only return a single thing, but
that thing could be a tuple, and now you can return as many
things as you want, okay? So if I had a function getSize,
get's a person's size, their height and their weight.
Let's say I can return a tuple with weight and height, and
so when I got it back I just x.weight or
even just getSize.weight or getSize.height, access
it directly. So that's what tuples, is I didn't make you
read about it tuple in your first reading assignment but
you'll be reading about it in your next one.
it's very simple, it's exactly what it seems,
there;s nothing magical here, there's no hidden things, it's
just a simple little struct, yeah? Sorry? Do they support
indexing? Do tuples support indexing, you mean like,
get thing number 1, or get thing number 2? Not really,
and we wouldn't really wanna do it that way. If we really
had something we'd index, we'd wanna use an array there,
because, you know what I'm saying? It would obfuscate
what's going on. The whole great thing about tuples,
you can name each one and let people know what they are, so.
All right, now, okay, that was it for
little things, now we're back to something very important.
This is a big thing. This is computed properties.
So all the properties that you saw in Concentration,
were stored properties. They were just normal vars
like you're used to in another languages, right?
Like this var foo: Double, that's a double precision
floating point number, and it's just stored in memory.
It's stored with whatever struct or class it's part of.
But it is possible to declare foo like this,
foo Double open curly brace, get with the curly brace, set,
with some curly brace.
In that case, foo is never stored anywhere, instead,
every time someone asks for
foo, it gets calculated with the code inside get. And
every time someone sets the value of foo,
this code that's in here inside set gets executed.
Okay, so I got a little pointer here. So
this code gets executed when you set, this code up here
gets executed when you get. Instead of it being stored
somewhere. Now, the set by the way, that set(newValue) part,
that's optional. So you can have computed properties
that are only get, call those read only computed properties.
You can't have ones that are only set,
you can have get only but not set only.
If you have set only make a function set whatever.
You wouldn't use a var like that. Okay, so why a computed
properties important? What do you use them for?
Well, a lot of times you have something that is perceived as
a property of your struct or class that actually is derived
from other state inside of your struct. And when you have
that situation, you do not want to have a stored property
because you don't want to have the same
information in two different vars. Because they can get
out of sync, all kinds of problems happens, so
you one way or the other wants to derive itself
from the other one. Here's an incredibly good example
indexOfOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard in concentration.
That is easily derived by looking at the cards. So
you really, we'll really kind of bad to have made that
a stored property, becauase we have to keep that thing
exactly in sync with the face up state of all the cards.
That's really error prone way to design. So, we could
imagine doing, implementing indexOfOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard as
computed property
with the get just looks at all the cards. And if you'll
only find one FaceUpCard it returns that index, otherwise
it it returns nil. And the set just looked to that index,
make sure that card face up and all the rest will face
down, you see? So, we're just using this computed property
to essentially provide this conceptual property,
which is the indexOfOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard,
that is the property of our game, but
it's computed from the other one. Everyone get what
I'm saying there? Okay, so let's go to Concentration and
make this change, see what this would look like
if you used a computed property here like we
should've in the first place, all right?
So let's go back here to X code,
here we go spring our code back up, get rid of that.
Let's go, oops, let's go to concentration, that's where
this is all right? So everyone recognize this code, right?
This is our entire concentration,
pretty efficient code as is but it's actually gonna look
even better once we do this as you'll see. So we're here,
we have index and one only FaceUpCard. So
I'm gonna make it computed by putting these curly braces in,
as soon as I do that, now it's a computed property. Actually,
before we do that, let me show you even simpler case of this
just to kinda get you warmed up on computed property.
Sometimes, you have just a simple calculation like this.
The number of pairs of cards which are calculated from
the card buttons, all right? There might be other times
inside our view controller, we wanna know this number,
how many pairs of cards do we have. So
that's kind of a property and is derived from this data. So
I'm gonna take this out of here and
have number of pairs of cards be a property.
It's gonna be a new var numberOfPairsOfCards, and
it's gonna be of type Int, and it's gonna be computed, so
I'm gonna have a get. It's gonna be read only, so
I'm gonna return this. It's not gonna have a set,
there's no, there's not gonna be any set right here. And
voila I've created a simple computed property that's read
only. By the way if you have a read only property,
you do not actually have to have the word get there. So
a read only property
can look like that. Only if you only have a get,
if you have a set can't do that. So this is a super
simple little one. So now let's go back over here and
do the little more complicated one over here.
This one does have a get and it also has a set. And
set right here, I put in the slide that has newValue.
This is just gonna be the local variable inside here
that contains the new value that someone set,
indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard two. A lot of times we don't
put anything there, if you do that,
it defaults to newValue. That's the name of the locals,
there's a special variable in here called newValue.
But if you wanted to call it something like index,
you could do that, it's totally up to you,
a lot of times we just say use newValue though. Okay,
so getting the index what do we have to do
to calculate the index of code. So I'm just gonna
write the little code and have a little look of variable,
say foundIndex which is gonna be an optional Int. So
I'm gonna look through all the face cards and
see if I can find one that's gonna be the one I found.
So I'm gonna use a for loop here and
go through all the cards.indicises, all right?
I'm gonna look at each card, and if that card is FaceUp.
So I found the FaceUp card, whoo-hoo.
I'm gonna say, if foundOne is nil, in other words,
I haven't found the card yet and this is my first one.
Then I'm gonna set not foundOne, what is it called,
foundIndex = index, all right? So here I'm just saying if I
just found my first one let's remember it.
Otherwise, if foundIndex is not nil that means this is
the second FaceUpCard that I found.
Cuz I already found one and I found another one, so
here I am just gonna to return nil. Because if there's two
FaceUpCards then obviously the index of the one and
only FaceUpCard is nil, there's no such thing. And
if I make it all the way through this for
loop I'm just gonna return the foundIndex, which is either
going to have been set to the one card I found or
it'll still be nil from this declaration.
Remember that optionals always get
this free equals nil when they're declared, right? So it
starts out nil and if I never found one, it'll still be nil,
which is right cuz that means there'll be no FaceUpCards.
We're gonna understand this simple code right here,
how about the set case? On the set case,
I'm just gonna loop through all the cards and
turn all face down except for this one that they just set it
to, which is gonna be new value, all right? So I'm just
gonna go through my cards for index in cards.indices.
Great way to go iterate through this countable
range of all the indexes in my array. I'm gonna say,
cards.index.isFaceUp = false,
for most cards. But in case the index here,
this index equals the new value of this, then I'm gonna
set it to true. Okay, so here this is an expression
that's true if someone said indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
equals whatever. If this is the whatever they said,
then we're gonna have this be true if the card's face up,
o therwise this will always be false. Everybody got this
little code right there? Come through with that? All right,
that's it. Okay, now the indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
is computed like this,
from the card, we do not need to take responsibility for
doing things like setting it to nil here. This is the case
where we found two cards, we got two cards that we're
trying to match, well, obviously there's two cards.
So we had to set the indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
to nil cuz there were two. But we don't have to do that
anymore, because it's always computing that,
every time we ask, it goes and looks at the card. And
even better than that is this case down here. Okay,
this case down here, we are setting the
indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceupCard to
be the index. That's because this was the case where there
were already two or there were none,
and now we turn those faceDown and do this new one.
So we're already setting this and it does all of this.
Setting this thing to something already turns all
the other cards faceDown. And already sets that card faceUp,
so we don't need any of that code. So you see how making
the computed property makes this code much simpler and
straightforward. Cuz it really gets at the heart of what's
going on. I'm just setting the indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
to this index
that I just clicked on or
I'm just turning this card faceUp. And the next time
someone asks for the indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
it's gonna do the right thing, right?
So let's go and run, make sure we didn't break
anything making this into a computed property. Here we go,
hopefully we can still match, yeap, that matches,
and the matching is working, and the mismatching is also
working. Really cool computed properties,
you're gonna see computed properties everywhere in iOS,
they get very common, yeah. >> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Okay great question, so
when would I reuse this var versus
having two methods, one which get's the index and
one really [INAUDIBLE] and one that sets it.
Okay, it's all about whether it's perceived as property.
This index in effect is perceived by us as programmers
it's a property right? It's, it's a property of the game
is the index on the face of the card, so
that's what you would do here. If another way of kind of
deciding is if the set or the get really does a lot of work.
Like it's really crunching on something,
you might wanna make that a function.
Just so the people don't think, oh it's a lightweight
little property that I can get. Now, this might seem like
a lot of work but it's actually very very simple.
And then later in the lecture, probably on Wednesday,
I'm gonna show you an even much simpler version of this.
When we learn a little bit more about Swift.
But it really is not that much work it's just looking at
another data structure. But if you were doing a lot of work
then you probably want to do set and
get to make it clear. But otherwise if it is
a var if it seems like a var make it a var. Good question.
Alright where is my, here it is, keynote,
lets go back here, back to our slides. All right,
so the next thing we're gonna talk about is here,
is another topic something we knew, access control. Okay, so
what is access control? So, how many people have worked on
a project, an object oriented program project of more
than a dozen classes? Okay, like two or
three of you, four maybe, so, not very many of you. Okay,
well when you're working on a very small project like that,
you can call any method in any class, whatever,
you're probably the only programmer working on it.
Or maybe you're working out with a buddy, and so
you can talk to each other. Okay, but now imagine
that you're working for Google. Or Facebook, or Apple,
or something like that, and this is kind of ridiculous.
But let's say you're working on concentration there. And
there's a whole another group in another building that does
game design and they write the model. And
you are just the UI team for IOS,
until you're only writing the view controller.
Okay, well now, you don't wanna be calling each others
code just willy-nilly. Calling any old method like
you wouldn't want your view controller cal someone like
indexOfOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard.
If those guys are like they got rid of that method
into the next month, and now your code broke. Now,
there are some methods that you have to be able to call
over there and their code, and we're gonna make it clear
which ones of those are using access control.
So access control about having keyword that we're gonna put
into our API, put it on the methods and bars,
it says to other groups that we're programming with, yes,
you are allowed to call this, I promise not to break this
on you. It also tells them how to use your thing because
the ones they're allowed to call or the ones they should
be using to use your concentration game or
whatever. So what are these keywords?
Well the first one is called internal. These are keywords
you put in front of vars and funcs. Or even classes and
structs, you can make entire classes and structs,
have their access controlled. So the default internal,
this one we never actually type in
because it's the default. So all of the methods and
vars that we've done so far in Concentration are all
internal. Now what does internal Access Control mean?
It means anyone in your app, any object, any code anywhere
can call that method or access that bar. So it's pretty much
unlimited control inside your app. Now as we start talking
about access control, we have to realise there's always two
kinds of programming, there's writing an app,
then there's writing a framework. Like Apple does,
UI kit, okay? That's framework. A lot more access
control issues if you're writing a framework. So
I'm gonna tell you what the things are for
writing a framework but, We're not gonna really pay much
attention to them because we are only going to learn to
write apps in this course. So internal means everything in
your app, or in your framework is, can access this code.
So it's pretty much almost unlimited inside
your Apple framework. Then there's the three privates.
These are very important, these are the ones you're
gonna be using all the time. One is just private,
that means its internal implementation to this object,
no other objects can call it. This is a good one to set,
it keeps someone in the other group at Google and the other
building from accessing that code. Because you're
keeping it private, it's your private implementation.
Private set is almost exactly the same, it's only for vars,
it means that setting this var is private, but getting it
is not private. So you allow people to get the var, access
并不是私有的。所以你允许人们得到这个变量，访问
it, but they can not set it. That's you purview,
这个变量，但是不能给它赋值。那是你的权利
that's your internal implementation sets it.
你的内部实现可以给它赋值
We'll see a good example of that in concentration.
我们会在翻牌游戏里看到个好的例子
And then there's fileprivate. Fileprivate in a Swift file,
然后是 fileprivate，文件内私有。在一个 Swift 文件里
you can have multiple classes and structs in there,
你可以有多个类和结构体
you don't have to be just one class which is what we've done
不需要想我们现在这样一个文件只有一个类
so far and fileprivate means anything in that in that
而 fileprivate 的意思是，任何在那个
file can access each other, right. So classes,
文件里的都可以互相访问，也就是类
all classes in there, it can each others methods, okay,
所有的都可以访问 fileprivate 的方法（和变量）
that's what file private means. Okay, the other ones
这就是 fileprivate 的意思。好，其他的
are public and open, those are for framework writers.
public 和 open，这两个是给框架作者用的
Public means that people outside the framework
public 的意思是编写框架以外的人
can call it. Doesn't make sense for outside your app,
也可以调用它。在你的程序外使用是说不通的
that would never happen, so outside your framework.
这也不可能发生，所以是在框架外使用
And open means not only can people outside your framework
open 的意思是不仅框架外可以
call it but they could sub class that class,
调用，他们还可以继承那个类
override your methods all that stuff,
重写你的方法等
so open is like wide open, okay. We don't care about that
所以 open 是很开放的权限。但我们不用管
cuz we're only, we're not doing frameworks, right. So
因为我们只写程序，不会写框架，好吧，所以
we're gonna focus on private of the various privates.
我们主要关注这几种 private
A good strategy to use these is pretty much put private on
最好的做法是基本都用 private
anything until you're sure, yeah I want someone else to be
除非你确信说我想要其他人
able to call this method somewhere.
在其他地方能够调用这个方法
Right that's by default you should make things private. So
所以默认你应该让所有的都是 private
let's look a concentration, what it would look like to
所以让我们看看翻牌游戏，它看起来是什么样的
put access control on concentration and
如果我们给玩牌游戏加上访问权限的话
pay attention here because I'm gonna require in all your
你要注意了，因为我要求你所有的
homeworks going forward that you mark things properly.
之后的作业里正确地标记访问权限
I want you to mark things private if they should be
我想要你把私有的都标记为 private
private. Okay, cuz I wanna just make sure that you
因为我想要确保你
understand what this is all about. So let's go back here
理解了这是什么。那我们回到这里
to Xcode. Let's start with our ViewController.
到 Xcode 里，从 ViewController 开始
Okay, we have three classes, or three data structures,
好，我们有三个类，准确说是三个数据结构
our ViewController, Card, and Concentration. So let's start
我们的 ViewController，Card 和 Concentration。那我们从
with ViewController. So this right here is our model. So
ViewController 开始改。所以这里的这个是我们的模型
would we want our model to be public, to be not private?
我们想要模型是公开的，非私有的吗？
Well that depends, actually.
其实那个不一定
It depends of what your model is and how it works. Often,
那取决于你的模型是什么，怎么工作的。一般来说
ViewControllers models are public by public I mean
ViewController 是公开的。我这个公开不是 public
non-private. We're inside an app so forget about public and
意思是非私有。我们写的是一个 App，所以你可以忽略 public 和
open keywords. I mean, when I say public I mean non-private.
open 这两个关键字。所以我所谓的 public/公开是指非私有
So a lot of times you do because you give a model to
而大部分时候都是这样的，因为你把一个模型提供给
a view controller and it displays it,
视图控制器，然后控制器就显示它
that's what it does. But that is not the case here. This one
这就是他的工作。但我们这里不是这样的情况。这里
wants to be private. And the reason it wants to be private
我们想要是 private 的。它应该是私有的
is because the number of pairs of cards in the game is
原因是 numberOfPairsOfCards
intimately tied to the UI, okay the number of
游戏里卡片的对数是和 UI 捆绑着的
cards we have in the UI. So if we wanted to make
是我们 UI 理由的卡的对数。如果我们想要
this public then we'd also have to make something public
让它公开的的话，我们也需要让另一个公开的
to specify the number of card buttons that we allow and
来指定我们允许的显示卡片的按钮的个数
we don't do that currently,
但我们现在并不是这样的
that's something that is in our little scene and
那现在是我们在 Interface Builder
interface builder, so we don't do it. So we keep this, we
的场景里设置的，所以我们不这样做。所以我们保持这个
keep this private. How about number of pairs of cards?
让他就是 private 的。那 numberOfPairsOfCards 呢？
Well, this is one where I don't mind if someone asks
嘛，这个我不介意如果其他人知道
what the number of pairs of cards is but
有多少对卡片，但是
setting the number of pairs of cards would be bad. But
设置有多少对卡片是不好的。但
the thing about this is it's already a get-only property.
这个的话，它已经是只读的属性了
You can't set it anyway, it derives it from other data.
你怎么都没法设置它，它是从其他数据衍生出来的
So we're just gonna make this private, sorry, not private.
所以我们就让他是 private 的。不好意思，让他不是 private
And we're gonna allow people to call this,
我们要让别人能够访问这个
people who are using my ViewController, they can say,
使用我这个 ViewController 人可以问
how many pairs of cards are there? But they can't set it,
这里有多少对卡片，但他们不能给它赋值
cuz this is not settable anyway. Okay, so
因为这个本来就没法赋值。好，所以
that's okay to make that in public.
这个是可以公开的
Same thing flipCount, I think flipCount,
flipCount 也是类似的，我认为 flipCount
it's okay for people to get it, but definitely, we don't
人们是可以读取它的，但肯定我们不
want people setting flipCount. That's something we do
想让人们赋值给 flipCount。那是我们
internally when the cards are flip, we implement flipCount.
在翻牌的时候内部实现的，我们管理的
So that's private for the setter, but will allow people
所以 setter 是 private 的，但我们允许其他人
to get the flipCount who are using our thing.
在使用的时候获得 flipCount
Our outlets, almost always we have private outlets.
我们这些 @IBOutlet，几乎我们都是让出口保持 private
Cuz our private outlets,
因为我们私有的出口
these things, and even our actions these are all kind of
这些，甚至包括 @IBAction 操作，这些都是
internal implementation of how we implement our UI.
内部对 UI 的实现
That's what a ViewController does it controls our UI.
这就是视图控制器的作用，控制 UI
Definitely something like update model from UI would be
肯定类似于 updateViewFromModel 的方法
private, that's internal implementation.
应该是 private 的，这也是内部实现
All this emoji business that's all private. Although you
这些表情相关的也应该是 private 的，虽然
could imagine trying to expose some public API eventually
你可以计划尝试最终暴露些公有 API
in this ViewController that let's someone who's using
让其他使用 ViewController 的人可以
our ViewController specify the emojis they want.
指定他们想用的表情
Like, you know, this theme required task that you have,
比如某个任务要求用某个主题
you could imagine that there was a way to specify I want
你可以设想我们有一种方法指定我想要
you mister view controller to play this game,
ViewController 玩这个游戏
but I want you to use this emoji as your theme.
但是我想要用这套表情作为主题
See, so you could imagine that something being public.
所以设想那种情况下肯定会是有公开的
I don't think it would be exactly this API,
但我不认为会是和这个一样的 API
it would be some other kind of API,
那会是不同的 API
I'm not sure what they would let you set the emoji to
我不确定是什么样的，但它能让你设置使用的表情
use. We can't really make this public cuz we actually consume
这个我们是不能公开的，因为我们实际会消耗
this. This is a var and we consume it. We have obviously
这个数组；这是个变量，而我们会移除里面的内容。肯定
had to deal with that in your homework I'm sure. And
在你们的作业里要解决这个问题。还有
you know, this dictionary we're building on a fly,
你知道的，这个字典我们是及时构建的
we wouldn't want anyone messing with it, so
我们不会想其他人使用它，所以
I'm gonna keep all this private.
我让这些都是 private 的
This is an example of making it private first and
这就是个例子，先让这些都是 private
then I'm gonna think about what I want to be public.
之后我再考虑我要公开哪些
You see, the design approach there?
看到我们用的设计方法了吗？
All right, let's go look at card, so
好，我们再来看看 Card 结构体
here's Card. Card definitely, this has to be public.
这就是 Card。Card 里这个肯定是公开的
We need to know whether the cards are face up,
我们需要知道是否朝上
we, this has to be public. Unfortunately,
这个也必须是公开的。不幸的是
this has to be public. Cuz otherwise,
这个也得是公开的，因为否则的话
we can't tell if two cards are the same without that,
没有这个的话我们不能判断两张是否相同
but these two guys definitely don't need to be public.
但这两个肯定不用是公开的
This whole idea of I, making identierFactory that's purely
我这整个使用 identierFactory 只是为了
internal implementation, okay, so no reason for that to be
内部实现，所以没有理由把它
public. And this really, I'd love this to be private as
公开。然后这个 identifier，我虽然想要是 private
well, because a card it's either face up it's matched
因为这卡，我就想知道是否朝上，是否配对了
whether it's the same as another card,
而两张卡是否相同
I shouldn't have to look an identifier to find that.
我不应该靠 identier 标识符来判断
I should be able to say the this card == the other card,
我应该能用 一张卡 == 另一张卡 来判断
wouldn't that be cool? And yeah it is cool and
那不更好么？是的，那是挺酷的
we're gonna be doing that, in, later in this lecture or next
而我们也就会这样做，要么等会儿这节课，要么
lecture. Um, this is really kind of gross but for now we
下节课。我挺讨厌这个，但现在我们
have to leave that public because otherwise we do,
就让他保持公开，因为否则的话
we can't tell what two cards are the same. Okay,
我们就不能判断两张卡是否相同了吧
here's the Concentration game, this is a really interesting
然后这个是 Concentration 游戏本身，这是个很有趣的
case of private and public because, here is an object,
决定私有还是公开的例子，因为这个对象
a model that is intended to be used by some UI somewhere,
模型本身就是给其他的某个 UI 使用的
okay. It's very intentional use kind of thing, and
就是为了被使用而存在的
there's some things we know are private,
这里有我们知道是 private 的
like this guy for sure, indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpC-
比如肯定有这里的 indexOfOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
ard, we don't need someone using us to know that,
我们不需要让使用的人知道
they don't need to know that.
他们不需要知道这个
And in fact, if we left that public, someone using us would
实际上，如果我们把它公开的话，使用我们的人会
be like when am I supposed to set that, I wonder?
想，“我是否应该设置它呢？”
Okay, but it has nothing to do with it, it's internal to our
但他们和这个是无关的，这是我们内部
implementation. Cards has to be public
实现用的。card 必须要是公开的
because otherwise the UI can't display the cards.
因为否则的话 UI 就不能显示卡片了
However, cards being flipped up and down or
但是把牌翻面，或是
matching that's my job. So I am gonna make this one private
让他们配对这是我的工作，所以我要让它是 private(set)
set, okay, so this is gonna be yeah you can look at my cards
所以这个会是，使用的人可以看我有哪些牌
if you wanna use Concentration game but I am responsible for
如果他们在用 Concentration 这个游戏的话可以看，但我负责
setting face up and is matched. So
把卡片翻面，设置是否配对了，所以
you can see this one's clearly private set,
我们可以明确地看出这个是 private(set)
everyone see that? Yeah. >> So for that you can access
大家都看到了吗？>> 所以 private(set) 就是你可以获得
the cards but you can't access the methods or
cards 和数组的元素，但是你不能访问元素 Card 的实例方法
properties associated with it? >> Yeah, so
或者实例的属性吗？>> 好，所以
the question is when it's like this does that mean I
问题是用 private(set) 是否意味着
can access the cards but I can't access the methods that
我可以访问 cards 的元素，但是不能访问方法
are on the cards you mean? No the methods on the cards,
这是你的问题吧？但并不是这样的。Card 实例的方法
that's over here, those are public, okay,
那是在这里定义的，这些是公开的
those are not internal so I can access those from here,
这些不是内部实现，所以我这里可以访问他们
okay? But you remember that this is a value type, so
但你要记得 Card 是值类型，所以
I can't set is face up and stuff, I can only set that
我不能赋值给 isFaceUp 这些，我只能直接
directly in the array. Like I'm doing right here. You see,
通过数组给它赋值，就像我这里这样，你看
here I'm modifying the thing in place in the array.
我这里直接更改了在数组里的 Card 实例的属性
That's the only way to do it. Well, I can't do this if this
这是我唯一能用的方法。而在其他地方是不能这样做的，如果这个
is private set. Okay? Cuz this is a value type.
是 private(set) 的话，对吧？因为这个是值类型
So this makes it so this, this it's kind of like it's a let.
这个让它有点像是 let 声明的常量
This almost makes it like a let for
对于其他人，不在这个范围内的
other people, people other than me. And then, and so
private(set) 就像是 let 一样，也就是
you can't touch anything in an array when it's a let. So
在数组是 let 常量的时候你不能修改数组的元素
that's a really cool feature of value types.
所以这是值类型很酷的特性
And remember that array's a value type and
然后，要记得数组是值类型
card is a value type. So that whole thing is frozen for
Card 也是值类型，所以这整个就被“冻”住了
people who, you can't be modified for outside people.
其他人就没法修改它
But for us, it's private set so
但 private(set) 对于我们来说
we can do anything we want in there which we have been
我们可以像现在这样为所欲为
doing. All right. And then of course, choose card.
好吧。然后肯定的，chooseCard
That's our fundamental public API. So we got to leave that
这是我们基础的公有 API，所以我们就让他
not private, okay. That's how people do it. And
不是私有的，这就是我们的做法。然后
initializing, initializers can be made private as well. But
构造过程，init 构造器也可以是私有的，但是
this one obviously can't be private because otherwise no
这个不能是私有的，因为否则的话
one could create a game, all right. So that's it. Everyone
没有人可以新建一个游戏，好，就是这样
got that? Now, while I'm here, I'm gonna show you another
大家都明白吧？现在我在这里还要给你展示另一种
API protection thing that's different from access control.
方法来保护 API。不是靠访问权限控制
That's still good, which is using assertions, okay.
（虽然也可以用，）那就是使用 assert，断言
Do anyone know what an assertion is from other
大家从其他语言知道了 assert/断言是什么吗？
languages? An assertion is just a function that you call
断言就是一个你调用的函数
where you assert something to be true. And if it's not,
以此来确保某个条件是成立的；如果不是的话
your program crashes and print out an error.
你的程序就会崩溃，然后打印出错误信息
And you put it in your code, the asserts are ignored when
你这代码里使用 assert 函数，但发布到
you ship to the App Store. But when you're in development,
App Store 时会被忽略。但你在开发的时候
it'll be crashing your program, which is good,
他会让你的程序崩溃，这是好事情
cuz it takes the debugger right to the assertion failed.
因为调试器会带你到断言为 false 的地方
And asserts are a great way to protect your API. For example,
断言是保护你 API 的好方法，比如说
look at this API, chooseCard.
看 chooseCard 这个 API
What if someone says at index -1?
如果别人传的 index 是 -1 呢？
Or at index 100 and they're only 12 cards.
或者我们只有 12 张，但他们选择在索引 100 的卡
Okay, that's gonna crash somewhere deep inside here,
那种情况程序会在这里的某个地方崩溃
probably like maybe here or
可能是在这里或者
something like that. And if I'm the Google guys again, and
类似的地方。再次设想如果我是 Google 的员工
these guys are in another building and
他们在另一栋建筑里
I accidentally pass -1 here and I don't know what's. And
我不小心传了 -1 给 index，然后
the crash happens in here, I'm gonna need to have this code,
程序在这里面崩溃了，那我需要拿到这份代码
and look in there, and I'm debugging it.
然后到这里面找，去调试它
That code belongs to someone in another building,
这段代码是在别的地方的其他人
why would I ever wanna be in here debugging it? Instead,
为什么我会想去帮他调试代码？取而代之
the guys in the other building should put an assert here.
在另一个建筑里的人应该在这里使用断言
That asserts that the cards indices contain that index.
assert(cards.indices.contains(index), )
Okay, if the card's indices don't contain this index,
如果 cards 数组的索引 indices 不包含 index
then we're going to crash, if we're in development and so,
如果我们在开发的过程中，那程序就会崩溃
then we want to put some kind of crash message here.
然后这里我们应该放崩溃的时候显示的信息
I like to put the name of the struct or class and
我个人喜欢放这个结构体或类的名字
the function which chooseCard. I even like to include
以及函数名，也就是 chooseCard。我甚至喜欢包括
the actual arguments that you passed so you can see what you
传给我的实际参数，这样调用的人就能知道
passed there and then, I give the message. In this case,
传给我的参数。最后是我的错误信息，这里
something like chosen index not in the cards.
就用比如“选择的索引不在 cards 数组里”
So that, so now if someone calls to choose
这样的话，其他人调用 chooseCard
card at minus one, it's gonna crash right away and
传入负一，那就会直接崩溃
put that on the console. And they're gonna be like,
然后显示这个信息到控制台里。调用的人就知道
oh, shows the index not on the card, oh, and
哦，说索引不在 cards 数组里，哦
I passed minus one. You see, they're gonna one stop shop.
我传的是 -1。你看，一步到位
Know what they did. And with the similar thing thing down
能知道他们干了什么。下面这也是类似的
here for number of pairs of cards because it's illegal to
对于 numberOfPairsOfCards，是不能有
have 0 or less pairs of cards. You have to have at least one
0 或者更少对卡片的。你必须要有至少一对
pair of card. So here I'm just gonna have the assertion be
卡片，所以我这里就加个断言
that the number of Pairs Of Cards is greater than 0.
确保 numberOfPairsOfCards 大于 0
And if there is an error then I'm gonna say yes,
如果不是的话，那我就会说
I'm in the concentrations Init and
我在 Concentration.init 里
you passed me this number of pairs of cards right here and
然后是你传给我的这个 numberOfPairsOfCards
the problem here is that you must have at least
问题是你必须至少有
one pair of cards. Okay? So, you see how I'm, I'm using
一对卡片。好吧？你看到我是怎么使用
assert here to kinda protect my API against improper use.
断言来保护我的 API 不被错误地使用
Question back there? Yeah? >> Sorry when you,
后面同学有什么问题？>> [学生提问]
Sorry when you- >> When would you set init
>> 能重复你的问题么？>> 你什么时候会让 init
as private? >> Oh, so
是 private 的呢？>> 哦
the question is when would I set my init as private, okay.
这个同学问我什么时候会有私有的构造器
Well, you might have a complicated object that
举个例子，你可能会有一个复杂的对象
only creates instances of itself. For example,
只允许它自己构造实例，通过比如
with static methods or something like that.
static 的静态方法一类的来实现
Or you might have multiple inits. Some of which you'll allow
或者你有多个 init。有些你允许
other people to call. But some of which you call internally
其他人调用，而有些只是你内部使用的
to create, okay. You might even have public ones that is
你甚至可能有公开的构造器
part of their implementation called the private ones. Okay,
会调用私有的构造器来实现
cuz inits can call each other which we'll talk about on
因为构造器可以调用另一个构造器。这个我们会在
Wednesday. So that's why you might have some private. Okay,
星期三讲。这就是为什么你的某些构造器可以是私有的
everybody cool with access control and
大家都对访问权限和断言没问题了吧？
assertions? All right, back to the slides.
好，我们接着讲幻灯片
Where are we? Here, okay. Cool one, all right extensions. So
我们讲到哪里了来着？这里，这个很厉害，extension
extensions are super powerful. They're kind of like
扩展非常强大，它就像一种武器
a weapon you'll want to be careful when you're wielding,
当你使用的时候需要额外小心
because you can go crazy with them. And what an extension
因为你可能会走火入魔。在 extension 里
allows you to do is add vars and functions to other classes
你可以给其他的类添加变量和方法
even if you don't have the code to those classes.
即使你没有那个类的源代码也能做到
Even if there in another frame work like UI Kits or something
即使那个类属于另一个如 UIKit 一类的框架
like that. So you can add vars and methods to it. You can add
你都可以向它添加变量和方法。你可以添加
it to UI Button. You can add it UI View Controller.
到 UIButton 里，可以添加给 UIViewController
Anything you want. Okay? So this is a very, very, very
任何你想要的类，知道了吧？所以这是个非常非常
powerful feature. And really I'm sure what's swimming in your mind about
非常强大的功能。我确信能猜到你们脑袋里想的
the possibilities is nothing compared to the actual
各种可能性只是实际能实现的微不足道
possibilities because there are other data structures that
的一部分，因为还有很多数据结构
we haven't even talked about that adding an extension to
我们还没有讲到，但给它们添加扩展
really is powerful and we'll get to that by end of
是真的很实用，我们会在星期三
Wednesday as well. The basic line of it is, is very simple.
下课之前讲。要添加扩展很简单
You just use the keyword extension and the name of
你只需要用关键字 extension 然后数据类型的名字
the struct or class you wanna add a var property to and
就是你想要添加变量的结构体或类的名字
then just put the thing you want in there.
然后在大括号里写你要扩展的内容
Now, it has one very some serious restriction which is
但是有一个限制是
that it can have no storage. This extension, this code that
扩展没有存储空间。作为扩展，这些代码
you're extending this other thing, it can have no vars
扩展了另一个数据类型，它是不能扩展
that are storage. It could have vars that are computed.
存储属性的。但它可以添加计算属性
But it can't have any vars with storage. So
但任何存储属性都不行
that does restrict the kind of thing that you can
这肯定会限制你们想添加的
add to a function. Okay, but you kinda turn out that
某些功能。但其实
restriction is actually a good restriction. It's not like
这个限制是很正确的，并不是说
the too bad they could invent it with storage. You
它们水平太差实现不了。你
actually don't want storage, and you will see as we
其实并不会想要有存储，而且你会从我们
go along why that is. So, this feature as you might imagine
之后讲的领悟到为什么。正如你所想的，这个功能
is easily abused and the number one ways to get abuse,
经常被滥用，而其中最常见的情况是
and I encourage you not to abuse at this way is you do
我建议你也不要这样做，那就是
not want to add a var or a func to class that doesn't
你不应该添加一个变量或方法到某个类
make sense for that class. It's a real temptation for
但对于那个类来说是毫不相关的。最吸引人的
example for an Int or String to add a function that has to
是比如扩展 Int 或 String，添加一个
do with concentration. Some concentration specific method
只为了翻牌游戏而存在的方法
you're adding to string cuz it'll clean up your code or
好让你的代码更简洁或者
look nice or whatever But you really don't wanna do that.
看起来更好看，但是你不应该这样做
The only method and functions you wanna add to string or
你想给 String 添加的方法和变量
methods that make string a better class. They make it a better
应该是为了让 String 成为一个更好的字符串
string not they make it knows about concentration. Now,
而不是为了让它了解翻牌游戏
it's probably possible to add string methods to make it
虽然可以添加方法给字符串来让它
know about concentrations that nothing really wrong with it.
了解翻牌游戏，这也不是什么错误的做法
It's just kind of bad design. Okay so
但并不是很好的设计。所以
this extension's feature like I said is very powerful,
就像我说的扩展是很强大的功能
since you're just beginning here, you can think of it at
但你们才刚开始学，你目前可以把它当作
the beginning as just a way to add utility, functions and
只是一种方法来添加实用工具，方法
things like that to clean up your code.
和其他东西来整理你的代码
Okay, that the first level of learning about extensions so
这就是我们对 extension 的简单认识
I am going to show you how we could do that for
我会给你们展示我们如何扩展
example in Concentration. So let's go to concentration and
比如我们的翻牌游戏，那我们回到翻牌游戏
use an extension to add something interesting and
使用扩展来添加有趣的东西
what interesting thing we are going to do is we are going to
我们要做的有趣的事情是
go to our view controller over here and
到 ViewController 里
look at this code right here which is kind of messy.
然后看看这有些乱的代码
Right here. Okay? What is messy about this code?
就这个，为什么说它很乱呢？
Well. Okay. All I really wanna do is remove a random emoji.
因为我想要做的只是随机移除一个表情
And you have to have a whole other line of code.
但却为此多写了一行代码
And that line of code has this horrendous amount of. Changing
而且这行代码还很复杂，转换
from unsigned ints to regular ints and all that stuff.
无符号整数和整数这些乱七八糟的
So it just really looks bad, and it's hard to read,
看起来很不好看，而且很难读
it's hard to understand what is going in here.
而且很难理解到底发生了什么
I'm having to do so many type conversions, stuff like that.
我需要太多的类型转换等
It's awful, okay? Really what I'd like to do is generate
非常糟糕是吧？我想要的只是生成
a random number and put it right here. So what if int,
一个随机数然后放到这里。如果整数
the type int, had a var which gave me a random
Int 类型有个变量可以给我随机的某个
integer? Okay, that's a very int thing, nothing to
整数该多好？这确实和整数相关
do with concentration, it's just int thing.
和翻牌游戏无关，只是整数的功能
It gives me a random integer. So we're going to extend int
它就给我一个随机的整数，所以我们要扩展 Int
to give back a random integer. Specifically, we're gonna make
来随机返回某个整数。更具体实现是
it so that when you ask an int please give me a random
我们要去请某个整数返回这个随机整数
integer it gives a random integer between 0 and that
那个随机数会在零到它本身之间
int. Okay, so if I say five, I can even say, I'm gonna be
比如我用 5，我还能够用
able to say here let x equal five dot random integer.
let x = 5.随机整数
And I'm gonna call this thing arc4random, this var.
我把这个随机整数变量叫 arc4random
Because I'm gonna use arc4random to generate it and
因为我是用 arc4random 生成它的
people know the semantics of arc4random which is
而且大家都知道 arc4random
a random a number
就是随机数
between 0 and another number. So this is, I'm gonna make
0 到另一个数之间的随机数。我会让
it so this will work and that will give me 0, 1, 2, 3, or 4.
这段代码通过编译，而且返回 0, 1, 2, 3, 4 中的一个
So how do I do that? Extension int and then in here
那我要怎么做呢？ extension Int 然后
I put this var arc4random. I have to say what type it is,
把 var arc4random 放在里面。我必须要声名它的类型
it's also gonna be an int. It could could be a string or
它也是 Int 类型的。扩展里的变量也可以是 String
whatever but it's also gonna be an int. And
或是其他的类型，但这个是 Int 类型的
I'm essentially gonna return all this mess right here. So
它最终返回的就是所有这里这些乱七八糟的
I'm just gonna cut that out of there. I'm gonna return this.
我就把它剪切然后粘贴到 return 后面
But it's not a random number between 0 and
但这里就不是 0..<emojiChoices.count
emojiChoices.count, it's a random order between 0 and
之间的随机数了，应该是 0 到
what? Yes, whoa, I wish I could give extra credit or
是什么？没错，我希望我能够给附加分或者
like Mehran, throwing some candy out there or
像 Mehran（斯坦福 CS106A 的教授）一样扔糖给你
something because yes absolutely, it's between 0 and
因为没错，它应该是 0 到
self. Because this is a var in int. And so self is the int
self 之间。因为这是 Int 到属性，所以 self 就是
you sent it to. Which is really kind of cool. So now,
你访问这个属性的整数。这还蛮有趣的
since int can do this, all we need to do right here is we
现在 Int 有了这个属性，我们这里需要做的就是
don't need any of this junk up here. Instead of randomIndex,
我们可以不要这些乱七八糟的 randomIndex
we're just gonna say emojiChoices.count.arc4random.
我们只用写 emojiChoices.count.arc4random
Okay, so, that cleaned up our code a lot. Now,
这样我们就让代码整洁了许多
if we were to do something like this, and we wanted to
如果我们写了这段代码，而我们想要
be really good programmers, we'd look at this and say, hm,
做优秀的程序员，我们看了这个应该想
what if self is 0? Eh, this is not gonna work,
如果 self 是 0 怎么办？这个就不行了
cuz arc4random_uniform doesn't work, but
因为 arc4random_uniform 不接受 0。那
what if self is negative? Actually, if self were
如果 self 是负数怎么办？事实上如果 self
negative, maybe I could do a random number between 0 and
是负数的话，我应该可以随机选择 0 到
that negative number. So, I might decide, I'm gonna say if
那个那个负数之间的整数。所以我决定判断
self is greater than 0, then I'll do this.
如果 self 大于 0，我们就用这段代码
Else if self is less than 0, then I'm gonna almost do this.
否则如果 self 小于 0，那代码基本不变
What I'm gonna do, is I'm gonna say return minus this,
我要做的就是返回负的这个
the absolute value of myself. Okay,
上限用 abs 取 self 的绝对值
abs is just a global function. But I could also just say
这个 abs 就是个全局函数，但我也可以用
minus self cuz I checked to see if it's negative.
-self 因为我已经知道它是负数了
Or else if self is 0, which would be the else case here,
否则如果 self 是 0，也就是最后的 else 分支
then maybe I'll just return 0. So if you say, 0,
我就可以直接返回 0。如果你用 0.arc4random
give me a random number, it gives you a 0. So here I've
来获取一个随机数，它就会返回 0。这样我
made it that this never crashes. This doesn't have to
就保证它绝对不会让程序崩溃了，这个也不必要是
be an optional int and it gives a reasonable response.
可选的整数，同时返回的也是合理的结果
See, and that's pretty good. When you add vars and
看，这挺不错的。当你添加变量
functions to any class, not even just extensions,
或者函数到任何类型的时候，不只是在扩展里
you want them to have good semantics, sensible semantics.
你应该让他们有好的，合理的语义
And you don't generally don't want them to crash which is
而且一般你也不希望它容易让程序崩溃
what this would have done otherwise.
也就是我们之前一行代码的实现
If you sent it to -3.
比如你通过 -3 访问的话
Everyone see how this makes our code a lot more readable.
大家看到扩展让我们的程序更加易读了吗？
And how we added something that was sensible for int.
以及我们是如何给 Int 添加了合理的功能？
All right, that's it, let's get back to our slides again.
好，这就是扩展，让我们继续讲幻灯片
Here is arc4random. Okay, optionals,
这是我们刚讲的 arc4random，接着讲可选类型
the dreaded word optionals. So I told you last
听起来很吓人的 Optional。我上周
week that an optional is just a regular old type in Swift.
说 Optional 在 Swift 里就是个普通的类型
In fact it's a enum,
事实上它是个 enum
an enumeration. So let's learn about enum because enum is
枚举类型。我们先来学习下 enum，因为
another thing I wasn't able to work it into concentration,
另一个我没法加到翻牌游戏的就是枚举
although I am gonna work it into next week's demo. Okay,
索然我下周的演示里会用到
our drawing demo. But I want to explain what it is so
我们演示绘画的程序。但我想先解释它是什么
that I can explain what optionals are a little better.
这样我就能更好地把可选类型解释清楚
So an enum is just like an enum in other languages.
enum 和其他语言的枚举类型是一样的
It's a data type, just like struct is a type or
就是种数据类型，就像 struct 是一种类型
class is a type, enum is a type.
class 也是种类型一样，enum 也是种类型
Exactly the same, you can use it in exactly the same places.
都是数据类型，可以在同样的地方使用
It's just that it has only discrete values. Here's
只不过区别就是枚举类型包含了所有不同的可能性
a FastFoodMenuItem enum, it can only be hamburger, fries,
枚举 FastFoodMenuItem，快餐店的菜单上只会有汉堡，薯条
drink, or cookie. That's it, it can't be anything else
饮料或是饼干，就这些，不能是其他任何的东西
besides one of those four things, so
只能是这四种中的一种
that's what an enum is. Enums are value types, like structs,
they get copied as you pass them around. Now enums in
Swift little bit more powerful then your typical enum because
each case can also have what's called associated data, or
an associated value. So in my fast food item one my
hamburgers have the number of patties,
is it a double burger or a triple or
a single? The fries has the size of the fries,
a large fry, or a small. And I've even used another enum,
you see down here at the bottom.
I have another, oops, my thing work here. There it is.
This is not very good. Okay, we got it. There it is. So
I can use another enum there to do the size of it and
then drink. It has two pieces of associated data.
Okay, let's see if we can get this working for that.
And if you look at its two pieces of associated data,
look at the first one.
That string, it has no name. These other ones have names,
like number of patties, size, this one has no name for
the first one, it does have a name for the second one.
First the strings and then an int. Now the names here don't
matter that much because when we extract this information,
we're gonna be able to give it our own name anyway,
kind of like tuples. In fact, these look a lot like tuples,
don't they? These little associated datas,
they're kind of like tuples because you can have as many
of them as you want, you specify the type,
they have names, they're super simple, and
they look very much like tuples. So, anyway,
so this is what it looks like to declare an enum with
associated data. Now, how do you assign an enum?
So here is two variables, one called menu item,
one called other item. They are of type FastFoodMenuItem,
that's their type. And so I set them just by saying
FastFoodMenuItem dot the case I want.
And if it has associated data, I have to provide it.
So the only time you can set the associated data of an enum
is when you assign it. That's the only time. Okay,
you can't go back later and change this to be a triple,
because this is fundamentally a double burger.
That's what it is. And it's never, if it changed, it would
change into a completely different thing. All right, so
you don't change the patties, got that? All right, so, when
you're setting these values by the way of course you can use
type inference, but only on one side of that equals. So
you could say menuItem equals FastFoodMenuItem.hamburger.
Which was what was on the previous slide, or
you could say otherItem of type FastFoodMenuItem equals
.cookie. You see,
I've just basically moved the type to the other side. But
you can't say yet another item equals .cookie. Swift doesn't
know enough there to infer the type on the other side. There
could be other enums with .cookie in it, for example,
that you might add later. And then all of a sudden your code
won't compile because it doesn't know. So
it just says from the start, I don't know what that is.
Now how do you check what an enum is?
You do not use equals. So you don't say,
if this menu item equals a hamburger then whatever, okay,
you do not use equals, you use switch. Again, other languages
have switch. Switch is more powerful in Swift.
This is the basic use of switch right here, where I'm
just looking at every possible case that it could be, and
if it's that case, I do a little bit of code.
So here I'm just printing out what the various cases are so
if it's hamburgers, for example,
you can see that I'm printing burger.
Notice that I'm ignoring the associated data here which is
perfectly fine.
You're allowed to completely ignore the associated data
when you're checking the state with switch. Now
switch requires you to address every single case. You are not
allowed to look at only two of the cases. But, of course,
it's got something that can help you with that. Oh yes,
by the way, you see I've taken away the FastFoodMenuItem.,
in front of hamburger, fries, drink, and coke. Becuase swift
can infer that, you're switching on a menu item, so
it knows this is a FastFoodMenuItem, so
you can take those away. All right, so if you have one of
the cases, and you don't wanna do anything, you can just
break. Break means break out of this switch. So
that's a way to do nothing in this case. So, right here,
this code, we print nothing because the hamburger case,
the menu item is a hamburger with two patties, and
that hamburger case does nothing, so
we'll just break out and do nothing. Similarly,
if you want to do something for all the rest of the cases,
like here I only want to do something for
hamburger and fries. Actually I do nothing for hamburger and
I do something for fries.
In all other cases, I just want to print other, then you
can use default instead of case whatever. Now in switch,
you can switch any type, you can even switch on a string.
But if you switch on a string, you'd have to have case A,
case B, case C, case AA, case AB, you see what I mean?
You'd have to have every case in the world.
So of course you're going to use default ion a string case
switch case the couple
ones you wanna case, then you would default the rest. So
default is a must even for enums we use it quite a bit,
all right? So that's break an enum. So
if this were a cookie then it would print other. All right,
multiple lines, I just wanted to make clear that, multiple
lines of code are allowed, it doesn't have to be one line.
That was just cuz I'm on slides here,
I'm trying to make everything fit, and
there's no fall through. So in this case, I've got fries,
you see up there at the top, fries,
large fries there. And
so this code would print out yummy fires and that's it. So
I have multiple lines of code in there under fries,
two lines of code, and it does not fall through and do drink,
like in other languages. In C, things fall through, in switch
but they don't fall through here. There is a keyword
called fallthrough that would let you fall through, but
by default it doesn't. By the way that it inferred
the type all along in here, it can for that type as well.
I don't have to say size,fries size enum.large,
I can just say, .large because it knows that the associated
data of fries is s fries size enum. Okay,
now, what if I want to get the associated data. So I do,
I am interested in it. We do that with switch as well,
we just do this little let business. See the little lets.
In all the cases that you want this associated data,
you don't have to do it in all cases, but
in the ones you want it? You just say, open parentheses,
let and a name of a little local variable for
each of the associated pieces of data. Now,
that little name that you use, so if this were a coke see it
would print whatever ounces coke right there, cuz just
getting the Coke into brand. It's getting the ounces into
something called ounces, and then it's doing that print.
This naming does not have to be the same names
as you declared the enum from. In fact,
if we look at this Coke one right here, this let brand,
remember in the original enum that didn't even have a name,
it was just a string, right? And it had ounces,
colon ounces, and up here with hamburger, pattyCount,
that was called patties in the original declaration. So
again, does this not look familiar to tuples, right?
You can rename them when you're getting the information
out of them. So this is how you extract data
out of the associated types. Very simple, and
again it's optional you don't have to have it there.
Also enums, they're like structs and classes.
They can have methods and they can have vars, but no storage.
All the stories of an enum is in which case it is and
that case is associated data.
That's it, you can't have many other vars or anything else.
So the only vars you could have are computed vars.
So see the example I have here where it's calories,
where you'd compute the calories of that menu item
that would have to be a computed type. Can't store
anything in an enum except for the associated data right
there. Now if you're writing a func like this one,
isIncludedInSpecialOrder number one or number two or
whatever. If you're doing that, then you can
get your own associated data using switch on self.
Cuz I'm inside the enum to permutation here, right?
So I can switch on self, and then,
I could get my associated data out so
I can calculate my calories. Or
in this case, I'm calculating whether the hamburger with
two patties is included in special order number two.
And my code here says yes because pretty much,
special order number one is a single burger,
and/or number two is a double. Now there's some other
interesting things to look at in this code. Notice that
fries and cookie right there. Right in the middle, fries and
cookie. Those I combine them into one case,
which that's allowed with commas you can have multiple
going on there. Also noticing drink, okay, I'm
getting the number of ounces in a drink but evidently in
a special order you can have any drink that's 16 ounces.
So I don't care what kind of drink it is, I don't care for
that brand. So I use the universal i don't care symbol
in Swift which is under bar, right? Remember, we used
underbar when we didn't care what the external name and
touch card was. We used it in a four loop when we didn't
care what the identifier was anymore in concentration,
so we can use it here as well, all right?
You can modify self in an enum as long as it's in a var. If
it's modifiable, you just say self equals some other case.
And if that other case requires associated data,
you'll have to provide it then, you can say self equals.
Now, a very important thing to notice here, if you're going
to modify yourself in an enum by saying self equals,
that's the only way to modify yourself,
by the way. Then you have to put mutating
in front of the function that mutates you,
that modifies self.
That's because fast enum is a value type and
remember the value types are passed around by copying but
there is copy on write. So if it doesn't copy on write which
means it doesn't actually make a copy until you write.
Well if it's gonna do that,
it needs to know which funcs might write. So
that's what mutating means, it means this func might write,
it might change this. You have to do exactly the same thing
in a struct. If you have a func in a struct, and
it modifies any internal state of
the struct, it has to be marked mutating, so
the Swift knows to copy and write. And not to worry, Swift
is super smart, it'll see your code, it'll see you're saying
self equal, it'll see that you're modifying your bars in
a struct And it will complain and say this is protected you
can't write to this thing coz this is not a mutating func.
And you can fix it by making it mutating and
in fact you can see that concentration demo in a second
here. All right so let's see if for enums, very simple.
So an optional then is just an enum, it looks like this,
kind of, conceptually. It's an optional,
it's a generic type like array is. Array can have anything in
it, an optional can be an optional Int,
an optional string, whatever it's a generic type. And
it has two cases in the enum,
the case none which is not set, nill, and the other case
some in which it has some associated data of that type.
So an optional int that would mean int, so that's it,
that's what an optional is. Now an optional, Why don't,
why didn't we just leave it in enum?
Well, God, can you imagine,
every time you wanna unwrap an optional, you're having to
switch on that thing in case some get the associated data?
That would be so much typing. So all of these special
characters we have are optionals, question marks,
exclamation points, ifs, double question marks.
All that stuff is just so that we don't have to be constantly
switching on our optional and doing case this, case that.
But that's all it's doing under the covers,
it's just syntactic sugar that is doing that.
It's not doing anything else,
it's not, nothing special. And so I'm gonna show you what all
these special characters look like in enum land.
And, and I'm even gonna show you a new enum or
a new optional thing, which is this thing at the bottom
called optional chaining. And it's where you use a single
question mark when you're accessing an optional.
Which that's the one thing we have not seen, and I'm gonna
show you how that works by showing you in enum land.
All right? So, declaring optionals, obvious, right?
If I say hello, which is an optional string,
that's just optional angle brackets string. And
remember that optionals always start out nil. So, I'm gonna,
it's gonna start out none. Couldn't be simpler.
Unwrapping, also very simple, that's just switching
on the thing. So, if I have an optional string hello, and I
say print(hello!), exclamation point to unwrap it,
I'm just switching on hello. And if it's in the none case,
I crash. And if it's in the some case,
then I print whatever the associated data is. Same thing
down with if let at the bottom there. I'm switching on hello.
If it's in the some case, I do it.
If it's in the none case,
I do the else part of the if. Everybody got that?
Implicitly unwrapped optionals are exactly the same. It's
just that when I say print hello over here on this side,
this print hello, I don't have to put the exclamation point.
And it still switches on hello and crashes if it's none. So
that's implicitly unwrapped. Those start out as nil too
because they're just optionals. The nil-coalescing
operator, which is that defaulting thing we used,
if you remember, in our code. We looked in our emoji
dictionary, and if it wasn't there,
then we returned question mark. That's just
switching on it. And if it's in the case none, then it uses
the default, okay, the thing on the other side. And
if it's in the case some, then it uses the thing it found.
This is optional chaining. So optional chaining, imagine
right here, okay, if you look at this little let x equal,
imagine that x and the method foo and
the var bar, all three of those, imagine those return
an optional string. Okay, so we don't know what they do,
but they return an optional string.
They may or may not return nil. Okay, well, what optional
chaining there allows us to do is to call those thing,
things in sequence called one. And
then when we get the value, call the next thing on that.
And we get the value, call the next thing on that. And
if at any time any of those things is nil, we just bail
out and return nil. So the way that works in optional land is
we switch on that first. If it's none, we return nil.
But if it's not, we get the data and call foo.
If that works, we get the, that data from foo, and
we call bar. And then eventually,
we set y equal to z that comes out of that, right?
We're just moving across the chain. If, at any time,
any of those things is nil, look at all the case nones.
Case .none, case .none, case .none, y gets to be nil, and
we're done and move along. Okay, so that's optional
chaining. I made it optional, no pun intended, for
you to read about that in your current assignment.
I recommend you do because you can make really beautiful code
using optional chaining. It's really nice.
Okay, so we're gonna finish up today with a little review and
a look forward to the data structures to use to build
an app in Swift. These are the four, class,
struct, enum, and protocol. Protocol is the new one that
I'm gonna talk about starting on Wednesday. So a class,
as we know, supports an object-oriented design.
It has single inheritance of both functionality and data.
You inherit the data, your vars.
Stored vars get inherited, um, as well as all your methods
and stuff. It's a reference type, lives in the heap.
Now one thing we didn't talk about, though,
this class lives in the heap. When does it get cleaned up
out of the heap? And how does that happen? Okay, so yeah, so
if, people who are coming from Java, you're probably like,
oh, garbage collection maybe? Okay, um, but no, okay,
Swift does not use garbage collection.
It uses a very awesome system called reference counting. And
in fact, it's automatic reference counting,
it's all handled for you. So how does reference counting
work? Okay, we need to talk a little bit about that.
So let's take a little detour here. By the way, examples of
classes that we've seen of course are UI view controller,
view controller, which is our subclass of it, UI button,
UI label, concentration, we made that a class. Those
are all classes, not structs, right? All right, so let's
talk about how this automatic reference counting thing
works. It's really simple, every time, somehow magically,
every time that you create a pointer to a reference type in
the heap, Swift adds one to some counter somewhere. And
every time that pointer to it goes out of scope or
is not pointed to it anymore, like it was an optional,
it got set to nil, for example,
then it decrements that count. And when that count goes to 0,
it takes it out of the heap instantly. It's not like
it's keeping track, and it's doing any marking and
sweeping, like a garbage collection. It actually
instantly removes it as soon as no one points to it. So
it couldn't be simpler, it's exact way you would think,
conceptually, to make it work.
It's actually quite difficult under the covers to do that.
Swift was designed with it in mind from start.
So it's an awesome system. You can influence
this automatic reference counting a little bit.
You can't really control it, but you can influence,
with these three key words when you declare a var,
okay, a strong, weak, and unowned.
These are the three kind of influencers you can do.
The first one, strong, is normal reference counting.
So that just means if there's a, this pointer is strong, and
so keep that thing in the heap as long as this is around,
because I need it, I'm pointing to it.
That's the default.
So, we never actually type the keyword strong.
It's the default. It's always there.
It's kind of like internal with that access control.
We don't actually ever type that.
Now weak, you've actually seen before. You all remember weak?
It was on the outlets. Okay,
when we made that outlet connection, I said oh,
that, see that weak? I'm gonna tell you about that next week.
Well, I'm living up to my promise, I'm telling you about
weak. What does weak mean? Weak means I'm
pointing to this thing in the heap, but I'm only really
interested in it if someone else is interested in it.
In other words, if someone else has a strong pointer to
it, keep it in the heap. But as soon as no one else is
interested in this, in other words,
all other strong pointers go away. Set me to nil and
throw the thing out of the heap. So this is the don't
keep that thing in the heap on my account kind of pointer.
And notice that it gets set to nil if all the other strong
pointers go away. So what kind of type does this have to be?
It has to be an optional.
So this weak only works with optional pointers to
reference types, okay, things that are in the heap,
which our outlets are. If you remember our outlets,
like flip count label was a UI label exclamation point. That
was an implicitly unwrapped optional. It was an optional,
right? Same thing card buttons was an implicitly unwrapped
optional. So those pointers to things in the UI.
If for some reason those things left the UI, okay,
got removed from the UI somehow, which is possible,
but rare. Then those things would get set to nil, okay?
And you would no longer be pointing to them,
and that's what they want.
Because if there's no flip count label,
there's no use trying to update it. So
that's why they make those weak All right, now, weak,
there's only a couple of places that we use we
commonly. One is for outlets, another one is for delegation.
Remember back to my NBC talk, I talked about the delegation,
the data source. And we have these pointers from the view
back to the controller where there's that blind and
structure of communication all that,
which I'm gonna talk about on Wednesday.
Those pointers are weak, because the view,
if the thing that they're sending will did and
should to goes away, well, they're not gonna send those
messages anymore, so they want to be nil, okay. There's no
one to send their messages to then they just want to be nil,
okay. They don't want to be pointed to something.
They certainly don't want a thing it points to,
to get stuck in the heap because of it.
Because they're happy to just not send the messages if
that thing wants to leave the heap, otherwise we don't
use weak that much. Okay, last is unowned.
Unowned is don't reference count this,
in other words I'm pointing to something in the heap, but
don't count it as a strong pointer. And I promise I'll
never access this thing when it's gone from the heap. Now,
this is very dangerous, this is basically trying to
outsmart the automatic reference counting system.
You're saying, you know when it's in the heap or not, and
this is really rare. And the way,
the one time we use this is to avoid a memory cycle, okay.
Everyone know what a memory cycle is,
that's where you have something in the heap and
it points to something else in the heap, and
that thing points back to it.
So, they're pointing to each other, keeping each other in
the heap. But no one else is interested in them. No one
points to either of them. They only just point to each other.
So they're just sitting in the heap for no reason.
No one's even accessing them, that's a memory cycle. And
memory cycles aren't generally created in Swift normally but
there's one way they're easy to create which is
closures, okay.
Which is a feature I'm gonna talk about on Wednesday, okay.
And so we will use unowned with closures. All right,
back to our list of data structures here, of course
there's struct we know all about that. It's a value type,
it's copy owned right, there's no inheritance of data.
But you're gonna learn with protocols there is inheritance
of functionality,
in fact multiple inheritance of functionality. And you've
seen examples of struct cards, dictionary, string, character,
int, double, UInt32, lots of structs have happened
there. And I have here, let's jump over to concentrations
see what happens when we make concentration of struct.
I start off the next one with that because we're pretty much
How about
out of time here. Enum, I'm not going to,
oh yes, this is the demo, which I will do next time. And
then enum here we already just covered, so I'm not going to
talk about it, another value type, discrete values. It also
can have inherit the same kind of functionality inheritance.
This functionality inheritance that I keep kind of mentioning
is done using this last one, which is called protocols.
So I'm gonna start off on Wednesday with a detailed
explanation of what a protocol is.
It's fundamental to the design of all of foundation,
all the array, dictionary, string, int.
And all of those things fundamentally using protocols
everywhere, massive number of protocols.
And it's also fundamental with things like delegation and
stuff like that, so it's very, very important. And to round
out our full understanding of how to build data structures
in Swift. Okay, so we'll start off on Wednesday with that and
I will see you then. >> For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.
>> 更多课程详见 stanford.edu