本字幕由志愿者义务贡献，采用许可协议
知识共享 署名-非商业性使用-相同方式共享 3.0 美国
>> Stanford University. >> Hey, well,
>> 斯坦福大学 >> 大家好
welcome to Lecture number 7, Stanford CS193P, Fall 2017. So
欢迎来到 2017 年秋季学期 CS193P 的第七节课
our primary topic today is combining MVCs to make bigger,
今天，我们的主要任务显然就是将多个 MVC 组合成组件更多，
more powerful applications, obviously. And
功能更强大的应用程序。
then I'm gonna do a big demo that shows you how to do that.
同时，我也将示范编写一个更大的样例程序来向你们展示该如何完成这项工作。
We're gonna do it with Concentration, we're gonna add
本次的示范将以 Concentration 这个 app 为基础，我们将来要向其添加
an MVC into that app. Then I'll come back to the slides,
一个 MVC。然后我会回到幻灯片上，
and talk I'll about timer and choose classes, some of you
（这里疑似all about）我会讲授有关计时器和选择类的相关内容，
used in the extra credit of the homework assignments. And
这部分内容你们可能会在作业的选做部分需要用到。
then I'm gonna dive into the next topic and try and
然后的时间我会尽可能深入讲解下一个主题，也就是动画部分，
get as far as I can which is animation.
能讲多少讲多少。
Which will be our topic on Wednesday and
这也将是我们在周三的课程上的主要内容，
I'll get to much more detail, do a big demo.
并且我会更深入地讲解更多细节性内容，做一个更大的示范程序。
But I wanna kinda get in as far as I can today just so
我今天会尽可能地讲解理论部分的内容，
we have more time for a demo on Wednesday.
这样我们周三上课时就会有足够的时间进行操作示范。
Alright so combining MVCs, remember this slide from when
回到整合 MVC 上来，还记得我们讲解 MVC 时使用的这张幻灯片吗？
I talked about MVC. This is the MVCs working together, and
这就是多个 MVCs 协同工作的示意图，
we saw that when we have MVCs working together,
我们可以看到，当多个 MVCs 协同工作时，
these other MVCs. Let me get my thing under control here,
其他的 MVC……（此处幻灯片动画出错）让我把它修好……
well, can't do it. Okay, these other MVCs down in the corner,
好吧，它彻底坏掉了。其他的角落里的 MVCs
they serve as part of the view of another MVC. That's
他们通过控制其他 MVC 中的一个 view，来为整个 app 服务。
the way MVC's relate. An MVC is a view, part of a view
这就是 MVC 之间相互联系的方法。一个 MVC 就是一个 view，同时也是其他类中的 view 的一部分。
of another class. And that has some ramifications for MVC,
most notably it has to have blind structured communication
back to the other MVC. But that's the way we
structure it, and that keeps everything well contained and
understandable. So we're gonna talk about how we do that,
how we make MVCs that are the view of other MVCs. So,
combining MVCs we do this using some special
controllers that iOS provides whose view is other MVCs.
Now you could write your own special MVC whose view is
other MVCs. But 99% of the time you're gonna use one of
the three that iOS provides. And the three that iOS
provides are TabBarController, SplitViewController, and
navigation controller. Now there are other ways to
combine MVCs we'll talk about later in the quarter but
this is the primary way that we're gonna do it with these
three MVC's. Those three here, TabBar, SplitView, and
NavigationController, they are the controllers of MVCs. So
let's look at them one by one.
TabBar is by far the simplest one,
you've seen this a million times, it's got
some tabs along the bottom there. You see those tabs,
like a little orange thing and the gray one's next to it. And
each of those tabs, when you press it, shows another MVC.
So you can already see that the TabBarController's view
includes the buttons at the bottom and another MVC. So
this is what we mean by the view of this tab bar
controller MVC gives another MVC. And the icon and
the title that appears down in the TabBar,
that's determined by which MVC is showing.
In specific UI view controller has this bar TabBar item.
And the TabBar controller, when it shows the MVC as part
of its view, it looks at that so it knows what the title and
icon to display down at the bottom there. This is all very
object oriented in that sense. So, for example here we've got
some sort of health oriented API here and
we've got the four tabs at the bottom. By the way, if there's
more than four tabs, more than four MVCs, it can show that,
actually, it'll show five. And if they're six, then
the fifth one becomes a little more button and you click it.
And iOS provides an API or UI, rather, for the user to pick
which tabs they want to be there at the bottom, or
to pick some other tab that's not showing. Generally though,
we recommend no more than five MVCs in a TabBarController.
That's kinda just pretty good UI,
It just starts to get a little complicated for
the user if there's more than that. So, in this case,
this whole thing is five MVCs, the TabBarController itself,
and the four MVCs that serve as its view and
you just switch between them by clicking.
So this is by far the easiest Of the MVCs of MVCs,
all right? Next, let's talk about SplitViewController,
probably the second simplest one. It's only two MVCs in its
view, and it puts them side by side with a very thin line in
between them. So, here's a little calculator app,
It's got the calculator on the left and then it's got maybe
a graph of what's in the calculator on the right. And
we call this MVC that's on the left, and it's usually smaller
like this, the Master in the SplitViewController, and
we call the one on the right the Detail. And
we call them master detail cuz usually what you do on the one
on the left affects what happens on the right. It's
the master, the detail is kind of little bit of a slave. And,
of course, this is on iPad. It also works on iPhone Pluses,
but non-plus iPhones. This little side-by-side mechanism.
You can, of course, rotate your iPad.
And when you rotate your iPad into portrait, now
it'll only show the detail, except for you can slide out
with your finger from the left and see the Master,
then slide it back. Now on an iPhone Plus in portrait,
it acts like a normal iPhone, it doesn't have the slide out.
Even if an iPhone Plus is not quite wide enough to
slide that thing out. So, SplitViewController, super,
super easy. And then there's NavigationController.
This is probably the most flexible, most powerful of
the MVC of MVCs, you've seen this a million times in IOS
apps. You can think of a NavigationController MVC,
as a deck of cards. And each card is an MVC. And what
the navigation controller does is let you put an MVC on top,
obscuring all the ones below. And then if you hit the back
button, it throws that one away, and shows you the one
that was there before. And you can keep going back, and
it keeps showing the cards off the top, and
you put new cards back on. So it's like a card stack, where
the stack are MVCs. And you can see that the navigation
controller as part of its view it does actually draw a little
bit. At the top it draws a little title there, right?
The settings, okay, that's not part of the MVC that's
showing right there. But the content that are in that title
are driven by whatever MVCs on top of the card stack,
the one that's showing. So that's called settings
because the MVC that's there is the settings MVC, so
it's being driven by what's there. And each MVC,
similar with the tab bar item and the tab bar controller,
there's a var in UI Controller called navigationItem. And
that contains things like the title and other buttons that
you can put in the title bar, all kinds of stuff.
You're gonna wanna go look at the documentation for
navigationItem and
see what kind of things the navigation controller can
do for you when your MVC is on top of the stack. So
if I then click on something, this is a table view here,
we'll talk about table views next week or the week after.
If I click on something here then a new MVC slides in,
animates in on top. Now there are two cards on this stack.
All settings one which is now behind,
we can't see it, and now this new one on top of course.
By the way you can also have tool bar
items on the bottom using the tool bar items bar of view
controller, so those two of our items would come and
go as new ones come on the stack. But
also notice that when we have two things on there,
a little back button appears in the upper left,
automatically. It even has the name of the one that's
lower down on the stack of cards. And if you press that,
of course it's gonna throw this card away, and
we'll be back at the other card. But lets imagine I click
on something in this one like this
accessibility thing. It puts a new card on there,
that's the accessibility card. Maybe I click on something
inside the accessibility card like larger text, and it puts
another one on. Now we have four MVCs on the the stack.
So there's a total of five MVCs here.
The navigation controller itself which is an MVC, and
these four MVCs which are part of its view. And of course we
know we can backup if we pres the back button and
it throws that button away, and it actually does throws
the card away. Throws it out of the heap.
So it's complete throw away, this card now gets thrown
away, we are just now seeing the card on the underneath
until we go all the way the back, To the beginning and
now we're seeing the root card, the root
view controller, this is called a navigationController.
All right, so everybody knows about navigationController,
you've seen it everywhere.
Here's how navigational controller's working behind
the scenes in terms of looking at it from an MVC standpoint.
So let's say I have a MVC that's shown there,
and I have more API or more UI than I can fit on
my screen, so I need to got to another screen to do more UI.
That's the little thing in the corner right there. Well, to
do that I have to make another MVC that will control that UI.
And then when I make my navigationController
to have them share the screen, the navigationController comes
up and this is what its UI looks like. But as soon
as you set a very important var in navigationController,
call it rootViewController to be some MVC,
then its view now includes the view of that MVC. And
then, if you interact with some button or
something that's in that MVC's view,
it can move to this other MVC, push it on the stack.
Now the other MVC is still there, it's just kind of
behind the scenes because it's lower on the stack, and a back
button will automatically appear as we saw.
When we click this back we move back to the other one,
and notice that the MVC that we had originally added
on there is gone. So it's very important to understand
as we use the navigationController,
usually when we put things on we're creating a new one and
when we take things off we're throwing it away.
That is the normal operation of a navigationController. It
can be used in other ways but that is it's normal operation.
Okay, so those are the three kinds of MVCs of MVCs.
How do you get at them? Okay, it's really easy actually.
Each of those three different kinds of MVCs has a var called
viewControllers, it's just an array of view controller. So
for a tab bar it's just the view controllers one, two,
three, four in order I think from left to right,
the tabs. If it's a split-view controller,
then view controller sub 0 is the master and
view controller sub 1 is the detail.
Or sometimes we say the first thing in the array is
the master and the last thing in the array is the detail.
And if it's a navigationController, then
viewController sub 0 is the rootViewController, and all of
these cards lined on top are the other viewControllers
in the array in order. So that's how you can get at all
the viewControllers that are in one of the MVCs of MVCs.
Now, how do you get at the MVC of MVCs itself?
How do you get to the navigationController,
the splitViewController, whatever?
Well there's three awesome vars in UI view controller
called tabBarController, splitViewController, and
navigationController. And they will tell you the tabBar
controller you're in, or the splitViewController you're
in or the navigationController you're in. It might be in more
than one, because you might be inside a navigationController
as the master in a splitViewController.
Which might even be in a tab of a tab bar controller, so
you could be in all three of these things, and this will
return what you're in. And so this way you can kinda get
at the other MVCs that are involved in whatever
combination of MVCs you have. So it's really good
kind of access to things. Now navigationController,
I wanna just briefly tell you about the API for
it, it has a method pushViewController and
popViewController, both can be animated. And
that takes an MVC and puts it on the stack of your cars or
popViewController pops the top one off. Okay,
so you can do that pushing and popping, but we don't usually
do it that way. We usually use what are called segues which
I'm going to talk about in a moment here.
All right, so
how do we wire all of this stuff in our storyboard up?
Okay, how do we get these navigationControllers, and
splitViewControllers and
tabBarControllers all hooked up to our MVCs? Okay, well
of course we do it with Ctrl drag in the interface field,
we do everything with Ctrl drag, right? Constraints,
outlets, actions, all of these stuff with Ctrl drag, and
we use Ctrl drag to do this as well. So
let's look at an example of a splitViewController.
If I wanted to have a couple of MVCs and
set them as the master and
the detail in splitViewController,
I would just drag out a splitViewController from
the same place I get a button or
something. It will come with a bunch of extra VCs by the way,
view controller is kind of, that it comes with for fun or
for free. I'm not sure why it does it. We usually almost
always just delete them. And then we Ctrl drag from
the splitViewController to our master and we control drag
to our detail. Same thing with a tabBarController, we drag it
out and then we just Ctrl drag to each of the MVCs in there.
NavigationController is a little bit different and
I'll show you that in a moment.
So this is what it looks like approximately in interface
builder ,here's the calculator again. I dragged out
a splitViewController there on the left, I just Ctrl drag
to the master. I choose Master View Controller from the thing
that pops up. I Ctrl dragged it to the other one,
I choose detail, bam, I've got a wired up splitViewController
right there. Couldn't be simpler. Now the split view
can really only do it's thing fully on an iPad.
Cuz there's just not enough screen real
estate on other devices to really do this side by
side thing, especially the portrait mode slide out thing,
there's just not enough room there. So what we often do
is wrap the master in a navigationController.
And when we do that then the system can show it
in a navigationController on an iPhone, and
in a splitViewController on an iPad.
It'll automatically adapt, that's the word we use to
describe that to the environment it's in.
So that makes it really easy for us to build UIs that work
on both. They work on iPads, they work on iPhones.
Okay, same exact storyboard. So here's what that looks
like, here's my split view with my master and
my detail there, we're looking at the master. And
I 'm selecting it and I'm going to the menu and
I'm saying editor embed in navigationController.
So instead of dragging the navigationController out,
which I could do by the way and
just Ctrl drag them up, but instead of dragging it out you
can actually do this embed in navigationController.
And it will insert a navigationController MVC
in as the master and make my previous thing that was
the master be it's rootViewController.
So, now I have a navigationController
wrapping around the master of my split view. Okay, this also
has a nice benefit, it puts a title on your master,
which is often nice to have a title of your master of
your split view. Now you can- One thing to notice about this
of course, is that now the master of your split view is
现在你的 Split View 的主视图控制器不再是 Calculator 了，
no longer the calculator, it's a navigationController.
而是一个 navigationController。
So if you actually wanted to get out the calculator,
如果你确实想要获取到 calculator，
you would have to get the master and
你必须先获取到主视图控制器，
then look at the master's rootViewController to find
然后找到它的 rootViewController，
the calculator there.
你要找的 calculator 在那里。
By the way, you can also put the detail, wrap it in
另外，你也可以把你的细节视图控制器放在一个 navigationController 中
a navigationController. The only reason you would ever
你想做这件事，唯一的原因就是
want to do that is to give it a title bar, cuz you don't,
想给它一个标题栏。
you always navigate from the master, that's why it's called
你总是从主视图控制器导入的，这也是他被称为“主”的原因。
the master. So you can do it, but again if you do that,
所以你可以这么做，不过再一次，如果你这么做的话
make sure when you look at the detail, if you find that
确保当你关注 detail 的时候，
it's a navigationController, you need to look inside and
如果你发现他是一个 navigationController，你就需要向里看，
see the thing that's inside of it, the rootViewController.
找到它内部的视图控制器，rootViewController。
Or you can also use visibleViewController
或者你也可以用 visibleViewController
on a navigationController,
that will tell you the card that's on the top,
that's visible. All right, so that's how we wire up split
views navigationControllers together. How do we make it so
that when we click something in a view it causes
some card to slide on, or it causes the detail of our split
view to change, right? We're doing the calculator,
we enter some equation, we press the graph button.
Well in the iPhone we wanna slide a graph in front,
on the stack. And on the iPad we want to replace the detail
view with a graph of what's in my current calculator.
So how do we do that? We do that with what's called
segues. A segue just makes a brand new MVC,
always a new MVC, I'm gonna say that three or
four times, so that sinks in. Always a new MVC,
it makes it and puts it on the top of the stack or
puts it in the right side of a splitViewController.
So here are the kinds of segues that exist.
There is a Show Segue, that's the kind of segue that works
in a navigationController.
Okay, that causes the new MVC to be
put on top of a stack if you're not Inside a Navigation
Controller you probably shouldn't be doing Show Segue.
Then there's Show Detail, that works in a split view. So
Show Detail will replace the right side of the split view.
Then there's Modal and Popover,
which I'm going to talk about later in the quarter.
Modal takes over the entire screen. So forget about any
navigation controllers or split view controllers, or
tab view controllers. It takes over the entire screen and
just fills the screen with the MVC.
We generally try to avoid Modal because it puts
the app in this kind of stuck state where it's only the MVC
that you've taken over the screen with is active,
can be kind of disconcerting for the user but
sometimes we do want things to be Modal. And
then Popover Segue is kind of like a Modal segue but
instead of taking over the whole screen,
it just puts it up in a little popover.
You've seen that on an iPad especially. But
it's still modal because the background is grayed out and
you can't interact with it,
you can only do the thing in the popover. So
we'll talk about those segues later in the quarter.
Today I'm just gonna talk about show and show detail. So
this is in red.
I'm just re-emphasizing that segues always create a new
instance of the MVC. Segues always create a new instance
of the MVC. This is important to understand. You're not
gonna be reusing some MVC that you had on screen before. And
we'll show in our demo today, what we can do about this if
we really do want re-use of MVCs. By the way, the back
button in a navigation controller is not a segue.
That's just part of the navigation controller,
so when you go back you're not creating a new MVC. You're
going back to the one that was on the stack underneath.
All right, so how do we make these segues happen?
Ctrl-drag. We do Ctrl-drag for everything.
It can also be done in code as well, and
I'll show you how to do that in the demo, too.
So, if I have this calculator example. Here's my split view
with the navigation controller around the master, and
I've got a button in my calculator
which is show me a graph of what's currently in
the calculator. I just Ctrl-drag from that button.
Down to the lower left here to my detail. And
when I let go of the control drag a little black window is
going to come up and there is it more detail and
it will choose the show detail segway there. Okay, and
that will create this little line. See the line that it
created right there, which we can click on and inspect. And
that little line is called a segue, so that's
a thing in your storyboard that you can inspect.
And why do you wanna inspect that little line?
Mostly because you wanna give a unique identifier which is
just a string. So I'm gonna call this one for
example show graph cuz that's what this segue does. And
then in my code, I can refer to that segue by the name,
show graph. Everything in interface builder files,
all these storyboards, is always referenced by name. And
the great thing about that is that you can copy and paste
things to one storyboard to another as long as the names
in your code are their right names, it'll just work.
So that's why it goes by name.
Okay, it does everything by name. Some people think it
kind of can be a little annoying that you have to have
these names that are exactly the same in the code and
in the storyboard. But it turns out to be quite
a flexible thing to do it that way. A little more work for
the programmer to ensure that those things are the same but
kinda worth it in flexibility, I think.
All right, so that's the main thing you wanna inspect.
You can also inspect whether it's show detail or
show, but you're gonna see that, in my demo, you actually
don't wanna change that show detail to show right there.
Your better off creating a new segue. Okay, so
that's segues. So that identifier. Why do we want it?
Where would we use it in our code? What's an example? Well,
one way is you can perform a segue from code.
So manually cause a segue to happen. Okay well to do that
you need to know which segue it is in the storyboard you
want to perform manually and so you can do perform segway.
We don't usually perform manually. I'll show it in
the demo we don't usually do it that often. Okay because
the real way we do it is just the control dragging and
that's gonna automatically segue from that button so
we don't need to do it from the code. But
the most important use of identifier is to prepare
the MVC that you're segue to. Okay think about
the calculator example. I press graph and it's going to
show me a graph, presumably it's going to show me a graph
of what's in my calculator. Well I have
to somehow let that new graphing MVC know what
equation to graph. We call that preparing that
MVC to do it's job and segues always create a new MVC so
they always have to be prepared to do what they do.
Makes sense? So we do that with a function called prepare
for segues. This function is implemented in the MVC,
that is causing the segues to happen. It's obviously
the only one who could prepare the new MVC To be ready to go.
This is what that method looks like.
Prepare for segue. It has two arguments: the segue,
which is a UI storyboard segue.
That segue mostly just has the identifier and
also the MVC that we need to prepare.
The MVC that it just created, that we're going to segue to
the second argument there, the sender that's the button or
the line in a table view. Or if you're doing it from code
it can be almost anything, that's why it's of type any.
That cause this segue to happen,
that could also be nil. It's happening, you don't know or
care, who did it. So that's what those two arguments are.
All right, now let's dive into this thing.
The first thing we usually do is take a look
at our identifier, our segue identifier which could be nil.
Shouldn't be, you always wanna set an identifier in your
story board. But we look at it and
here I'm gonna switch on it, although,
we can use if then on it, and find out which segue it is.
And that's because an MVC can have multiple different
buttons, each that segue to a different kind of MVC. So
we obviously, have to prepare them differently.
So, we need to know which one is which.
So, that's why we check the identifier to see
which segue we're talking about. Then, we need to get
the MVC that we are segueing to and prepare it.
Okay, well, segue.destination, that var segue.
That var destination in the segue object is passed to you.
That is the view controller that you're segueing to,
the brand new just created MVC, all right. But
the type of that argument is not gonna be a graph
controller or something like that, it's going to be just
UI View controller. That's because Segue,
UI Storyboard Segue Class, each var has to have a type,
and it can't know anything about a graph.
It was written by Apple years ago. It's
a type UI View controller. So that means we have to use as,
right, the typecasting to downcast it,
to the kind of MVC controller we think this is,
based on which segue it is. So in this case,
it's the calculator case, I think it's a graph controller,
that controls one of these graphing things. So
I'm going to downcast. If that fails,
then obviously I can't prepare it.
That's why I do if let there. Okay, but if it doesn't fail
then now I can set properties in the graph controller,
call methods, whatever is necessary to get it to know
what function to graph so that it can do its job. Okay, we
prepare it. Cool, everybody? Everybody make sense?
It's very important to understand prepare for segues.
You can't do any multiple MVC stuff without understanding
this method. It's the most important method in all of
multiple MVCs, all right? Now, red again.
Look, some red on the slide. It is absolutely crucial to
understand that when you're executing these yellow lines,
you're preparing that MVC when that's happening.
That MVC's outlets have not been set yet. So
all those outlets,
like in our Concentration the card buttons,
the flip count, all those labels they're all nil. Now,
they're implicitly unwrapped optionals, but they're still
gonna get unwrapped when you try to access them.
This will cause many crashes in your apps cuz you'll
forget, oops, and during preparing,
I accidentally accessed one of my outlets. Especially since,
when you're preparing, you kinda want the outlets because
you're trying to prepare the UI. But you have to get used
to this fact that this happens before. I'm not sure
why they made the decision to do this, but
it can be a pain. I mean,
sometimes when you prepare the MVC that you're preparing,
it's just collecting the information. And
then, in its view did load, which is a function, remember,
that we know is called after our outlets are hooked up.
Then you talk to the outlets and parcel out the information
or whatever. So it can be annoying.
But I'll intentionally crash in the demo, just so
you can see this happening, because it will happen to you.
All right, so that's prepare for segue. You can
prevent a segue from happening with this method
shouldPerformSegue in UIViewController.
Okay, you get the identifier, if you return false from this,
then the segue will not happen.
So some will click on that graph button, the system looks
at this method. If it says no, then it will not segue
to a new graph controller. It's just like you never even
clicked on that button. This is pretty rare to do,
but occasionally, you might wanna do it. All right,
so let's see a demo of all the stuff.
I'm probably gonna show you all this stuff in here.
I think we have time for all of that. Yeah, we probably do.
All right, so let's head back over to our Concentration. So
what I'm gonna do here, this is Concentration as we left it
off last time. I'm gonna change it to have multiple
MVCs, so the new MVC I'm gonna add is a theme chooser.
Remember how you all in your homework added theme to your
Concentration game? You did, but it chose a random theme.
So I'm gonna add a theme mechanism to mine, a simple
one because it's a demo. And then, but I'm gonna have
another MVC that lets me choose the theme. So, let's do
that. Let's start by one thing I wanna do in here after I've
been putting off, but I wanna do is now that I have multiple
MVCs, I do not want any of my MVCs to have their controller
called view controller. Okay, that's just way too generic.
Okay, I'm gonna have multiple MVCs.
I want each one to have the class of controls.
It'd be, you know, nicely named. So here,
I'm going to go, Oops, controller here.
And I'm gonna rename this. And the way to rename this,
you can't just type in a new name here.
Because this also appears in the storyboard by name.
Everything in the storyboard is by name. So
the way to rename here is to do the special Cmd+Click,
remember that menu? And choose Rename and
the Xcode will go and look at all the places that is used.
And now I'll just type in,
I'm gonna call this my ConcentrationViewController.
Because it's the view controller that controls this
view controller right here, my Concentration game, all right?
Okay, so let's go and add this theme support to my app.
I'm gonna do it super simply. Here's where all my emoji
stuff is. I'm just gonna add a var called theme, which I'm
gonna have be an optional string, which is one of these.
Okay, so my theme, when you set my theme, you just set
the emoji you want, and that is the theme. Okay, so like,
this would be the Halloween theme if we pasted in here.
And when its didSet happens,
I'm just gonna reset my emoji choices to equal this theme.
By the way, this is an optional.
It's gonna start out nil, and if you set it to nil,
then I'll just have no emoji as your theme.
In which case, you're gonna end up getting this question
mark if you'll remember, if you don't have any emoji.
And then I'm also gonna reset the emoji that we have used so
far because it might be from a different theme.
So I'm gonna reset it, and by the way,
all I need to do to create an empty dictionary is that
because Swift is gonna be able to infer the type from this.
So I don't need to put card and string in here.
And finally, what if someone sets my theme, and
I'm in the middle of a game? I think I'd better update my
view from my model. Okay, remember updateViewFromModel,
so that whatever is showing, if it's got the wrong theme,
will update to my new theme. Okay, so that's it.
That's how I'm gonna do my theme. it's really simple,
probably a little too simple. Another thing I'm gonna do is
that, since we now let the theme be set, I really don't
want this Halloween color theme here. So I'm gonna
change all these things to be a more kind of standard color.
Blue, blue is this default blue right here is
probably one of the most standard colors, so
let's make everything here be blue. I'll have to change up
my code as well, easy to change here. All right,
and then, the background doesn't wanna be black,
it's very unusual, we're gonna make that white. And
then our flips down here wants to be black,
just standard color black, where's black, there it is.
So now our UI looks a little more standard color.
Let's go do the same thing in our code over here.
Concentration ViewController,
see we've got these colors here,
so this orange right here,
which is the back of the cards, we'll make that blue.
We don't want the card's background to be white, and so
our overall background is white.
So I'll just make it be light gray, so
that we can see the edges of the cards better. And
then I also, we have our flip count label,
we'll make that be black. Okay, so I've added the theme,
I've changed my color scheme. Let's just run and make
sure I haven't broken anything here before we dive in.
Okay, so we got this blue theme, and
we got the Halloween default, kind of our default theme,
looks like it is functioning properly.
We're even getting our outline font. And
we've got normal colors here. Okay, so now let's go and
add this other MVC, right? We've got this MVC,
we need another one. How do we add an MVC to our app? Well,
we just go over here, same place that we get a button or
a label from. The very top one is View Controller.
I just drag it out and drop it in.
So now I have two MVCs, two view controllers here.
We call these things, by the way,
each one of these things a scene, S-C-E-N-E, scene. Okay,
so, we, we have these two view controllers right here,
two MVCs, and one, a couple things I need to do here.
One is, every time I have a view controller, it needs
a view controller subclass to control it. This one has one,
ConcentrationViewController. We need to make one for
here. And I do that with File > New File.
That's always how I create a new class. And
it's a UI thing, so I'm gonna do Cocoa Touch Class.
It's a subclass of UIViewController.
I'm gonna call this my ConcentrationThemeChooserView-
Controller. Nice long name right there, won't have to
type it very much though. And I'm gonna make sure not to put
it at the level of my project. I'm gonna put it down a level,
where all my files are, are there. And here we go.
This is our viewController. We're gonna get rid of
these viewController lifecycle methods like we always do.
And that leaves us with this one method,
all important prepare(for segue. So we will get back
to prepare(for segue) there, and implement it quite soon.
But the first thing we just do is the same thing you did
when you dragged out a blank UI view. What did you do?
You went to the identity inspector over here. And
you changed its identity to be your custom subclass.
So we wanna do the same thing here. So I'm gonna select this
guy, I'm gonna go here to the identity inspector.
I'm gonna change it from being just generic UIViewController
to being my ConcentrationThemeChooser
ViewController. Okay, don't forget that step.
If you don't do that step, then your prepare(for segue),
for example, will never get called.
You won't be able to create any outlets, or any actions,
or anything. You need to do that. Another thing I'm gonna
do is this little arrow, you see this arrow right here?
This is the arrow that says when this app runs,
which view controller do I show first? Okay, and
obviously now, I wanna show the theme one first. So
I just, you can just pick this up and drag it to whatever MVC
you want to be the first one. All right, so here's my theme
chooser right here. If we were really doing this for real,
this would probably be a table view. Or some extensible list
of themes, that I could add more themes to with one line
of code, like you were asked to do do in your homework.
But I haven't taught you table view yet, so I can't do it
that way. Instead, I'm just gonna have three buttons,
each of which is a theme. So, I'm just gonna grab three
buttons here, and make this nice UI to this MVC.
We'll make the font nice and big, so you can see it.
Go over here, and maybe 40 points or something like that.
And we need three of them so I'll copy and paste,
and then paste another one. Okay, so,
the three themes that I have, I have a Sports theme,
I have a Faces theme, and I have an Animals Theme. So
these are my themes. Lets do a quick review of auto layout.
I'm going to select these and put them in a stack, with this
button down here. Then in stack view, here they are.
I'm going to make them be centered in the stack.
And I'm going to make them be equal size.
And I'm going to pick a standard spacing, like that.
I'm also going to put this in the center,
and do my control drag to my outer level, and
have the center, horizontal and vertical there.
Notice I get the yellow. That yellow is just warning me,
that these frames will be different at run time.
I can fix that in the document outline.
If you'll recall this little guy right here,
with this yellow button in the upper right, and go here, and
then click on anything that's yellow. And
it can fix the misplacement for me by updating the frame,
so we'll do that. It moved it slightly, and
now everything is resolved. Okay, so this is great.
I got my nice UI here, I've got auto layouts, so
it should work when I rotate, and do all those things. So,
now all I need to do is wire these two MVCs up. Okay,
make it so that when I click on one of these buttons,
it shows this MVC over here on the right. And I
do that with control drag. So, I'm just gonna control drag
from the sports button over here. I'm gonna put this
in a navigation controller to start anyway.
So I'm gonna pick Show here, not Show Detail which is for
split views, I'm gonna pick Show. Okay, let's do the same
thing with this one. That's also gonna be a Show, and
this one here also a Show, so they're all going to Show. And
I want to make sure to click on each one of them,
it's nice it shows you what's causing the segue here, and
go over here to the inspector and
change the identifier. What does this segue do?
It basically let's you choose a theme, so
I'm going to call this Choose Theme, and I'm gonna
call all three of them, identify with Choose Theme,
because all three of them do exactly the same thing.
They choose a theme, all right?
Now I'm gonna do something kind of bad, in fact not kind
of bad, very bad, which is I'm gonna look at the button
that caused the segue to decide which theme to show.
Can anyone think of why that would be really bad?
Should never do that, no guesses? Because, what happens
when I convert this to French, or Chinese? Am I gonna have my
code have to have French, and Chinese in it so
that it works in those languages, no makes no sense?
So you never really want to drive your code from something
that's in the UI,
cuz your UI is gonna be in 40 different languages,
you hope if your app is successful. But for
downloads it's really good, because it's very little code,
and I can do it quickly. So this is download ware,
do not copy this aspect of what we're doing today.
All right, so we have created these segues right here.
Lets go ahead and run and see.
Wait, one more thing we have to do. We're missing an MVC.
We've got the first card on our stack, the second card of
our stack, but we don't have the stack itself.
We never have put a navigation control, which we could get
from here by the way. If you go down and look here, right
here navigation controller. I could just drag it out, and
then control drag to wire it up, but
I'm going to use that embed that I was telling you about.
So I'm just selecting this view controller, and
doing editor, embed in, navigation controller.
Now we have three MVCs here okay,
the navigation controller, the first card on the stack, and
then the one that we're going to push on to the stack Okay,
are we cool with that? All right so now let's run,
and notice it automatically moved the arrow when I
embedded that, which is kinda nice. So,
let's hope this works, and see what happens.
All right here's our UI, all right. Okay, it came into
the right space at least which is our chooser. Let's see if
when we choose one of these themes, if it will segue to
that other MVC. In fact let's move it out of the way, so we
can see what's going on here. Ready go, woo hoo it did it.
But, the theme is Halloween. So, how about animals,
still Halloween. So of course this is still Halloween,
because we never did anything to actually
prepare that MVC to be one of these themes, right? We just
put the name here, we didn't actually do the prepare. So,
our next step is to prepare this MVC, that gets put on to
the top of the stack of cards to have the right theme.
So, we're gonna prepare that. So, let's go do that. And
we do that in the code of the ConcentrationThemeChooserView-
Controller, right? That's the controller that we're choosing
the theme. So, let's uncomment out
this all-important function right here. And
get rid of the comments. And we gotta implement prepare.
So, what do we have to do to implement prepare?
Well, the first thing, as I've talked about before,
is we're gonna check to see which segue we're doing.
Now, we only have one kind of segue. So let's check for it,
and if the identifier equals the Choose Theme segue,
that's what we put in the inspector,
remember in the storyboard. Then we want to see if we can
find the Concentration game MVC and
prepare it by telling it its theme. So,
let's get the theme. How are we gonna get the theme?
Well, to speed things up I actually created a little
code snippet here, that creates this dictionary. So
this dictionary, it's just got the name of the theme,
which is the same as the button title,
that's why I'm saying that's bad design, and
then the theme itself. All right so there's sports,
there's a bunch of animals,
there's a bunch of faces. Okay so, we want to get that theme.
So, we're going to get the name of theme from the button.
That's this sender argument, the sender is the thing
causing this segue. So, we want to say something like,
if we can let the themeName equal the sender's
currentTitle, then we're gonna get the theme from that. But,
this we can't do because sender, what type is sender?
It's of type Any, optional Any, in fact.
You can't send an optional Any with the method currentTitle,
that's a button method.
Okay, so we're gonna have to use as, any time we see Any
we're almost always gonna have to use as. So I'm gonna say,
if I can let button equal the sender as a UI button,
then I can do this theme main thing. Because I now have
a var of this button which is of type, Button, UIbutton,
all right. So, now I can say button.currentTitle. So you
see how we used as to resolve that ending right there.
Now that we have the theme name, I can say if I can let
the theme equal my themes sub theme name.
Then I'm ready to go to prepare, right?
And we're just looking at this theme as this. So
I'm looking it up, and we know that that can fail of course,
because maybe this theme name is not in this dictionary. So
that's why we if let. By the way, these two if lets are so
related to each other we would almost certainly go up here,
and put them on the same line with a comma. Cuz they really,
really go together. By the way,
we probably wouldn't do this line either.
We'd take this and put it right here.
In fact, I'll show you how to do that.
So, instead of creating a separate bar here, I would
just take this right here out of that, get rid of this,
put parentheses around this. Since this could return nil
I need to optional chain it. And now I can get rid of
all this. This is how we would write this code right here.
We wouldn't have all those extra if lets,
we try to make this concise because this is all
has to do with the same thing which is getting this theme.
If you didn't understand what I did right here.
Ask on Piazza, go to a TA, go back and do your reading
assignment, this is important to understand what's going on
here. Alright, so I got this, now I've got the theme,
now I need to prepare the destination.
So I'd like to say something like segue.destination,
set your theme to be this theme. Oops,
not that theme, this theme. But I can't do that either.
Because again, this segue destination,
let's look at the type of this segue destination.
Option click on it. It took type UI view controller.
And of course, UI view controller does not have
the var theme so we can't do that.
So we have to say here use as and say if we can let CVC,
Concentration view controller, equal the segue destination as
downcasted to a Concentration view controller. Now we can
compare, prepare this thing by setting it's theme.
Everyone see that? See how we're using as to downcast?
Super important to understand that. So now that's it,
we have successfully prepared this thing. So let's go,
run our app, see how it works. Okay,
hopefully Sports. No, what's going on? My app crashed.
Why did my app crash? No, Let's take a look and
see if we can find out here. It says,
unexpectedly found nil while unwrapping an Optional value.
And here's my call stack here on the left and it looks like
card buttons here. My outlet to all my card buttons is nil.
Let's make sure that's true. PO card buttons nil,
no. So, let's go back up to call stack and
see how we got here. Okay, so we're in update view for
model. That got called from setting the theme.
Cuz when we set our theme we update
the view from model. And that theme setting got called for
preparing. So, the preparing is work it's trying to prepare
it in setting the theme. But when it sets the theme it
calls updateViewFromModel which tries to access the card
buttons which is nil, because of that red on the slide.
Which is that your outlets are not set when you're preparing.
Okay, so what do we do about this. Unfortunately,
even though this is an implicitly unwrapped optional,
we're gonna have to check and see if cardButtons does not
equal nil. And if cardButtons does not equal nil,
then we can update our view from our model. But
if it's not nil then we, if it's nil then we simply just
can't do this. Now, hopefully, somewhere later in our code
either in viewed load or case, when someone touches a card,
update view from model happens.
And so, everything's gonna be fine, cuz all the cards
are faced down until someone touches one, so we're good to
go. So it's very important to understand, you've got to
protect your code that can be called when your MVC is being
prepared. Okay, now, let's try again.
Let's try Sports. All right, it segued.
Let's cross our fingers that these are sports related, and
they are, excellent. The game is working just fine. Let's go
back, we're gonna hit back, when I hit back, that sports
game got thrown away. So now, when I pick animals, and
go forward, look, brand new MVC. Game started over, and
it's animals, so that's good. Go back over here, Faces.
Brand new MVC. Segueing always creates a brand new MVC.
It's a very good example of that happening,
all right. Now let's do iPad. This is the first time we've
done iPad in this course and
you're going to be doing it from here on out and
you're going to have to do it in your next assignment. So
let's do this, let's take the app that we have right now and
see what it would look like in our story board on an iPad. So
here we're looking at it in iPhone X view here,
I'm just gonna switch over and look at it as an iPad.
And you can see that as an iPad it's really large so
maybe I wanna zoom out a little bit so
I can see it a little better. And this UI doesn't look very
good. Look at all this extra white space around.
If I had an iPad app and it looked like this, I'd be like,
this is a terrible design. And it's kind of a waste because
we really would a split view where this is on the left and
this is on the right.
That would be a much more effective use of the space,
especially in landscape. Imagine this in landscape
with this part on the left and this on the right,
that would be really good use of space there.
Okay, so that's what we wanna do. How are we gonna do that?
Of course, we need a split-view controller for
that. Now, I recommend anytime you add a split-view
controller to your app, that you zoom way out.
Okay, really, really far out. And that's because when you go
over here to grab one of these split views and you get all
those extra views that come with it, it's gonna be really
big. See, so it's nice to have your scale be small.
So I'm gonna drop this in here. And you can see this
has dropped the split view controller here. And
then it gave me a navigation controller and a master and
a detail. Okay, I don't want any of those things.
So I'm just gonna select them and delete.
Right, cuz I already have my master, it's right here, and
I have my detail right here. So let's move this up, if I
can grab a hold of it it's so small. So we can do that and
I'm even gonna move my detail, right here. If I can grab it,
it's hard to get a hold of it when it's small.
Over to here so that I can easily control drags. So let's
zoom back in now that we've collected everything here.
Get that out of there. And two things I want to do, one,
I want to get this arrow to be here on the split view
controller so that my app starts with the split view
controller. Doesn't start with the master showing.
Then I'm just going to control drag to my master and
choose master view controller right here. And then I'm gonna
control drag to my detail and choose Detail View Controller.
Now notice I still have these segues right here.
So my master when I'm clicking these is still trying to segue
to this view controller. So let's just run on an iPhone,
on an iPad rather and see if this works on iPad.
We put it in a split view. Let's just try it.
Let's see what's going on here. Okay so
here's my iPad, wahoo, it looks like it's working,
right? We've got our master on the left we've got our game
here on the right, okay, looking good.
Let's go ahead and choose a theme. Oops,
that's not good. That's not what we want. Look at that.
Now why is that happening. When I click Choose This,
I want this over here to change to a new sports game.
Why am I getting it in here? Well,
that's because of the type of these segues.
You see these segues? They're all Show Segues.
Show Segues mean do the navigation controller's trick.
I want show detail, also know as replace because it
replaces the detail view of your split view. Now,
you might think let's just change it, oops we changed it.
Okay, there is a bug interface builder, this does not work.
So do not try to just change your kind here.
I'm not sure under what circumstances it doesn't work,
but it often does not work. So what we're gonna do is delete
them. I'm just selecting them all and hitting Delete. And
I'm gonna rewire them up. It's a simple matter to rewire them
up. And this time I'm gonna choose Show Detail.
It lets me show you acquiring it and
hitting Show Detail, which is kind of a nice side effect.
I'm gonna wire all three of these up, and
which is not that bad. But, unfortunately, I also
have to inspect them all right here and
put the identifier back into steam for all three.
And you can see that all three of them are of kind show
detail now. Show detail, show detail, show detail. So
now when we run it's gonna work.
Okay, here we go, cross our fingers. So
we've got this is the Halloween style. And sports.
Now again, it created a new game, hopefully with sports.
Animals, new game with animals.
Now, the real question here is did we break the iPhone
version here? Cuz we did a lot of iPad work here.
We added this split view,
which we know doesn't work on an iPhone at least not in
iPhone Plus. And we changed these segues to be
Show Detail. And the iPhone can't show split views, so
it can't show detail. Did this break everything?
And the answer is no. Because iOS is really smart and
it knows that if this structure of having a split
view with a navigation controller inside it,
even with Show Detail things. That when we're on the iPhone,
this means do it all in a navigation controller. So
this is called adapting to a different trait collection.
And we'll talk about that when we talk more
about auto layout. But here's our UI appearing here.
One thing interesting to notice here, it didn't come up
showing the Themes, it came up showing again with the default
theme. Now I can go back and choose a theme and it worked.
But interestingly it comes up when. When it first comes up,
it comes up with this default theme. And
that's just a decision they made, some apps want this,
some apps don't. I guess Apple figured this is the most
common one. In our example, we don't want that.
We would want it coming up with this, right? So
if we have time in our demo, we'll fix that. So to do that,
we have to become the split view's delegate so
it's a little bit of complicated work.
The code's not complicated, but being a delegate, you guys
have not seen much yet, so we would have to do that. But
otherwise, notice that it's working just fine.
Okay, and notice that in landscape on an iPhone,
it does not do the side-by-side split view thing.
It uses the whole screen. However, on an iPhone Plus,
like let's look at the iPhone 8 Plus and
run it there. On pluses, it does do the split view.
You see? This is doing the split view here,
faces, sports. So it's doing the split view here.
But in Portrait mode, it does navigation controller. See
look there's a Back button. I can't slide out from the left,
when I pull out from the left it goes back in the navigation
controller. So an iPhone Plus, iPhone 8 Plus, iPhone 7 Plus,
those are kinda hybrid devices half way between an iPad and
iPhone. All right, let's take this one step further and
put this whole thing in a tab bar controller. Just so
you can see what this looks like. Again, really easy.
I'm gonna zoom way out again. Anytime I drag these view
controllers out they bring a bunch of extra junk. So
here's a tab bar controller. I just drag it out. Here it is.
It brings it out. I don't know if you can see it.
But it actually gave me two little blank view controllers
right there, which I'll go ahead and leave.
I'll just leave them there. It has three tabs total.
So let's see if we can get hold of this and
drag this up here. So
I'm gonna leave these two that are brought out as tabs and
then I'm gonna control drag to my split view to make it be
relationship view controller here that's how you add it.
It's not a segue. It's just adding it as a view controller
right there. And we can zoom in see what it
did there. Here's my tab bar controller. If you zoom
in you can see it says tab bar controller right there. And,
of course, I wanna move this little arrow arrow to here so
it starts in the tab bar controller.
You can set the attributes about that the little tab has,
here in the storyboard if you want. You see right here?
If you click on it. Like this is my Concentration game so
I can say Concentration. These ones that it added down here,
lets see what it has for them, maybe we'll just leave it.
It has item one. And item two are the two things that has,
we'll just leave it like that. And you can click on these and
not just set the name that it uses.
Where are we? So when you zoomed in it's hard to find
where the heck you are.
So that's when we often zoom way out. So we can also click
on this thing and set things like the image.
By the way, this image that goes into this tab bar item.
Okay, it's an alpha only image. So all the drawing you
do is either with transparent pixels or opaque ones.
And if they're transparent, then kind of iOS is gonna
shine light through those transparent pixels and
that's what's gonna show up as your tab bar.
The other thing you can do that's kinda cool is you can
reorder the tabs. So here I've got my three tabs,
Item 1, Item 2. Let's move our Concentration one to be
the left most tab. Okay, so let's run it again. We'll do
it on an iPhone 8 Plus. It doesn't really matter. Okay,
here we go. You can barely see these tabs on the bottom.
I don't know if it helps to make it any bigger.
But there they are. There's the Concentration tab.
Here's Item 1 tab. Here's Item 2.
They're blank. If we go back to Concentration,
we still have our full UI here. Okay,
it's just in a tab right there and same thing if we rotate.
Got the three tabs here. Okay, so that's bar. So
it's really, really simple. Okay. Lets talk about another
little bit wonky thing with this app that we have.
I'm going to run it on the iPad again. And just note that
it does. Actually before I do that even I'm going to do one
other thing which is lets show you how to make a segue from
code. Okay so the segues that we have here are just directly
from these buttons like if I click on a segue it's directly
from a button to the MVC. There is a way to make it so
that you do this performed segue business in code without
performed segue lines. So to show that I'm going to delete
these segues. So now the buttons no longer segue and
instead I'm gonna segue from code. And I'm gonna do that by
changing these buttons. Instead of being seguers,
they're going to do target action. So
lets just bring them up here. Zoom in a little bit. And
just do our normal target action.
So this is nothing different than you been doing target
action all quarter long. I'm just gonna control drag
from the button here, and create an action.
I am going to call this action ChangeTheme,
because that's what it's going to do. Just for fun,
you know where usually I say, set this UI Button or else.
Well, actually now you don't need to set that UI Button or
else because you know how to deal with Any. So
I am going to connect this with any as the argument.
Okay the sender instead of being UI Button its Any,
and you know how to deal with that now. Okay,
you didn't before, but now you know,
with the as you can deal with that. And we'll put on that,
we'll have all three buttons send the same thing right
here. So I'm gonna put a choose theme segue in here,
but its not gonna be from a particular button.
It just gonna be a segue from this view controller to this
view controller. So it's kind of like a generic segue
between these two. So how do you create a segue like that?
Well, you control drag like a buttons,
but instead of control dragging from some UI element
You control drag from this little round yellow thing.
You see that's just Concentration theme control.
This right here represents this MVC. This is the thing
you can use to drag from or to, to mean this MVC.
So, I am going to control drag from here
to here. Okay, it's going to be showed detail, because we
are in a split view context. I am gonna go here and
still give it a name. The same name, choose theme, and now,
I've created a segue between this view controller and
this view controller, not between these buttons.
See when I click on these buttons, or
when I click on this it's not selecting these buttons.
It's selecting the whole view controller.
So, this is how you do a manual segue. You create
a segue between the two view controllers. And then, in your
code you just say performSegue with that theme name.
Okay, or you may, or may not want a segue here.
Now, you can also use that should perform segue method to
conditionally segue, but I'm gonna show you how we can do
conditional segue right here,
a really good example of it. So, let's go back to our iPad
Pro that we had running here. And I'm gonna put a cool
feature in here, which is if I'm in the middle of a game,
and I hate sports, it's not going to replace this.
It's going to actually change the theme on the fly and
not reset the game. Wouldn't that be a kind of better
UI here? We don't really wanna start a new game every time we
change the theme. So,
if I am gonna do that, I can not segue.
You see why I can't segue and do that? Because segue always
create a new MVC, so there's no way for me to segue and
keep this MVC like it is. So, I have to do this in code
instead, so in change theme here, instead of segueing.
I'm going to look in my split view controller, and
find this find this little view controller over here,
and talk to it directly. Just gonna talk to it,
I'm not gonna segue to it, I'm gonna see if I can find it.
And if I find it there, I'm just gonna talk to it,
and tell it to change its theme. Okay, so
how I'm gonna do that?
So, now, I'm gonna put that code back that I deleted
this themeName here. And
if I have a theme, then inside here, okay, inside this
thing I'm going to talk to the detail of my split view. So,
this is gonna be a thing where if I'm in split view,
and I can find my detail I'll just talk to it and
tell it the theme otherwise, I'll do the performSegue.
So, that's what I mean about conditional performSegue here.
So, I'm gonna find out, find that split view controller by
saying, if let cvc = and then I'm gonna create a little var,
which is my splitViewDetailConcentrationV-
iewController, which might be nil, if I can't find it. So,
I'm going to do that, and then if I can find that,
then I'll get the theme and set the CVCs theme equal
to this theme. There we go,
like that. Else, I will perform segue. So, everyone
see what I'm doing here. So, I just have to implement this.
This is going to be a var that finds my split view
detail controller as a concentration view controller.
So, that's going to be a private var called this.
Copy. Paste.
It's going to be of type Concentration view controller,
optional though, because I might not be able to find it.
And I'm just gonna return the splitViewController I'm in if
any, dot its viewControllers, which is the master,
an array of the master and the detail, right? Dot last,
which should be the detail as a ConcentrationViewController.
So, if all the optional chaining, and
then as make it through here,
then I was able to find the ConcentratonViewController
in my splitViewController's detail.
See what I'm doing there? Okay, and
if I'm able to do that, then I'll set the theme here.
So, let's see if this works. All right, here we go,
let's try it. So, we've got our Halloween theme here,
that's great. Now, I'm gonna hit sports, hopefully,
it will not reset the game, cuz it will hopefully find
this Concentration view controller. Woo hoo! It just
reset the theme, didn't reset the game, cuz we didn't segue.
We did this, instead, of segueing. All right, what
about this on the iPhone? This is going to work on iPhone?
Let's go over there and see. Okay, so
let's go back, actually, let's pick one here, let's say like,
here's ours sports one. Now, let's go back and try and
change it to animals and see. No, it didn't work.
And why didn't it work? Because, oops.
Sorry, because we only can do
this if we're in a split view controller that has a detail
view controller. And on the iPhone there is no detail in
the split view controller. We use the navigation controller
to get to it. So, how would we fix this on an iPhone? Well,
on an iPhone what we are going to have to do is grab ahold of
an MVC that we segue to, and hold on to it with a strong
pointer. So, that when it gets thrown off the navigation
stack it doesn't leave the heap and we will keep ahold
of it. Then the next time someone wants to go to it,
we will just put it straight on the navigation control.
We will not segued to it, because that would reset it.
We will just push it right on there, and
it will show you how we do navigation
controller direct pushing and popping.
So, how are we going to do that? Well,
I am just going to create a little private var here,
which I am going to call my LastSeguedtToConcentrationVie-
wController, which is going to be
a ConcentrationViewController optional. And
I'm just gonna set this any time I successfully
segue to something. So,
that becomes my last segue to concentration view controller.
Right?, so I'm just grabbing onto it right there.
This is a known normal var, so it's gonna be a strong pointer
too. It's gonna keep it in the heap. So,
even when we hit the back button,
it'll get thrown off the navigation stack, but
it'll stay in the heap, all right? Pointed to by this var.
And then, over here, when we change theme, if I can't do
the splitView trick, then I'm gonna say, else if I can let
cvc equal that last segued of two thing. Then,
I'm just gonna push it right unto the navigation stack.
And remember how we do that from the slides? We just say,
the navigation controller I'm in, if I'm in one,
.pushviewController this last of the CVC actually.
Animated? True. And lets make sure that we, of course,
set it's theme. Got to copy and paste in code here, so
we will want to clean that up a little bit.
But we will set its theme here before we push. All right?
So, a lot going on here.
You're learning about how to find into a Split View.
You're learning how to hold something in the heap that
gets thrown off the navigation deck. You're learning how to
push things on a navigation deck without segueing.
And you're learning how to segue from code. All in this
one method right here. So, let's go see if this worked.
All right, here we go, so
we'll pick a theme like maybe animals,
here we go looking good. Now, let's go and
change it to sports, go back here sports. Woo hoo,
it worked, because we didn't segue to it the second time.
The first time we segued to it and we grabbed it. And
the next time, we just pushed it on the navigation stack,
and set. We go can back and set it to, you know, sports,
how about faces, animals. Okay? So, the last
thing I'm going to do, and this one a little complicated.
Again, not complicated to implement, but it's using some
concepts like delegation here that you're not quite used to.
But I'm gonna make it so that when I run my iPhone version,
it doesn't come up showing me a Concentration game that has
the default Halloween. I want it to come up showing this.
So, to do that, my ThemeChooserViewController
here is gonna make itself the delegate of the split view
controller that it's in. Remember that even on iPhone,
it's still in split view controller even though it
doesn't show it as split view controller. Now it turns out
that one of the ten or so split view delegate methods is
one that controls whether it collapses. The what he calls
the secondary view controller, which is the detail.
Whether it collapses it on top of the primary
at any given time, in the running of the app. So we're
just gonna implement that splitView delegate method.
And we're gonna return some bool that says what to do.
And we're just gonna tell it to do the right thing.
So how do we do that? Well, first we have to set our self
as the split view controller's delegate,
and I'm gonna do that in that function awakeFromNib.
I haven't had a chance to show you awakeFromNib.
It's a function that's called on every object that comes out
of your interface builder file. Here you would never,
extremely unlikely that you would ever build this whole
split view navigation controller tab bar thing
in code, that would be a lot of messy code.
You're gonna build it in a storyboard, so it's okay for
me to do this little split view trick in awakeFromNib.
I don't have to worry about
this being created somewhere else. I'm just gonna tell
my SplitViewController that I'm in, if I'm in one,
to set it's delegate to be myself. So
that it will call that method about the collapsing on top
of, now of course it says you can't do this because it says
self is not a UISplitViewControllerDelegate.
So I have to go up here and announce that I am a
UISplitViewControllerDelegate and all the methods in there
are optional it's an Objective-C protocol.
So I've implemented it, no warnings or
errors everything's good. But of course I do need
to actually implement one of them which is that collapse.
And I don't remember what it's called but
I know it has collapse in it, here it is right here it's
this one. Okay, so I'll let you take a look at this guy.
It's called UIViewController collapseSecondary onto
primaryViewController. And this secondaryViewController
is the detail, the primaryViewController is
the master. And it's basically asking here,
hey I'm adapting to the fact that I'm a splitViewController
on an iPhone. And I want to collapse the detail, using
the navigation controller, on top of the primary,
the master. Should I do it. And unfortunately the return
value of this seems like it should be true, do it.
But actually, if we wanna prevent this from happening,
we return true. And the reason that happens is if you return
false from this method,
you're basically saying I did not collapse this for you so
you do it. So the return values are kind of inverse.
But the bottom line is if we don't want that collapsing
to happen, okay, we need to return true from this method.
So when do we not want it to collapse? Well, we don't want
it to collapse any time that secondaryViewController,
that concentration game, has a nill theme.
If it has a nil theme then the theme's never been set,
we want, don't wanna do that collapse. So I'm just gonna
say here, if I can let cvc = secondaryViewController as
concentrationViewController. Then,
if cve.theme==nil. So
it's never been set, then I'm gonna return false. Otherwise,
I'm just gonna return true, which says to the system true
means yes, please do that collapse for me. Actually it's
the other way around. See, I always get confused, true and
false. So true means I did it. But I'm actually not going
to do it. So it's not gonna get done.
False means no, I didn't collapse it so
you should do it. It's very confusing.
Even I get confused between this true and false.
But this is the way it is. So it's a little complicated.
Little bit of advanced use of delegation there.
But let's see if it works. So when we first run it worked,
because that thing that would normally had put on there had
a nil theme, which is using that default theme. But
if I click, now it does collapse it on there because
the theme is not nil. I set the theme to sports, right?
So the now it's a sports theme. Let me go back here and
now we're getting the reuse because we're not segwaying.
Okay, all right so that's it, I showed you
a lot of stuff about multiple MVCs there, right? So,
you know, make sure you pile through this and understand it
all because you're gonna be using it all pretty much in
your next assignment right away. You're gonna have to do
pretty much all of these stuff in your next assignment.
All right, let's jump back into the slides and
get as far as we can here with
this animation thing. We only have about seven or eight
minutes left, so we probably won't get all the way through.
But that's okay, we'll just continue on Wednesday.
Any questions about that MVC stuff?
I didn't see any raised hands, so. Okay, timer, so timer,
I'm talking about timer right before I talk about animation.
Timer is not really used for animation.
You wouldn't use a timer to do animation.
But sometimes it's used in concert with animation. So
I'm teaching it about the same time.
Now some of you actually used timer in your extra credit.
For assignment two I guess, I'm not sure, yes assignment
two and timer is super simple little struct very,
very simple struct. It's basically made for you to
give it a closure, a little function which will execute
sometime in the future. And you tell it how much,
two seconds in the future, ten seconds, a minute, an hour,
and it will go and execute that code.
And it can do it every hour if you want or
every two seconds or it can just do it one time.
So how do we use Timer? The easiest way to use timer
is to use this class function on timer called
scheduledTimer. It only has three arguments.
One is the time interval to wait until it executes it,
whether it repeats it, keeps doing it, and
the block of code which is a simple little block that takes
the timer as the argument and returns nothing. And
it'll jut execute that code, so it could not be simpler.
So here's an example of it,
I have this private weak var, which is a timer, I'll
explain why that's weak cuz this is the first time besides
outlet that you've seen me use weak.
And I just set that timer var equal to the results of
calling Timer.scheduledTimer. Here I'm doing TimeInterval
of two seconds and it does repeat. So every two seconds,
it's going to implement your code here. And every time he
calls it, you pass over the timer back to you so
that you have a hand of these. I putting it in a var, so
I wouldn't need it. But it's nice to put a passage over
there in case you don't wanna store it around in a var.
Now why did I make that weak.
I make it weak because as soon as that timer stops running.
Either because it wasn't a repeating timer or
because someone stopped it from repeating.
Then no one else will have a strong pointer to it. So
if I don't have a strong pointer to it,
what will happen to this timer var? It gets set to nil.
Which is great. So this time the var will automatically set
to nil as soon as the timer is stopped, which is a really
nice feature. So I can always tell whether the times are on
there, time there is running by
whether that thing is nil or not. So
it is kind of a cool feature. So how do you stop a repeating
timer? You have timers going off every two seconds. Well,
you just send the message invalidate to the timer and
it will no longer run. In fact invalidate is going to throw
it out of the heap and set our weak vars to nil and it's all
gonna be done. So that's it. Super easy to use class timer,
struct timer. Now timer, sorry, I thought I didn't put
this tolerance in here. But the timer you can also specify
a tolerance on your timer.
That just says. If this timer goes off once an hour, it's
okay if it goes off 30 seconds earlier or 30 seconds late.
That's fine, and why would you wanna set a tolerance? Because
it could help the system be a little more battery efficient.
Cuz the system might not be awake exactly one hour later,
it might be sleeping.
But it might wake up to check cellular status or
something like that, and then it could run it.
So if you give it a little tolerance,
it won't have to wake up specifically to try and
run your timer. By the way, these timers,
even if they have tolerance zero, they don't run right
on the microsecond of what you specify. These are not
microsecond level timers. They probably, I mean, in practice,
they're probably a tenth or a hundredth of a second,
very reliably. But these are not for real time animation or
something like that. >> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Yeah, so the question is,
can the timer run when the app is in the background? And
we haven't talked about the whole application life cycle,
and when things are in the background, and
I will talk about that. But
the answer is, once the thing has gone to a suspended state,
no, nothing runs in your app. But in that 30 seconds where
it's not fully, you know, backgrounded,
it could run in that short time. So we'll talk all about
that when we talk about the application life cycle.
What happens to your app when you go to another app, for
example. Okay, so brief overview here of the kinds of
animation that exist in iOS, or at least some of the kinds.
One is animating UIView properties,
there's a few UIView properties,
very important ones which we'll talk about,
that you can animate the changing of.
Okay, this is the most common animation that goes on, okay,
and we'll talk all about that one.
Then there's animating controller transitions,
this is like you're in the navigation controller, and
a new card comes on top of the deck. The animation of that
sliding in or popping in or flipping in, or whatever.
That can be animated, we're not gonna talk anything about
that. That's kind of an advanced animation topic,
we're not gonna talk about that.
There's core animation that,
just like there's a CA layer underneath UI for drawing,
there's kind of core animation under this UIView property
animation at the top there, that I'm gonna talk about.
I'm not gonna get into core animation much,
it's basically the primitives for animating properties.
It can animate more than just the UIView properties that I'm
gonna talk about, but I just don't have time to get
down to that layer. Even for UIView property animation,
I'm just gonna kind of show you the real easy,
top way to do it. Most of this class is really just
trying to get you introduced to things, and you can look in
more detail if you want to do more detailed stuff. If you're
doing 3D, of course there's full 3D animation engine,
OpenGL, and also Metal, which is a fantastic system for
doing that. I'm not gonna talk about any 3D in this class
either, so if you are a 3D person,
I'm presuming you might already know OpenGL.
You may know how to figure how to get your OpenGL into
a view on you own, but it's not actually that difficult.
There is also SpriteKit, a whole framework for
doing 2.5D animation,
basically that's like Mario Brothers kind of animation,
right?. Where you have Images and they're overlapping to
create what appears to kinda be a 3D world, but it's really
drawn 2D, where the images just overlap. So there's whole
mechanisms for that, not gonna talk about that either.
Maybe we'll have a Friday section on that, possibly,
later in the quarter. But I doubt it,
cuz we've got some other things in the pipe for that.
And finally, there's dynamic animation,
this is animating views using physics. So
you give the view a mass and a velocity and
an elasticity, and then you operate on it.
You push it, for example, and it'll just start flying across
the screen. And depending on what its mass is and
what it collides with, it'll bounce around and do various
things. This I am going to tell you about on Wednesday.
Because it's really great for kind of moving views at,
on math and having them interact with each other.
When you slide up from the bottom on your iPhone,
and it kind of bounces a little bit,
that's the dynamic animation, right?
It's just kind of a little bit of elasticity and bounce.
Let's wait on UIView animation,
cuz I don't wanna rush this too much, so
we'll start Wednesday off with this.
UIView property animation is just these yellow properties
right here on your view, like where it is, its center.
Or the transform, remember the thing we did to rotate
the View upside down when we made the corner of the card.
Or alpha how transparent it is, making things fade in and
out, or the background color, which is rare to animate.
These properties and these properties alone,
you can animate, so that your view can fly across screen,
it can fade out, it can flip around because its
transformed can be changed. It can scale up and get big, and
then go back small, because its scale,
the transform scale can be changed, etc.
So there's a whole API for animating these things,
and that's what we'll start Wednesday's with.
And then I'll do dynamic animation, then we'll do
a demo, gonna be time constrained at that point, but
we'll do a demo that includes all of that stuff, hopefully,
in it. And then your assignment that's gonna
be due on Wednesday is to set your set game and
add animation to it. And
there's also going to be another part for
multiple MDCs. All right, sound good, all right,
I'll see you next time. >> For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.
>> 更多课程详见 stanford.edu