[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Okay, well welcome then,
to Stanford CS193P. This is
Developing Applications for
iOS. Hopefully you're
in the right place.
This is fall quarter of 2017.
And I'm gonna breeze through
a few slides here. And
then I'm gonna sit down and
do a nice involved demo just
to show you what it's like
developing apps for iOS.
That's the best way to learn,
it's for me to show
you how to do it. So
this will be what I'm gonna
talk about briefly first.
So what are you gonna
learn in this course?
Of course you're gonna learn
how to build cool apps.
iOS apps are cool.
Why are they cool?
Well, they're cool because
they live in your pocket, you
can show them to your friends
right there, also incredibly
easy to sell and market your
apps online because you have
the App Store. And there's a
very vibrant community that's
because Apple is always doing
cool new things like virtual
reality and machine learning
and all these things.
And there are millions of apps
on the app store, so there's
a lot of people doing this
stuff. But you're also gonna
learn in this class
a little bit of real life
Object-Oriented Programming.
You all are taking classes
networking and databases and
graphics, your other CS
classes. And here we're gonna
do all those things in
a real life platform.
Because over the weeks we
are going to do all of those
computer science things for
real. And especially
Object-Oriented Programming,
cuz iOS is completely and
utterly object-oriented.
You cannot develop for
iOS without being serious
object oriented programming.
And that brings me to my
prerequisite for this course,
which is Object-Oriented
Programming. You have to be
comfortable with
Object-Oriented Programming.
Definitely CS106 A and
B and hopefully CS108,
which is Object-Oriented
Programming here at
Stanford. And the other thing
you gotta to be comfortable
with is writing a lot of code.
All your homework in this
class, there's a little bit of
reading the first few weeks
about the language that
we're gonna develop in.
But mostly it's just
programming, programming and
more programming. So if you're
not comfortable writing a lot
of code then this class,
you might wanna wait until
you've taken some other
classes that ask you to
write a lot of code
before you dive in here.
So what's in iOS? What am
I gonna be teaching you?
I've divided it here
into four layers.
The bottom layer is
near the hardware, and
the top layer is near the
user. So at that bottom layer,
you might be surprised to
find out that iOS is Unix.
It's a BSD variant of Unix.
And so all of the stuff
that's going on down there is
all happening in C basically.
Unix is mostly written in C,
most of that stuff is in C.
I'm not gonna teach you
anything at this layer.
This is
an object-oriented class,
everything we do will
be object-oriented.
You will not see me teaching
you anything down there,
The next layer up is called
the Core Services layer.
all right?
This is an object-oriented
layer on top of those lower
services. This I will be
teaching you. So if we wanna
do things like find out where
the phone is on the planet or
find out its orientation or
access some files in the file
system, we're gonna be using
this layer right here and I'll
be teaching you all about this
layer. Core Services layer.
The next layer up, this is
kind of not a strict layering,
but is the Media layer.
Don't forget that your iPhone
is essentially, originally
an iPod with a phone in it. So
it's got all kinds of media,
video, audio,
many different kinds,
images, all this stuff. And
unfortunately this is a layer
I'd love to teach you but
I have to cut something, so
I'm not gonna talk much about
this layer, unfortunately.
So I know some of you might be
wanting to write a cool game
that has 3D sound with TIE
fighters ripping around from
the back of you to the front.
And that's all possible, and
quite straightforward to do,
but in ten weeks I have to
pick what I'm gonna teach you,
and so I'm gonna focus on Core
Services. And then this layer,
which is Cocoa Touch. So Cocoa
Touch is the UI layer of iOS.
This is where the buttons and
the sliders,
all those things are in. And
there's also, really powerful
objects here, like the Map Kit
has a single object that you
can just drop in your app
that gives you pretty much
the entire functionality of
the map's app inside a
rectangle, inside your window.
So, you're talking about a
wide variety of UI stuff here
and I'm gonna try and cover
as much of this as I can. So
that's what you're gonna
learn in this class.
The platform we're gonna
develop on is Xcode 9, so
you're all gonna need
to download Xcode 9,
it's free and
it only runs on your Mac.
And, there's this other little
app, Instruments, but it's
really kind of just an add-on
to Xcode 9. We're gonna do
everything in Xcode 9, source
code, editing, debugging,
all that stuff is gonna happen
in Xcode 9. You're also gonna
have to learn a new language.
iOS has two languages you can
develop in,
Objective-C and Swift.
Swift is the newer one, that's
the one I'm gonna teach you.
Everything you learn though
in Swift, all about iOS,
will apply if you later wanna
go learn Objective-C and
work for a company that is
still writing in Objective-C,
which is perfectly valid
language to write in.
But Swift kind of
a cool new language,
I think you're really,
really gonna like it.
If you're a serious Computer
Scientist another language is
like big yawn whatever. Just
tell me what the syntax is,
tell me what they key
fundamental mechanisms for
designing with it are,
and I'll learn it.
So, if you don't have that
attitude towards languages,
you're gonna be kind of having
trouble out in the real world
being a programmer.
And then of course,
there's millions of what
we call Frameworks in iOS.
Frameworks are just
collections of objects.
Like the biggest one is UIKit,
that's where buttons, and
sliders, and all that stuff
is. Foundation is another
big one. That's where a lot of
that core services stuff I was
talking about is. But there's
the Map Kit, Core Motion,
Core Data, Object Orient,
Database, all kinds of them.
And I'll try and get to as
many of them as I can. And
last but definitely not least,
there is a Design Strategy for
building iOS apps
that you have to use.
This is not like an optional,
here's a good idea, why don't
you design this way? You must
design this way. It's called
MVC, Model View Controller.
How many people have,
some experience doing MVC in
any other? Okay, it's not so
many this quarter. Usually I
get half the people but
I'll be teaching
all about MVC.
The start of electron
Wednesday is gonna be a full
coverage of MVC. What it is,
how it works, all that stuff,
all right? So now, I'm gonna
dive right into a big demo
that's the best way to learn
how to do iOS development is
with a demo. Seeing it happen,
we're gonna build
an application from scratch.
This slide right here,
is a slide for
you to look at later, and
see, did I learn all these
things, because I should have
learned them today. This
is not a slide to read now.
Since I'm not gonna get
back to the slides,
let me just say what's coming
up real quick. You are gonna
have a reading assignment
that goes out today.
It's basically starting
to read the manual on
Swift. So you can learn this
new language. It'll be all
spreaded out over three maybe
four weeks, so you don't have
too much reading all at once.
>> But
those reading assignments
are gonna be in addition to
programming assignments. The
reading assignments are going
to go out on Monday,
they come back on Monday,
they're due the next Monday.
And
then the program assignments
go out on Wednesday and
then they're due the next
Wednesday generally.
Okay, at least we'll start
the quarter that way.
On Friday,
we have an optional section,
it means optional that you
don't have to go there.
The topics we're gonna cover
are kind of additional, but
this Friday is one is
a big one, it's tips and
tricks of Xcode, including
how to use the debugger.
So if you've never used
the debugger in Xcode,
this is a good one to go to,
so
you can see how to use
the debugger for your problem.
If not, you know, it's
a debugger, if you used other
debuggers, you could probably
figure it out, but anyway, it
says right there that it's in
Hewlett 205, but I don't think
there's such a room. I think
it might be in Hewlett 105.
I don't know, watch Piazza and
we'll tell you where it is.
But it is gonna be 11:30 to
12:20. And so next week we'll
talk more about Swift and
then launch into all of iOS,
all right? So let's jump
right into the demo here.
And I apologize in advance for
going fast on this demo,
because we have
a lot to cover, and
you're gonna find that in
this course, in general,
I tend to go pretty quick, cuz
I wanna teach you as much of
this stuff as I possibly can.
All right,
Xcode. Here's Xcode.
I went to the Mac App Store.
I searched Xcode, I found it.
I downloaded it.
It was free, it doesn't cost
me a dime to develop for
iOS. When you launch Xcode for
the first time,
you're gonna get this
thing right here. So
we need to build an app. Now,
I decided to show you the app
that I'm gonna build here in
real life. So you see these
cards that I've very artfully
taped up here? These cards
are going to let me play
a game called Concentration.
How many people have heard
of the game Concentration?
Not too many. Okay, so
Concentration is just a card
game. Behind these cards
that are all face down,
there are some pictures,
and the goal is for
you to match the pictures up.
So there's 12 cards,
6 pairs of pictures, so I get
to pick two cards at a time,
and if they match, I win, and
the cards go away.
If they don't match,
I have to turn them back down
and pick two other cards, and
it's called Concentration
cuz I have to concentrate on
the ones that didn't match, so
that later I can go back and
match them. So, let's just
flip some cards over here.
I'm gonna start with
this one right here.
I really don't know what's
behind there, but let's see.
Okay, this one is
a pair of purple bats.
So now I'm trying to find
another pair of purple bats,
let's try right here.
I found them right away, okay.
So this is a match,
I get some points.
These come off the board.
So now I'm searching for
more matches. All right, let's
try this one right here. It's
a ghost. I got the ghost right
there. Let's try this one.
No, no match. That looks
like a Rorschach thing, but
it's a witch. Turns out
that's a witch on her broom,
if you can see right there.
So, I don't get any points for
this and I have to turn these
back down and pick two other
cards. All right, so
I'll turn these down.
Hopefully you guys
are concentrating, and
you can remember what these
things are. I'm gonna try this
one. It's a cat, kind of
a cute cat right there, and
let's pick another one,
how about this one. A pumpkin!
Okay, well, in some ways,
this is bad,
because we have
another non match,
but it's kind of good
in that supposedly,
if we we're concentrating we
know where four cards are. So
turn these back down.
Pick two new ones, and
I'm gonna pick cards that
I haven't seen before,
because I already know
where these cards are.
All right,
that doesn't fall down.
All right, how about this one.
This one is, The witch,
the witch! Okay, so
now if I was concentrating,
I remember where the witch
was, now where was it? Was it,
I think, was it this one?
Yeah? Witch, yes, okay!
So we match these, and these
come off the board, and this
just continues, and obviously
the fewer things you choose,
okay, the fewer times that
you pick, like here is a cat.
Where's that cat?
I think it's down here.
No, that's not a cat.
Now this kind of a mismatch
I should be probably
get a big penalty for,
because the cat I've seen
before, it's right here.
So I should have matched it,
and I didn't,
I wasn't concentrating. So
this is the game we're gonna
build an app to do. All right,
make sense? Simple game.
All right back to Xcode right
here. Now this Xcode portal,
the splash screen
that pops up here.
It has all the apps that
you've been working on all
quarter. Right here, and then
it lets you create a new app
over here where it says create
a new Xcode project. So,
we're gonna create
a new Xcode project.
I just click that button.
When you create a project,
it asks you what kind of
project do you wanna build?
And we wanna build an iOS app,
you see up here at the top.
We could build a watch app,
or an Apple TV app,
but we're building an iOS app,
and
this is saying what kind
of iOS app would you like?
So here's a game, augmented
reality. We're always gonna
pick this one in the upper
left corner, single view app,
because it's the simplest
starting template, and I wanna
teach you how to write
the code to do all those
other ones. I don't want you
just click a template, and
it just shows you the
infrastructure for a game, or
whatever. I wanna show
you how to do that.
So we're always gonna
pick single view app.
When we pick the kind of app
we want it's gonna ask us some
questions like what do
you wanna call this app?
Well this game is called
Concentration, so I'm gonna
say Concentration. The next
one down here is Team.
That's the development team
working on it. That's you. Now
when are on it it's gonna say
Add Team or Make Team right
there. To me, it knows it's
me, and when you do that,
all you're gonna need to
create a development team is
an Apple ID. You don't
have to pay any money.
Any Apple ID will do,
go through the process.
You'll creat
a development team. Next,
is this Organization Name.
That can be anything you want.
It just shows up in the
copyright in your Swift files,
all right? But this one,
very important that this be
uniquely identifying you.
So a real easy way to
do that if you're
a Stanford student is
edu.stanford.cs193p, your
SUNet id.
Instead of lecture there,
put your SUNet ID.
That's clearly gonna identify
you. If you're not a Stanford
student, you have to figure
it out on your own, and
then the language I told you
about, the two languages,
we're gonna do all our
development in Swift. You can
mix Swift and Objective-C
even in the same application.
They're very interoperable.
Swift was designed fully with
Objective-C in mind, so it's
not a problem. So we'll always
pick Swift here, and we're
not gonna do any of these
things down here in
the first two weeks,
but we will eventually get it,
object-oriented databases, and
testing, we'll eventually
do that stuff.
So I'm gonna click next.
Now it's asking me where do
you wanna store your project?
I strongly recommend you put
it in your home directory,
in a folder called Developer,
that's the kind of a canonical
place that people
put their projects.
All your projects will collect
here, okay, concentration, and
then the other ones we're
gonna do later in the quarter.
This source control,
we'll talk about that later
in the quarter as well, but
we're not doing that for the
first week. Okay here it is,
your first iOS app. Now what
we're seeing in the middle of
Xcode, how many people have
done something in Xcode
before? Okay, so about half of
you, so that's pretty common.
So you know that in Xcode,
this middle area is your main
editor, and right,
we're seeing right now,
in this main area,
is our project settings.
We answered some of these in
those previous little things
that came up, and the reason
it's showing our project
settings is because on the
left here in this blue area
we have the project selected,
see the dark blue selection at
the top. That's
the project selected, and
this whole blue area on the
left is called the navigator,
and the navigator let you
navigate through your project,
and in this particular tab
it's showing me the files in
my project.
I have six files right here,
they were given to me chose
that template, the single
view template, but I can also
now navigate by searching,
right here. If I'm debugging I
can navigate through my break
points, etc. So you'll get
real familiar with using this
blue thing right here,
and you can say how much
space you want it to have to
navigate through
your application.
Now on the right hand side,
this over here,
you can actually see a little
area that has a top and
a bottom. This is called
the utilities pane, and
I'm gonna show you all
about that in five minutes.
So I'm gonna hide
it right now.
You see this button in
the very upper right.
That hides that, and this one
hides the navigator. So if you
wanna give more space to your
main window, you can do that.
There's another button here,
you see that one?
That hides your debugger and
console window.
So this is the debugger right
here where you're looking, I
think, going on your debugger,
and this is the console.
Now, the console is just a
place where there's a function
in Swift where we can
print text out there.
It's really great for
lightweight debugging.
We're just printing out what's
going on. Inside my app.
And that's what I'm
going to do today,
I'm not going to show you
the debugger today, that's for
Friday. I'm just going to show
you using print to debug and
you can also move this up and
down as high as you want. So,
it's very nice to be able to,
kind of, organize your space.
I have a fairly low
resolution screen here. So
I'm going to be trying to hide
things as much as possible to
make the text really big so
you can see what I'm doing.
All right, one last thing I
want to show before we dive in
here, is this area up here,
you see this, this is how you
run your application. Okay so,
when you run your application,
you have to decide where are
you gonna run it. You can run
it on a device, so you can
hook up a device to your Mac.
And you can hook it up
wirelessly actually or
with a little USB cable or
whatever. And I don't have any
hooked up, so I can't do that.
But I can also can run on all
of these simulators. So, these
simulators simulate these
various device like an iPad or
iPhone 8+ or whatever. And
you can run your app on any
of these that you want and
in fact, the simulator
will open both of these,
multiple of these as a time,
if you want. So I'm gonna
do the latest and greatest
here which is the iPhone X.
Okay I'm gonna run my
app on IPhone X and
let's go ahead and run it.
We haven't done anything, so
it's just a blank app and
let's just run it for fun.
You see this play button right
here? That's how you run, so
I'm gonna click that play
button. Now it is compiling my
app as you can see at the top,
it's it building into
a binary. It's loading
it onto the device, or
in this case, simulator.
And it runs it. Okay so
here it is.
It looks like an iPhone X and
it's running my app and
it's completely blank.
Well because I haven't
done anything,
I haven't built any UI.
But if I press the home button
on the iPhone X, everyone know
how that works? You slide up
from the bottom. Sliding
up from the bottom is like
the home button because there
is no home button in iPhone X.
And you can see there's our
app concentration right there.
But all other apps
are there too.
Settings, right, you can go
into the settings app. And
if you want, you might have
your app needs to set some
setting like I dunno text
size or something like that.
So these simulators are truly
simulating the device, they're
not just running your app
only. So that's kinda cool.
And we can always go back to
our app. Just go back here and
say Concentration, here's
Concentration. All right,
so now we're familiar
with Xcode and kind of
all its pieces right here.
Let's take a look at the files
that were created for us.
Now, There are six files but
actually we're only gonna look
at two of them. For example,
this one, assets, right here,
that's your images,
including your app icon,
which we haven't set,
I don't really need that. Your
launch screen right here, I'm
selecting that as well. This
app delegate up here, we don't
need to touch any of these to
make our Concentration app. So
I'm selecting them all and I'm
going to right-click on them,
and go down to new group from
selection, and put them in
a group. And I'm going to call
that group Supporting Files,
because that's what they are,
they're supporting files.
By the way, I would not
put your info.plist in
your Supporting Files,
leave that at the top level.
It seems to be better. So
this other file here,
ViewController.swift,
is just some Swift code, we'll
get to that in a second. And
right here, Main.storyboard,
that's your UI.
Now you're gonna build your
UI in Xcode graphically,
okay you're not gonna code
it up, you're gonna do it
graphically. And not only that
the way you're gonna build it,
you're gonna drag
out buttons and
text fields and sliders and
things like that.
And it's going to actually
put real buttons and
real sliders live on
the screen at a time. And
you're going to edit them and
set them up the way you want.
And then when you run
them on your app,
it kind of freeze dries them,
brings them over and
adds water and they come back
to life. And then they run. So
when you run, it's not like
you don't click a button here
and it generates a lot of code
to put those buttons there.
It's actually editing
these buttons live. Now,
notice that I got this, sort
of, iPhone shaped rectangle.
Can you all see that? Yeah, it
looks pretty good. This iPhone
shaped rectangle is where I'm
going to edit my UI. And in
particular this is an iPhone 8
sized rectangle, you see that?
It says view as iPhone 8 down
here. I can click on this and
actually look at other iOS
devices. So I can look at
my IU, how it would look
let's say on an iPad.
Now an iPad is huge so maybe I
wanna zoom down a little bit
to see it better. I can also
look at it in landscape mode.
So here's portrait and
landscape of an iPad, for
example. I could go to
a different kind of iPhone,
like here's my iPhone X,
all right? So I can look at
all possible iOS devices and
see how my UI looks.
Now our goal eventually, once
we learn enough about iOS,
is to build UIs that look good
even if they're in landscape
or portrait, iPad, iPhone 8,
iPhone 8+, which is big,
iPhone X, it doesn't matter.
Okay that's our goal.
Now in the first week, I can't
teach you any of that, so
we're gonna have our UI just
try and
look good on an iPhone X.
But next week, not to worry
we'll try to make it so
it looks good on other
iPhones as well. And
your assignment two is gonna
really ask you to make
an app that just looks good
on all possible iOS devices.
Now on the left over here,
when we brought up this,
this area in Xcode by the way
is called Interface Builder
because we're building
our user interface,
so Interface Builder. This
area over here is essentially
all the things
that are here but
in text form,
like a text outline.
And I'm gonna hide that,
you do that with this
little button down here,
see it says hide
document outline.
I'm gonna click that to hide
that. We'll go and hide this
phone chooser as well and
we have our little UI here.
We'll look at that document
outline later in the quarter.
I want to build my UI,
how do I build a UI?
Okay I'm trying to build
Concentration here.
So I'm going to need some
cards. And I'm going to
use a button to represent
a card, which is kind of cool,
because you tap
on a button and
it does something.
And that's good,
because when you tap on a
button I want it to flip over.
Okay, I'm going to have
my cards flip over. So
that's the first thing you do.
Let's build one card that will
flip over when we click
on it all right. So
I'm going to zoom in, by the
way, you can hold down alt.
You see in the lower left I
have a thing here that shows
when I'm pressing alt,
and control, and command,
and all that stuff.
If you hold down alt and
use your mouse wheel you can
zoom in and out, on your
UI, which is kind of cool.
Otherwise your mouse wheel
moves it up and down, which is
also kinda cool. All right so
we have our UI here, how do we
put a button in this UI? Okay,
as promised, we go over to
this thing that had a top and
a bottom,
called the utilities pane.
And we're going to look in
the bottom to start, and
specifically, in this
object library tab. And
we're going to see a whole
bunch of objects, remember,
and I mean objects like in
an object-oriented sense,
this is all object-oriented.
And all these objects,
like labels and buttons and
text fields and switches,
even web views and table views
and text views and even ARKit.
Here's a little ARKit of
augmented reality views.
These things can
all be dragged out,
multi touch gestures,
dragged out to build your user
interface. Okay and I'm going
to cover the vast majority of
the stuff in this very
large list right here.
But we're going to start with
a simple one which is towards
the top, which is buttons. So
I just wanna drag
a button into my UI, and
I just drag it in,
I pick it up with mouse, and
drop it in my UI.
Now, when I move this around,
look at these blue lines,
see these blue lines.
They're trying to help me put
it exactly in the middle, or
exactly in the middle
on the bottom edge,
or up in the upper
right corner.
These blue lines are critical
to building a UI that will
work when you rotate or on a
bigger device or whatever. But
we're gonna ignore
the blue lines for now
because I said I'm gonna
teach you that next week,
all right? So here's my
button, it's very, very small.
I want it to be bigger. Well,
I can just grab these handles
on the edge here and resize it
to whatever size that I want.
Maybe make it a little
more card shaped or
something like that. And
I could also edit the text on
here by double-clicking
on this.
I don't want Button maybe, but
let's do the back of the card,
let's see what the back
of the card looks like.
So I'm just gonna delete it,
so now my button has no
text on it, all right,
which is fine. How about
setting the background color
to orange, these cards orange,
and our Halloween theme here,
they have orange background.
How do I do that?
Well, that's the top of this
utilities pane. Notice that
when I select a button, I get
this UI over here that is
specific to setting the
attributes of a button. And
not only that,
it's object-oriented. So
I have the button stuff here
and as I scroll down, look,
I get UI for a control because
button inherits from control.
And then control
inherits from view. So
I get UI to enter to view
because a button is a view,
right? It inherits from view
in the object-oriented sense.
So the background of any view
is settable here in this UI.
It's right here under View,
it says Background.
Right now the background
is clear, that little line
through a thing means clear.
So there is no background, so
it's showing the white from
behind is showing through. But
I can easily change this to
orange by clicking there and
going down here. You know,
there's a lot of
preset colors here.
I can go to Other and pick it
by name, I could pick orange.
I could pick a crayon
that looks orange,
color wheel, whatever.
But here I want orange, so
I'll just pick it by name. And
now I've set the background
of my card to be orange, so
that's good. That's looking
pretty much exactly like this,
I'm happy with it so far.
And in our Halloween theme,
to make it even scarier,
let's make the background here
be black. So I'm gonna
change this to be black.
And the way I do that is
I just click on it and
now this right-hand side
doesn't say button on the top.
It say view because this big
space is just a blank view.
It's not a button view or
anything. It's just a view,
but it's got this background
thing, same way. So
I click on it, and here I'll
just pick it from this list of
predefined things. Black
color, and now, I have a nice
orange on black UI. Looking
pretty cool. Now, what about
when the cards are face up?
Well, when they're face up,
they're white. And then
they have an image on them.
Now I could have the cat or
the spider web here or
whatever be some JPEG image or
something. But
I got a really cool idea to
make this be real easy, let's
make it be an emoji. Cuz if
we just put an emoji in here,
then we have a lot of choices.
And it's really easy and
we don't have to go find the
images or anything like that.
So that's what we're gonna do.
So
I'm gonna make this look like
the front of the card. So I'm
gonna go down here and change
this orange back to white,
okay, this white color.
And I'm gonna put on here,
instead of blank, I'm gonna
put an emoji. Most Mac apps,
if you go to their Edit menu,
at the bottom of it,
there's this emoji and
symbols. I don't know how, how
many of you know that. But if
you go to emoji and symbols,
you get this window right
here that lets you choose
all these various emoji. We
got a Halloween theme here, so
let's look for a ghost.
Yeah, Mr. Ghost, right there.
Okay, so that's a good, he
looks like a fun ghost even.
We'll double-click right there
to put him on the card and
there he is. He's very, very
tiny. I could go zoom in and
look at them. But he's even
small compared to the size of
the iPhone X. If my user was
doing this, they'd be like,
what is that. It was just
like a little smudge. So
we wanna make this
much larger. So again,
I'm going to the top side, top
half of this utilities pane.
And if I look down here, look,
font, system font 15 point.
So I'm gonna make
that way bigger,
let's make it 50 point.
Now we got a nice big ghost.
Awesome,
we have got all we needed in
terms of design to do our UI.
Let's go ahead and run and
see what happens here.
See if this black background
and this ghost and
all this stuff is showing
up in our app when we run.
And of course it will be, here
it is. And when I click on it,
can you see that it's
flashing a little bit there?
That's saying, that's giving
me a little feedback, yeah,
you touched on that.
It's nice, but
it doesn't do anything, right?
And we want it
to do something.
Mainly we want it to flip
over. So let's go do that.
How do we make it so something
in the UI does something?
Well, we're gonna hook it up
to some code. Specifically,
we're gonna hook it up to
this Swift code right here.
Now they gave us these
things right here,
which I'm gonna delete so
as not to distract you.
But this is your first
look at Swift code.
Let's look at it real quick,
see what it does. Import,
it's just like include. It's
just bringing all of UIKit
in for our use. UIKit is iOS's
framework that has buttons and
sliders and all that stuff.
Kinda that top cocoa touch
layer we're talking about.
So this is the declaration of
a class, in an object-oriented
sense, a class. Of course
we use the keyword class.
This is the name of the class,
ViewController.
This is not a very good name,
it's very generic. Probably
this wants to be called
ConcentrationViewController or
something like that. Do not
change the name of this in
your homework, okay?
Changing the name of
this requires a little
more than just changing it
right here, because it's
also showing up in your UI.
So you have to change it in
away that it changes in both
places. This is its
super class. This is
Object-Oriented Programming.
We have inheritance.
It's inheriting from
UIViewController.
Class UIViewController is in
UIKit. You can tell because it
starts with UI.
And what that class does,
it knows everything about
controlling a UI like this.
That's what it does. So
by having our ViewController
inherit from that, it inherits
all the capability to control
that thing. So all we have to
do is put the code that has
to do with the Concentration
game in here, so
that's great. Then inside
this curly brace, we're gonna
put all our methods and
instance variables. Who
does not know what the word
method or instance variable
means? Okay, good, everybody
does. And you should because
that's fundamentally an
Object-Oriented Programming,
right? So we're gonna put all
our instance variables and
methods inside
those curly braces.
That's how we're gonna declare
our class. So how are we
gonna make this button
do something here? Well,
what we're gonna do is we're
gonna create a method in here.
And we're gonna make it so
that when you press this
button, it calls that method,
of course.
How are we gonna do that?
To do that, believe it or not,
we need to get this UI and
this code over here on
the screen at the same time.
And we do that with this
little button right here.
This little circles
thing right here,
this is called the assistant
editor. And when I click it,
they come on screen, both of
them on screen, at the same
time. And I can adjust
this space however I want.
Maybe we'll get
rid of this now.
All right, so here's my UI and
my code on screen at the same
time. Now, why do I want them
on screen at the same time if
I need to hook them up?
Because the way I hook them
up is I hold down the Ctrl key
and drag a line from the UI to
my code.
I know that's kinda weird, but
that's how we do it. And when
we let go of that drag line,
it says, you will make
a connection between UI and
code. No problem, what kinda
connection would you like?
You can make an action,
which is a method, or
one of these two
outlet things,
which I'm gonna talk about
later in this lecture. So
let's start with this action
one. An Action connection
means when this button is
pressed, call a method.
And I get to say what
the name of the method is.
I'm gonna call it touchCard,
cuz that's what's happening,
someone's touching on this
card. And this method that's
gonna be created for me,
it can have arguments,
it could have no arguments,
that's none. Or
it could have one argument,
which is the sender,
in other words, the button
that is sending me this.
I really need that argument,
because when this touch
card gets sent to me,
I need to flip it over. So,
I have to talk to it, okay, so
I want that argument.
And really important,
pay attention right now if,
if you're dozing right now,
is that we do not. This is
the type of the arguments.
See it says Type Any? And we
want that type to be Button,
okay? Because a button is
sending this method to us.
Now I don't know why that
doesn't default to Button.
I've been saying that for
years, it should. But
it doesn't. And if you don't
change that from any to button
the rest of this code is not
gonna work. So definitely,
if you remember nothing else
from this, remember to change
that. All right? So we have
this button here and I'm gonna
hit these other things. But
you know, here's obviously,
we were sending it to
the view controller.
The event touch up in side
just means when you touch
up inside the bounds of
the button, send this message.
All right, so let's connect.
I'm gonna hit Connect.
It's gonna give me a method.
This is your first look at
a Swift method right here.
And let's look at the parts
of it. Interestingly,
this is not part of a Swift
method, okay. This is just
a special directive that
Xcode is putting in there.
That causes it to put this
little round circle here where
the line numbers are. You see
how line number lucky 13 there
is a circle instead.
If I mouse over that circle,
I'm not clicking just mousing
over. If I mouse over that
it'll show me which
buttons send this message,
which ones invoked
this method. So
that's all the IBAction does
just cause this circle to
appear here. Now this is
the syntax of a Swift method.
So let's look at it's parts.
Func. It's just a key word
that says this is a function.
A method is just a function on
a class. It is legal to have
functions outside of classes.
They're global functions.
We almost never do that cause
we're very object oriented,
but you can do it. This is
the name of the method,
touch card. I chose that
in the little pop up.
This is a list of all
its arguments. Okay,
this method has one argument.
The type of the argument comes
at the end with a colon, colon
type, which is a UIButton,
obviously,. We said we
wanted one argument,
which the sender was
a UIButton, that's what it is.
This are the names
of this parameter.
Names plural. Now, there are
two things about Swift that
are going to be quite
different from what you're
used to in other languages.
One, every argument has a name
that you actually include when
you call the method. Okay?
So like in Java you would
say touchguard open
parenthesis six comma hello
comma five. You would
never do that in Swift.
Each parameter would
have a name in front of
it. That way if you're
calling it and you're reading
the code you don't have to
remember that first argument,
what's that again? Because
they're each named. And
the other thing is it
has two names. Okay.
The two names
are the external name.
That's the name callers use
and the internal name. That's
the name we're going to use
inside of are implementation.
Now I'm going to write my own
method in a second here and
we'll talk about this more,
but that's what's going on
here. Now if this method had a
return value, you show that by
saying arrow Int lets say
that would mean this method
returns an Int. Very simple
syntax for that. But
this method doesn't return an
Int, but you could make it so
it does. Okay, so let's
make sure this is working.
I'm just gonna use that print
function I was talk about this
is a global function called
print. It just takes a string
and prints on the console. So
here I'll print agh! a ghost.
Okay, and
we're gonna run our app and
see if this is working when
we press the ghost. So
by the way, when we are gonna
print stuff from the console,
we probably wanna bring
this up from the bottom so
we can see our console, we can
make our debugger smaller.
Here's our console bring it
up. There's actually a cool
thing you can do,
I'll show you a Xcode tip.
If you got here to Xcode,
Behaviors and Edit Behaviors.
And you go down
you can have it so
that Xcode does things,
opens windows,
does other stuff when certain
things happen. For example,
if you're running and
it generates some output
on the console, you can say
show the debugger. Okay, and
it will automatically bring
that up from the bottom
if it's not there.
So that's kind of a nice
little feature. All right, so
let's run it. Those are the
kind of tips and tricks we'll
cover on Friday, by the way.
Good reason to come on Friday.
Question, yeah?
>> Can you go over again
how you link the button
to the view controller?
>> Yeah how we
connect to the button
view controller?
Yeah, I'll show you
that in just a second.
So let's make sure
it's working and
then I'll show you how we
connect to it again. So
we have this button here.
I'm gonna click the ghost and
look down in our console.
Look, agh! it's a ghost, okay.
So it's working. So
we're clicking the button and
it's doing that. So
the question is,
how did we hook it up again?
Well what we did is that we
held down control, the control
key, and we dragged from
the button into our code.
And when we let go it asked
us all the questions.
What do you want to call it?
That kind of stuff. All right,
so we got this hooked up,
right. Now we need to flip the
card over when this happens
instead of just saying, agh!
a ghost. Okay?
So we're not gonna say agh!
a ghost anymore. So
to do that, I'm going to add
my own function that flips
the card over. So let's create
our own Swift function.
So we have to say func cuz
its a method on a function.
I'm gonna call this flipCard,
okay.
And I£m gonna have
two arguments.
One is the emoji that I
want to be on this card,
the ghost or whatever.
The other one is the button
that I want to set
the emoji on, or whatever.
So, interestingly here, I£m
going to call in these things
constrain what you might
think are strange names.
I'm gonna say with emoji,
emoji of type string. So
this is in external name with
emoji internal name emoji. And
how about this one on
button UIButton. Okay?
Now, these might seem really
strange to you as names of
parameters, both internal and
external.
And in your reading assignment
on the last page, it's gonna
link you to a document you
have to read that explains
how to pick good names here.
Cuz there's a very well
defined set of rules for
picking good names here. But
the number one rule is when
someone calls this function,
it should read like English.
That is the number one
requirement of
picking these names.
So let's call this function
in touch card right here,
cuz we want to call it with
the ghost. So I'm gonna say
flipCard. Okay, notice, by
the way, as I start to type,
look at Xcode trying to
help me. Xcode's so nice,
you see look, it know that
I have a flipCard method.
In fact, I'm just gonna hit
tab and it shows me the method
with the argument names. And
I'm just ready to fill it in.
So this is called, from
the caller's point of view,
flipCard(withEmoji).
The emoji is let's say, for
example, our ghost.
I'll just copy and
paste him from right here. On
the button and which button?
Of course, the sender. That's
this sender right here. So
you see when I call it,
it reads like English.
Flip the card with the emoji
ghost on the sender button.
That's our number one thing
we're trying to accomplish.
But inside here we wouldn't
wanna be saying like, well if
the button title equals with
emoji that just is weird.
It's sending a message to the
button that says on.whatever,
that would make no sense,
so that's why we have
these different names.
Now, it is possible and legal
to only have one name like
just emoji. Then the external
internal name would both
be emoji. And this underbar
thing like right here.
That means there's
no argument,
in other words it's
just like Java or
some other language. We almost
never do that, it is done,
the document will tell
you when you can do it,
we almost never do it.
It's here in this touch card
because that's an iOS thing
that's sending this message.
It's from back in
the Objective-C world.
Objective-C doesn't have this
internal external name thing.
So that's why it's under
bar there, okay, but
we don't really use under
bar that much. All right, so
how we're gonna implement
this flipCard right here?
Well, this flipCard is
essentially gonna toggle it,
and I'm just gonna have
this flipCard method,
look at the button If
it's already the ghost,
then I'm gonna have it flip it
over to orange with no text.
If it's not, then I'm gonna
put the ghost on it with white
background. Just exactly what
we played around with earlier.
So, we need to check to see
if the buttons current title
is this ghost. So I'm just
gonna try and type this in
let's see, if the button.
Okay, now I need to send
a message to the button asking
it what's your current title.
Well, probably I wanna go look
in the documentation, figure
out what button does. In fact,
that's what you want to do.
But there's actually a cool
way if you just wanna guess
what it is. You can press dot.
That's how you send a message
in Swift to just like Java,
right, dot to send a message.
And when you do that Xcode is
gonna show you all the methods
and variables that button
understands, and let me say,
there are quite a few. Okay,
I'm scrolling through here,
I'm only down to the Cs okay,
we got Ds,
there's probably
a couple hundred. So
how does this help me?
This doesn't help me at all.
Well, the cool thing is, if I
just type a word here that I
think might be in the name of
the method I want like title.
I want you to set the title.
Now it just shows me things
that start with title, or
that have title in it, or
have T-I-T-L-E in it,
which is not very useful, but
that's why it puts those
at the bottom. But anyway,
we got the title. So now I
can start looking around in
a much shorter list here,
to see if I can find it.
So here's title color,
definitely I don't want that.
Title rectangle, no.
Here's set title.
I don't wanna set
the title right now but
that's kinda good to know.
Look at this one, current
title. Current title that
is displayed on the button.
Victory, I found exactly what
I want. And when I find what I
want here, looks like by
the way, returns a string?
We'll try it anyway.
If I double click on it,
it's gonna put that there for
me. And now I can just say
is that equal to the emoji
that you're asking me to flip
the card to. This first
argument. Notice how I'm using
emoji and button as my
internal names here.
I'm not using with emoji or
on. That was for the caller.
Okay, so now I found out
that the button already here
has the ghost on it. So
now I wanna make it orange and
blank. So now I need to set
the button's title, and I saw
before that it was set title.
Here it is, set title. Now
this set title has extra thing
here, for UI control state.
You see that? It's like,
what the heck is that?
I don't know anything about
buttons, so, I'm not sure.
But I don't see any other set
title, so I guess I'll have to
go with this one. Okay, so I
double click on it. The title
I want to set here, of course,
is empty string because,
I'm trying to do the back
of the card here.
So I empty it out. And now I'm
kind of at this control state
impasse, because I don't
really know what this means.
So, here's another
cool thing you can do,
is hold down option and
mouse over anything,
you see how it's highlighting
things with a little question
mark right there? And you can
click on it and it'll show you
the documentation for that
thing. So here is set title,
the documentation for it.
And if I read through this,
the third paragraph and
description says,
at a minimum,
you should set the value for
the normal state. Okay,
sounds good. Now I'd like to
understand how to get that
normal state, so I'm gonna
actually click on this link
here, you see UIControlState?
And it's gonna take me
to the documentation and
show me control state.
So here we go, click brings up
the documentation, here's
control state, see that? And
here it is normal, the very
first one is called normal.
And we're gonna see later
how we use these things but
this is a static,
you see it's a static bar.
So it's kind of a property
of the type, and so
the way that we will
type that in is to say,
UIControlState.normal. So it's
awesome we found that, but
while I'm here in
the documentation,
let me briefly show you how
the documentation works.
Right here, you can see
that I'm looking in UI kits
at its views and controls at
the class UIControl, which
button inherits from. And
we're looking at this thing,
UIControlState. But
I can click anywhere here and
go back and maybe look at
UIButton if I want. And here's
UIButton. Now, when you're
looking at the documentation,
I super strongly recommend you
read these overview sections.
You see where this
says Overview?
This overview section
in each class,
only take you five minutes
to read. And it's really
gonna help you understand what
the heck is going on here.
So, I strongly recommend
you do that for
all the common classes that
you're using, UIButton later
we're gonna do array in
dictionary. Go read it so
you understand what the heck
is going on in here. Got that?
You can also search the
documentation of course here.
And in addition to overview it
has a list of all the methods.
And here, for example,
here is set title again. Go
back and see if it's the same
that shows up in that little
box. So now we know that this
control state here is supposed
too be UIControlState.normal.
It's gonna set the normal
control state. We also want to
set the background color so
I'm going to do button dot and
I'm gonna just take a flyer,
backgroundcolor.
Sure enough, look
backgroundColor or something,
exactly called backgroundColor
that takes a UI color,
I think? Let's double
click that one. And
I'm gonna set that equal to,
believe it or not you can
actually put a color
literal in here. You just
do that by starting to type
the word color, and you're
gonna see the first choice
is always Color Literal.
If you double click on that,
it puts a little
square in here.
If you click on the square you
can pick the color you want.
So let's go back and
pick our nice orange,
cuz that's what we do
in the background.
And so, we've set our
background color to orange.
And it's really nice to be
able to see that in your code.
It really highlights
the colors you're using.
All right otherwise if it's
not, doesn't have the ghost
right now then we want to
put the ghost on there.
So I'm gonna do pretty much
exactly the same code here.
It's just that I'm gonna set
the title instead of blank,
like the background.
I'm gonna set it to the emoji,
the ghost in this case. And
I'm gonna double click on this
orange square and change it to
white, because I want a white
background for the front.
We got that? Okay,
let's run, see if our card.
Our card should flip over now,
which is getting us quite
a long way along the path here
to getting concentration
working. Right here is
our ghost. Cross your fingers.
Whoo, it flips over and
back. Okay, excellent.
All right, we're on a roll.
Now, let's go and
add another card. Okay,
we got one card. Let's go to
the second card. Believe it or
not, you can take things in
Interface Builder that
are the way you want it and
just copy and paste them.
So now I have two cards and
this card already is
the right shape that I want,
it's got the right font
size all that stuff.
So it's really recommended to
copy and paste verses dragging
out a new one and trying to
set it to all the same thing.
Just copy and paste.
Now this one wants a different
thing on it, so let's do
something like pumpkin. Yeah,
well we could do a pump and
now we'll do pumpkin,
all right? So we got pumpkin.
So we had pumpkin card and
we got a ghost card.
Now this pumpkin card,
it needs a method.
So we're gonna Ctrl+drag
to create another method.
So if you missed it the first
time, this is how we do it.
It's an action. I'm gonna
call this touchSecondCard.
The type, of course, we want
a UI button, argument sender.
Connect it, here it is.
I'm gonna take this
exact same code from here,
put it down here,
but instead of the ghost right
here, I'm gonna use R pumpkin.
Okay, looks good, right? This
could not possibly go wrong,
this is so simple.
It's gotta work,
okay, let's do it.
All right, here we go,
the ghost still working like a
charm. And a Pumpkin, pumpkin
not working. Okay, what is
wrong with our pumpkin?
How could this pumpkin
possibly not be right. Well,
we could get in the debugger
here, set a breakpoint,
it's real easy to set
a breakpoint by the way.
You just click on
a line number,
puts the breakpoint there. But
we're gonna do a little
more lightweight debugging.
I'm just going to put a print
here in flipCard, to see if
this is even calling flipCard.
It should be calling flipCard,
because it's connected here to
this method, so it should be
calling flipCard. So
I'm just gonna go in here and
say print, that I'm in
flipCard withEmoji. And
now I wanna put this
emoji in here. Now,
in a lot of other languages,
you would probably say %s,
emoji, or
something like that, right?
This would be your, oops,
this would be your string.
But we don't have this
%s business in Swift,
we have something better,
which is\(). So
\() means put something inside
there, it's gonna interpret it
as a string, and embed it in
this string. So that's exactly
what we want, emoji, and
the cool thing about it is,
I could put, this is a string,
so it's easy to embed.
But I could put an Int here,
anything that can be converted
to a string, which most things
in Swift can, I can put there,
I can even put an array there,
or a dictionary.
As long as the array only
had things that could
be converted to a string,
then it can convert the whole
array to a string. So
this is a really cool feature,
this\(), all right?
So let's run again, and
see if that pumpkin is calling
flipCard, which it should be.
All right, so the ghost,
it's definitely calling it,
see flipCard withEmoji, the
ghost, how about the pumpkin?
It looks like it's calling it,
but I didn't press that twice,
what's going on there?
That that's kinda weird,
let's do it again. No look
at that, it's doing both.
Every time I press
the pumpkin,
it's doing the ghost and
the pumpkin, ghost and
pumpkin. Why is it
doing it twice, okay,
that's clearly they're
messing things up badly.
Well, let's look and see why
it's doing that. We know that
this method is being
called by the pumpkin. And
this method is being called
by both. that's the problem.
And why did that happen, cuz I
copied and pasted the ghost.
And when I copied and pasted
the ghost, it copied and
pasted the fact that it was
sending that message. So
this is a common
mistake to make,
really easy. So I did it
intentionally to show you how
to get out of this, which is
to right-click on something.
If you right-click on anything
in the UI, it will show you
all the connections that it
has. So this is the pumpkin,
it's sending touchCard and
touchSecondCard, but
we only want it to send
touchSecondCard. So
I'm gonna disconnect touchCard
by clicking right here.
Now I fixed it, okay, now
the pumpkin is sending this,
and only the ghost is sending
this. So right-click is
an important thing to know,
if you ever get in a situation
where it seems like,
I thought I wired that up,
why is it not sending it?
Or even why is it crashing
trying to send something that
I didn't intend? Right-click
on it, will tell you why.
So let's run, see if that
indeed fixed our problem here,
I imagine it will. Okay, it's
got the ghost flipping over,
we got the pumpkin flipping
over, okay, excellent,
all going great. Now before I
add yet more cards, I want to
have some UI that tells me how
many times I've flipped cards.
Because you notice
in this game,
the fewer times I flip it,
the better I am at it, right?
If I flipped them all over,
up and down,
up and down, then I'm not
very good, it's easy,
I didn't have to concentrate.
So I wanna have some UI that
says how many times I've
flipped a card, okay? So to do
that I'm gonna start, let's
get rid of this print in here,
we don't need that debugging
anymore. So I'm gonna
start by adding an instance
variable to my class that
keeps track of the flip count,
okay, real, real simple like.
Move this down here so we can
get some space, all right?
So what does it look like to
add an instance variable to
your class? Really simple, you
use the keyword var, short for
variable. Then the name
flipCount, then the type,
: Int, that's it. So I have
added here a variable called
flipCount to my class, and I£m
gonna keep that flipCount up
to date as these cards
are flipped on. But,
look what happened here, I had
an error. So this red, when
you have a red error, your app
won't even compile and run.
You can also get a yellow one,
then your app will compile and
run, but do not submit your
homework with yellow ones
either. Even though
they're just warnings,
they are usually indicator
something bad, so
don't do that either. But this
red, I gotta fix this red.
Now what's funny is this red
came up on a different line of
code. I typed this line of
code in, and it came up on
a completely different line.
Well what does this say here,
it says, class ViewController
has no initializers.
Why is it saying that, what
does that have to do with it?
Well, this is happening
because Swift requires
all instance variables,
which by the way in Swift,
we call instance
variables properties.
So when you hear me
saying property,
I mean instance variable.
So all instance variables,
all properties have
to be initialized,
you are not allowed to have
them like this flipCount int.
What is the value right now?
It has no value, okay,
it has to have
an initial value,
it's just not allowed to be
sitting out there. Now there's
two ways to initialize
an instance variable,
one is using an initializer.
So that's what this error is
trying to tell us,
get an initializer here, dude.
An initializer is just this
method with a special name,
init, short for
initializer, and
it can have any arguments
you want. In fact,
you can have multiple inits,
each with different arguments.
But each init is responsible
for initializing
all of the variables, okay,
that's what the init's job is.
So we could add an initializer
here and do that.
Now, unfortunately, adding an
initializer to a class can be
kinda complicated because
of inheritance, right?
Because your superclass
has initializers,
you gotta make sure they
get called properly.
So I'm not even gonna talk
about initializers yet, okay,
I'll talk a little bit about
them on Wednesday. Next week
we'll really talk more in
depth about initializers. And
so what's the second way
that I can initialize this,
since I don't wanna do
initializers right now?
And that's just right
here to say, = 0, okay,
if I just, why do I keep
pressing v there, okay,
Int = 0, okay.
That initializes this,
that's gonna cause this error
to go away, all is well. And
this is how we initialize most
of our instance variables.
Now while I'm here, talking
about instance variables,
I wanna talk a little bit
about Swift and typing.
Swift is an extremely
strongly typed language,
I mean extreme. It does have
a type which is kind of like
untyped, but
really it's mostly for
backwards compatibility with
Objective-C. In most cases you
want to be very specific about
what types you're using,
and some people complain about
strongly typed languages. It's
so much burden to always be
typing something. Okay, well
Swift is also a language that
has strong type inference,
which means it will, if it
can, guess the type for you.
So in this case, you see
I have this : Int type,
that is completely
unnecessary in Swift. And
not only unnecessary, we would
not put it in there, there is
no reason to put that there.
Why is that, because this 0 is
clearly an Int. Swift treats
all literals like this,
that don't have any decimal
points as Ints. And
so this is an Int, and how do
we know that? If we hold down
Option, just like we did when
we clicked on Title down here
to get the documentation,
we can click on flipCount, and
it'll say flipCount is an Int.
You see that, and if I
had said flipCount was 0.0,
then if I hold down option and
go back here to flipCount,
it says flipCount is a double,
okay? So into, it infers it,
if I said flipCount equals
"hello", it's
going to say okay,
flipCount is a string All
right, so it's gonna infer.
Now, this is easy to infer
cause this is a constant but
swift can even infer in
the most amazing complicated
situations. There's only
one type that thing can be,
it'll make it that type and
you don't have to
put the types.
So it's surprising in Swift.
The time you put types in
the most is arguments to
functions. Because that you
kind of have to say what, what
you're expecting there. But
otherwise you rarely are
actually putting the types.
It's quite amazing, actually.
All right, so we have this
flip count here. Let's go
ahead and increment it. K,
every time someone steps,
presses on a card I'm gonna
say flip count plus equals
one and ug I'm gonna copy and
paste the code. God.
Anytime you're copying and
pasting code,
you're doing it wrong.
Okay, that can't be right.
So I just did something that's
not right but I'm doing it
anyway. I could probably put
that somewhere else but
I'm gonna just.
We'll do it this way for now.
You'll see why in a second and
we'll fix it. But we don't
want to complicate the code.
But each time
a card is touched,
I'm gonna increment the flip
count. Now that's great, but
I need this flip count
to appear in the UI,
okay. I want the user to see
how many flips they've made.
So I have to have this int
appear in the UI.
So how do I do that? Well,
I need some sort of other UI
element besides a button And
that's just a little text
field. Okay, in fact there's
a read-only text field which
is called the UILabel in iOS.
And so of course anytime we
wanna add something to UI,
I go here, to the bottom side,
in fact right next to button,
here is label. I'll drag
it out and put it in here.
I'll try and center it or
something like that.
It's really really small so
I'm gonna make it much bigger
cuz I'm gonna be using big
font in a second here.
Even make it taller.
The text is black so
it's black on black.
That's a little hard to see so
I'm gonna go back over to
here, go to the top half here,
change the color of the text,
okay,
which is a label property
right here. From this,
to our favorite color, orange.
This text is really small, so
I'm going to change
the font from 17pt,
which is the default here,
to something like 40.
Much better. I don't want
it to say label here,
I want it to say Flips, let's
say we'll start out Flips: 0.
I don't want it left-aligned
like that, okay,
I don't want the text
left-aligned,
I want it in the center, so
I go over here and hit center.
So see how I'm just using this
editing inspecting up here to
kinda get the thing to look
the way I want it to look.
I can even use my dashed
blue lines here to
put it right along the bottom
and right in the center. Okay.
Even though I said we
are not really using those,
it£s still useful
to do that one.
>> All right, so
now I have my UI, how do I
talk to it? How do I tell it
when the flips change to show
the flips? Well, I£m gonna
do that also by making
connections between my UI and
my code. And we know how to
do that, Ctrl drag Right?
Ctrl+Drag, put it right here.
And this time,
though, I'm not doing an
action, I'm doing an outlet.
And what an outlet does is it
creates an instance variable.
So action creates a method,
Outlet creates an instance
variable or property and
that property is gonna
point to this UI label and
I'll be able to talk to it and
tell it to update itself when
the flips change. All right,
so what am I gonna call
the name of this thing, I'll
call this my flipCountLabel,
it got the type right here
didn't see any. Don't worry
about this storage week.
I'm gonna talk about
that next week. And so
I'm gonna hit connect and
it's gonna create another var.
Like var flipCount. But
this var is gonna be a little
different. This var is,
sorry wrong place there.
This var is var
flipCountLabel: UILabel!
Okay? Now you can't infer
this type by the way because
that UI enables in the UI. So
it doesn't know how to look in
the UI and infer a label so
it can't infer that there.
So we do need to explicitly
say it to UI label here. Week,
I told you to look,
we'll tell you next week.
This is another kind of
directive like this one that
puts the little dot there so
that we can see that's that,
that's that, that's that.
Okay, so here's the var,
exactly the same as we
did with flip count.
Notice there's a little
exclamation point there. That
is super important. But I'm
not gonna talk about it today.
I can't talk about everything
all at once. Notice that this
very important thing
also has a side effect.
It's not the primary
purpose of it but
the side effect is. It doesn't
have to be initialized.
notice this doesn't say
equals anything and yet
we don't have an error. Okay?
So don't freak out about that.
I'm gonna talk all about
this exclamation point.
It could not be
more important,
probably the most
important newish
thing that you're going to
learn about Swift, okay,
is what its all about.
All right, so I got this flip
count label right here.
Now, all I want to do is,
every time this flip count
changes, like, right here.
I'm going to talk to the flip
count label and I want to set
it's text, label. I want to
set it's text, so I'm going to
send it a message and I want
to set text, so I'm just going
to say text. There happens
to be something called text,
the very first one there.
You see that?
It says text as a string, so
I'm going to double click on
that All right and I'm gonna
set that text to, Flips:,
and then I'm gonna use my
favorite feature right here,
\(). And I'm gonna put
the flipCount in there. So
that's gonna change the text
on this flipCount layer here,
and we'll say Flips: 1, so
it's going to whatever And
of course, I have to copy and
paste again right
there because I need to
update it each time. So,
let's see if
this works.
Okay, here we go. Let's try to
flipping this card. Ooh, yeah.
Everytime we flipped
over our back.
It's incrementing the flip
count. Okay, fantastic.
Except this really is nasty.
I just copy and pasted.
I mean, imagine I really
was doing it this way and
I had another button
called New Game and
I had to set the flip
count back to zero.
I'm going to have to put this
same line of code there to.
And what if some day I said,
well,
I don't want this to say flip,
I want it to say flip count.
Now I've got to change
it all three places.
This is just
horrendous coding.
Luckily, in Swift, there is
a way to avoid doing this in
this case, which is that
any property, if you want,
you can put code after it that
says, did set. And it will
execute this code every time
that thing gets set. Okay?
That's called a property
observer. Because this code is
observing changes of this. So
we can take this outta here,
put it up here, and we can
take it away from here now.
Every time flip count changes,
it's going to Execute that
didSet, and talk to the label,
and update it.
So now if I add a new game
asset, flip count equals zero,
it would automatically
update it.
Property observer
is really cool.
Obviously we use property
observers a lot to keep the UI
in sync with te instance
variables of our class. Okay,
so you'll see that happening
all the time. All right, time
to get more buttons. We got
these two buttons. By the way,
notice that we're driving
our UI from the code, right?
It's this line of code that's
saying what's in the UI.
So I'm actually gonna change
these two buttons to be
face down.
Okay when they start.
And what's interesting is if I
select them both, and go over
to the top here of this thing,
notice it notices
they're both buttons. So
I can change things, like here
it says multiple values for
the text, ghost and
the pumpkin.
I can set that to blank, and I
can go down to the bottom and
set the background color here
to orange And it's affecting
both of them. So
if you select multiple things,
as long as they're of
the same, they share the same
type, then you can edit
them all simultaneously.
Okay. So I have these cards,
let's make some more cards.
I'm going to copy and
paste these cards. Actually,
before I do that,
let's do one other thing.
I'm pretty unhappy with
my architecture here,
because if I wanna add more
cards I guess I'm gonna have
to do copy, touch third card,
fourth card, fifth card,
sixth card, seventh card,
eight card, nine, okay.
That is gonna be the worst
code, you would get an F on
your homework if you did that.
That's just awful, so we're
clearly not gonna use that
architecture to do that and
in fact I want to get rid
of this touch second card
entirely, and I just want to
put everything in touch card.
And that means I won't have
this line of code duplicated
and this line of
code duplicated.
This is gonna be great.
This is much better, UI.
So to do this I'm gonna
right click on this one and
disconnect touch second card
and instead have this guy
ctrl-drag to here. Look at
that you can hook it up to one
that already exist by
just dragging to it and
letting go. So now both of
these are sending Touchcard.
Okay, so that's great but
inside here we
obviously can't do this.
Have this ghost thing here,
because then it would set both
cards to ghost. So how are we
gonna have code in here in
touch card, that works for
all the cards? Well what I'm
gonna do is I'm gonna create
an array of all these cards
and when touchCard is pressed,
I'm gonna look in that array,
find the button that's being
pressed, and then I'll know
which card it is. Then, when I
know which card it is, which
index it is in the array.
I'm going to lookup in another
array, the emoji to put there.
So, it's going to be data
driven. Right, and so
if I want to add more cards,
I just add more cards
to my emoji array.
It's going to be great.
All right, so
let's make more cards.
I'm going to copy and
paste to make more cards,
so I have four cards and
now I wanna make an array that
includes these cards, okay.
So how do I do an array
that include these cards?
Well, that's a connection
between the UI and the codes.
So I'm gonna control, drag and
create another var right here.
Okay, but this one's gonna be
the third kind which is outlet
collection. So now outlet
collection means an array
of the things in the UI. So
I'll call this myCardButons,
I'm actually gonna make
a mistake, okay and
say card butons
instead of buttons,
because I want to show you how
to fix this mistake if you do.
And it's got the type right,
this is gonna be an array of
UI button. Okay, so I'm gonna
connect it right here and
it created another var for
me right here.
This one and look at its type.
See that right there. That is
special syntax in Swift that
means an array of UI button.
This might look more familiar
if I use another Swift syntax,
array of UI button,
that look familiar to
you from Java, right? So array
is a generic class, everyone
know about generics in Java,
hopefully. It means that
you can't have the class array
on its own be a type in Swift,
because I told you Swift
is very strict about types.
So when you are putting things
in and out of that array,
Swift would have
a heart attack if it
didn't know the type of thing
you're putting in there. So
when you create an array you
have to specify what type of
thing is in the array so that
Swift can breathe easy, okay.
Now arrays are so common
that instead of using this
normal Swift, this is normal
Swift syntax right here, but
for arrays, we do this
special thing here, where
we say [UIButton]. It's just
for arrays that we do this,
dictionaries also have
a special one, I'll show you
that on Wednesday. Okay?
So that's our array,
CardButons is array, now I
have this cardButons here
okay, and this is connected to
that one card, I haven't put
the other cards in there yet
but I will. It's connected to.
Now what if I decided no,
I don't want Butons,
I made a mistake, it's Buttons
and remember I told you,
you don't wanna edit things
in here then also in the UI,
okay like the name of the
class and things like that.
Well if you do that look what
happened to the little circle.
Okay it doesn't have a dot
in it anymore because
it's not connected anymore.
Because this, if I right click
on it, it's connected to
Card Butons there, okay? It's
not connected to Card Buttons.
So, how can I fix this?
If I said this Card Butons,
okay it's back to being
connected now and
I want to change this.
It's another magic key.
The command key. We all ready
showed you the alt key for
getting into
the documentation.
If you command click
on something, k,
like this cardButons
right here.
You get another kind of menu
here that'll do some cool
things like jump to
the definition of this thing,
which happens to
be right here so
that's not gonna go anywhere.
Show the health,
just like the option one does,
and also rename and
when I click rename here,
look at what happens.
The UI kinda turns a little
bit. It looks through my
entire project and finds
that cardButons everywhere
including in my storyboard.
See that? So now if I change
this to cardButtons here,
it changes it everywhere and
now, this is not broken.
And if I right-click on this,
it cardButtons. So command
click rename. That's how you
want to rename things that
touch both your UI and
your code. Right, so I've got
this card buttons here. Now,
I need to somehow in
touch card, I need to
look into my card buttons
array and find that button.
Okay? By the way, before we do
that, let me put the rest of
these cards in there. I'm
going to show you another way
to connect up your UI to your
code. It's this yellow button
right here. You see this
yellow button at the top?
It says view controller. This
button also represents your
code. So, if you want to
control drag from here,
you can do that as well and
hook up to card buttons.
Control drag from here.
CardButtons and I'm
intentionally not gonna hook
up this card cuz I'm gonna
show you what happens when
we don't hook up a card. So
look at cardButtons, got those
three cards and not this one,
right. All right, so how am I
gonna look in cardButtons for
mine? Well of course Swift
array is a fantastic class.
It's got so
much great functionality and
one thing it knows how to do.
Is look inside and
tell you what the index is of
something inside of it and
that method is called index of
all right. So let's just call
that method, I'm gonna create
a var called card number
which I want to be the number
the card 0,1,2,3,4 wherever it
is in the array. I'm gonna set
that equal to cardButtons dot,
right sending a message card
button index. Now interesting,
look how many methods
are called index in array,
multiple methods. In Swift,
that's perfectly legal. Swift,
you can have 100 methods all
with the same index, but they
all have to have different
arguments. You see how all of
these index methods have
different arguments?
All right, and they get
the index after something,
index before
something whatever.
I want this one down here
index of something which is
returns a int, okay, that's
gonna be a problem that int,
we're gonna see in
a second here but
if I double click that,
I've got the index here. So,
I wanna find the index of the
sender cuz I'm in touch card
right here, so this sender and
I'm just gonna print this out.
So I'm gonna say card
number equals and
we'll do our magic thing here,
and
we will just print out
the card number, okay.
So before we go look in up in
an array and find the emotion,
let's just make sure that
we're finding the right card
right here. Now, right away
I get two warnings here.
Hm, let's go look at
these warnings in depth.
Let's make our whole screen
show these warnings.
The first one is Variable
cardNumber was never mutated.
Consider changing
to let constant.
What does that mean?
Well indeed, cardNumber,
we give it an initial value
here of looking up the card
in the card buttons array but
we never change it again.
So it is not back in fact
variable. It's a constant.
Okay, and in Swift we always
mark constants as constants.
But we don't use
const like in C and
other languages,
we use let, L-E-T.
And here's another cool thing.
You see this little triangle?
If I click on it, oftentimes
Swift will fix it for me.
You see that where it
says fix. It's saying,
you want me to replace var
with let? Like yeah, sure, and
it did, see? Now why do we
use let instead of const?
Because we want Swift
to read like English.
let cardNumber =
cardButtons.index of
the sender, sounds like
English to me, ish, okay? So
that's better than
const cardNumber =.
So you're gonna get used to
using let, always use let when
something's a constant,
never use var, all right?
This other warning right here,
I'm gonna ignore. And
let's just see what
happens here when we run.
So let's run this guy in our
simulator, we're ignoring
that, pay no attention to
the yellow warning there.
Okay, here it is, let's click
some of these buttons and
see what happens.
See, it's going to print.
We'll put this over on the
side so you can see the code
at the same time. We're just
gonna print out the cardNumber
that we found by
looking that index up.
Ready, click. That's kind
of weird, look at that,
Optional(1), Optional(2),
what's that Optional about?
There seems to be seeing the
card right, right, 0, 1, 2,
but it's saying Optional, why
is it saying Optional? Well,
this is that super important
thing I was telling you about?
Here it is. Lets option-click
on index right here, and
go look at it's documentation.
And
the return value of
index is not an int,
index is an optional,
that's what that
question mark means.
We've seen question marks all
over in the documentation,
right? It means optional.
And optional is a different
type entirely from int. Okay,
has nothing to do with int.
Optional is a type that has
two and only two states,
set and not set.
It's an enumeration.
You probably seen enumerations
in other languages,
enumerations are things that
have discreet set of values.
This one only has two values,
set and not set,
that's it. But the cool things
about enumerations in Swift,
not a lot of other
languages have this. For
each case of an enumeration
you can have associated data,
just data that goes along with
that thing. Well, an optional,
when it's in the set state,
has associated data,
which in this case is an int.
So this index method is
returning whether or not it
could find that button in
there by returning set or not
set. And if it does find it
it also gives you the
associated data of the int.
That's what you're seeing
down here. It's printing out,
when we print cardNumber it
says this is an optional.
It's in the set case and
the associated value is an
int. Got that? Now what if we
click on the button that's not
in the cardButton's array?
Let's see what that prints,
that does right here. Oops,
we stopped, let's go back and
run it again. I'm gonna click
on that fourth button
that is an in cardButton.
So when index looks it up
it's not gonna find it.
It's gonna return not set.
Let's see what that looks
like? Click nil, N-I-L. So in
Swift the word nil means the
not set case of an optional.
That's the only thing it
means. In other languages,
it means zero pointer and
other things. No, in Swift it
always means an optional
that's not set. Got that? All
right, so that's no good to me
though, to have an optional.
I can't look that optional up
in another array of emoji,
I need the int. So how do I
get that associated value in
the set state?
Well, one way is to put
an exclamation point at
the end of it. If you put
an exclamation point at the
end of an optional, it says,
assume this optional is set,
and grab the associated value.
So let's see what that looks
like. You're gonna see
this optional syntax is all
really simple question mark,
exclamation point, one
characters, because it's so
common to do these optionals.
All right, so
here look, cardNumber = 0,
1, 2, excellent,
it's working. What do you
think happens if I press this
one right here?
>> Crash.
exactly. Why is it gonna
crash? Because you're
>> Crash,
returning an option that's not
in the set state, so we don't
have that associated value,
so it crashes your program.
And you're gonna see this
crash quite a bit, okay,
when you're developing because
you'll just accidentally do
this quite a bit of time. And
if you look in your console,
look what it says.
It says an error here,
fatal error unexpectedly found
nil, that is to say not set
while unwrapping an optional.
Get used to that error,
you see it all the time. Now,
this might make you say, whoa,
I'm never using
exclamation points,
gonna crash my program,
scary. Yeah,
it's scary, but crashing your
program can be really good,
because it makes
you find problems.
Like in this case, that fourth
button is supposed to be in
card buttons It's a bug that
is not in card buttons. And
if I didn't crash right there,
I might not find that bug,
cuz I might not have
clicked on that one,
I might not have noticed. This
way, I'm for sure gonna find,
it's gonna crash. And now it's
gonna crash, it's gonna crash
right where it matters,
right in the debugger so
I can look at it. So don't
be afraid of crashes, okay?
Crashes can be good. But let's
say you wanted to do this
code in a way that
didn't crash,
that kind of conditionally
looked to see if it was in
the set state.
And if it was, then use it,
otherwise didn't do it.
To do that, instead of putting
exclamation point at the end,
you take that off and put if,
at the beginning, okay?
And so now, if this optional
right here is in the set state
then this code will execute,
otherwise it won't crash. So
that's if that's conditional,
you can see again,
optional minimum
possible syntax here.
So now, we can put this print
cardNumber inside here,
and we could even,
if we wanted to, put an else.
Could something like chosen
card was not in card buttons,
or something like that, so we
could notice that it happened.
And here we're
conditionally doing it, so
let's go look at
this I'm gonna move,
make this console wide here so
you can see what's going on,
all right? So here this is
still working cardNumber 0, 1,
2 because I'm using that if
let right there. But now,
if I click on this bad button
it just says chosen card was
not in card buttons, right?
It says this, okay? So that's
optional is how to unwrap
them. Super duper important.
Really gonna have master this.
I know that's new to you.
We're gonna talk about
these exclamation points up
here, that I mentioned before.
That made it so you didn't
have to initialize your thing,
those are optionals as well.
They're a little different
kind of optional because their
exclamation point instead of
question marks. Remember
this index one right here?
Okay, that was a question mark
one. These are exclamation
what one's they're slightly
different optionals but
they're still optional.
We'll talk about that later.
So the last thing I wanna
do here is just take this
cardNumber that I got, and
go look it up in an array of
emojis. So I'm just gonna
make a var, I'm gonna call it
emojiChoices. It's going to be
an Array of String emoji
strings basically.
And you can create arrays
right on a fly by doing open
square bracket and just put
in the things in the arrays.
So I'm gonna go put my emoji
in here, lets go back to our
emoji chooser, probably
its in frequently used.
Here we go,
there's the [INAUDIBLE] for
the pumpkin there,
I'll put a pumpkin here.
We'll put a ghost here,
put a ghost over here,
all right? Now we've got that,
so we're gonna look
the cardNumber it's gonna
be index 0, 1, 2, 3.
We're gonna look it up in
here. While we're here let's
go ahead and wire up that last
wayward button that's not in
the cardButtons array.
I'm gonna do that again from
up here, Ctrl + drag, down to
here to put all four buttons
in there. Go back to Automatic
here, and one other thing I'm
gonna do is note that this,
is that necessary?
No, because it's clear that
this is an array of strings.
So if I option click on this,
on emojiChoices right here,
it says array of strings.
So that again, the inferring.
We would never put that colon
array string there, never.
Totally unnecessary. Okay, so
now let's say just printing
the cardNumber out right here,
I'm going to call my flipCard.
FlipCard with emoji and
the emoji is gonna be
emojiChoices sub cardNumber,
okay, and it's on the sender.
Got it, let's run it.
Okay, here we go.
Pumpkin, ghost.
All these considered working.
Now, we might be very proud of
ourselves here because we got
this data-driven architecture.
It's really great
we can add more buttons now.
We can make 20 buttons and
all we gotta do is add
more things to this array.
But this is actually not
a very good architecture,
because this is very fragile,
okay. The number of emoji here
has to exactly match the
number of buttons in the UI,
and you have to put them
in there exactly twice.
And they're not
in random order,
so the cards are always gonna
be in the same place kinda
not a very good solution.
So we really need to
take another step and
have a real concentration
engine driving our app, it's
doing not only all of this,
but all this matching and
all that stuff. Now to do that
we're gonna use this design
paragraph dime I talked about
the very beginning model view
controller. So I'm gonna start
Wednesday's lecture with some
slides explaining how model
view controller works.
Then we're gonna apply model
view controller here, and
you're gonna see wow, that is
a way better way, to do this.
The much more flexible and
extensible easy to add cards
not gonna crash everything. So
I'll see you on Wednesday.
>> For
more, please visit
us at standford.edu.