[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> All right, well,
welcome to Stanford CS193P,
this is Fall of 2017,
I think this is lecture number
10. And we have two very
important topics today. The
first is multithreading and
the second is autolayout size
classes. So let's talk about
multithreading first.
Multithreading is all about,
for the purposes of this
lecture anyway, keeping long
running things off of the main
queue where the UI runs. And
that's because we want the UI
to be incredibly responsive.
When someone touches down,
we wanna immediately respond
to their touch and
not be having our app freeze.
It's just death to have your
app freeze, even for one
second is an eternity for your
app to just be not responding
at all. So multithreading
is a much bigger topic.
You can do a lot of other
stuff with multithreading. But
we're gonna focus on trying
to get long running things.
Things that might block off
onto other threads. Now,
the way that multithreading
works in iOS is using queues.
So I'm using queue
in the sense of like
you go to the movies and
you stand in line,
that's a queue, right? And
what's in the queues in iOS
multithreading is blocks of
code, almost always closures
that you put in this queue.
And so you got these queues,
there's multiple different
kinds of queues. And the
system then comes along and
it has threads. Threads
are threads of execution.
They're essentially
opportunities to run code.
And it can run them kind of
in parallel. I actually guess
if you had a multiprocessor,
or a multi-core processor,
it could actually run
things in parallel. But
even if you had a single-core,
single thread of execution
processor, the operating
system knows how to share
that time up in tiny little
increments between all
of these threads of execution.
So the OS comes along and
takes things off the queue,
the next person in line,
the next closure in line,
takes it off and it runs it.
So that's how we do queues.
And there's two kinds of
queues. We have serial queues,
which is iOS comes along,
takes something off the queue
and then as soon as that
thing has run to completion
then it goes back and
gets another one off that
queue, that's called a serial
queue. Then there's
also concurrent queues.
Where iOS comes along and it
grabs something off the queue
and it starts it running and
maybe it has another thread
that it can use and
it goes and
grabs another thing before the
other one is even finished,
and maybe another. And so
it might have two or three or
four or ten things running
off of the same queue all
at the same time. That's
called a concurrent queue.
So we're gonna talk about both
of those kinds of queues.
Cuz we're gonna use both
of those kinds of queues
to accomplish what we want.
And what we want is for
the UI to be unblocked.
And the UI runs on
a single serial queue,
called the main queue. And not
only does the UI run on this,
it's the only queue that can
have blocks of code put on it
that do UI things. So we keep
all of our UI stuff here.
That way we don't have to
worry about multithreaded UI,
where we got two different
threads of execution both
trying to draw into
the same space or whatever.
We never have to worry
about that in iOS because
all drawing, all UI activity
happens on this one queue.
And since it's a serial queue,
it all happens on a single
thread. So you never have to
worry about multithreaded UI
activity going on. Now, the
way they make queue works is
it mostly sits there waiting
for a touch event to happen.
And when the touch event
happens, it processes it,
figures out what code to run,
runs your code, and then goes
back into this quiet state,
waiting for another touch.
Well, when it's in the quiet
state, it could also pull
something off the main queue
and run it. So you can put
things onto the main queue,
blocks of code, and it will
run in the UI thread, the main
queue, the main thread. So
our goal is to get everything
else off the main queue.
And anything else is
gonna take a long time or
certainly is gonna
block waiting for
the network or
something like that,
we definitely want that off
the main queue. So where do we
put those things? Well,
we put those in global queues.
Now, there's actually you can
create your own queue to do
that, but we're gonna use one
of these four global queues.
And these are concurrent
queues that you can throw your
code on and the system will
just come along and run them.
And there's really no
restriction there about what
you can put in there. It's
just, it can't be UI code. But
you can do other stuff
all you want. So
let's talk about those queues.
How do you get the main queue?
How do you get a hold of it?
Well,
there is a struct or class
called DispatchQueue and it
has a static var called main,
that gives you the main queue.
So now you have
the main queue,
you're ready to go, and I'm
gonna talk to you soon about
how you put a block of code
into the queue, right?
Put it at the end of the line,
waiting to run.
The global queues
are a little more expressive.
There's not just one of them,
there's four different
kinds here that we're going to
talk about. And the four of
them are different based on
their quality of service.
That's what this QOS that
you see referenced here.
The quality of service tells
you what kind of thing,
what kind of activity the
blocks that you're gonna put
on there are doing. So let's
look at the four. The first
one is userInteractive. This
is a very rare one to use.
This means that the user is in
the middle of like dragging or
pinching or something and
you wanna do something
off the main queue
that has to happen so
fast that it can get back to
the main queue in the middle
of that drag. So we're talking
about highly interactive,
tiny little pieces of
work that you might wanna
throw off the main queue.
The reason this is unusual to
use is because it's really so
tiny and executes so quickly,
you could probably do
it on the main queue.
You're probably waiting for
it anyway on the main queue.
So user interactive
much more readily used.
The most common one to use is
the next one, userInitiated.
So now this is something that
might take a very long time or
it might take couple
of seconds, or
it maybe take a few
milliseconds, you don't know.
But the point about it is
the user has asked for
it right now.
They touched on a button.
They swiped somewhere and
they are asking for
something to happen. So
it was initiated by the user.
So they expect you to be
done as soon as possible. So
you are running this
in the background.
It's not happening
in the main thread,
but you're trying to do
it as soon as possible.
So this is a very
high priority queue.
iOS is going to be pulling
things off that queue and
running them in threads that
have very high priority
because the user's asked for
it right now.
The other two, background and
utility. So background things
are things the user hasn't
asked for right away but
they're kinda things that they
expect to be done fairly soon
or when you have time
kind of a thing.
And then utility ones
are even lower priority,
those are things that your app
wants to do as part of its
architecture. For example,
you have a big database and
maybe every week or so or
every certain amount of data
in the database, you wanna go
clean it up to remove though
out the database. So that's
just utility operations, so
that will run at very
low priority. So
you pick the global key you
want based on the quality
of service you want
that queue to receive.
So you have a queue now.
Either the main queue or one
of these background concurrent
queues with a certain
quality of service.
How do you put a block
of code onto that queue?
Put it in line to, to get
run at some point. Well,
you do it with one of these
two functions, async or sync.
Each of them take
one argument.
That argument is a block,
a closure. Takes no arguments,
return no arguments.
It returns no values. So
it's just as basic
a block as you can be.
And what it does is it puts
that block on the queue that
you're sending it to. Now, the
difference between async and
sync is that async puts
it on the queue and
returns immediately, and then
just goes on to the next line
of code you have. So now it's
in the queue and someone
eventually will go pull it
off the queue and run it but
you return immediately. Sync,
it puts it on the queue and
blocks. Waiting for someone
to take it off a queue and
run it and for it to complete.
So you would never do sync
on the main queue, right?
Cuz we never wanna block
the main queue. But
you might do sync on
a non-main queue, in fact,
you might do sync waiting for
the main queue
to finish something,
when you're on another queue.
But mostly we're using async
here cuz we don't really care.
async is short for
asynchronous.
We don't really
care when it runs,
we just want it to run
whenever it can run.
So that's it. So
that's really all there is to
multithreading, believe it or
not. It just leads to
a little bit of interesting
programming, which you're
gonna see here, and the things
you have to be careful with.
Now I'm not gonna talk about
this, but you can create your
own queues by just calling
DispatchQueue's initializer,
which has this label argument.
That label just shows up
in the debugger so you can
see which queue you're on.
The debugger's full
support for queues,
it'll show you what thread
everything is on. And
you can also do a lot of other
things with multithreading,
like protecting critical
sections in your code or
doing synchronous dispatch or
locking between things.
You can do all that stuff, I'm
not gonna talk about any of
that. I'm just gonna talk
about how we're gonna use that
main queue and those
background queues to keep
things off the main queue.
There's a whole other API to
this besides the DispatchQueue
API I'm gonna show you.
OperationQueue and Operation
are the two classes involved
there. And those would
be used if you're doing
some huge
mathematical equation
that has a lot of parallel
processing that you could do.
But a lot of the parallel
pieces depend on each other.
Because Operation allows
you to set up dependencies.
This little block code depends
on this one running first. But
I'm gonna start these all off
and just wait until the ones
that depend get finished.
Do you see what I'm saying?
All this dependency
management.
I'm not gonna talk about
any of that either.
But you get that by using the
object-oriented OperationQueue
and Operation APIs.
In this class we're just gonna
use DispatchQueue, okay.
DispatchQueue is part of what
we call grand central dispatch
because we're dispatching
these blocks of code onto
these queues. All right, so
where else are you gonna
encounter multithreading?
In addition to do your old
multithreading like you'll see
in the demo that I'm gonna do
today, you also might have
iOS API that takes blocks
as arguments. And when it
runs those blocks, like when
it finishes doing something or
it encounters an error, it
runs those blocks off the main
queue. And when you call that
API in iOS, you've gotta
really be careful that in
the blocks you give to iOS for
it to run when it's done,
don't have any UI in there.
Or if you do have UI, dispatch
it back to the main queue.
Because you can only do UI
stuff on the main queue. So
let's see what it looks
like to call an iOS API,
like this that takes a block.
So here is an iOS API called
URLSession. This is used for
fetching stuff from
URLs over the network.
We already saw in our demo on
Monday how we did that with
the data object. But that was
kind of a dumb thing, you
can't get any HTTP response
out of it. The errors,
you have to handle them kinda
funny. This is much more
sophisticated way to request
something on the network,
URLSession. As a very
simple API, you just create
a URLSession with a certain
configuration. The great thing
about URLSession is you can do
things like I want my timeout
to be five seconds, for
example. You can't do that
with the data thing,
it's got some built-in time.
Out here you can specify how
long you wanna wait before
you time out on the network or
whatever. So
you create your session
with some configuration,
usually the default
configuration.
Now all you need to do to
make it go fetch something
is create a URL and
call the function on the
session called dataTask with
URL. A dataTask with URL
creates what's called a data
task, a task to
go get some data.
And it starts out paused,
and then you're gonna say,
the very next line you almost
always say resume, and
that starts it going. Now
notice that dataTask with URL
function takes another
argument. I'm using trailing
closure notation to put it
outside the parentheses, but
it's just an argument
to dataTask there.
And that argument is a closure
that this URL thing is gonna
call, URLSession is gonna
call when it gets the data.
And you can see the closure
actually takes the data that
it gets as an argument, which
makes sense. Also response and
error which is HTTP response
and any error that might come
along in there, okay. So don't
worry too much about that.
But the bottom line is
you give it a closure.
Now the interesting thing
about this closure is it's
executed off the main queue.
So if you wanna do UI things
in there, which you might well
wanna do because you wanna do
something with the data you
got back, put it in the UI.
Can you do it in there? And
the answer is, no, you cannot,
because you cannot do UI
stuff off the main queue. But
what if I need to do UI stuff?
How do I do it?
Well, you're just going to
dispatch back to the main
queue in there.
DispatchQueue.main,
get the main queue, async, put
a closure on that queue, and
you do your UI stuff in there.
Now this all it looks almost
too good to be true it's so
easy, right? But there's
a little bit to think it about
here in terms of timing.
So I'm gonna walk you through
the timing of this code.
This is the exact same code
with just some labels on
the lines here. And
we're gonna go through this
step by step how this happens.
First, line a executes., of
course, we're starting to do
this URLSession request. Then
line b where we create this
dataTask, this line b
returns immediately.
It immediately creates
the dataTask and
grabs that closure and
hold on to it for
a second and starts the task
paused. So that's the second
line that executes. Then line
g. Because of the fact line b
returned immediately of course
line g executes next, and you
say, resume. That starts that
task fetching the URL over
the network in the background,
not in the main queue. So
the next line that
executes is line h.
Because resume just instantly
starts in the background, but
line h continues in
the foreground and
runs. What do you think the
next line that executes is?
Well, about five seconds or
five hours or five minutes or
whatever later,
line c will execute.
This happens when the data
comes back from the URL. So
now I'm doing something
with the data,
processing it, looking at it,
we're doing whatever I want.
Then line d executes because
I need to do some UI work.
So I dispatch a closure that
says do UI stuff here onto
the main queue, and it gets in
line to run on the main queue.
But the main queue
might be busy or
there might be other things on
the main queue ahead of this
closure. So this is not
gonna execute immediately.
Instead, line f will execute
immediately. So notice that
line e has still not run, but
line f has. What happens next?
Finally, line e runs whenever
the main queue is quiet and
ready to do it. And all the
other closures that were ahead
of it in line run.
Then e runs, okay.
So do you see how what's
happening with what runs when?
So the code makes it look like
the stuff will run top to
bottom, but it doesn't.
It runs a little out of order
there because it's happening
in a background thread.
All right, so the summary is
that it goes a b g h c d f e,
but this is only
the most likely order
because this is threads.
Things are happening
simultaneously.
It is possible, believe it or
not, that line e,
the UI stuff, could
actually run before line f.
It's possible that it
dispatches to the main queue,
and the main queue
immediately grabs it.
The main queue is a very
high priority queue.
Maybe it immediately
grabs it and
starts running it before f
has a chance to even run.
And if you have
a single processor,
that would definitely be
possible. So that's the most
important thing to understand
about multithreading is its
kind of asynchronous nature,
and
that will take some getting
used to, believe me.
All right, so the demo I'm
gonna do of multithreading is
we're gonna take Cassini and
we're gonna enhance its user
interface a little bit.
And then we are going to,
where is Cassini? Do I have
Cassini up here? Yeah, I do.
Let's just hide that.
Whoops, not mess with that.
Let's just go like this. All
right, so here's Cassini. So
right now, Cassini just
displays this image,
this demo URL that we made
right here. So I'm going to
comment that out and
instead, I'm going to build
some UI to use my
ImageViewController as
a generic image viewing MVC.
I'm gonna add another MVC
similar to like we did with
the themes, when we chose the
themes. This MVC is gonna pick
which Cassini image I
wanna look at. I have some
Cassini images which I'll show
you the URLs for in a second,
that were taken related to the
Cassini probe to Saturn. And I
want to look at them onscreen.
So let's start by doing our UI
first. So let's just go all
UI here. So here's our UI,
our existing, kinda
generic image-viewing MVC.
And I'm gonna go down here and
create a new view controller.
Just drag it out here. Course,
view controllers all need to
have their own subclass. So
I will create a new subclass.
I'm going to call this my
CassiniViewController.
I'm going to make sure I
put it in the right place,
not at the project level.
All right,
so here it is.
I'm going to select it and
make sure I go to my identity
inspector over here and
change its identity to
be ImageViewController.
I'm going to have it
be the place I enter.
Let's actually go ahead and
build our whole UI. In fact,
let's make this both on iPad
and on iPhone. So
I'm going to take this guy and
I'm going to embed it in
a navigation controller.
I'm going to take this view
controller right here.
Embed it, Embed in
Navigation Controller.
And then I'm going to take
this whole thing, right here,
and make this be the master
of a split view. And
this is going to be my detail.
So let's zoom way out here and
grab a Split View Controller.
This out, as usual, our
Split View Controller brings
out the document outline and
has all this extra stuff here.
Whoops, we don't need any of
this extra stuff, so
let's delete that. Then we'll
zoom back in. Grab our
Split View Controller here.
Let's make the Split View
Controller be where we enter.
All right, let's make this be
our master. Let's grab this
and bring it down here and
make it be our detail. So
we've set this up. Hopefully,
you're used to doing this.
You're doing this
in your homework,
pretty straightforward. So now
we got a UI that will pretty
much work on both devices.
Both Split View on iPad and
then also it will
work on an iPhone.
So we need to prepare this
imagery controller right here.
And we need to have or sorry,
prepare this one. Then we need
some UI in this one to
choose the Cassini image.
So I'm gonna do the same kind
of silly thing I did before,
but not quite as silly as it
was the last time. Which is to
put three buttons in here. So
I have three Cassini images,
so I'm gonna have
three buttons.
Let's go ahead and
make them big font here.
40 points seems to be my
favorite size font. And
the three images I have
a image of Cassini itself, and
then I have an image of Earth,
and
then I have an image
of Saturn. Okay.
Oops, not Satrun, Saturn. Okay
cuz Cassini is a probe going
from Earth to Saturn.
And I'll do a little review.
We're gonna to embed this in
the stack view. I'm gonna make
it fill, I'm going to make
them be the same size buttons.
I'm gonna set the standard
spacing here.
Let's go ahead and put this in
the middle. I'll go ahead and
control+drag to make this
always be centered vertically
and horizontally. You can see
it's a little off-center from
there. So I'm gonna go over
to my document outline,
which is where we resolve
all auto layout issues,
with this button up here.
I'll click on that.
Here's all my problems.
It's just this one problem.
This thing's not positioned
where it should be.
I'm gonna click the little
triangle and fix it,
either by updating my frames
or updating my constraints.
In this case,
my constraints are right but
the frame is wrong, so
I will fix the misplacement.
It moved it,
no more auto layout issues.
We have a great UI there. It's
a quick review of auto layout.
I'm gonna try and review auto
layout as much as I can,
because there's a lot to
auto layout. All right, so
now we're going to set up some
segues from our master here to
our detail and I'm gonna do
this one a little differently.
Before, remember before,
I had one kind of segue,
one identifier and then I
looked back the button title.
And I said,
that's kinda bad code,
because what if those button
titles were in French?
And then it's like so
I'm gonna do this a little bit
different way. The real way
I would do this probably
is I'd use a table view.
Which is this extensible table
list of things. And then I
could both add more things and
also, I could easily find out
which one was picked by its
index into the role of table,
but I haven't taught
you table view yet. So
that's why we're using these
button solutions. All right,
so I'm going to create a segue
from Cassini down to here.
It's going to show detail
because we're in a split view.
Same thing with Earth.
Show detail. And
with Saturn, show detail.
But instead of having them
all have the same identifier,
I'm gonna give them each
a different identifier,
which is which image to open.
That way if I change
the language here, they'll all
still open the proper image.
So here, this one is
the Cassini one, right? So
I'm gonna have its identifier
just be Cassini. And then this
one is the Earth one, so we'll
have its identifier be Earth.
And this one is Saturn, so
we'll have this be Saturn.
So I am just setting the
identifier of these segues, so
I know which one to show.
A little bit better,
more kind of accurate way to
do that. But now, of course,
we need to prepare our generic
Image View Controller,
set its model, its public
model which is that image URL.
So let's go look at our
CassiniViewController code
right here. We'll clean out
all the junk. These are view
controller lifecycle methods,
hopefully you recognize.
We'll get rid of those. Let's
uncomment out our navigation
stuff here and
do our prepare for
segue. So how am I gonna
prepare for the segue?
Well, I need to look at the
identifier to see which image
I'm gonna show. So let's say,
if we can let identifier =
the segue's identifier,
in other words, it's not nil.
Then I'm just gonna see
if I can get a URL.
Here's my demo URLs.
I showed you this before,
but let's show it again. See I
have this dictionary here,
this NASA dictionary that
has strings as the keys and
URLs as the values.
And so for each one, Cassini,
I have a little URL.
For Earth, I have a URL.
For Saturn, I have a URL.
So I'm just gonna look up in
this dictionary to see if I
can find the name of
the identifier. And if I can,
then I know I have an image
to show. So let's do that.
I'm just going to say,
oops, not identifer,
identifier, fier,
fier. Fier! Okay.
So here I'm going to say, if I
can let the URL equal my demo
URLs.NASA sub the identifier.
Okay so
if that comes back true, I was
able to get an image and so
now I can do a segue to a
image showing view controller,
which is my Image View
Controller I built in the last
lecture. So I'm gonna
say if can let imageVC =
segue.destination as? An
ImageViewController then I can
set the ImageViewController's
public API.
Let's remind ourselves
what that is.
Here's the ImageVewController
that we worked on last time.
Its public API was this.
ImageURL sets the URL you
want, so we're gonna set that.
Public API imageURL equal to
the URL. I'm also going to
set the title of this thing.
And here I am going to
use the Button title.
Sender as UI button.
If it's in fact a button,
get its current title. Now
is this bad? This was not so
bad because here I'm setting
the title of that destination
image view controller to be
the same as the title of the
button. Well then presumably
the button is localized to the
local language, so I'm putting
button title now in the title.
It's not so bad. This one's
not bad because we're talking
about UI elements that have
been localized in both cases
right there. So that's all we
really need to do to prepare,
let's go ahead and run and
see if this works.
We'll run this on the iPhone
here, and hopefully when we
click on one of those
buttons it will go out and
hopefully the network will
work today and it will fetch
those images. Now those
images are quite large, so
it might take a while to do.
Right, so here we go. It comes
up showing the detail, right,
we didn't put the little split
view trick in there to make
it collapse the thing.
So let's go back here, here we
go, here's our UI, Cassini,
Earth and Saturn. Let's try
Cassini. It didn't work. So
why did this not work?
Let's go
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Sorry I missed,
did something in the story
board let's go back and look.
I love it when the students
are on top of it.
So what did I do here?
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> This one right here? Yeah,
that's interesting, yeah.
So when I set the identity of
this right here,
I accidentally set it to image
view controller, it should be
a Cassini view controller.
Where is my Cassini view
controller, there it is.
Good catch right there. Could,
probably could have looked
at that for five minutes.
All right, so yeah. So I
accidentally, after I made it,
I picked the wrong one,
so here we go. And
that's a common thing
to do actually,
to either forget to set this
guy's identity or to set it to
something wrong. So why did
that make this not work?
Well, because this prepare
right here was not getting
called because that was not
a CassiniViewController but
now it is, so let's try it
again. Okay so here we go,
go back, let's try. Cassini.
Hopefully, it doesn't seem to
be working. No! It crashed.
Okay now, it crashes.
We hate crashes but hopefully
we're getting comfortable with
looking at why crashes happen
especially looking here at our
back trace. So let's look and
see what happened here.
Why did this crash? Well we're
crashing in our image view
controller right, there's
our image view controller.
Where we set the image. This
is where we set the image to
something, we size to fit, and
then we adjust the content
area of our scrollView, right?
But no, something's nil,
here. Well we know the
imageView can't be nil because
we set it right off the bat
to be in imageView,
so it must be that
this scrollView is nil.
Let's see. Self, here's
my self down here. Yeah,
sure enough self
scrollView is nil. Well,
let's go back up the trace
here and see what's happening.
This is happening because
someone set our public API,
that makes sense. And we're
setting the image to nil to
clear out any old image. And
then where was that call from?
Prepare for segue, yeah. Okay
any time you have a crash,
something's nil, and
you were in your prepare for
segue you're gonna go, oops.
I have an outlet and
it was not set because
that's what happens right?
Prepare happens before your
outlets are set and so
when we look up here, this
is an outlet. Scroll view is
an outlet, right here, and
it's not yet been set because
we're preparing.
So what's a good fix for this?
How about we just optional
chain. That makes it so
that this line will be ignored
if scroll view is nil, and
that's okay because all that's
happening here is that we're
trying to set the image
to new anyway. But
since we're just preparing,
it's going to start out nil so
it won't hurt anything
to do that. So
here's what we want to do
that. Simple fix to it. So
I obviously left that in
there again so we could do
this again because I know you
guys run into this crash and
you want to make sure you're
comfortable with diagnosing
it. So lets go back,
lets try again now. Cassini,
it doesn't seem like it works.
Wait, it did work. So
what happened there. So let's
see, is this my Cassini image?
Yeah, look at that.
There's the Cassini probe,
right there.
So let's try another one.
Let's go try Earth. No, it
didn't work. Well, let's go to
landscape. How come it's not
going to landscape here?
Forget it, let's go back. But
the back button doesn't work,
what's going on here? So you
see how my UI was stuck there.
I was trying to do back,
I was trying to rotate.
My UI was just blank,
not doing anything.
My UI is completely and
utterly stuck.
No matter where I touch. Even
if I rotate, nothing happened.
Well this is a horrendous
experience for
your user. This is the kind
of experience that will cause
your user to go and
delete app.
Because you cannot have your
UI freezing up like that, so
that's why we have
multi-threaded,
that's such an important piece
of the kind of app development
we do in IOS. So let's go
in here and see if we can
fix this with multithreading.
So how are we gonna do that?
We're gonna go back to my
image view controller,
this is the thing that's
hanging. In fact,
it's this line of code right
here that is hanging my app,
right? This is why I'm trying
to go out on the Internet,
get that Cassini or
Earth URL and it's big and
even on our fast Stanford
network it's taking a long
time to come over. So the line
of code is not returning.
So I cannot have this line of
code executing on the main
queue, which is where all my
code pretty much runs unless I
specifically put it
somewhere else or
unless I use some iOS API
that puts it somewhere else.
All right, so how do I get
this off the main queue? Well,
I just use this dispatch
Queue, main queue and
then use the async func to
put a closure onto the queue.
So this is gonna
take this code and
run it,
run it on a different queue.
Now, I don't wanna run this
on the main queue though,
I wanna run it on one of those
quality of service queues. So
how do I do that? I'm gonna go
global queue, and the argument
I want to it is quality of
service. Not q, q, o,s,
quality of service. And the
one I want is user initiated.
Because the user did just ask
me to do something, right? So
I'm going to put it on the
queue that gives me that good
quality of service that I want
from something initiated. And
what am I gonna do here?
Well, I'm just gonna do this,
right here. And
I'm just gonna put this
right there, go do that. And
this will immediately stop my
app from blocking like that,
because it's going to be doing
this network fetch on some
other queue. Now see,
it's complaining here,
cuz of course this is now
inside of a closure. So
I have to do self like that.
Now every time I do this,
what did I tell you to do?
Check to see if you have
a memory cycle, right?
And we don't have one here
because self does not have
a pointer to this closure.
There's no pointer inside self
that points to this closure,
so there's no cycle. However,
with multithreading, when you
do the self., you have to
think of another thing.
Which is, what happens if the
code before this line that has
this elf takes a long
time to execute? So
long that this view controller
doesn't even wanna be
here anymore? Can't you
imagine that easily happening?
Someone clicks to go get
an image, the image is taking
five minutes to come along,
they're like, forget it,
and they click somewhere else.
Go back, or something.
Now that view controller, that
requested that image? It's
meaningless. It has no value.
It should not be in the heap.
But if being kept in the heap
by this closure. Do you see?
Because I have a reference
to self in this closure,
this view controller,
my image view controller,
is being kept in the heap for
as long as that
image request is outstanding.
So, this is a case where
I want to do weak self here,
okay.
Not having anything to do
with memory cycles but
having to do with the fact
that I don't want self held
in the heap by this closure
if this closure takes so
long to run, that the user
doesn't care about self
anymore, then I don't care
about self anymore. So,
by definition I want it to
be weak. Any question about
that? So, that's just another
thing you need to do when you
type that self dot because,
so after I warned you about
this inside enclosure, if
you're doing multi threaded,
think about whether things
wanna be weak here or
whether you really wanna hold
things in the heap. All right,
so this is good, but
this is not gonna work either.
While this will stop
my UI from blocking,
it will probably screw up
my UI. Probably cause my UI
to draw all funny, or get
completely wedged. And why is
that? Because of this line of
code. Here I'm setting image,
which is this thing right
here. And if you look at
the setting of image,
it sets a UIImageView's image,
that's a UI think. It sized to
fit that UIImageView thing,
that's a UI thing.
It sets a scrollView's content
area to a certain size,
that's a UI thing.
I'm doing all kinds of Ui
stuff when I set this image.
So, I can't do this on the
queue that I put this code on.
This global queue is not a UI
queue, I can't do it there.
So, what I have
to do here is to
DispatchQueue.main.async this
code
back to the main queue. Now,
it's gonna get in line and
run on the main queue when
the main queue is quiet.
See that, so
this is cool this railway,
they can see this
code is awesome,
this is like the easiest
multi threading code you can
possibly write. But you do
understand that this stuff is
happening perhaps a minute
after this line of code right?
Okay because we're putting
on another queue it might be
blocking on the network. Now,
that leads us to another one
last thing we need to do here
which is what happens if we
request this thing?
And not through our UI, but
some UI someone calls this
image URL and sets it to
something else. They set
this image URL to something
else, and we go to fetch that
image. What happens when this
image comes back? We don't
care about it. We're off on,
we're working on a new image.
So,
when this comes back,
we need to check to make sure
that our current image URL is
the URL we requested here.
And we can easily do that by
just saying URL equals our
image URL.
This is week so we got. So,
here I'm just checking after
this maybe takes five minutes
I'm checking to see if that
URL is the one I asked for.
Because if it's not I don't
care about it anymore in this
class. Do you see? So, this is
what I'm talking about where
when you're doing
multithreading you have to
think about
the timing of things,
things might take a while and
they come back
things might be different than
they were when you left. So
this is a great little piece
of code to really understand,
cuz it covers a lot of ground,
from the weak self, and
checking this, and dispatching
back to the main queue,
getting one of these
background queues.
Really make sure
you understand
this little piece of code
right here. All right, so
let's run and see if this has
indeed fixed our nice UI to be
responsive. Here we go let's
try it again. Let's go Earth.
And can we go back? Woo hoo,
look at that! I can go back,
and now I want Cassini. Here
comes Cassini and Earth is
still probably being requested
and here comes Earth. Ugh, and
it didn't do anything. That's
great, it just dropped it on
the ground because we don't
care about Earth anymore.
I changed my mind. So here's
Cassini, that's great, right?
I can rotate, we can go back.
Let's pick Earth.
Now while I'm waiting for
Earth, I could rotate. My UI
is completely responsive.
I could go back and
choose something else.
Let's go ahead and
let Earth arrive, so Earth
is a big image. There it is.
Earth seems to be a picture
of people, somehow, maybe
we'll zoom out a little bit,
it's the Earth. So this is
a picture of Earth made up of
a lot of little people looking
up and saying hello to Cassini
and that's what this one is.
And, similarly they
have a similar
kind of construction
with Saturn here. But
you can see that our UI's
just dramatically improved by
putting that stuff on
the other thread there.
All right? But
our UI's still not that great
because watch.
What's happening right now?
The user has no idea. They
wanted the Earth Image and
it's not here. They're like, I
guess there's no Earth image,
you know? They click back.
We need to give them some
feedback that we are off
getting their Earth thing.
We need something to let them
know, yeah, I'm working on it.
Even though you can hit back,
you can stay here and you can
see your Earth image. So,
how are we gonna do that?
We're gonna do that with
a little spinner.
Called an activity indicator.
It's just a little
spinning view. And
this is a good one to show
you for another reason too.
Which is that it can sometimes
get a little crowded trying to
build the UI you want,
especially when things go all
the way to the edges
like this scroll view. So
this spinner, you can search
for it, activity, it's called
UI Activity Indicator View.
See it right here?
I'm gonna drag this out and
try to put in the centre of
my image view right here. Now,
this did a very bad thing,
okay. You can't tell, it looks
like it's just fine, but
it's bad. But
the way you can find out and
see the badness is going
to your document outline.
If we go to document outline
and try to find this indicator
right here, you see it?
Look what happened to it,
it was made a sub view
of the scroll view.
Okay any time you drag
a view in it gets made
a sub view of the thing you
drop it on. And we don't want
that, cuz we don't want this
scroll view scrolling thing to
be in the content area of the
scroll view. That's what a sub
view of a scroll view means
interface builder the content
area. We want it to kinda
sit on top and luckily it's
super easy to pull it out on
top in the document outline.
It's very difficult to pull
it out on top over here.
But here we can
just lift it up and
put it, actually that
puts it behind, and
here we can put it in front.
So, now it is not
a sub view of the scroll view,
it is in front of it,
sitting in front of it. Now we
also want it to be centered,
but not centered in
the scroll view,
we want to be centered in the
super view of the whole MVC.
So how can we do that?
I mean, my God it's gonna be
impossible, control drag.
How do I find the edge without
hitting the scroll view?
It constantly wants
the scroll view right there.
Well, we can control
drag in here.
Look at that, then control
drag up to here and
say we wanted to be standard,
horizontally and
vertically in the safe are.
We got a little displacement
there, no problem,
we'll fix that, update frames.
We put it in the middle. So
control dragging inside
the document outline is a very
good way to get at things that
are hard to C. Now, another
thing we wanna do is this is
very tiny little control.
I wanna a bigger one. It turns
out there's a bigger one,
this large white one. Although
I don't want it white cuz this
is gonna be white on white.
So I'm gonna pick a different
color, let's make it blue,
let's say. So I've got this
nice spinner right here. This
spinner by the way, you can
either start it out animating
or turn it on when you want,
which we're going to do.
Also you can have the spinner
automatically hide itself
when it's not spinning.
And then when it is spinning,
it shows itself so we want
that too. So let's go turn
this thing on and off, let's
go turn the spinner on and
off. Where do we want to turn,
first of all,
we need an outlet
to it of course,
we're gonna talk to it so,
let's put that out
there right here.
I'm just gonna Ctrl+drag,
normal outlet.
I'll call it my spinner,
that's what I'd like to call
my activity indicator there.
So here it is, and we just
need to turn this thing on and
turn it off. Well, the place
we need to turn it on is right
before we do this really
long expensive operation.
So I'm gonna write say here,
spinner.startAnimating.
That's how you turn it on. And
where do I wanna turn it off?
Well, you might think I wanna
turn it off in here. But
again, thinking
about multithreaded,
really I don't wanna do that,
because what if another image
request goes out, and
I'm waiting on it?
I still want the spinner
to keep spinning. Really,
I want this spinner to stop
spinning whenever the image
actually gets set. So any time
we actually set our image to
something inside here. Then I
want to stop my animating. So,
I'm just gonna say spinner and
I'm also going to be careful
here of people preparing,
getting me. stopAnimating, so
this is a reliable place to
stop animating. So once I put
an image here, I clearly don't
want that thing spinning
anymore. All right, so let's
see what that looks like.
So we didn't request anything,
so there's no spinner. Let's
go here to ask for Cassini,
it's spinning you see, and
as soon as Cassini arrives,
it stops spinning.
If we zoom down you'll
see that it is not there.
It's hard to see in this
background but it's not there.
And let's just quickly make
sure this is all working on
iPad. Let's go up here,
iPad and run it on there.
It's kind of especially cute
on iPad when you click this,
if you don't have a spinner
there, it's just really
unclear what the heck is going
on here. All right, Earth.
And while this is spinning,
we could change our minds and
go to Cassini.
Okay, and now it starts.
Now this is a new
ViewController and
it starts again, and
now we have Cassini.
Now one thing that's kind of
a bummer here is when we're on
the iPhone, remember we took
the title of the button.
And we put it on the top,
and there was a title.
But notice on the iPad,
there's no title here, where
the detail is? The detail
has no title on the top,
it's just kind of up, to
the upper left and of course,
it's kinda ugly actually. So
I'd really love to put a title
over here just like I have a
title right here. So how can I
do that? Well, it actually
turns out to be quite easy to
do that. I'm just going to
take my detail right here, and
I'm gonna embed it In
a NavigationController.
So I'm putting this in
a NavigationController,
not because I'm doing any
navigation down there.
The navigation I'm doing is
all controlled by this one,
but just because I want
the thing to have a title.
Now let's see, does that work?
Okay, let's run it and
see if that works. All right,
here we go,
Cassini, uh-oh, no.
It's not working, I'm not even
getting my spinner anymore,
that broke it. It put a title
up here, but it broke it.
Now why did that break our
code? Well, let's look at our
code and we'll see pretty
obviously why it broke it.
In our prepare for segue,
what did we do? We look at
the segue's destination
which is the detail.
And we check to see if it's
an ImageViewController, but
it's not
an ImageViewController,
now is it? Right, if we go
back to our story board, this
destination of these segues
is a NavigationController.
Not an ImageController, it's
a NavigationController. So
that line of code is failing,
right? This line of code,
this imageVC = destination
as ImageViewController,
not true anymore. Because our
ImageView, our destination is
a NavigationController. So we
can check that though. Let's
just go set our destination
here equal to the segue's
But I'm gonna say, if I can
let navcon = destination as
destination.
a UINavigationController. Then
I'm gonna let my destination =
navcon.visibleViewController,
which might be nil.
In which case, then I'll go
ahead and return the navcon.
And then here I'm gonna use
destination, and so this
is going to basically unwrap
the NavigationController and
get its visible
ViewController. This would
still work if there weren't
a NavigationController there.
Because then this line of
code would not happen,
and we'd just be saying
segue destination here.
So let's see if that works.
Here we go, Cassini, look,
we got the title,
we got the spinner,
woo-hoo, it's working!
Okay, Earth, quit to title,
spinning. All right, now this
is very common to wanna do to
put your detail in
a NavigationController.
And you have to do this
little indirection.
A lot of times what 'll do is
create a little extension to
UIViewController. I call, it's
a little var I call content,
which is the content of the
UIViewController, which for
most ViewControllers is just
itself. But if it's a navcon,
if we have to do this
little doohickey here,
then it will return its
visible ViewController.
So I'm gonna say if
I can let myself
be a NavigationController.
Then I'm going to return
my visibleViewController,
or if that's nil then I'll
return myself. And if I'm not
a navcon then I'll just return
myself. So content just is
the viewController itself, or
if it's a NavigationController
it's the contents of
the NavigationController.
You could also do this
with a TabBarController.
You can have an else, if it's
a TabBarController, then show
me the ViewController that is
the current tab, you could do
the same thing. So here I
don't need to do this anymore,
I can just say
segue.destination.contents,
right? And this is going
to give me what I want.
See how this cleans up this
code really nicely? So you'll
often wanna have an extension
like this when you have, when
your detail might be wrapped
in the NavigationController.
Cassini, works perfectly
there, all right yes?
>> [INAUDIBLE]
URL to a URL [INAUDIBLE]
URL.
>> Yeah, right here.
>> So where is the URL then is
it the [INAUDIBLE]
say if like the URL-
>> Yeah.
>> But how does that would
define [INAUDIBLE]
>> Okay so
by letting url = imageURL
we're creating a local
variable called url.
It's a local variable local
to this function, and
its value is the imageURL. Now
this closure right here and
this closure for that matter.
Closures always capture
the local variables around
them when they need them. And
since we're referencing url
inside these closures, it got
captured. So it hold on to
this, even for five minutes or
however long this takes.
It holds it in the heap
as long as this closure lives,
it holds on to it. But
it still stays set to
what it was before.
If in the meantime while
five minutes is happening,
this changes,
that doesn't change this,
because this is a local copy,
right? It's a local variable,
it's a copy of this thing.
>> But
how does that have a value
just because you say,
isn't it like a root instance.
Well, okay.
So, image URL, I don't know
whether URL is a value type or
a reference type,
it wouldn't matter here. But
let's say it's a value type.
If it's a value type then
we know this copied it. And
then when we say equals,
equals,
it means that URL would have
to implement equatable,
which it, certainly it does.
If this is a reference type,
then it's just grabbing
a pointer to that thing and
then here we're comparing
the pointers. So
either way, it's going to make
sure that if it's changed,
we know. Good question,
though. All right,
let's get back to our slides
here. Let's talk about
our other very important topic
today, which is more about
Autolayouts. I'm gonna do
a quick review about a layout,
just to make sure you
understand what you
understand.
Here is kind of some of
the things we've seen
with Autolayout so
far. We know to use the dashed
blue lines to try to tell
Xcode what we mean, right?
Put things in the centre, put
things on their edges by the
dashed blue lines. And then we
can do we reset to suggested
constraints, remember,
in lower right corner which
will try to make constraints
that make the blue lines make
sense, but we know it doesn't
really work more and
about 50% of the time. So
then, we learned how to
control drag to the edges or
the other views and
then set equal,
set the widths or aspect ratio
or the edges to be the same or
whatever. We know that we can
go to the size inspector and
look at all the constraints
that are constraining
a certain view just by
clicking on the view.
Looking in the size. In fact
we can even edit simple things
about the constraints right
there in the size inspector,
like constant values or
things like that.
We also, if we can get at it
in the interface where we can
click on a constraint and
open up the inspector and
inspect detailed information
about the constraint.
We also know about the pin
menu in the lower right that
let's you set some
constraints like, but
this hooking it to the edges
and things like that.
There's also an arrange button
right there by the way,
I didn't show you but
is similar,
lets you line up front edges
and things like that. And we
also learned that the document
outline is the awesome
place to go to really
look our constraints and
details, cuz it list every
constraint as a line item,
it's also where the special
place do you click to resolve
problem with your constraints
is. So the document outline
is just fundamental to using
Autolayout. So we know all
that stuff. Understand that
mastering Autolayout
takes the experience.
You don't just have someone
tell you all these things or
even show them to you and
it's like, now I'm on MAC I
can do auto layer now.
You have to have laid out
a lot of things and understood
the conflicts that arise and
what the limitation are and
all that. It's really a
fantastic system auto layout,
very powerful, but it does
take some experience to master
or so,
don't get too frustrated.
Luckily, you're definitely
gonna have more assignments
where you're gonna
have to do Autolayout,
and your final project you
definitely wanna do Autolayout
so you would get some of that
experience. It is possible to
do all this Autolayout stuff
from code and now it's not we
have controlled dragging a lot
not in interface, but actually
light code to do all of this.
And I'm not gonna teach any of
that unfortunately If you want
to learn a little bit about
that, you can start by going
to UI views documentation and
search for "anchor" and
"autolayout".
Those are the two main sets
of API, there's a ton of
API there and then there's
also just documentation. How
to do the autolayout system.
You can read through all of
that if you really want to get
to be a master of autolayout
from code. It's not
necessarily that difficult,
but to really truly understand
requires understanding auto
layout and how it's working to
do it from code. All right,
having said all that auto
layout is sometimes just
not enough. The autolayout
you know so far is just not
enough. Sometime when
you rotate your device,
your geometry changes so
dramatically there's just
no way to control drag
to make things happen.
For example, in concentration.
We know that
concentration with a lot
of buttons looks great but
in portrait. All the buttons
look square but then when you
go to landscape the buttons
are all smashed down.
There's barely enough room to
say flips 27 at the bottom and
it just really gets smashed.
It really would be great if
when I switched to landscape
if I had 20 buttons, let's
say, it went 5 across and
4 down.
Maybe it moves that flips then
off to the side. That will be
a much better landscape but
no amount of control dragging
to the edges is gonna make
that happen. Right,
it just can't be done.
Just, you can not
constrain the view enough
to make them relay themselves
out like that on rotation. So
what's the solution to that?
Size classes. Now,
Apple made their, I think,
a great decision that when you
rotate to landscape versus
portrait, instead of their
reporting to you, here's your
new dimensions, figure it out,
they just simplified it down
to two and only two values for
your horizontal and vertical
size. You are either compact
or regular size in width and
height, and
that's it. They are going to
report that to you and there's
a whole system for letting you
know when that changes and
then you build your UI so
it looks good when it's
compact vertically.
It looks good when it's
compact horizontally.
It looks good when
it's regular vertical.
And it looks good when
it's regular. Vertical and
horizontal, right?
So that simplifies the system
dramatically, and you're gonna
see that it works in the vast
majority of situations. So
let's talk about this
whole size class thing and
how it works. First of all,
you have to understand
what the devices,
what size classes
the devices are in. For
example, iPhones are compact
in width and regular in height
when they're in portrait.
When you rotate an iPhone,
not an iPhone+, a regular
iPhone, when you rotate it,
now it is considered
compact in both directions,
which a little counter
intuitive. You would think,
well, now it's regular in
width, but no, it's considered
compact in width and it's
amazing how often that turns
out to be exactly what
you want, all right?
And you'll see that to be
the case. Now iPhone Pluses
are different. iPhone Pluses
are still compact in width and
regular in height in portrait,
but
when you turn them
to landscape,
now they are regular in width
and compact in height. So
iPhone pluses are different
than regular iPhones in that
way. iPads are regular
width and regular height.
Portrait or landscape doesn't
matter they're always regular
in both which you can imagine
they're big, iPads are huge.
However, notice that an MVC
that is in the master
of the split view is
compact in width,
even though it's on an iPad,
it's still compact in width
and regular in height. So it's
not just the device you're on
that says what environment
your MVC is in,
it might be the MVC situation
that it's in. So, and
that's why we don't look at
things like am I on an iPad?
Because then I'd have to say,
am I an iPad and
am I in split view?
We just ask, am I compact or
am I regular in my width and
height? And then we react to
that. So here are all the
devices in a little grid for
that and
let me show you what an app.
So here's an app like
a calculator similar to our
concentration calculator
has a lot of buttons and
maybe it will look better
with five across and
four down in the two cases
where the compact tight, see?
Whether there's compact width
or regular width, it still
looks better to have only four
high on your compact height.
And when it's regular height,
it always look better
to have five high.
Maybe even more
would be better, but
it always looks better
to have five than four.
So this is what we're going to
do in the demo, we're going to
do concentration the same kind
of way as this calculator.
Okay, now we have, we know
the size class we're in.
We always know that as our
MVC is doing its business.
What can we do based on
that knowledge? Well,
one thing we can do is vary
a lot of view properties like
the fonts on a UI label for
example, a background color
even whether a view is hidden
or not, even whether a view is
even in the view hierarchy can
be controlled by size class.
So if you're a compact height,
maybe you have a view that's
just completely hidden
in compact height.
Maybe it only appears
in regular height.
That's perfectly controllable
using your size class. But
more importantly and the most
powerful thing you can do
is have your constraints
be tied to your size class.
Okay because remember what
puts anything on screen in any
place? Well it's just
the constraints, right.
The constraints are what
constrains a view
to being in a certain space in
autolayout. Well if you can
control those constraints
using the size class.
Then you can make those views
move around to different spots
depending on your size class.
Like go five by four instead
of going four by five. Or
moving the little flip
label off to the side. So
constraints, being able to
control constraints with your
size class is really the power
of this size class stuff.
Now the cool thing,
by the way,
is InterfaceBuilder
has support for
doing all of this graphically.
So you don't even have
to do this in your code.
You can do it all graphically.
Now it is possible to find out
what your size
class is in code.
For example, if you wanna know
your horizontalSizeClass,
whether you're compact or
regular horizontally,
you just call this method.
You access this object
that's in your view controller
called trait collection.
It's a collection of
all your traits and
one of your traits is your
horizontal size class.
You can get back into enum.
It's either compact or
regular. I suppose it could be
unspecified but it wouldn't
actually be that while you
were running. Again, it's rare
to do this. We're gonna do
this all in InterfaceBuilder,
and so that's something
that's all visual, so
I'm gonna have to show
you to it in a demo.
This is one place where a demo
is worth 1 billion words.
To try and explain it without
a demo, be almost impossible.
And so I'm not gonna get back
to the slide so let me just
summarize here that we do
have a Friday section.
Please come to it on Friday
it's about Instruments which
is a performance
analysis tool.
And especially when you're
doing the multithreaded stuff.
You wanna know what's taking
a long time to execute, right?
So that you can put it
off in another thread.
Sometimes it's obvious when
it's a network blocking thing,
but other times you have stuff
that you're computing that
actually turns out to be
taking a lot time. So using
instruments to find out what
that is will save you a lot of
putting stuff on other threads
that doesn't need to be. Only
the stuff that needs to be.
And you all know Donald Knuth,
right?
Don't prematurely optimize.
Don't obfuscate your code
to make it run faster,
unless you're sure that's
actually what's running slow.
Well, you need instruments
to know that. Next week,
we'll dive into
some more topics,
Table View,
Collection View, Drag and
Drop, stuff like that.
All right,
so, let's go and
do our concentration.
So here is concentration. It's
exactly where we left off,
except for two changes. One
change I made is I turned off
all the view controller life
cycle logging, because if we
need the console, I want to be
clear, so you can see things.
Cuz I don't think we'll
need the console, but, hey,
you never know. Tech and
I added more buttons,
this used to have 12, so I
just added a couple more rows
of buttons here,
so there's 20.
So, let's see, what it looks
like now with those two
very minor changes, I haven't
changed any of the code or
anything like that.
All right, so here we go, so
lets do sports, working like
a charm, okay. Looks good. And
of course, that's not so good.
I added those more buttons,
but it caused the flip count.
The flip count is at the
bottom here it flips eight,
it got pushed completely off.
And look at the buttons,
they're barely big enough
to hold the emoji anymore.
Also there are ugly buttons,
they are really flat.
A lot of blank
space on the size,
this UI looks terrible.
So we're gonna fix this UI and
by doing two things. One,
we're gonna do five across and
four down only in landscape
because back here,
we like these nice square
buttons here. We wouldn't want
to switch to five across and
four here and then we start
looking bad here. So that's
one thing we're gonna do.
And the other thing is we're
gonna move this Flips thing.
In landscape to be over to the
side here, over on the side.
This will help the buttons be
even more square and use
the space more efficiently on
this side. So those are the
two things we're gonna do,
all right?
So how do we do this?
How are we gonna do this?
Well, we need a strategy for
doing all this.
And my strategy is going, and
remember, we didn't really,
haven't looked at this a lot.
But remember, you can look at
all your devices down here,
including whether they're
in landscape or portrait.
So here I'm looking at this
thing in landscape. And here's
where my problem is, it's
four across and five down.
I want it to be five
across and four down. So
my strategy is gonna be,
I'm actually gonna add four
buttons here. And then when
I'm in landscape, I'm gonna
hide these four buttons.
And when I'm back in portrait,
I'll hide the new buttons
I added. So I'm actually
gonna have 24 buttons but 4 of
them will be hidden in one or
the other. See that strategy?
So this is only,
this is one strategy for doing
it. It's a simple strategy.
So we're gonna start with
a simple strategy, all right?
Now to do that, so you can see
what I'm doing a little more.
So lets do that.
See this little constraint
right here? This is
the constraint that's holding
this to this right edge.
I'm going to delete this
constraint just temporarily
here so it makes some space
for me to work. So I'm just
gonna delete that and so it's
not pinned to that edge so
it moved over. Now I'm going
to add these four buttons.
Remember, I said I'm gonna put
four buttons on the side. So
I'm just gonna copy and paste
one of the existing buttons.
In fact,
I'll paste it four times. And
I'm gonna select all of them.
I'm gonna go down here to our
embed, and make a stack view
out of it. I'm going to
inspect that stack view.
Give it some spacing.
I don't want it to be leaning.
I want it to be filled.
All right, and I want it
to be filled equally.
I want all the buttons to be
the same height, all right?
make sure that we wire it up
to our card buttons array.
Let's go ahead and
So let's do that.
Control drag, there's one and
there's two and
there is three,
let me up a little bit,
sorry and there is four,
okay. So we've got inner card
buttons, now we want these
four to join the party. Okay I
want them to join here so
I'm going to select,
both of these stack views, and
I'm going to embed them in a
stack view. We'll go ahead and
put some spacing in there, so
we can see a little better.
Here, I don't want them
aligned on the bottom,
I want them to fill, however,
I do not one fill equally.
why I don't want fill equally?
That would make this one stack
Do you see
view, the same width as this
whole big stack view. So
that wouldn't be really wide
and those will be small but
I do want this stack
view to be the same width
as all of these. So
how am I gonna do that. Well,
I'm going to control
drag from this stack view
to one of these buttons over
here. And say please make them
equal widths and that's
perfectly legal to do that,
to have one view and just say
please always be constrained.
These are all constraints,
constrain yourself
to be the same width as this
one over here. Okay and
that's gonna ensure that even
as this get wider that that
row will always be same width
as all of the other rows in
here. So I've created this new
stack view right here. This
stack view has no constraints,
right? If we look over here,
there are no constraints on it
cuz I just created it. And so
I really want it to zoom out
to be constrained to the edges
here. What I really want is
I want it to constrain to
the top up here and
to all the safe areas on
the other three edges. So
I'm gonna try the pin again.
Remember this pin over here?
So I'm just gonna try putting
an eight point pin and
it's gonna do that
to nearest neighbor.
I'm hoping it's gonna pick
the right nearest neighbor,
all in all sides.
Let's see what it does. Well,
maybe that worked.
It's close. Let's look.
It picked the top space to
superview. I don't want that.
I wanted this safe area there.
Then trailing the safe area.
Yeah, leaving the safe area
bottom to the flip count.
Whoo! This thing did
pretty well, but
of course this superview
thing is wrong.
So let's remind ourselves
how we fix that.
We go to our document outline.
Let's find it,
it's right here.
Stack, stack view top to the
top of the view plus 8. And
remember, we don't want that
to the superview. We want it
here to the safe area. So now
we've got this set back up.
Now the problem here is
we have all 24 buttons
showing right here. See all
24 buttons? That's no good.
So I don't want these four
buttons showing in landscape.
So how do I do that? I'm just
gonna pick this stack view,
and I'm gonna make it
disappear in landscape, but
not in landscape.
It's gonna disappear when I'm
in a compact vertical size
class. Which is only iPhones
in landscape, it turns out.
So how do we do that? Well,
if we inspect this stack view,
I'm just going to
the normal attributes and
spectrum over here. Look at
all these little plus signs.
You see these plus signs here?
Plus, plus, plus, and
you go down here,
plus. These are all attributes
of the selected thing,
that can be varied
by size class.
So it's not just whether it's
hidden or not, which is what I
want right here. You see it's
hidden right here. That's got
a plus. But also things like
the background color. Or for
the stack view, even the
alignment, the distribution,
you can have this change when
you go to a different class
size. It's pretty darn cool.
So we're gonna do a simple one
which is hidden. And the way
you vary is you just press
the plus. And when the press
the plus, it says,
you wanna vary hidden based
on the size class. Well,
what size class would you like
to vary for? Well, in my case,
it's compact height.
I don't care about the width.
So I'm going to set Width to
Any. Any width is fine. But
height, compact, yes. I want a
compact variation. This gamut,
by the way, you vary based
on the color capabilities
of the device you're on. We're
not doing that. It's really
not a layout thing per se, but
it still can be varied. And so
I'm gonna hit Add Variation.
And watch what happens right
over here when I hit
Add Variation. See, we've got
a new hidden. We have this
hidden and another hidden.
This one is HC, which stands
for height compact. And
right now it's not hidden
in height compact, but
if I turn this on, woo hoo!
See, it hid that entire
stack view, cuz I'm in compact
height right now. And if I go
back over here to my portrait
mode, you can see that it's
not hidden. It's still there.
See four across, five down.
It's still there. But now I
want this one to be hidden. So
l am gonna click on this stack
view, select the whole stack
view here, if l can. No, it's
hard to, well, let me zoom in
a little. Selecting
this whole stack view.
And here l'm gonna do the same
thing. l'm in portrait mode
right here, l'm gonna
add another variance.
This is a variance for any
width and regular height. And
in that case,
this one is hidden. So voila,
look at that, four wide,
five high, and over here,
five wide and four high.
Let's see if this works.
It's not quite gonna work,
but it's gonna be close.
All right, so here we go.
Let's go to Sports.
Look at that, five wide and
four high. Excellent,
let's pick some things here
like this. Now let's rotate.
Whoop, looking good, let's
pick something down here.
Rotate, oops, what happened to
those? See that? They're gone.
I picked two that were in
this row that got hidden. So
it makes perfect sense when we
went over they got hidden. So
how am I gonna fix that? Well,
this is kinda of a clunky UI,
because we're using these
outlet collection to gather
all these cards.
But one trick I could
do really easily is go
back to my code here for
the concentration
View Controller. And
just everywhere that I'm
doing cardButtons, looking at
the cardButtons, instead of
looking at all 24 cardButtons,
I'm only gonna look at the 20
that are visible at any given
time. So I'm gonna create a
little private var here called
visibleCardButtons. It's gonna
be an array of UIButtons also.
In fact, it's even going to be
implicitly unwrapped, and it's
gonna be computed. I'm just
gonna return my cardButtons,
if they've been set.
And I'm gonna filter them by
the buttons superview
being visible.
Because if the button's
superview is visible,
then it's visible, right?
So I'm gonna say
!$0.superview!.isHidden.
So these are the visible
hard buttons.
This is a little
fragile to do this, but
we know that all our buttons
are in stacked views, so
this is okay. Probably could
find a much better way
to calculate whether it's
actually on screen or not.
But anyway, and I'm just gonna
now replace everywhere that I
use cardButtons with
visibleCardButtons, so here,
and here, and here. I'm just
finding and replacing here.
Paste. So now that's going
to fix this problem, I hope.
Let's find out.
All right, it's worked again.
All right, let's go down here.
These are the ones in danger.
Let's try, woo hoo, no. How
could this not have worked?
That code was infallible.
Well, here's the problem here,
when I switch back and
forth, all those views get
relaid out, right,
layout of views happens.
But nothing ever causes them
to get re, out, reset out for
my model. So they've all
still got the buttons from
what they were before. So what
I need to do is every time I
relay out my
subviews like this I
need to update my view from
a model. Well, guess who comes
to the rescue here? It's view
controller life cycle, right?
viewDidLayoutSubviews in
vieweDidLayoutSubviews.
I'm just gonna do update
my view from my model.
We got Sports.
Now we have these done, oops,
it's the other way around, so
we go this way. Looks work
we're good. Now we can get
these offending ones and
they're there. Now they're in
random places, because we're
using this outlay collection,
but at least it's working.
Now what about the problem
of where's our face,
our flips number?
There's no flips there.
Gotta push down below
the tab bar down there.
How are we gonna fix that?
All right,
we're gonna fix that in a
different way just to show you
there are other ways to do
these things. What we're gonna
do is we're gonna move
this Flips things up here.
Now you could imagine,
let's create another one and
then do Is Hidden on
the two of them. And yeah,
we could that, but that kind
of starts getting ridiculous,
cuz now I'm gonna have to have
another outlet to that other
one. What a pain.
I really just wanna move this.
Well, what makes this be here?
What makes it be here
is these constraints on it,
the fact that it's aligned to
the center, that it's
hooked to the bottom,
that the top space is
hooked to that stack view.
That's what makes this be
here. So if I could change
those constraints, I could
make it be over here. And
as long as those constraints
only happen in height compact,
woo hoo, it'll switch, right?
So that's what we're gonna do.
Now how do we do that?
Okay, we don't have the little
pluses by all our constraints,
how the heck do we do that?
Well,
we do that with this
magical button right here.
You see this Vary for Traits?
We don't even need this.
In fact, we could probably,
oops, we can probably use,
don't even need document
outline here. So
you can really see what's
going on here, right? So here
I'm working, and if I click
this Vary for Traits button
right here, it'll say, okay,
you're going to go into a mode
where all the constraints
that you're doing are only
applicable to the thing you're
in. So let's do it, ready?
Vary for Traits, it says do
you want to vary by width or
height or both? Here is the
height that matters to me and,
whoa, look at that bar.
It got dark blue. So
that dark blue is warning you,
whoa, dude, you are editing
constraint only in compact
height. And in fact,
it's only showing me compact
height devices right here. So
that blue warning
is a warning,
make sure you pay attention to
that. All right, so how do I
get Flips to move? Well, I
gotta take all the things that
are constraining
Flips to be here and
get rid of them. So I'm
just gonna go over here and
delete all of these
constraints. And if I go over
to my document outline here
and I look at my constraints,
you'll see that they didn't
actually get deleted.
See how they're grayed out.
Why didn't they get deleted?
Cuz I only deleted them for
this size class.
They still exist in the other
size class. So that's why
they're only grayed out here
when I'm looking in this one.
But it is good,
it freed up Flips.
You see, Flips is no longer
tied to anything and
also, by the way, of course,
this little constraint right
here, if I can click on it,
This little I-beam right here,
that's gotta go as well.
Because that is no longer
going to be constrained
to the edge, it's gonna
be constrained to the edge of
this Flips thing, all right?
This is gonna be constrained
here. So let's go ahead and
use Ctrl+drag to put this
thing centered vertically.
Let's also use Ctrl+drag to
hook it up to the trailing
space, although I don't
want it to be 11.667.
We'll do our standard
8 right there.
And then let's go ahead and
have this guy.
We'll use the pin menu for
him, and
have his right edge there
be to the nearest neighbor,
which happens to be Flips.
And then also,
we'll do pin again to hook
this bottom of this right here
to also be 8 from its nearest
neighbor which is the bottom.
Now all these constraints that
I just put in are all only for
height compact. But now I'm
done varying with that.
Now if I go back, you'll see,
look, it had no effect
over here. Flips is
still at the bottom and
over here it's at the sides.
So let's go ahead and run.
let's go make sure that it's
still working in the old way.
So first of all,
So here's Flips, working fine,
it's staying there. Now let's
go over and do it here.
This one, whoa, it's kind of
jumping around a little bit.
Why is that happening?
Well, because the 14, 15, 11,
those are different width so
that label is kind of
changing it to width.
Wouldn't it be a lot cooler
if, instead of doing Flips:14,
if I made the Flips
be a multi-line.
Remember the multi-lines
stuff we did before? And
instead of having Flips:0,
what if I did Flips return 0?
This makes more space and
also this 0 could be 100 and
it still wouldn't be
jiggling around in width.
Well, that's actually
really cool.
Unfortunately, I just
edited that and it's also
going to be true over here and
I don't want it over here. So
how am I gonna have something
that is gonna be different
in these two size classes
that's driven by the code?
Cuz it's the code that decides
what these things are.
Well, we can do that in code
as well, let's just jump over
here real quick.
Here is where we do this flip,
I'm just gonna say
traitCollection.verticalSizeC-
lass = .compact.
Then I'm gonna do one thing or
if it's regular then I'll do
this old thing. And the thing
I'm gonna do in compact is I'm
going to have carriage return
instead of colon.
And I was gonna run this and
then we would see that this
doesn't quite work, but we're
time constrained, I can hear
1,000 people outside the door.
So I'm gonna tell
you one other thing,
which is that if we had gone
there it wouldn't work, okay.
When we switch back and forth,
it would not switch. That's
because when switched back and
forth, we need to get
notified that our
trait collection changed. And
there's a view controller life
cycle method which I didn't
mention last time because
you didn't know about traits.
But now I'm gonna tell you,
it's called
traitCollectionDidChange. And
this gets called every time
your trait collection changes,
right, every time your
size class changes. So
here I'm just gonna update
my flip count label.
Because my flip count label,
if you look at its code,
it depends on the trait
collection. So of course every
time it changes I need
to update it, right?
So here we go. We'll go
Sports again, and see,
this is working
nicely over here.
It's not jumping around any
more because it's underneath.
And now let's go look here.
And we got our colon. Woo,
look at that. And we'll
go back here. That is it.
We finished before the crowds
came in and trampled us. And
I will see you on Monday.
Your homework, remember,
is due on Monday,
before lecture on Monday.
you'll have a new homework
going out on Monday, or
And hopefully,
maybe next Wednesday.
Let's see what happens
over the weekend.
>> For more,
please visit us
at stanford.edu.