[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Well,
welcome to lecture number
11 of Stanford CS193P,
this is fall of 2017 quarter.
And today, we have two huge
topics to talk about. The
first one is drag and drop,
which is a way of sharing
information between apps,
especially important
with iOS 11.
Because on the iPad, there's
quite a great multitasking
ability to have two apps on
screen at the same time. And
nice, nice to be able to drag
and drop between them. And
then we're gonna talk about
TableView and CollectionView,
definitely a big step up in
complexity of what I've been
teaching you so far, but I
think you're ready for it. So
drag and drop,
what is drag and drop about?
It's very simple, you
literally just press and hold,
which we call a long press on
iOS, on something that could
be dragged and start moving.
And when you do, the operating
system, iOS, is going to let
you drag that thing around.
And then you can drag it over
things that might receive it
and let go, and it drops them
in there, simple as that.
You've seen drag and drop on
the desktop all the time,
so now we have it
with multitasking.
What's really incredible about
the way they did drag and drop
is that while you're dragging
and dropping, and you're
dragging thing around, you
can use your other finger and
still completely use your UI
however you want. So drag and
drop does not interfere with
the operation of your iPad at
all. Which is quite amazing
cuz you can be in the middle
of a drag and say, well,
actually I need to navigate to
this other part of my app to
drop that and it'll work. And
it's kind of the value
of having multi-touch
multi-fingers. You can also be
in the middle of a drag and
say, hm, I wanna drag
these other things too.
And just tap on other things,
it'll add it to the drag.
So they really use the
multi-fingers or multi-touch
to great effect with drag and
drop. So how do we implement
drag and drop? What do we
do in our code if we wanna
participate in drag and drop?
The real gateway to making
this work is through these
things called interactions. So
drag and a drop is a view
thing, it's a UI view thing.
In the same way that gestures
are kind of a UI view thing,
you can sort of
think of drag and
drop as just another really
powerful gesture if you want.
But you don't enable drag and
drop by adding a gesture
recognizer, instead you do it
by adding a dropInteraction or
a dragInteraction.
But it looks
almost exactly the same as
adding a gesture recognizer.
UI view just has this method
called addInteraction,
and it takes either a drag or
a drop interaction
that you create. And
the drag or drop interaction
is created really easily.
It just has one argument
to its initializer,
which is a delegate. And
then, what's gonna happen is,
when a drag or a drop or both,
you can have a view be both,
starts the Delegator's gonna
start receiving some messages.
And you have to respond
to those messages,
that are sent to it if you
wanna participate, and
those messages are really
easy to respond to.
So let's take a look at that,
let's first look at being
a drag person, a view that has
something in you that you
want to drag into other apps.
If you want to register that
dragInteraction on your view,
then when the user does
that long press and
move, which looks like a drag,
you know,
for drag with drag and drop,
you're gonna get this message,
DragInteraction,
itemsForBeginning. And
this is really simple. You're
just gonna return an array of
the items you are willing to
have dragged from your view.
So what does a drag item look
like? Well a drag item really
only has one important thing,
which is,
what's called an itemProvider.
Now an itemProvider is just
something that can provide the
data that's gonna be dragged.
And you might ask, well how
come the drag item just
doesn't have the data?
The thing you want to drag.
And the reason is it
might be expensive for
you to create that data.
Maybe it's an image or
something you have to load
up for some reason or
do something else. So drag and
drop is incredibly completely
asynchronous.
You start that drag and
it's really lightweight and
it's dragging around and
almost nothing is happening
as this happens. But then,
when the drop happens, then
if you're an item provider,
you have to actually,
give the data out.
Even if that takes
a certain amount of time.
So that's why we've
added itemProviders.
Now luckily, there's a lot
of built-in itemProviders.
Classes that already exist in
iOS that are itemPoviders like
NSAttributedString. So you can
drag, pick up pieces of text
and they'll drag around with
their fonts and everything.
There's also NSString, which
is text without the fonts.
UIImage of course.
You can pick up and
drag UIImages around. NSURL,
that's a really nice one.
You go onto a web page,
you pickup a URL and drop it.
Maybe it's a reference to
an article or a URL for
an image like we're gonna have
in the demo that we're gonna
build, etc. UIColor, MapItem,
a contact from the address
book, lot of things you
can pickup and move.
These are all itemProviders.
So to create a drag item you
just create them with
NSItemProvider and
provide the object that is
going to provide the data.
Now of course you could write
your own item Provider that
provides your own kind of
data, but you know, most of
time your just gonna use these
nice pre-made ones. There's
one other thing in a dragItem,
which is for local drags.
Drag and drop can work within
an app and between apps.
It only works between apps on
iPad, because you can only
get two apps on screen at
the same time in iPad.
But on the iPhone and iPad,
you can do it inside the app.
And if you're drag and drop
inside the app, then you can
kind of short circuit all this
itemProvider business and
just use this little var,
localObject in your dragItem
and that'll just mean you're
dragging this local object.
And that local object can be
anything, it's of type any, so
you can put anything you want
there and drag, use drag and
drop to drag anything in your
app from one place to another.
So that's getting
a drag started,
you just got to provide this
items for beginning array and
that's it. If in the middle of
a drag, someone uses another
finger to pick on something
else that they want to drag.
Then you're gonna get this
message itemsForAddingTo,
this session. And all you
have to do there, provide
an array of drag items.
Often that array of dragItems
would just be one dragItem or
it could be empty in
neither items for
beginning or items for
adding two if you return
an empty array here,
it means I don't have anything
to drag. Thank for asking. So
it's really easy to just not
participate if you don't want
to. So that makes the drag
start and that's it.
That's all you have to do
to be a drag source. Now,
what about accepting a drop.
So now you're on the other
side of the drop.
Someone dropped it on you.
Well, this is kind of
a multi-step process.
The first one is you're gonna
get this message sent to you.
Again, this is if
you add interaction,
UIDropInteraction to UIView.
You're gonna get this message
when a drag starts heading
your way, which is canHandle.
Drop interaction canHandle.
And you're gonna get this
session thing and it returns
a Bool which is whether you
can handle a drag like that.
So what is a drag like that
mean? Well you have to look at
this session that it passed
you there, that UIDragSession.
And you usually aren't gonna
call one method in there which
is canLoadObjects(ofClass.
You're gonna ask that session.
Well can you provide
an NSString?
If so, I'm in. Can you
provide a UIImage? I'm in.
Or if not, can't provide the
things you're interested in,
then you just return false
from this canHandle session
and it won't bother you
anymore during this drag. So
that's to get it started.
Now if you were to say yes, I
can load objects of that type.
Then you're going to start
getting this sessionDidUpdate
message sent to you. Again,
this is gonna pass that
session to you again.
And the session might
have changed a little,
cuz maybe the finger has
moved a little bit and so
maybe that changes your
decision about whether you
want to accept this drop.
But what you return from
sessionDidUpdate is
a UIDropProposal.
Now this is your proposal
as drop receiver. For
what you're willing to do with
this Drop, and there's really
only three things you can do.
You can have a Drop Proposal
which is cancel, which is to
say, I propose cancelling this
Drop if you want to try and
Drop it right where you
are now because I don't accept
it there. And the Drag,
we'll have a little icon that
appears on it, which is like,
you know, a red circle with
a line through it, saying,
no, you can't drop here.
Then there's Copy and Move.
Copy and move is a proposal
that says, yes, I propose,
I will receive this drop and
I will either copy the item or
move it. Now, copy is most
often which you're going to do
here.
Move would only make sense for
a drag within your app.
Because you're gonna be moving
it from wherever it was,
it won't be there anymore and
now it's gonna be
at the new place,
that can only happen
within your own app.
So move is only inside your
own app if you're actually
moving the thing, rather than,
copying and making a copy
of it. If someone's
dragging from outside,
you'll always gonna be copying
it. So that's it, you just
have to say, cancel, move, or
copy each time you are asked
about this. By the way, you
can look at the session and
find out where the finger
is in your view,
by asking the session
the location in the view.
So some places in your view
maybe looks up to drop,
in some place not, all right.
So that's super simple, and
so this proposal is kind of
a contract to accept the drop,
if it were to be dropped at
this location. And so
if you do accept it, then,
like if you don't say, dot
cancel there in your proposal,
then you'll get performDrop
when the finger Is released,
and the drop happens.
Now, perform drop,
you're gonna get that
session back again. Here,
you're almost always only
gonna call one method,
which is loadObjects ofClass.
So we saw all ready
the can load object class.
Now, we have the actual
load objects of class.
Now this is an awesome
little method.
This is one of the ways they
made drop, drag and drop, so
simple, the implement without,
with all that asynchrony, but
without a lot of difficulty
in your app, which is,
you just call load objects
of class. You specify
the class you're willing to
receive from the drop, so
like attributed string or
a color, or
a URL or image, whatever.
Presumably, the things you
said you would accept earlier
on, and it will go and
get that data asynchronously
on another thread. And
when it gets all from
the drag source,
it will call the closure
you provide with the first
armament being an array of
those things. So in this case,
I'm saying, load objects of
class in a distributed string,
so it's gonna call that
closure with the The Strings
to being an array of and as
attribute to string. Now, it's
actually an array of something
that implements the provider
protocol, so you're gonna
have to cast it with AS.
But this is essentially array
of those MS attributes and
strengths. Similarly,
you could do UIImage.self and
all of that. By the way that
NSAttributeString.self that's
the way
you specify the class in
it's attributed string,
if you wanna pass it as
an argument to the function.
We haven't seen that before
but that's all you do.
And, this closure is sent
to you and implemented
on the main queue, so you can
feel free to do IU stuff here.
You don't have to dispatch the
main queue if you don't want
to, and so it's really,
really super convenient,
to do whatever you want.
And you know,
you accept this drop, and it
might take a little while for
this information to appear,
but when it does,
you just have the code right
here automatically executed.
And you can do load
objects of class,
multiple different
classes in the same drop.
We're going to do that
in the demo for example.
We're only going to accept
drags that are images, but
that also have a URL for the
image, so we're looking for
two pieces of data in the same
drag, a URL and an image. And
we will be doing loadObjects
of class both of URL and
of the UI image,
perfectly legal. They'll,
they'll both be
happening asynchronously,
you don't know which
one's gonna finish first.
But you've gotta
write your code so
it doesn't matter.
But that's all you need to do,
and that's all you usually
do in performDrop, or
you're not really
gonna do much else,
it's just get that data to
start coming your way. So
I did drag and drop, super
duper simple to implement.
So we're gonna do a little
demo of it, so you can see it
in action, and I'm going to do
this on the actual iPad and
I think we figured a way to
get this on the screen that
will make everybody
happy here.
So the way I'm gonna do this,
is I'm going to use Quick
Time, so here's Quick Time,
it's just showing my ipad.
Let's hide others here, so
this is just showing my iPad,
so this app that we're gonna
build, we're actually gonna
build this over the course of
this week, and next.
It's called, Emoji Art. And
it lets you build a nice
little artistic painting,
if you wanna think of it that,
by using emoji.
So we love emoji in this
class, as you know,
this is Emoji 101. And so
how does this thing work?
Well, it uses multitasking,
both to drag and drop
the emoji. And also to go find
an image to be the background.
So let's see how that works.
So if you haven't seen
the multitasking UI in iPad,
you just swipe up from
the bottom. And when you do,
you can see all of your apps
if you swipe all the way up,
you can also pick
your favorite apps.
I just picked the one on
the right there, which is this
one. And if you want, you can
swipe up to bring this up. And
you can take a second app,
I'm gonna do Safari here.
And you can pick it up and
drag it, and actually have it
be side by side. So now I've
got both of these apps,
running at the same time,
side by side.
I got Google up on the right.
So I'm going to use Safari
here to to find a nice
background image for the
picture. So I'm gonna draw.
Let's draw something nice.
How about countryside cartoon,
I think of some pretty
cool images, yeah,
here's some images.
We'll view these images. So
here they are. So
I can kind of scroll through
on the net here trying to
find some image that I like,
I don't really like
much of these,
let's see. What do we got?
Yeah, maybe something like,
how about this one right here.
So I'm just gonna press and
hold, look what happens
when I press and hold,
you see I'm picking this up,
I can drag and drop.
And when I drag over into my
view over here, and drop it.
Woo hoo, that image appeared
in my app. And we're gonna do
that part of it today. That's
the demo we're gonna do today.
Now, this app also has on
the left here a table view
with the documents.
So I'm currently working on
Untitled document here. I can
add new documents by pressing
plus. Or go back to my
document here. I can also drag
these emojis from the top,
down. So I'm gonna pick
the bee here. I'm pressing and
holding. Look, I'm doing drag
and drop again. Notice, I can
use it to re-position the bee
in this thing at the top.
This thing at the top is
called a collection view. And
that's, so we're gonna
see both table view and
collection view in this app
that we're gonna build. And
I can also pick up the bee and
drag him down here into my
emoji art document. I could
get a couple of bees here.
I can select the bees and
make them smaller, let's say,
have a bunch of bees there.
Maybe someone rode their bike
out here. Smaller, maybe
an apple fell off this tree.
We can zoom in, for example,
really close here to maybe
make this apple really small.
It didn't fall far from
this tree right here.
We can zoom back out. So
basically, we can build
ourselves a nice image here
with our emoji art editor.
So that's what we're going to
build. We can also do things
like add more emoji. So
we click on here to add more
emoji, I can bring up emoji,
and I don't know, put some
farm animals here, or I can't
even, right here isn't a farm
animal, right? Add those, and
just put these into my row, so
I've got it right there and
I could pull this out. So
that's what we're gonna build.
Pretty cool app,
lots of pieces to do it.
We're gonna start out by
building this thing where we
can pick up an image and drop
it in here, right? So we pick
up this, and we can even
replace the image we have or
whatever. So, how are we going
to do this? All right, so
we're gonna create a brand new
Xcode project. Single view app
as always, we're going to
call it EmojiArt, all right.
Where we put all of our
apps of course, here it is.
I'm going to go and
clean up a little bit here and
move these things out of
the way as I want to do,
put that in
supporting files so
that we can see exactly
the files we are working on.
I'm gonna delete this generic
controller, that was given to
me and just move that into the
trash. Here's my storyboard
right here, of course we need
our own custom controller and
our own custom view actually
for that emoji view.
So I'm gonna create those
right off the bat, okay so?
I'm gonna create my, a new
file, which is going to be
a custom UIViewController,
UIViewController and
I'm gonna call it my
EmojiArtViewController.
This is gonna be the main
view controller of that
There it is.
thing that does all the stuff
that we're just talking about
right there. I'll go to my
story board and make sure that
I remember to set this
thing's identity to that, so
we'll go to the identity
inspector and
make this be an EmojiArtView
controller. Right there.
I'm gonna do all this stuff on
iPad since this is gonna be
an iPad only app, right?
It relies on drag and drop, so
it's an iPad only app.
Actually,
let's see if we can make
it landscape. I think it'll
fit a little better as
we're doing stuff here. So
here is our nice UI. Now we
need a custom UI view to,
except all those drag and
drops and then view and
all that stuff. So let's go
and do that. New file again,
and this one is gonna be a
custom subclass of UIView and
we'll call it EmojiArtView.
Here's our EmojiArtView and
we're gonna, right off the
bat, go and implement this.
I'm gonna start by just
doing the background image.
So I'm gonna have a var
here called background,
groundImage, which is
gonna be a UIImage.
And whenever you set it,
I'm going to make sure to
call set needs display.
Because I need to call my
dra_rect I'm gonna use this
background image to draw
my background in dra_rect.
So here's dra_rect, I'm just
gonna say backgroundImage,
please draw yourself
in my bounds. So
world's simplest draw,
drawing an UI view here.
And that's all its
gonna do for now.
Eventually, its gonna do more.
Its gonna draw all those
little emojis that I'm gonna
drop in here of course. But
for now, its just a background
image only. Let's go ahead and
build our UI in our
story board here.
I'm gonna actually do
something, you'll see why I'm
gonna do this later. But I'm
gonna create just a generic UI
view here to be my drop zone,
okay, UIview.
Where is it? Here we go.
This is generic UIV.
I'm not even going to create a
sub class, submit or anything.
All it's gonna do this fuse
only have one responsibility
which is to accept
the drops of the image and
set that image. And add
EmojiArtView, I just created.
So we go up here with this
guy. All the way to the edges,
actually let's just use
the pin to do that.
We'll go over here and say,
hook up to all the edges.
My favorite constraint things,
I'll just put all
zero's over here and
say add constraints. Let's
double check our constraints,
we always want to do that and
make sure they did the right
thing. Bloop, it looks good
right and put all the edges up
to the safe area looking good.
And so that we can see
this view clearly,
I'm gonna give it a little bit
of background color, not much,
instead of white I'll make it
like a really light grey here,
yeah like that. Can you all.
Yeah. You can see. Its just
light touch of light grey,
so we can identify this is
our drop zone view. And
then I'm gonna put in
EmojiArtView inside of it.
So let's go do that, we know
how to add a custom view,
is add another generic view.
But this one,
we're gonna go to our
identity inspector here, and
change to be an EmojiArtView.
This is how we make this be
an EmojiArtView, as opposed to
being just a generic UIView.
This one, also I'm going to
use the my favorite little
constraint maker. Bleep. Smash
it. So it's now jammed up
retaliated. So now we've
added the emoji view and
let's go ahead and put outlets
to both of those things.
So I'm gonna go over here and
create outlets both
to the drop zone and to that
emoji view. So it's kinda hard
to get act those two things
as the right on top of each
other. So again we're gonna
use the document outline.
The document online is
fantastic for getting app
things that are hard to get
at. There is another way,
I'll remind you
Control-Shift and click,
Control-Shift click
brings up a menu and
you can pick the things that
are underneath the mouse even
if they're inside each other,
right? But I tend to prefer to
use the document outline cuz
it's just clearer when I'm
doing here. So this top level
view is our drop zone, so
I'm gonna create a outlet to
that by just dragging from
the document outline
into our view controller,
actually before I do that,
let's go over here and
clean out this code in here.
So
that it's a clearer, oops
not to clean up that much.
How about this much?
So I usually do that, but I
didn't do it here. But so this
is my EmojiArtView controller,
right here you recognize that?
So let's go ahead and create
the drop, drop zone outlet.
I'll call this drop zone and
again this is just a generic
UI view that I'm going to
register that drop interaction
with. And then let's also
create an outlet to our
EmojiArtView, that's just so
I can set its background
image when I want to.
So, EmojiArtView. Now,
you might ask the question,
why didn't I just make
the EmojiArtView be
the drop zone?
Why do I have this separate,
drop zone thing? Well, that's
because two reasons. One.
I need to keep track of at
the controller level what's
dropped in. Cuz I'm actually
going to remember the URL of
what's dropped in. And
all of the keeping track of
the document, which we're
going to do next week,
has to happen at
the controller level.
We don't want the view doing
that. And secondly, sometimes
I'm gonna eventually put this
view in a scroll view and it
might be small. It might not
be filling the space anymore.
And so I want the dropZone
to be as big as possible,
so that when I drop stuff in,
boom, it always works. So
that's why I made
those separate.
But it's not really
that big of a deal,
not really that much of
a requirement to do it.
I didn't want you to think
there's some special reason,
like you have to make your
dropZone be a separate,
generic view. You don't
have to. All right, so
right off the bat, you might
dropZone is set up for me.
I am going to add
that interaction.
So I'm just gonna
say dropZone, Oops!
dropZone.addInteraction(UIDro-
pInteraction),
because I am trying to
receive the drop of that
thing and all that we
have to do provide here
is a delegate. And, so
I'm gonna make the delegate be
myself. So the controller is
the one who's going to handle
the drop delegate methods and
of course, we're gonna have to
say that we are a
UIDropInteractionDelegate,
for that to work. All right,
now all the methods in here
they're Objective-C methods,
they all happen to be
optional. So I implement this
but of course,
I don't actually do anything,
I'm kinda surprised they
didn't make at least it can
handle be required but they've
decided not to do that.
So that's all we need to do,
to make this drop work though
is do canHandle and then
when the session updates and
the perform drop we have to do
those three things to make it
work. So let's do that. We got
the canHandle, that's this
one, dropInteraction canHandle
session. So inside here,
I only want drags that have
an image and also a URL for
that image. So I'm gonna say,
return only through if the
session.canLoadObjects(ofCl-
ass- NSURL.
Notice that NSURL, this
whole thing is Objective-C
compatible, and in Swift it's
called URL, it is a struct.
And in Objective-C it's NSURL,
it's a class. Now, those two
things are automatically
bridged to each other, so
you can always add one to
the other. But here you just,
this is one of the few places
in Objective-C where you have
to use an Objective-C thing.
That's because we're
specifying the class here,
the actual class all right.
We're not taking
instance where Swift can kind
of figure out what you want.
It's the actual class NSURL or
talking about here.
And we want this session,
to say it canLoadObjects
ofClass: UIImage.
So I want both the URL and
the image. Or I'm not
interested in the drag.
So if you drag an attributed
string on me right now.
I don't care. In fact,
I'm only interested
if you can drag something
that's both an image and
the URL for the image.
Maybe that URL.
Maybe you would drag something
that's an image and a URL and
it's not a URL of that image
but we're gonna find that out.
You're gonna see here
pretty quick. All right,
so that's saying that we can
handle a drag like that.
So this is basically just
saying, if you're not
that kind of drag then don't
even talk to me. So if it
is that kind of drag then
it's going to talk to us and
it's going to do this
update session. Okay,
this one right here. Session
did update, you see that? And
all we need to do hear is
return our drop proposal. And
so I'm happy to have something
like that dropped anywhere
inside of my little
grey dropZone.
So I'm gonna return,
oops. No there,
I think right there,
return UIDropProposal and
the contractor
here is operation,
operation. Ad the operation
I'm gonna return is .copy
because this is always being
dragged from outside my app so
it's always gonna
be coping in. And
there's no reason I
would ever cancel it.
I'm always happy to accept
a new image. All right, now if
someone let's go of the finger
I'm gonna get perform drop. So
here's the perform drop one.
And in here like I said all
I'm gonna do is go
tell the drag and
drop system, let that guy
know I want the data and
give it to, and then call this
closure. So I'm going to have
sessions.loadobjectsofclass
and
I want the NSURL ones. And
here is the completion handler
that gives me the NSURLs,
all right? So this is, the
complete handler means it's
going to get called when
it's completed going and
getting the data. And
then I also wanna load
the objects for UI image and
give me the images. Now,
what are we gonna do with this
URL on this image? Eventually
I need to hold on to that URL
because I'm going to
create a document which is
a emoji art document and
its background is gonna be
a URL. Because I don't want to
store that huge image with all
my documents. I am just going
to store the url and any
time I display the document.
I will go get the image
off the network.
Now my documents won't work if
there's no network. But eh,
it's a design decision.
So how am I going to do this?
Well, to make this go
a little quicker in here.
I actually created a little
bit of utility code which
you will of course
be free to look at,
at your leisure. We'll take
a quick glance at it. And this
utility code right here has a
class called ImageFetcher. And
all ImageFetcher does is it
takes a URL, goes and fetches
the image, make sure it is an
image. And when it's sure it's
got an image it calls you back
with a handler that you get
to it. So it's just kind of
this a synchronize check and
make sure this is
actually an image. And
it has this other cool feature
where it has a back up image
so if I go out and
fetch the URL and get it back
and that's not the URL of
an image. Then it uses
the backup image and
creates an URL for that and
local URL in the file system
and then gives you that URL.
So it's kind of a back up and
that's exactly what I want
here. Cuz I wanna go fetch
that image like of the country
side. And if I can get it.
I'll use that URL. But if I
can't, I want the image that
was being dragged instead. And
I'll create a local URL to it.
So that's all
imageFetcher does.
And to use it is super easy.
I'm just gonna create
a var imageFetcher which is
gonna be a type image fetcher.
I'm gonna make it be an
implicitly unwrapped option.
It truly only going to be
active during this, while
we're waiting for these things
to come back, and so I'm going
to create it. Image fetcher
equals an image fetcher.
It takes no arguments except
for a closure to call back.
And this closure calls back
with the URL. Did it fetched
and the image to use, either
the actual image it fetched or
the backup image if
you provided one. And
inside here, I can do whatever
I want with the URL and image,
but I am not on the main
queue here. This guy,
when he comes back after
fetching that thing,
it's not on the main queue,
so I have to dispatch queue.
Back to the main queue here
with Dispatch async. Now,
I can, for example set my
EmojiArtView.backgroundImage
to that image. So, I am not
really looking at the URL yet,
because I am not really
saving the documents.
So, I am just ignoring that,
I am just setting
the backgroundImage
to the image that I fetched
from that URL. All right.
So how do I fetch it? Well
in load objects right here,
I just say image,
self.imageFetcher,
fetch that url. Okay that's
what the imageFetcher does,
it fetches that URL and then I
say to the imageFetcher here,
use as backup this image.
Now this notice
is NSURLs. So a drag can
have multiple URLs remember?
I can start a drag and then
tap on some more things and
I'm dragging a whole
bunch of things. So
how do I get the url I want?
Well, I 'm just gonna
grab the first one hang in and
say,
if I can let url =
nsurls.first as a URL.
Cuz I wanted that Swift URL
then I will go fetch it.
And similarly down here if I
can let image equal the images
that I got. The first one as
a UI image then I'll do it.
And remember I have to do
it as here Not just because
this is NSUrl and I want URL.
I know you say,
even we have to do it here
when this is our UIImage,
because the type of this
array is NS item providers.
Right? So we have to convert
them to the actual commander
provider that we're expecting
here. And of course, for
some reason that doesn't
work it as question mark, so
it will crash,
just do nothing in here.
And that's one thing
about drag and
drop is, if you drag and drop
and you can't get the data or
whatever just nothing happens.
For the user it's was just
an experience of, I dropped
that name it didn't work.
Maybe they'll either try
it again or go try drag and
drop something else.
So it's kind of a quiet kind
of not a noisy system where
it's putting a lot of alerts.
Drop failed all this and
that's very disturbing
to the users,
users will quickly move on, if
a drop doesn't work. So that's
it. That's all we need to do
here to make this drag and
drop works, so let's go run
this version over on our iPad
over here. So, let me
bring this up, click Time.
So here's our iPad. Here it
is. Not much of a UI yet but
this is it. This big white
area is my emoji art view.
I'm going to do the same thing
I did before. Go down here,
grab Safari, bring it up here
get them both on screen.
This time lets look for
something else,
lets look at Stanford
images maybe.
See what we can find here.
I see a lot of images there.
Let's grab some of these and
see what we find.
How about this one right here.
I'm going to drag this.
Notice the green plus? You see
the green plus? That's become,
because we returned that
UI drop operation copy.
That's what the green plus
means. I let go, woohoo.
Dropped it in. It's showing
it. Let's try another one.
Let's try this one right here.
This one is bigger. Look how
long it's taking to load here.
It's fetching this URL,
gaining the data, asynchronous
and finally One in there, but
it, how big the data is will
decide how long it loads. So
that one is a low resolution.
You can see it's very grainy,
the other one was
higher resolution so
let's see if we can find
a really high resolution one,
The problem with showing these
demos in Stanford is gigabit
now with me.
everything is super fast but
if you do this on any other
Ethernet and
network, these things
take a little time.
Now if we're really
doing this out for real,
we'd probably put the spinning
wheel there. Because we're we,
as soon as we get that drop,
perform drop, we know we've
gone off to fetch that. So put
the spinning wheel there and
see what happens
before it turns.
That gives our user a better
idea of what's going on.
Pretty cool? So that was step
one of building our app.
We're making quite a lot
of progress. The next thing
we wanna do is that table view
on the left and the collection
view on the top. So I'm gonna
go back to the slides and
talk to you about
those topics.
Let's go over here
to slides and
talk about these.
All right, table view and
collection views.
So what are table view and
collection view? You've seen
these things all over IOS.
You actually know what
they are already.
They're UIScrollView
subclasses that are used to
provide unbound access
to unbounded amounts of
information. And it displayed
them, they each display them
a slightly different way.
A table
view displays the information
as a big long list.
The list might be divided
into sections, but
it's a big long list.
Collection view, presents
it in a configurable way,
almost any two-dimensional
way. Now by default, the way
it presents it is called flow
layout. And flow layout,
you wanna think of this
being just like text, right?
If you have text, it flows
across from left to right and
when it runs out of space,
it goes to the next line.
And then it flows some
more and next line.
That's how a collection
view by default lays out.
You give it a bunch
of items to lay out,
they might be of different
sizes, whatever and it'll just
start laying them out and then
wrapping to the next line. And
in the, it'll even justify,
you know how text is justified
on both sides, it will do
that as well if you want.
So that's how a flow
layout works.
Now, I say collection view is
arbitrary, like people have
written layouts for collection
view they're like a fan of
cards, all right. And you pick
a card and it's no problem,
it's quite easy to actually
write a layout like that.
But I'm not gonna talk
about any of that
custom layout writing,
we're gonna do only flow
layout which is the default.
You don't have to do anything
to turn that layout on,
it's just the layout that
comes with collection view.
So that's all I'm
gonna focus on.
But I do want you to know that
there's a way that you could
write your own layout, that's
not flow layout. And have your
collection view present
things in some other way. So
that's what table view and
collection view are. They're,
I'm going to talked about
them together because
their API, in other words,
the programming interface
you use, very similar,
almost identical. Really
the only difference is we're
talking rows versus arbitrary
items that are being flowed or
otherwise layed out in 2D, all
right. So UITableView, just in
case you're not understanding
which thing I'm talking about.
I know you've seen it.,
it's just a big long list like
this.
The list can be super simple.
I've got a list of food here,
it's just listed out. Or
a list can be divided
into sections. So
I've got junk food, fruits,
dessert, vegetable.
I divided the list
into sections. So
those are sections in a table
view, and it can show a little
bit of simple ancillary
information kind of for free,
like here I've got a little
image of the food.
You can probably barely see.
Yeah, you can see it there.
And, it has four
different ways,
to present the simple
information. One is this,
called subtitle style where
the ancillary information,
it appears right below
the main information.
This is left detail,
everything over on the left,
here's right detail where
the ancillary information
is on the right. And
the main stuff on the left,
or there's basic style where
you don't see
the ancillary information.
So these four styles are kind
of built into table view,
you kind of get them for
free, but it also has a very
powerful style called custom
style. And a custom style
look, the rows can be anything
you want. In fact, this UI,
you just build it in your
storyboard using auto layout
and all those things to build
whatever kind UI you want.
Now, collection view, all
cells are custom. Collection
view does not have those four
simple ones. All right.,
so this is what,
how these things can look,
how table view can look. So
collection view, sorry, and,
in table view, the rows can be
grouped together in addition
to being sections. They can
also be, the sections can be
made to look kinda like
they're grouped. You probably
notice this UI. It's from the
settings app in iOS. We almost
always only use this group
style like this when the data
in the table is static. In
other words, it's not showing
arbitrary information like
a list of foods that might be
changing over time,
it's showing fixed things.
Like here, the accessibility
settings, those never change,
they are fixed, right?
So that's the only time we use
this group style otherwise,
it's in what called plain
style, that's all things I
was just showing you. So
collection view, like I say,
it kinda flowing like tech so
here I've got these foods
with an image of them.
And it's kinda flowing from
line to line, happens to be
all the same size so there's
three per line, but there's no
rows here. This might,
you might look at this and
say, it's just like table,
you got rows.
No, there's not rows,
these items just happen to be
flowing from line to line,
they're lining up in rows.
If they were different sizes,
they wouldn't look quite so
rowed there. And
you could also have sections
in collection views as well.
So collection utility both
have this concept of dividing
the information up into
sections. All right. So that's
what they look like. How do
you get one into your app? And
you drag it out, of course,
from the object pallet, right.
Table view or
collection view, drag it out.
There's also prepackaged
MVCs if your entire view,
so your entire self.view
of your MVC is going
to be a table view, you are
gonna wanna use the table view
controller that you can drag
out. It's like dragging out
a view controller. You drag
out table view controller and
boom, you'll get one,
it will all be prewired up and
you'll have the table view
in there and all that,
same thing with the collection
view controller. So this is
kind of a convenience thing
and, but I do recommend if you
ever do have an MVC that the
entire view is a table view or
a collection view use
these convenience things,
they are convenient. So
the most important thing
to understand in the API or
using these things is where
does the data come from?
How do I get the data
into my table and and
we know that from my MVC talk,
views are not allowed to own
their data. So we can't have
a var in table view which is,
here's the data. We can't
just give it the data.
The table view has to ask for
the data. So it asks for
the data in the same
way as delegation.
There's gonna be a var,
it's called dataSource.
Both table view and
collection view have this.
And that data source is,
it's type is a protocol, and
in that protocol is a bunch of
methods that ask for the data.
Give me that data. They're
just constantly asking for
the data, that's how
they get their data.
And we're gonna talk about the
important methods are in that
data source protocol
in a moment, so
then you're gonna understand
how to load up your table or
your collection view. Now
table and collection view also
have a delegate,
that's a different var.
And that controls how
the data is displayed.
Like how the collection
view and
the table view are configured
not what's it's displaying.
Not the actual data,
just kind of the how.
All right, so you set these
two vars to your controller,
99.99% of the time, if you
drag out those pre-package
ones, this vars gets
automatically set for you. But
the bottom line is that
your controller is gonna be
answering all these, give me
the data questions. All right?
So, this give me the data
protocols have many
methods in them, surprisingly.
You would think it would
not be that much, but
it's actually, I think,
over a dozen maybe even 15 or
more. But there's three super
important ones. The three main
give me the data ones and
we're gonna talk about those
three. And they're pretty much
the same in both, I'm going
to talk about, mostly about
the table view ones, which
are pretty much identical to
the collection view. And
here they are. In Table View,
in Collection View, they both
have number of sections.
I told you that
the information can be divided
into sections, so of course,
it wants to know,
how many sections are there?
Often times the answer is,
one. In fact,
if you don't implement this
method, that'll be the answer,
one section. Everything's
in one big section.
All right? Second one is okay,
how many rows in each section?
So it's just gonna ask you for
every section,
how many rows in this section?
How many rows in this section?
Or in the collection view
section, how many items are in
this section. That's the next
question I'm gonna ask you. So
these two make obvious sense.
Then there's the biggie,
is getting the data
in each row or
for each item. Now, this one
is quite flexible because
the data you're gonna
present in your table view or
collection view might be
quite complicated, and so
we're gonna talk about this
method in great detail here.
But notice the argument there
though that green type index
path. Index Path is just
a little tiny little structure
that contains the section and
the row, or the section and
the item. So it's just
a way to combine the row,
section and row, so
that the Collection View and
Table View can ask
you very simply,
give me the data for this
section and row, it gives you
an Index Path. So, nothing
special about an Index Path,
it literally just has bars,
row, item, and section,
those are the only bars
which you're gonna use.
When you use Index Path
in this class,
super simple. All right, so
let's dive into cell for
row in index path, I'm gonna
do the table view one,
like I say, but this is
the same for collection view,
it's just called cell for
item at index path. So,
this method is going
to return a UI view.
You see that red thing,
UI table view cell?
That is a subclass of UI view.
This is the view that's gonna
be used to draw the row, or
the item in a collection view.
See, super duper simple,
right? But it's a little bit
a complexity here because of
this first line of code, this
is always gonna be pretty much
the first line of code in your
cell for row at method, which
is dequeue reusable cell with
identifier for index path.
Now, what the heck does all
that mean? Dequeue reusable
cell with identifier, so
let's break down that line and
understand what's going
on there. First of all,
let's understand reuse. If I
had a table view with 10,000
things in it, let's say, all
the songs in my iPod library.
10,000 of them in there, and
I had 10,000 views, each of
which might have, well, you
know, the album cover, art,
and let's say, imagine that
would just be ridiculously
inefficient, 10,000 UI views,
all populated, no way. So
the table view actually only
creates these UI table view
cells for the visible rows.
And as you scroll through and
they fly off the top,
it reuses them,
puts some on the bottom.
So it's constantly
reusing these views as you
scroll through your data.
Which makes sort of perfect
sense, right, for efficiency.
That's exactly
what you wanna do.
So when things fly off
the top, no longer in view,
this cell that was displaying
them, the UITableView cell,
which is a UIView,
it goes into a reuse pool, and
you get things out of
that with that method,
dequeReusable whatever. Right?
It gives you a cell out of it,
but what if that pool of
reusable things is empty,
like, let's say, your
table just came on screen.
Well, obviously,
there's none in there. So
then what happens. Where, when
you can dequeue reusable cell,
you still get a cell where
does it come from? Well,
the answer is,
it's created by copying
a prototype that you create
in your storyboard. So
you're gonna build this cell
with all the labels and
buttons and images that you
want. Build it right there,
using auto layout in your
story board, and then it's
going to make copies of that
every time it needs one,
and it can't reuse one. So
that's how this is gonna work,
and here's an example of it,
so this is a screenshot from
my storyboard. This is like
the top of my table view
controller right here.
I've got two cells here,
two prototypes. The first one
is just a basic cell. And
the second one is that
complicated one I showed you,
that's got the image in
the category, the food, and
the name of the food, and
some details about the food.
Etcetera, okay so these
are two separate prototypes in
here and for each of them, I'm
going to set their style and
also give them an identifier.
You see how the top one has
the identifier food cell.
The bottom I gave the
identifier, custom food cell.
So this is just a string that
you're gonna use to identify
which cell you want
when you're dequeuing
a reusable cell. So dequeuers
of the cell will never reuse
one of the wrong type.
You told me you're gonna reuse
one of the type you want, and
if there are none to reuse,
it'll make one by copying what
you see here. All the views
in there, the image view and
the text views are all
be copied, for
you to make another row. So
now you understand this yellow
line, right? Dequeue reuseable
cell with identifier,
that's like food cell or
custom food cell,
says which of the prototypes
you want. And of course for
index path is the index path
we're at because we're going
to be asked to create
something for that index path.
Got that? All right. The fact
that these cells are reused,
notice red, the fact that
these cells are reused, has
big implications from multi
threading. Because you might
have an image in your row and
you have to go fetch it,
so you fire off some fetching
thing on another thread
to go get something
off the internet,
it's taking a long time.
Meanwhile, the user flicks and
scrolls that cell away and
it gets reused. And
now it's showing something
else, and then here comes
the image back. Well,
if you're not careful you'll
splash that image from the
other cell into the new one.
Do you see why you're gonna do
that? So when that image comes
back, you gotta make sure,
is this cell still showing
the thing that I made that
request for? We this is,
we talked about this, all
the time with multi threading,
when it comes back, you gotta
check to make sure the world
is still what you thought.
This really happens a lot with
these cells because they're
constantly flying around and
get reused. All right? So
now that we know about this,
we, sometimes we'll have
a line like this in our thing,
which is let the prototype,
which is a string here,
equal some decisions, some
code that makes a decision,
either food cell or
custom food cell.
So that decision right there,
it might be made on what index
path you will have, like,
which section it's in, or
maybe it's based on the data
that's going there,
like, maybe some fruits.
We have detailed information
about and some foods,
we have detailed information
about, some foods we don't,
right? So we're gonna
use the detailed one,
custom food cell, when we have
the information and food cell,
when we don't. You see how we
can just decide right here,
which one is appropriate, and
then we dequeue that one to
get the right cell. All right,
now we've got the cell.
It's a table view cell,
UITableView cell,
okay, that got dequeued.
How can we configure the cell
to have the data in it? Okay,
well that depends on whether
it's one of these basic four,
like, subtitle, left detail,
right detail, or basic or
whether it's a custom cell,
like the one with the apple
image and all that. So
let's look at the basic ones.
That one, basically TableViews
cell has a couple of outlets
on it called, text label,
a detail text label that
you can just set. For
the defaults, it also has
another one called ImageView,
a little image can
appear on the left
of the cell. So
if that's good enough for you,
then you can just use those
outlets and you're good to go.
So you just set it.
This is just a, UITableView
cell is just a view,
it happens to have outlets,
it's a view with outlets, and
we're gonna talk about that in
a second cuz we've never
seen views with outlets,
only controllers without
outlets up until now. But
if that's not good enough and
you need something complicated
like that detail apple cell
that we had right there,
then you're gonna have to
make a custom subclass
of UI table view cell.
And let's see why and
how we do that. So, we have
this custom cell right there,
we clearly need outlets to it,
right?
Otherwise how are we
gonna set those?
We gotta have outlets, and
so you might think, well,
I'm just going to put that in
my table view controller like
I always do, right? My
subclass of my controller, but
we can't do that, and do you
see why we can't do that?
Because there could be 100
of these cells. This is
a prototype we're copying,
we can't have one outlet
which one wins? They can't,
you know what I'm saying, and
these could be arrays I guess
like an outward collection,
that's not, that wouldn't make
any sense either, because
but that but
those things are constantly
being reused, that array would
be going crazy as people.
So we can't do that,
we cannot use our controller
as a place for outlet. So for
the first time we're actually
gonna put outlets in a view,
and this view has to be
a subclass of UITableViewCell,
that thing that
the cellForItemAt returns. So
you're gonna make a subclass
of it, MyTableViewCell,
and you're gonna put
the outlets in there.
So each row, is gonna have
it's own TableViewCell, and
each table cell's gonna
have its own outlets. Even
the basic and subtitle ones
have their own outlets text
label, detail text label,
and image view, right? But
yours can have whatever
outlets you want,
because you're just gonna,
this is gonna be a class
you're gonna write.
Now, don't forget,
when you create a custom
UITableViewCell subclass you
gotta go the identity
inspector with the little
prototypes row there selected,
and set the identity,
cuz by default it'll be
class UITableViewCell,
so you have to change it to
be class MyTVC, or whatever,
my table view cell. Again,
just like you set the class
for the controllers and for
the views, you also do
the same thing for the cells.
All right and that's it.
So it's not that hard actually
the only thing is back in
cellForRowAt, if we wanna
access those outlets, we have
to cast the cell that comes
back from dequeueReusableCell
with identifier, cuz that
comes back. That's a class
UITableViewCell so it doesn't
know about my outlets, so
I have to cast it to be MyTVC.
Now, I've got this local
variable myTVC, my TVCell,
which is cast, and I can
do things like TVC.name and
TVC.emoji. Those outlets that
I had, and I can set them to
be myData. Notice that myData,
I have these,
I've created functions in my
controller called food at
indexPath, an emoji at
indexPath. This is a common
thing you wanna do, which is
basically I have functions
that take in indexPath and
go look in your model. So
that you can easily just drop
them in here when asked.
So that's it.
That's how you load up cells.
In collection view, you always
have to do it this way,
collection view has no
basic or sub-title,
and in table view, any time
you have anything more than
just the simple cells you
have to do it this way,
but it's done exactly the same
way in the both collection and
table view. Now,
take a breath from this and
talk about static table views.
So, sometimes a table, we only
use it to lay out our UI,
we're not actually using it
as a place to have arbitrary
amounts of data,
it has a fixed amount of data.
Usually this is something
like a settings app,
or a preferences table in
our app, where everything is
fixed, and we're just using
it to group things and
layout things in nice rows.
So, when we do that we don't
have to do any of this stuff.
Number of rows and sections,
nah, none of that. Self of row
at, because we just do it all
directly in our storyboard,
and we can wire the things in
the rows directly to
your controller, why?
Because there's only one
of everything. This is not
a prototype that gets copied,
because it's static.
The data is static, so
we can just go directly to
our controller in this case.
It's quite easy, and so this
is not uncommon to use this,
and the way you do this, kind
of make a table into this,
is you go, click on
the table in storyboard and
change its content,
right there,
to static cells. By default
it'll be dynamic prototypes,
but you're gonna set it to
static cell, and by the way,
the style there's almost
always grouped. Remember I
showed you that grouped style
like it's in the settings app?
That's pretty much what you're
gonna use when you have static
cells. That's what looks the
best when static. Then you go
into the document outline.
This is a little obscure, but
don't forget this piece. You
go to the document outline and
you'll find the sections
there, these static sections,
and you can go to each
section. First of all, you can
create more sections by just
inspecting the table view, and
say how many sections you
want. But then when you find
the section of the document
outline, you click on them and
inspect the section, and
you can add rows to it,
cuz a lot of people are like,
how do I add a row
to this section?
I can't figure it out.
That's how you do it, document
outline, click on the section,
inspector, hit the number
of rows you want. And
then you just start
dragging in labels, and
buttons, and switches,
whatever you wanna do, and
control dragging them right to
your controller. Cuz it's just
a way to lay those things out.
So that's a totally different
kind of table view we call
static table view. All right,
how about segueing
from a table view.
So I want to click on
a row and have it segue.
Well this is absolutely
exactly straightforward as you
might think until we get
to prepare for segue.
I also wanna talk about this
Detail Disclosure Accessory.
So if you inspect your
table view cell, and
you go over to the inspector,
and under accessory,
you choose detail disclosure,
you'll get that little i with
the circle around it.
And you can segue from it or
from the row. So if someone
clicks on the row it'll do one
segue, if they click
on this little thing,
it'll do a different segue,
and why would you want this?
Well, let's say this is our
emoji art document list and
clicking on the row is
obviously gonna bring up that
emoji art document,
maybe clicking on the little
i segues to a different MVC,
which lets us maybe change
the name of the document,
who authored it, when it was,
see when it was last created.
You see what I mean,
kind of informative,
information about
the document.
So you can have both of
those things segue and
going on. And, but you make
the segue the same way,
you control drag from the row,
and yes you can control drag
from a prototype row. This
works for prototypes as well
as for static.
So, you just control drag, and
when you let go, you can see
that you can set the segue for
your main row, and
you can also set the segue for
that little button,
that little accessory button,
that little i with
a circle around it. So,
that just sets up normal
segue, or possibly two
segues if you have that little
i, and then you inspect it.
You set it's identifier,
like we normally do.
I'm gonna call this my ABC
segue, and then you prepare,
and that's where it gets
interesting in the table view,
because if you're segueing
from a prototype, you gotta
know which row that is when
the segue actually happens.
Here's how we do that.
Here's prepare for segue.
The key to this is the sender
argument to prepare for segue,
which remember that was like
button, if we clicked on
a button to segue, well,
if you click on a row it's
the UITableViewCell.
So you need to figure out,
from the UITableViewCell,
which index path is this so
that you can go get the right
model data to prepare
the thing you're going to.
And so the way you do that
is you first cast it to be a
UITableViewCell, or a subclass
of it if you have a subclass
of UITableViewCell right here.
Then you call this
very important method,
in table view, called
indexPath(for: cell), and
it will return an index path,
i.e., the row end section for
that given cell. Notice that
you can't pass an any to this,
or you can't say indexPath for
sender,
you have to have cast it first
to be a UITableViewCell or
subclass thereof.
Once you get the indexPath,
then you can go ahead and
do your normal thing where
you get the destination as the
MVC you're segueing to, and
then you get from
your model somewhere,
you get the data based on the
section and row, and then you
assign it to the public API of
the MVC you're segueing to. So
that's the magic of segueing,
the sender's gonna be
TableViewCell, you need
to go indexPath for
cell to find out which
indexPath, then you can segue.
What about segueing from
a collection view item.
So in a collection view item,
this is actually best done
with target action, kind of.
A collection view's delegate
has a method in it which is
called every time an item
gets touched on. It's called
CollectionVewDidSelectItemAtI-
ndexPath. All right, and
from here use perform segue
and then prepare normally.
Now, when you do perform
segue from here,
probably the sender that any
you're gonna specify something
that makes sense to you and
use that in the prepare. So
that's the way to segue from
cells in a collection view.
You could use that
same strategy for
UI table view, by the way.
There's no reason not to use
the exact same thing. In fact
some people do table view once
by implementing table views
did select row and index path
and passing the index path as
the Emmy. Okay? So now you've
got the index path. You don't
even have to do any of that
index path for cell business.
That's perfectly reasonable
too, to do that if you want.
All right, something to think
about with these table and
collection views is, what
happens if your model changes,
right? You've got this table,
you're showing all your
songs in your iPod,
and then you add a song
somehow. It's gotta update. Or
a new food gets discovered or
something and
our food list has to change.
So what do you do?
Well, there is a method in
table view and collection view
called reload data. That will
cause all of those methods,
number of rows and section,
number of section,
the table view.
Give me the table view cell,
it will call them all again.
For all the visible cells, and
go get a new table of cells,
reload your whole table,
basically.
It's a little heavy handed.
It's not too bad,
because actually,
only in a call that get me the
cellForRow and IndexPath name,
it's only gonna call that for
the visible cells, so it's
not too bad, actually. But
there are finer grained like
reloadRows at IndexPaths that
gives an array of index paths,
and you can reload just those
rows. And collection view has
similar things. It's not, you
know, it's not so bad to do
a reload data, but you do have
to think about the fact that
if your model changes,
you gotta update your table.
You don't really
want your data or
your collection to get out
of sync with your model for
very long.
You want them to stay in sync.
How about the height
of the rows?
How do we determine the height
of these rows? Well,
there's three ways really
per table view rows.
One is a var in table
view called rowHeight.
Now this is also settable in
the storyboard, this just
fixes the rows. They're
always gonna be that height.
And that works for the basic
rows and things like that.
Second one is setting the row
height using auto-layout.
Okay so you got
a complicated thing and
maybe sometimes there's
a fruit has a lot of detail
information. So
the cell needs to be big and
sometimes the fruit
has very little and
the cell will be small. So
you setup your autolay layout
properly, so that it's pushing
out on a generic view. So
you're gonna put a generic UI
view as the top level view in
your row, and then put
all your stuff inside and
then have constraints
that push that thing out,
push that generic view out.
And then have the generic view
pinned to the edges
of the row.
And if you do that,
then table view will
be able to come along,
auto layout that thing,
and it'll know what size
it has to be. So to do that
you set the rowHeight instead
of to a number you set it to
UITableViewAutomaticDimension
that's a special
value that let it node to go
do that out of the lab thing
as you can imagine
that's quite expensive.
You're not gonna do it 10,000
times for your iPad library.
So you also wanna set
an estimatedRowHeight.
And the estimatedRowHeight
just tells table view for
the cells that
aren't on screen,
assume they are this big.
Don't go auto layout
them. So that's something to
consider. Another way you
can set the height is by
implementing this method table
view heightForRowAt indexPath.
And then this return
the height for the row with
that index. Now if you can
much more efficiently
calculate the height without
doing all the auto
lay out stuff,
then this is a great one for
you to do.
Maybe you know the certain
cells are one height and
certain tells another
height and that's it,
just one of these two and
you can return which
one it is, all right?
Or maybe all your cells
are the same height and
it's just more convenient to
calculate it and return it
here, that's perfectly fine.
Collection view has a similar
thing. The only thing about
collection view is one,
which is size for item at,
because remember,
these items are rectangles in
a collection view, not rows,
they don't have a height,
they're rectangles.
The only thing about that
is notice this extra little
argument there besides
sizeForItemAt is layout
collectionViewLayout right
there.
That's the magic thing that's
doing the flow layout,
by default. But if you provide
a collectionViewLayout,
you can do other kinds
of layouts. But for
your purposes in this class,
leads beginning using this.
That's always going to be a UI
collection to flow layout,
which does the flowing.
That's why there's that extra
argument here for that one.
How about those headers?
To put the headers in there,
you know, like junk food and
then desserts and fruits, and
vegetables. Those headers in
table view is super easy,
you just implement this
method, table view,
title for header section,
it returns a string, and
just puts it in there.
Couldn't be easier.
There is actually another one
that returns the UI view, so
you can actually have
your headers be UI views
with anything you want in
there. Take collection view,
much more difficult. Much
more difficult to do section
headers and table view in
collection view. And that's
because collection view, their
header views are reusable.
Just like the cells are. And I
guess this decision was made,
because you could imagine
collection views had a lot of
sections. Where as a table,
it's unlikely
you're gonna have a table
with thousand sections.
Collection view,
maybe you could have a lot.
I'm not sure why they decided
to do it this way, but
they did.
It plays out very similar to
using the cells. What you
do to enable your headers
is you inspect your collection
view and click the button
section header or section
footer and then a little thing
will appear in your storyboard
that you can go drag things
into. That little thing
is a prototype and
it's gonna be repeated for
every section header.
You can put anything you
want in there, though, but
you're gonna have to
create this subclass.
The subclass is of something
called UIReusable,
UICollectionReusableView
instead of UITableView cell or
UICollectionView cell. So
you're gonna sub close up
put your outlets in there.
And then you're gonna
implement this method,
viewForSupplementaryElementOf-
Kind which is kind of like
self row at index path but
just for the headers. And
inside there you're gonna
use another deque method,
this one's called
dequeReusbaleSupplementaryVie-
wOfKind with identifier for
index path.
And that's going to make
a copy of that prototype and
reuse them as they scroll
around on screen. So
I'm just giving you, you
understand the general brush,
but if you actually wanna have
headers you're gonna have
to go figure this all out,
headers and footers,
that's for collection
view only. All right,
there are a billion
other methods,
dozens of other methods in
these classes, these are very
large sophisticated classes.
You can swipe to delete rows,
you can move the rows around
until you can scroll around,
scroll to a certain row.
I mean, there's so
much in there, it's hardly
to even get started on.
So this is the kind of thing
like everything on this class.
I'm just getting you started
and you're gonna have to look
at documentation for
these things to see,
ooh, what can I do?
Read the introduction.
I think I said this
in the beginning and
I haven't re-emphasized
enough. For all these classes,
read the text at
the beginning, the overview.
It'll give you an idea of
what these things can do and
what they're capable of etc.
So when I was making these
slides, I actually created
that little fruit thing,
right? When the little thing,
and so I decided,
you know, I'm just gonna give
you that code. The code that I
used to actually
create the screenshot.
So I'm gonna post that code.
And it's just two things,
a table view and
a collection view that
shows you the fruit.
And so you can get an idea for
simple stuff, how to do that.
But I'm also gonna do a huge
demo, which is emoji art.
Cuz you noticed that emoji
art both a table view and
a collection view.
So we're gonna do that. And
today we're going to start by
doing the Table View. And then
on Wednesday we'll continue
and do the Collection View.
And the Collection View is
cool because you notice
the Collection View has
drag and drop in it.
And there's special support
in Collection View and
Table View for drag and
drop, as well.
So we'll bring those two
things together. I won't get
back to the slides. So just to
let you know what's coming up
on Wednesday, in addition to
doing the Collection View and
Table View Emoji Art, we're
also gonna do Text Field.
I don't think I showed you.
Yeah, I showed you the feature
in there where you can
add more emoji, right?
So there was a little text
field that appeared there, so
I'm gonna show you
how to do that.
We're done with Friday
sections for this quarter.
The three we had were great,
and but that's enough.
And then next week,
I will be talking about your
requirements for your final
projects. And then more iOS.
Give me more, needs more iOS,
so we'll be doing that.
Back to our emoji
art right here. And
what are we gonna do? So
we're gonna do that tableView.
So let, let's throw that
tableView thing in there,
and let me, I don't know where
I was here. Yeah, here we go.
So the tableView is part
of a split view, right?
It, it slid out from the side.
So I'm just gonna go right
to my storyboard right here,
and put that split view in
there. Okay, so as I always
recommend, zoom out when
you put split viewing,
cuz it gives you all of this
kind of default things.
So I'm gonna search here for
split view. Here it is.
So here's my split
view controller.
You can drag it out here,
give me all this stuff. And
I'm going to delete all of it.
So I'm gonna get rid of that,
I'm gonna get rid of that,
and get rid of that.
So here's my split view.
I'm gonna make it be the entry
point by moving the little
arrow. This is my emoji
art view controller.
It's the detail, right?
It's obviously the detail.
The master is clearly
choosing which one I want,
which document I want. So I'm
gonna control drag over here
to set this up as the detail
right there. All right, so
now how are we gonna make
that tableView master? Well,
notice that that tableView was
all tableView, right? That MVC
was all tableView. I didn't
have any other UI in there,
just the list of
the documents. So
I'm going to use the tableView
pre-packaged controller here.
See, here's tableView,
just the view,
and here's tableView,
the controller.
So I'm gonna drag this out.
It makes a controller right
there. I'm gonna embed this
in a navigation controller.
And you might say,
why do I need to do that?
This is an iPad only app. But
there is actually one case on
iPad only where you will get
a navigation controller here,
which is, you're in portrait.
You have another app side by
side like we had Safari.
It jams up the thing so
much that it turns that master
thing into a navigation
controller. Which was a really
a cool decision on Apple's
part, since you're mostly
learned to build this kind of
hybrid split view navigation
control thing anyway. So
we are gonna do it.
So let's select this one and
go embed in
Navigation Controller. And
then this combination of this
Navigation Controller and
our little emoji art document
chooser, is going to
be our master. So I'm gonna
go over here and Ctrl drag to
make this my master. Now I'm
going to have this tableView.
Right now, its identity
is UITableViewController,
generic UITableViewController.
So I'm gonna create a subclass
of UITableViewController
to control this table.
So I'm gonna go File > New.
This time when I create coco
touch class,
it's gonna be a subclass of
UITableViewController I'm
gonna call it my
EmojiArtDocument, Document,
TableViewController.
Nice long name there. And this
controller is the thing that's
going to control this
tableView right here. So
let's go and select this and
check its identity to be
Emoji Art Document Table
View Controller. Now I'll be
able to do all my magical
delegate things. And in fact,
if you look at this code,
whoo! It gives you a lot of
commented out code that has
to do with being a tableView.
I created it as a subclass
of UITableViewController.
Cuz you know,
So it knows it needs
all these things.
So I'm gonna delete the ones
we're not gonna use like
our view controller life cycle
methods. Recognize these?
Whoo, number of sections,
number of rows, cellForRowAt.
Right up front, these
are the most important ones.
These are the
UITableViewDataSource methods,
source methods here. So
we want to implement these to
make this thing work. Now as
with any view controller,
or any MVC we create, we wanna
think about what is its model?
This is the world's
easiest model.
It's just a list of
the emoji art documents.
So I'm gonna make that
be a list of strings. So
this is var emojiArtDocuments,
and it is a list of strings.
And we're even, even gonna
start it out with some.
Document one, document two,
and document three.
Now of course, as our app
progresses, we're gonna be
allowing new documents to be
added, etc. But I'm gonna
start with three documents,
cuz we're just trying
to learn a little bit about
how tableView works here.
So that's my model. So this,
this table is gonna display
this model. Well, this model
doesn't have enough stuff
in it to have sections, but
you could imagine it would.
What if I had recently created
documents, recently deleted,
other kinds of sections?
I could have sections
of documents, but
I'm not going to. So I'm
only gonna have one section.
Definitely wanna get rid
of this warning right here,
because I've completed that.
Then here is number of rows in
section. Well,
I only have one section, so
I don't have to
check the section.
I don't have to say if section
equals zero, then something.
If section equals one or
whatever. So here,
it's only one section.
I'm just gonna return
emojiArtDocuments.count.
That's how many rows are in
the only section I have, is
however many documents I have.
And then we got this guy right
here to dequeueReusableCell.
And remember,
there's really a couple of
things to dequeueReusableCell.
First, we have to figure out
what kind of cell we're gonna
use. And
here I only have the names,
so I'm just gonna
use the basic cell.
We'll see how to do a subclass
of cell on Wednesday, but
here, it's just gonna
the basic cell.
So I'm gonna go back
to my storyboard here.
Okay, here we go.
Notice that it starts out,
it just has one prototype
cell, but if I want more
prototype cells, all I have to
do is click on the tableView.
Inspect the tableView itself.
You can always tell what's
being inspected by the first
word in the inspector there.
And I just go here,
see prototype cells one.
I say, I want two, three,
four. And, you know,
maybe this is a custom cell,
and I wanna add a label to it.
All right, drag this label
out, put this in here,
do auto layout, control drag,
all that stuff.
I can build whatever UI I want
in here. But if I do that,
I'm gonna have to make a
custom subclass of UITableView
cell to have outlets to all
this stuff. But I'm not gonna
do any of that, yet. So
I'm just gonna have this one.
So I'm gonna go back here
to my Table View, and
say, Table View. Sometimes
it's hard to click on
the controller versus
the Table View
versus the cell.
Don't forget about Shift+Click
is a good way to do it. Or
you can always resort over
here to your document outline.
So I'm gonna go back down to
just one cell right there.
By the way, here's where we
said static versus dynamic.
All right, so I have this one.
I'm gonna have it be a basic
cell. I don't even have enough
information to be a subtitle
cell. I don't have any
detailed text information.
I just have the name of it.
So that's all I'm going to do,
have this basic cell.
But it's gotta have
a reuse identifier,
because we've gotta, when
we create the initial ones,
it's gotta know what prototype
to copy. So I'm gonna call
this my document cell. Cuz
that's what, it's a cell that
represents a document right
there. And so that's good.
So let's go back to our
code right here. And now we
can de- queue ReusableCell of
the identifier DocumentCell.
It's the only kind we have, so
that's, we can clearly just do
that. And the cell that comes
back is gonna be of type
UITableViewCell. And we know
that it has this nice outlet,
basically, called UITextLabel.
Which they made optional,
which is kinda strange,
they didn't make it implicitly
unwrapped optional.
So you have to do that
question mark there.
Anyway the text, and now we
have to go to our model, and
get the information.
And we have to do that for
this index path, this section
and row. Well the section is
always going to be zero cuz
I only have one section. So
I'm just going to use
the row and say give me my
emojiArtDocument at
the indexPath.row. So I'm
just getting out of my model
for that row, the information.
That's all you need to
do to make this work. So
let's go see this in action.
This, all right here we go.
And sure enough, here it is.
It came out on the left here.
Oops, you can see it there.
But, let me make this a little
easier to see, let's hide
others. There we go. So
this is on the left and I can
select them over here. You can
see I'm selecting one, two,
three. Now it would be really
cool over here to be able to
add new documents, right?
So how would I add
new documents?
That turns out to
be really easy.
I'm just gonna put up on the
top of, right above the top
row here. On the right, I'm
gonna put a little Add button.
And when you click it, it's
gonna add a new document. So
let's go do that. Here we go.
And I'm gonna do that in my
storyboard of course. Now this
is a key thing to wake up for,
which is, when we add
buttons to these top
areas of a navigation
controller right here,
we don't add regular buttons.
So we don't go over here.
If I search for a button,
you'll see there's this
button, we do not do this.
It'll let you do it, but
don't do it, it's this that
you want, a bar button.
Cuz it's in a little
navigation bar at the top,
that's the button that you
want. You get all kind of
messed up if you use the wrong
button there. So we got this
button and I'm inspecting the
button right here on the top.
There is some predefined
buttons like a camera button
right there or a,
what do we got,
let's Save, a Save button.
That's is just a word and
there's also Add, and
Add happens to be a plus.
And I strongly recommend using
one of these pre-defined ones,
if it describes what you're
doing. Because usually you'd
be used to that icon or that
image doing what you expect
right there. Now this is
just a normal bar button and
we can just Ctrl drag to
it to create an outlet,
so let's do that. So here's my
controller on the right and
here's the button.
So where do we put this.
Let's put this right below
our UI tableView data source
methods right here. So
I'm control dragging
from the plus down here.
It's going to be an action.
I'm gonna call it newEmojiArt,
that's what it does,
it creates a new Emoji art.
And I'm gonna have
the argument not be typed any,
it's gonna be typed.
Bar button knows that you
can have no argument here,
which is kind of interesting
for bar buttons.
You have to have the argument
unlike a regular button, I
don't know. So now that we've
hooked that up, all we have to
do is make this code right
here, create a new document.
Well that's really, really
easy. We're just gonna say
emojiArtDocument. I'm gonna
do += and add another array
to it, += to an array you have
to have another array. But
it's only gonna have one thing
in it, which is Untitled.
That's what I'm gonna call my
new document. But actually
what if I already have
something called Untitled?
I don't wanna add two
documents to Untitled, so
I'm gonna use this little
utility that I created,
called
madeUniquewithRespectTo.
And it takes another array,
looks in that array and
make sure that it creates
something unique.
So in this case we'll do
Untitled 1, Untitled 2,
Untitled 3, until it find
something unique. And so I'm
gonna do that withRespectTo
the other emojiArtDocuments.
So these little
thing madeUnique,
is in that same utility place
where the image factor was, so
you can go and
look at that later. It's very,
very straightforward.
Now this is not enough.
I've changed my model here,
now what do I need to do?
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Update the table, yeah.
If I don't update the table,
I'm gonna be out of sync.
So how do I update the table?
I'm just gonna do
tableView.reloadData.
I don't have a lot of data in
there and it's not expensive
to reload it, so let's just go
ahead and reload the data, and
run. All right, so
here we go. Let's, okay,
we can still select here,
let's go plus, untitled, yeah.
Plus, plus, plus, plus, woo
hoo! No, I got carried away,
I did it too many. Now let's
delete. No, I can't delete,
I wanna swipe to delete,
everyone knows about swipe to
delete. How come I cannot
swipe to delete? Well,
turns you have to obviously
get involved with delete,
because when you delete, it's
not just delete in the row,
it's updating your model
to be deleted as well. So
let's go do that as well.
Let's go back here and
the very next things that
are coming out have to do with
this. This one is,
canEditRow at indexPath.
That's saying whether you're
allowed to delete this row.
Now the default is yes,
so you actually don't
have to implement this, if you
allow all rows to be deleted.
This is only a way to prevent
deletion from happening here.
So we're gonna allow
all our rows to
be deleted, so I'm not even
gonna uncomment this out, but
then why is delete
not working? Okay,
if that's the default?
Well because you also have
to implement this method.
Commit editingStyle,
the editingStyle is either
delete or insert. You have
to commit that, that means
commit it to your model. And
so this is really easy to do,
it just has an if delete or
an if insert. This insert is
a kind of UITableView UI for
adding, we don't need that
cuz we have our Plus button.
So I don't really have
to do anything here,
I'm just gonna to delete.
And even notice it says,
delete the row from the data
source, in other words from
your model. So
how do I delete it here?
I'm just gonna say
emojiArtDocuments.remove(at:
the indexPath.row). And then
I'm gonna update the table to
do that. I will tell you
right now, you, all of you,
when you're doing your final
projects, you will mess this
up. Because these two things
have to be perfectly in sync.
If you do not have these
perfectly in sync, you will
get a crash when this happens.
And it'll say something like,
number of rows in the table
did not match when I went to
go update the rows.
Okay, in other words,
it's saying your model and
your table don't match up. So
it's easy to get
them out of sync.
This is a simple case where
it's not easy to get out
of sync, right?
We move within the model,
we delete the rows from
the table. But, this is using
delete rows instead of reload
data, for example. There
are other ways of deleting
the rows and moving them, etc.
Updating them, you might do
the wrong thing depending
on how you're updating
your model there.
So now we should be able to
swipe to delete. Here's our
table with One, Two, Three,
plus, plus, plus, swipe, okay,
to delete, and gone. Also, I
don't know if this is new for
iOS 11, you can actually swipe
all the way across and delete,
in one motion, whoop! Whoops,
I didn't go far enough. If you
swipe all the way to the edge,
it will delete. And if you
only do partial way then you
get to Confirm button. So
that's all of the time
we have, perfect timing.
That's it pretty much it for
our table view. Now like I
say, we are not going to get
to the part where we actually
have document storing until
next week. Cuz I got to
teach you a little bit of how
we make things persistent
in IOS on the disc, to can
store things on the disc. But
we will on Wednesday do our
whole UI with the collection
view and dragging and dropping
to add more things, and
putting a text field in the
upper left to add more emoji.
All that stuff, we're gonna
do that on Wednesday.
So I'll see you then.
>> For
more, please visit
us at stanford.edu.