[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Okay, well,
welcome to Lecture number
12 of Stanford CS193P,
Fall of 2017. And today,
we're gonna continue the demo
we started with Emoji Art and
we're gonna,
we learned a little bit about
table view in the last one.
This time, we're gonna learn
more about collection view and
also learn a little bit
how drag and drop, and
collection view and table view
all go together. And then I'm
gonna go back to the slides
and talk about TextField.
And I originally had planned
to do a demo in Emoji Art,
of adding a TextField
in there, but
we also have to finish early
today, because there's some
huge midterm, in this
room right after us, and
we have to have time
to clear out of here.
So, I will probably do that
demo first thing, next Monday,
or I might just skip that
demo, we'll see how it goes.
All right, so
back to Emoji Art here.
What we're gonna do is make
first I'm gonna make Emoji Art
scrollable, because we didn't,
it just currently,
it's fixed. Then we're gonna
add a collectionView along
the top there,
you remember it from the demo,
where we're gonna be able to
choose our emoji from. And
then we're gonna add some
drag and drop from that
collectionView, both into our
view and into other apps, and
vice versa, etc.
So let's, actually,
let's take a quick look at
what our app looks like so
far, okay, and it's
basically working nicely and
that we can pick up images.
So I pick up an image here and
drag it in and
drop it to change it.
And of course, we have our
table view on the left for
choosing documents and
adding documents.
Of course, we haven't hooked
our table view up, and
that's okay, but because we're
gonna do that next week. But
one thing I wanna have you
note about this table view
that's kind of annoying is
that I can't get rid of it.
See this table view right
here? You can't swipe it away,
and that's because
essentially, this app thinks
it's in landscape mode on
an iPad, and so of course,
this master and the detail to
splitView are side by side.
But, since I'm in
multi-tasking mode right here,
so much of my
screen is taken up,
with Safari over
here on the right,
that it's annoying because I
really wanna focusing on my
Emoji Art document. So I'm
gonna talk to you a little bit
how to make it so that that
splitView on the left can be
slid out of the way, even in
splitView and landscape mode.
So that's the first little
thing we're gonna do. So let's
hop on over to our code over
here and see how we do that.
It's quite easy, actually,
splitView has a var,
a property in it called
preferred display mode, and
you can control what happens
with the master through that.
And, it's just that the
default here is not what we
want. Now the kinda
kooky thing about that,
I'm gonna set this var in my
master code. So I'm gonna go
to my emojiArtDocument
TableViewController, right?
That's the TableViewController
with the one, two, three,
the thing that we want
to slide out. And
what I'm gonna set it is
kind of an unusual place.
I'm gonna set it in
viewWillLayoutSubviews. And
you might be like, whoa,
viewWillLayoutSubviews,
that seems like a weird
place to set that. Well,
the reason I'm gonna set it
there is cuz when the layout
changes, of a splitView,
it often resets that preferred
mode. So if I wanna keep
enforcing this thing of it,
the master being in slide
on top mode, I have to keep
telling it to do that, but
I also have to be careful
because setting that preferred
mode can cause it to relay
out. So I don't wanna end up
in an infinite loop here,
right, where in
LayoutSubViews,
I'm setting preferred mode,
it's causing a layout,
I'm coming back in. So I'm
gonna do this by saying, if my
splitViewController?.prefer-
red,
to call preferredDisplayMode
!= the one I
want. And you can see
there's quite a few here,
there's primaryOverlay,
there's primaryHidden,
there's Automatic,
there's alwaysShowBoth, etc.
But the one I want is
primaryOverlay, so if it's not
primaryOverlay, then I'm gonna
set my splitViewControllers,
preferredDisplayMode =
.primaryOverlay. And so
that'll keep enforcing
it every time, even if,
every time we rotate or
whatever,
I'm gonna keep forcing this
cuz I always want that, this
table view to be appearing
on top of my emoji art view.
But I also wanna be able
to swipe it out of the way,
I just swiped it
out of the way.
Wait, you can't see, hold on,
I'll show you. Let me hide
here, Hide Others, okay, so
here, I'm swiping it in, and
then I'm swiping it away.
Swiping it in, swiping it
away, and I always want it to
be that way because it's very
unimportant to access this
table. I just go in here,
pick the document I want, now
that the document's in there,
I wanna be having as
much room to you know,
to drag my stuff in and
work here as possible.
Do you understand that
primary overlay thing?
And I'm gonna ask you to do
that in your homework, just so
you kinda see, what it's
all about there. All right,
the next thing I wanna
do is to make it so
that my EmojiArtView
is scrollable and
zoomable, right, cuz right
now, it's just a fixed image.
And we already know
how to do that, so
I'm not gonna waste too much
time showing you how to make
it scrollable, I'm gonna do it
quickly. I'm gonna have some
precanned code to do it, but
it's nothing new, it's nothing
that you haven't seen before,
in our previous demos.
So I'm gonna go back to my
storyboard, here it is,
right here. I'm gonna go down
to this viewController right
here, and instead of,
right now, what we have,
just to remind you,
is we have this drop zone.
And inside the drop zone,
we just put our EmojiArtView.
That's why it's not scrollable
right there. So I'm gonna
delete it, and instead I'm
gonna put a scrollView there,
so I'm gonna go down here and
search for a scrollView,
here it is. I'm gonna drag the
scrollView in here, I'm gonna
pin the the scrollView to
the edges of the drop zone,
of course. So I'll go here and
just pin it right up to the
edges. We know how to do that
with this little pin thing,
bloop, it spins out, that's
great. Now I'm going to create
an outlet to this scrollView,
put it up, where are we gonna
put it? Let's put it right
under the drop zone, in here.
So I'll Ctrl+drag,
create that scrollView.
Now we know that when we
have a scrollView outlet like
this, by the way, down here,
this emojiArtView is no longer
gonna be an outlet. Okay,
it's just gonna be
a regular var and
I'll just set it = creating
one. This is exactly what we
did with our image view in our
other demo. So we haven't done
anything new here. And when we
have a scrollView like this,
we remember we've got to set
its minimum scroll view,
maximum.
We've gotta set the delegate,
we've gotta implement
that view for zoom.
Remember all that? So I'm
gonna do all that really quick
here. Trying to remember what
I called, yeah, emojiscroll.
So here it is, here's all that
code. I just pop it in there.
In fact, let me go over
here and show it in big, so
you can see it. So
here's the ScrollView Outlet.
So I just added a didSet
to it, to set those things,
right, the delegate. And
then I added it as a subview.
Here's viewForZooming.
We're obviously zooming
in our emojiArtView.
Then I added a var here,
emojiArt background image,
which does the stuff we need
to do like setting our content
size equal to the frame.
Right, remember we want that.
We always want that frame of
our image view to the same
as our content size.
I put a little bit of zooming
code in here you can go
look at later,
which is kind of fun,
to give it an initial zoom
that's good. And then,
of course, we need to go
down here and use this.
So instead of just setting the
emoji art, we use background
image directly, I'm gonna use
this emoji art background
image var that I just created.
That's this var right here.
Hey everybody. See everything
I did right there?
And of course it's complaining
that I'm not a UI split view
or UI scroll view delegate
by the way, so I'll do that.
UI scroll view delegate,
now I implement that. So
let's make sure this all
works. So here I am in my app,
I'm just gonna swipe that
thing out of the way.
I'm gonna grab an image
here and drag and
drop it in. Here it is and
hopefully I can scroll. Whew!
I can I can scroll way
in scroll pan around
scroll in but you know what?
That looks incredibly ugly
to have that thing in
the upper left. Like that,
if I really were working
on this thing, and I have
to all my work in
the upper left,
that would be absolutely
ridiculous. So
what I really want is, I want
this thing to stay centered.
As I'm zooming in and out,
when I'm zoomed out here.
And when I zoom in, I want to
say in the center. Not jump up
there to the left like that.
So how am I going to do that?
Well, there's a lot of ways to
do that, actually. I'm gonna
do it in a simple way that
lets me teach your about how
to control the constraints in
your storyboard from code.
That's what this little thing
is all about that I'm gonna
show you here. So what I'm
gonna do is I'm gonna go back
to my storyboard.
And I'm going to
have this scroll view right
here always be centered.
So I'm going to keep this
scroll view in the center,
now, normally that's already
happening, because I'm pinned
to the edges. So of course
it's in the center, but
what I'm gonna do then is have
the scroll view's width and
height stick to its content
size. So if you zoom in so
that the content area
gets really small,
the scroll view is gonna get
small and it's gonna stay
centered. So that's how
we're gonna do this, that's
the trick. So how we gonna do
that? Well, of course we need
to make it to our scroll view
right here stays centered.
So I'm gonna click down here
and just pick horizontally and
vertically in the containers,
so now it's centered.
Again, that's not doing
anything because those other
constraints. But I still want
these other constraints over
here. I just don't
want them to be fixed.
I want them to be greater than
or equal. This is something
we did in the previous one, as
well. So I'm gonna edit all of
these ones about the edges to
just be greater than equals,
because I really just want
my scroll view to never go
outside the bounds.
But I'm fine if my scroll view
gets smaller than the bounds,
I just don't want it to get
bigger than the bounds, so
that's why I'm putting this
greater than or equals into
here. Now you can see that
things have turned red. That's
because it's undetermined
right now what size the scroll
view is. Because we
turned those equals to be
greater than or equal, so it
doesn't know how big it is. So
I'm going to fix
the size to start.
I'm gonna ctrl drag to itself.
And
fix both it's width and
height. That fixes it, but
of course now the scroll view
is always gonna be this size
which is, we'll look over here
and find out. 748 by 703 and
a half. So I clearly don't
want that. What I want to be
able to do is make this
is make this width and
height equal to the scroll
views content size. Now,
unfortunately I
can't do that here.
I just know the way to
control drag. To do that,
I have to do that in code. So,
I'm going to make outlets to
these two constraints and then
modify those outlets in code.
So, that that within height
is controlled by my code.
So, that is the trickery here.
And
the last thing I wanna do
though is I'm gonna try and
set the scroll view size to
its content size. But if it
gets really big, I want these
other constraints to win.
I want the constraints that
keep it from going out, so
the edge is to win.
So that's why I'm going to
set the priority of these two
height ones, the height and
width ones, to be lower. So
here's the priority over here.
It's currently at
the required level.
I'm gonna move it down to low
priority for both of them. And
so that will be fine when it's
inside the bounds because it
won't be conflicting. But once
the scroll view gets big cuz I
zoomed way in then it will get
pinned to the edges which is
perfect. All right so how
do I make outlets to these?
Just control drag of course.
So
I'm going to bring up my code
and we'll put it right there.
So I'm gonna ctrl
drag from with.
Over here you can see that
the type of this outlet is NS
layout constraint. I'll call
this my scroll view width.
Same thing here with
the height. We'll ctrl drag.
This one's going to be my
scroll view height. Now
what are we going to change
about these constraints?
So if you look at the
constraints in the inspector,
let's inspect
these constraints,
like constraint width. These
are all the things you can
set in a constraint,
right, the items involved,
the relationship whether it's
equal to, greater than or
less than. And
look you can set the constant
which is currently 703 and a
half. This is the thing I want
to change to fix my width,
this constant right here. So
I'm just going to change
that constant in my code.
Now when do I need to change
it? Get so you can see here.
When do I need to
change these constants?
Well anytime I zoom I
definitely need to change it,
right? Because as I'm zooming,
I want my scroll view to
be changing size. So,
let that's in scroll view did
zoom delegate method. And
all I'm going to do in here
is set my scroll view height
constant equal to the scroll
view's content size.
ContentSize.height.
And same thing here, the
scrollViewWidth.constant is
equal to the
scrollView.contentSize.Width.
So now I'm just fixing
the width of the scrollView to
its content size. Now again,
if it gets too big, this,
this constraint is gonna lose,
cuz it's low priority.
The other place I need
to do it is, obviously,
when I first set up
the image down here,
when I'm first setting all
these content size and
all that. So right here
I'm gonna be careful and
optionally chain in case this
gets called during a prepare.
Might, get, do that and then
the, I have the content size,
actually, in a local
variable here, size,
from setting these things up
here. Okay. And that's it.
So let's go see if this is
enough to make this work. And
controlling your constraints
from code, I'm gonna show you
another example. I'm not gonna
actually do the other example,
cuz I don't wanna,
I don't have time in the demo
to show you things twice. But,
we'll see another place where
it would make sense
in this very app. So
here I'm going to drag in,
it's sizing it to this size,
now watch, I'm going to
zoom in, the scroll view
is staying the size of it's
content size. I'm sorry,
you guys can't see, recall,
always remind me of that,
because it's hard for me to
remember that. So what I did,
I dragged this in,
started here, and
now I just shrink it down and
you can see that the scroll
views' bounds are staying
hooked to its contents.
And even if I make it very
large, now the scroll view's
bounds are way bigger
than the borders but
those other constraints
are higher priority.
So the scroll view is
actually, you can see it
the scroll view indicator's
there on the right edge,
it's actually staying
inside the bounds. Okay. So
pretty simple, cool fix for
keeping this thing centered
right here. All right so
that's that little trick to
get back to our code and start
talking about our collection
view, here it is. So we're
gonna add that collection view
along the top that just has
a bunch of emoji that we're
going to use to drag in to our
little UI. And how are we
gonna do that? Well, it's
pretty easy actually. Let's
start in the storyboard. And
here's our, this is where
we're gonna be adding it.
Right here,
same place we just were. Now,
one thing about when you're
manipulating your views,
there's a really strong
tendency to dive right in here
to these things and just
start grabbing the handles.
Grab this, like I wanna put
this collectionView on top, so
I really just wanna
grab this handle and
pull it down to make room. But
you cannot do that. Because
you have constraints that are
holding that thing to the top.
And if you just start
dragging it down,
all your constraints
are gonna turn red and
yellow Things like
this can be terrible.
So if you really want to pull
that down, you've gotta unhook
it first. And really, this
requires you go a little bit
slower on your kind of editing
to think ahead, am I going to
have to unhook something? So
we definitely have to unhook
this top connection
here of the drop zone
to the top of the view,
because we're gonna put
a a collection view in
between there, all right?
So where is that connection
to the top? I've got the drop
zones collect, selected
here in the outline, and
here we got right here. Align
top to the safe area, I'm just
going to delete that. Now it's
no longer hooked to the top.
Now I can safely drag it down
to make room for my collection
view. And eventually I'm gonna
put my collection view in and
put a constraint that hooks
the collection view in.
All right, so how do we get
a collection view? We just go
down here and search for
collection view, this is the,
you know, pre-packaged MVC but
I already got my MVC so
I just want this one which
is the collection view.
We're gonna drop it in here.
Let's go ahead and
do its constraints. So I want
it hooked right up to the top,
I want it right to the left,
right to the right.
I actually want some standard
spacing here to the bottom
which I'm hoping it's going to
say it's nearest neighbor is
that drop zone.
So let's try that.
Looks like it worked, but
what happened to my collection
view? It disappeared. Why did
my collection disappear?
Let's look at its constraints.
Here's its constraints. It's
got the trailing, leading,
bottom space to the drop zone,
top to the safe area. What's
the height of the collection
view? Not specified, right?
It's like zero.
We never set the height.
Now, what do we want
the height to be?
Actually we want the height
to kind of be big enough to
include those emoji and want
those emoji to be whatever
size the user's accessibility
font is, right?
That's what we really want.
I don't have time to show you
that but you know what you
need to know to make that work
because what we would do is
create the height constraint
in here. And then wire
it up into our code and
then we would set it based on
the size that is necessary to
fit the font,
the accessibility font.
But in this case what we're
going to do is we're just
going to fix its height.
So I'm gonna go here.
I've got the collection view
selected. Oops wrong one.
I'm gonna go here and
fix its height.
I'm gonna fix its height to
be about 80 points high or
so. 80 points is enough to
make an emoji that kinda fits
under your finger nicely and
it's a good default size.
So there's my collection
view reappearing. Another
thing we wanna do is set the
size of these cells. Cuz we're
gonna have a bunch of cells
in our collection view,
that's what a collection view
is a bunch of cells in there.
Remember from the food demos,
all the food things?
So you do that by
inspecting the collection
view under the size inspector
over here. And you can see our
cell size is 50 by 50, I'm
gonna make it a little bigger.
Let's go whoops, 80 by 80.
And there's one other thing we
wanna do about this collection
view, is that we want it
be scrollable horizontally.
We want all those emojis to
be falling off to the right,
or to the side of the screen.
We don't want them
going down, so I'm gonna go
back to the normal inspector
collection view and make sure
that my scroll direction is
horizontal. So that it's
scrolling horizontally.
In collection view,
you can only scroll in
one of two directions,
either vertically or
horizontally.
It doesn't do them both. The
other thing about collection
view, very important to
understand, never make your
cell size bigger than
the non-scrollable width or
height of the collection view.
Collection view does not
know how to have cells that
are bigger than will fit in
the direction it doesn't
scroll. So you have to ensure,
like in your homework
you're gonna be making your
cells different sizes, make
sure you make it bigger than
the width of
the collection view.
It doesn't really know how to
deal with that. So this is
nice now. These cells are just
gonna have an emoji in them,
remember? So let's go ahead
and put a UI label in there so
we can put our emoji in there.
We'll just put this in here.
Let's go ahead and just do,
how about vertically and
horizontally centered? Let's
make the font a lot bigger,
although I'm gonna
set the font in code,
again because I want it to be
accessibility friendly there,
but just so that it looks
nice in my storyboard,
I'll set it to 64 points,
nice and big. And then I'm
also going to put just a nice
little smiley face or
something in there.
So, again, this is mostly,
I'm doing this just so
it looks nice in
the storyboard, right here.
So, I can kind of imagine
what my thing is gonna,
look like right here. Now,
let's go to our code and start
loading up this collection
view with some emoji.
All right, let's go over here.
Let's bring up our code,
we have to create an outlet to
it of course. So let's go down
there, right before all
our drop business and
we'll put our collection
view stuff here.
So I'm just gonna Control drag
from the collection view into
my code, make sure that it's
in the collection view, it is.
I'm gonna call it, I'll call
it emojiCollectionView.
So there's my
emojiCollectionView.
Now whenever you wire up
a collection view like this,
where you've dropped
it in to a MVC,
the very first thing you're
gonna wanna do. All the time,
is go and do didSet. And
set you new collection view's
data source,
To be yourself and
the emoji collection view's
delegate to be yourself.
Now if you do that prepackaged
collection view thing where
you get the whole MVC it
will do this for you.
But if you drag your
own collection view in
your definitely wanna do this,
and of course it's complaining
that I don't implement those
protocols so we'll go up to
the top and say.
UICollectionViewDataSource,
and UICollectionViewDelegate.
And
by the way, while you're here
you probably also want to do
UICollectionViewDelegateFlowL-
ayout.
This one you automatically
get to be if you're
the CollectionViewDelegate.
This is the delegate
of the thing that does all
that text-like flowing layout.
Remember the collection's
layout is completely
configurable? But this is the
default one so I usually throw
this in here, too. It just
helps with escape completion,
and all those kinda things.
Now it's complaining because
I don't implement one of these
protocols. Let's find out
which one. It's the one
UICollectionViewDataSource.
I don't implement that.
It has required methods in its
protocol, even though it's
an Objective-C protocol.
Let's see what they are.
I'm gonna hit Fix and
it added them for me right
at the top of my file.
I'm gonna move them, but the
two are numberOfItemsInSection
and cellForItemAt.
Of course, those are two of
the three we talked about.
The other was
number of sections.
We don't have to implement
that because it defaults to
one. That's true for
tableView, true for
collectionView as well. So
I'm gonna move these back down
here where the rest of my
collectionView stuff is, and
we're gonna implement those.
So we need a model for
this part of our MVC. And
I have this as my model, which
is an array of emojis strings
so I actually took a string
of emojis and I mapped it
to an array of strings.
Hopefully everybody's
getting comfortable with map.
Map just takes a collection
and turns it into an array
where it executes this closure
on each of the items. So
now emojis if you look at its
type is array of string, and
each string is one emoji.
Okay, so how many items do I
have in my only section? Well,
of course, it's the number of
emojis. That's how many items
there are in the collection
view. I only have one section,
and that brings us down here
to the all-important sell for
item at where we
have to let some
cell =
collectionView.dequeueReusabl-
eCell with ReuseIdentifier,
right? And we're gonna have to
specify something. I'll call
it an EmojiCell, and for
index path. There that's
the index path we're creating
the cell for. And we're
gonna use the return cell.
Now we need to load up
this emoji into that cell.
And for collection view, all
the cells are custom cells.
You have to have a subclass
of, if you're gonna have any
outlets to anything,
you have to have a subclass.
Because we couldn't have
an outlook in our collection
view itself that
pointed to the emoji
because there could be
a hundred cells. And so
we just can't do it, and so
instead, we have to go and
create a new file, which is a
subclass of UI collection view
cell. This one is actually
on the right one.
I'm gonna call this an emoji
collection view cell, right?
Subclass of UI collection view
cell. So it was created here,
let's put it in the right
place. Okay, here it is,
right here. I'm gonna mutely
go to my story board,
where's my story board?
Here it is, and I'm going
to inspect this cell. And
I'm gonna set its reuse
identifier to emoji cell,
that was the thing I dequeue,
whatever,
do reusable cell with, and
I'm gonna set its identity to
be an emoji collectivity cell.
All right? So this cell is
of type my subclass, and
its identifier of this cell,
didn't I type that in there?
Emoji cell? Emoji cell,
that's its type.
All right, so now that we have
this, let's go ahead and wire
up this little label where
we're gonna put the emoji to
that custom cell. Now, a lot
of times, Interface Builder
will not get this right,
but it did this time.
Where if you go to
automatic mode,
it kinda realizes that that
thing that you have selected,
could be hooked up
to the controller,
if there were just one of them
or more likely, it's hooked up
to this custom cell. So you
don't have to use automatic,
you could use manual and
go find the file. But
automatic sometimes will work,
sometimes not. So here we go.
We've got this label. I'm just
going to create an outlet to
it in my custom subclass,
so here we go. And
then there into UI label,
I'll call it Label.
It's this cell's label and
that's it. Now,
I'm not putting any other code
in here, but I could. It would
no be not unreasonable to put
a bunch of logic in your cell.
If you have logic that is per
cell. Then putting it here
could make a lot of sense.
Just because this one
only has an outlet,
it's a very, very simple cell,
doesn't mean you couldn't put
other code in there. I don't
want you to get the idea these
are only outlet bags, they
actually could have logic in
them if it made sense as well.
Probably will make sense in
your homework test logic in
your cells. All right?
So we've got this cell. So
let's go back now to our
place where we're creating
this cell. And we've got this
dequeued reusable cell. For
us to access the outlets
of it, we have to cast it.
We have to say, if let
emojiCell equal the cell,
as our custom subclass,
EmojiCollectionViewCell.
And if we can successfully
cast it, then we can tell
the emojiCell label, okay, to
set its attributed text equal
to something, text, so
what is that something?
Well, that something is gonna
be taking one of these,
whatever thing is at
this index path, and
set its font cuz I wanna
control its font in code and
then put it in there. So
I'm just gonna let text equals
NSAttributedString. The string
of it is going to be
the emojis sub indexPath dot
item, that tells us which
emoji we're talking about
here. And the attributes,
I'm going to just set
the attributes of the font,
that's the only attribute I'm
gonna set. I'm gonna set it to
this var font, which I'm
gonna create up here,
private var font, which
is gonna be a UIFont. And
I'm going to do the whole
accessibility thing here.
Which is, I have to use
UIFontMetrics, all right? And
I want the font metrics for
the text style, dot body. And
I'm going to scale the font.
Scale font for,
and the font I'm
gonna use is UI font,
preferred font body, but
I'm going to scale it up.
I'll say it with size,
it's a little easier,
with size 64. So I want 64
point, but I'm gonna have it
scaled by whatever the
accessibility thing is, right?
So if your accessibility is
in the middle, size of font,
I'm gonna do 64 to
make it bigger,
it'll be bigger in 64 and
smaller.
Now, this is not going to work
well right now because I don't
change the collection view's
size. So if I set this big,
it's gonna be cut off, and
if I set it really small,
the collection view won't
shrink up to kinda hold it,
do you see what I'm saying? Do
you see what I mean by that?
So we'd have to add
that later, but again,
I don't wanna show
you hooking up
to a layout constraint twice.
So that's it. This is
all we need to do to get our
collection view loaded up.
We implemented those
data source methods
that are required, right?
Number of sections,
number of rows, items in
section and then the cell, for
a certain one. And so let's go
over here, so you can see. And
sure enough, along the top,
we can see right there that we
have our emojis. It's really
nice scrolls. The collection
view is a scroll view, so
it's scrolling back and forth,
it's very nice. Now,
the next thing we wanna do
is be able to pick these
things up and drop them in our
nice background, like if
this is our background here,
we wanna pick these things up.
Remember, I dropped the bees
in there, the apple, or
whatever. We wanna do that. So
how are we gonna do drag and
drop? Well, we haven't done
drag yet, we only did drop,
the only thing we've done
is dropping in there.
So I'm gonna show you drag in
collection view's world, which
looks almost exactly as same
as non collection view world.
The only difference
between drag in collection
view world is,
collection view helps you out
with which index path are you
dragging. It knows where your
finger is, and it's like,
you're dragging that index
path and you're dropping it at
that index path, so really
just providing index path but
otherwise, it's pretty much
exactly the same. All right,
any time you wanna do dragging
in a collection view,
the first thing you're always
gonna do, just like you
do a drop interaction is
the first time you do drag and
drop with a view,
with a collection view,
you're gonna set your
collection view's drag
delegate to be your self.
And then, of course, that's,
you're gonna go up here and
you're gonna say, yes,
I implement the UI collection
view drag delegate. And
as soon as you do that, it's
gonna complain, no, you don't,
and you're gonna click on
this and it's gonna say,
do you want me to add
the protocol stuff?
And you're gonna say, yeah,
sure, what do I need to do?
And it's gonna say, you
have to implement items for
beginning. If you remember
from the lecture, items for
beginning is the thing that
tells the drag system,
here's what we're dragging.
So we have to provide these
drag items to drag. So let's
do that, let's move this down
again. And in here,
so what're,
how are we gonna provide our
items for beginning? Now,
notice the collection view
one has add index path, so
it tells us which thing, which
IndexPath we are dragging
from, which is really,
really convenient for us. So
I'm gonna create, I'm gonna
call a little function here.
I'm just gonna return
dragItems at indexPath.
This is a function I'm
gonna have to write,
private func dragItems
at indexPath,
which is an indexPath, which
is just the section, an item.
And it returns this
array of UIDragItem,
those are the items that
we have to return. So
this all we have to do to get
started with drag. And for us,
again, it's really, really
easy to implement this because
what we're going to drag
Is NSAttributedString,
that's what we're gonna drag,
that's an item provider
just like NSURL,
UIImage, NSAttributedString.
Also, NSString we
could, do but we're gonna do
NSAttributedString, gives us
a little more flexibility for
what we're dragging around. So
that's going to be
our item provider.
So all we have to do is get
the attributedString we want
to drag and then return
it in the drag item and
that's it. So how do we
get that attributedString?
So I'm gonna say, if I can
let the attributedString =,
and what I'm gonna have to do
is look at this indexPath,
find my custom cell,
look at its outlet, get its
attributedText. Everybody cool
with that? That's how I'm
gonna do this. So let's do
this all in one line of code,
right? So I'm going to first
ask my CollectionView for
the cell for
this item at indexPath.
Now this is like
TableView's cell for
row at indexPath.
Thing, this only works for
visible cells but, of course,
that's going to work here.
I'm dragging this thing, it's
got to be visible, right? So
I've got this cell that we're
dragging from right here.
Now I'm going to as it to
be my custom subclass.
And if that works, hopefully
it will, I'm gonna get its
outlet, and I'm gonna
grab its attributedText.
So if all that works, I just
grabbed the emoji at that
indexPath. So
now that I have the emoji,
all I need to do is create
one of these UI drag items,
using that attributedString
as the provider, right?
The thing that
provides the data. So
I can do that by saying
let dragItem = UIDragItem.
And the drag item creator,
you can see it right there,
takes an ItemProvider. And we
can create an ItemProvider for
an attributedString by
saying ItemProvider.
And it has a few constructors
but a really nice one is this
one object where you just
give it an object and
it knows how to be
provider like a UIImage or
NSAttributedString.
So that's what I'm gonna do.
And I'm gonna give it this
attributedString that I found
in my cell. And that's it.
This creates the drag item,
and now we just return this.
We return an array of them,
but we're only dragging
this one thing. But
before I return it,
I'm gonna do one other thing,
I'm gonna set the drag
item's local object
to be that attributedString.
Now what does this mean? Well,
if your drag is local within
your app, you don't have to go
through all that itemProvider
stuff, right? The asynchronous
getting the data from that,
remember all the stuff we
had to do in the drop? You
don't have to do any of that,
you just grab
the local object.
So this is a way of like
short-circuiting all that,
if it's a local drag. But it's
gonna work to actually drag
out of our CollectionView to
other apps, but when we're
dragging locally, we're going
to be able to use this.
So here I'm just gonna return
an array of just this one
drag item. By the way,
if I couldn't
get the attributedString
out of that cell for
some reason. Then I'm just
gonna return empty, so no,
don't do any drag then. So
it's gonna know from this
not to begin a drag. Now,
remember I also told you
that once you start to drag,
you can add more items by just
tapping on them. So you could
be dragging multiple things at
once. That's easy to implement
as well. Just like we have
this items for beginning,
we have another one called
itemsforaddingto, which looks
exactly the same as this.
And we're gonna return exactly
the same thing. Because it's
giving us the indexPath
that someone tapped on
while I was dragging and
I'm just going to get the
emoji out of it and return it,
and this is all that's
required to do the dragging.
Watch this.
I can drag just from that.
Watch, here's the bee
hold down and drag. And
the thing about this is if I'm
dragging, I can't drop in my
CollectionView because I
haven't implemented drop.
But I can drop other places.
I'm going to go over here and
just drop this bee in
the Google search bar.
And it searched for bee,
believe it or not. So that's
pretty cool. So I got dragged
up working to other apps,
so I hardly had to do
anything in my app,
just provide that
attributedString and drag and
drop. So that's one of
the cool thing about drag and
drop, it's so easy to get it
going in both directions. So
now, we want to drop.
Now we want to be able to pick
this bee up right here and
drop it somewhere else in
our CollectionView, so
let's go do that. All right,
so to do the drop part of this
just like we did when we went
to do the drag delegate here,
we have to do
emojiCollectionView.dropDele-
gate = self.
And up to the top, look at how
many protocols we implement.
Woo, we're cruising today.
So let's do
UICollectionViewDropDelegate
and when we do that,
wait for it to compile. It's
gonna complain, it says you
don't implement that protocol.
Sure, fix. And it says, this
one you must implement which
is performDrop. Makes sense,
right, you have to do perform
drop or you're not even in
doing drop. So let's copy and
paste that one down here.
I'm actually gonna implement
perform drop last.
Because there's a couple other
ones that I need to implement,
if you remember from what we
did before? CanHandle and
session moved, the session
updated. Gotta, we can
implement those two so that we
get the right little plus sign
when we're dragging it around.
And so that we don't try and
accept drops that we
don't understand. So
let's do the canHandle. Here's
canHandle's collectionView
version. Calling it canHandle
looks almost exactly the same
and it will be implemented
exactly the same,
which is I'm just gonna say
if the session.canLoadObjects
ofClass NSAttributedString,
then I'm in. Cuz that's what
my CollectionView can accept.
This, by the way, means we're
going to be able to drag
just random strings into
our CollectionView. Not just
emoji, and first I was like,
I don't want that but then I
was like that's kind of cool.
What if I wanted to put
a label on something down in
my picture. So I decided
that's good, so I'm going to
keep doing that. Then we
have the sessiondidupdate,
that we have to do,
sessiondidupdate.
Is that what is called?
DidUpdate, is this the one?
Yes, dropSessionDidUpdate and
what do we need to do in here?
This is where we need to
return that drop proposal,
either copy move or cancel,
that's all we have to do. And
you can see that here it's a
UICollectionViewDropProposal.
And why is that different?
Well, let take a look at it.
Let to return
a UICollectionView,
CollectionViewDropProposal.
[BLANK AUDIO].
And look at the constructors.
And there's another
constructor, second one,
look at that, intent
UICollectionViewDropIntent.
Well, the intent in
a CollectionView says,
are you dropping this
into this cell or
you want to add a cell?
You see the difference?
So that's what we
have to specify.
Now in our case, we always
want to add a cell, so
you'll see that our intent,
let's, sorry,
let's go back and pick that,
we want this constructor.
So the drop operation we're
gonna do it first is copy,
I'm gonna change that
in a second. But
then the drop intent we want
is insertAt destination as
opposed as to insert into
the destination cell. Now,
let's talk about copy. If I'm
moving the bee around inside
my collectionView, I'm not
copying it. And I don't want
the user to think that the bee
is going to now be copied and
there will be two bees.
So it's move.
So I have to know, somehow,
that I am inside my own
CollectionView. Okay, so how
am I going to do that? Well,
what I'm gonna do, what's
this problem by the way?
Just the indexPath. Yeah,
so how I'm gonna do that?
What I'm gonna do is when
I start my drag up here in
itemsForBeginning, I'm gonna
set something in the session
called the localContext, and
this is in any type any.
And I'm gonna set it to be my
collectionView. So this is
just something in the drag
session that lets droppees,
people who have dropped know,
hey,
this is a local drag, and
here's the context of it.
Well,
since this drag is coming
from the collectionView,
I'm gonna use the
collectionView as the context.
All right, so now I can look
at this local context down
here to determine whether
my drag variables should be
a copy or a move.
So I wanna say something like,
let isSelf is myself or
whatever, = the session,
Session, it has a thing called
a local drop DragSession.
That's the session with
discharged it, .localContext,
oops, localContext. I really
wanna say if that = my
collectionView.
This is what I'd like to do,
but I cannot do this because
this, what type is it?
Any, and you cannot do ==
with any, because remember,
the == is just using the
equatable protocol, right? And
any can't have any methods or
vars, it has to be casted to
something before you
can do anything on it.
So you certainly can
have equitable for any,
you can't have anything for
any. So
what I'm gonna do is take
this little thing and
attempt to cast it as
a UICollectionView. I mean if
it's not a UICollectionView
it's not to be equal anyway so
I might as well try it.
Now if that's nil, we can do
equatable with nil because
optional can do equatable,
all right? So now I know
whether it's myself or not.
So if it's myself,
then I'm just gonna do move,
otherwise I'm gonna do copy.
Now I'm not,
I haven't even implemented
performed drop yet.
But let's take a look at what
the collectionView does just
with this small amount
of information from us.
So here's my
collectionView right here,
now watch I'm gonna drag,
click the coffee here.
Look at the collectionView,
look what it's doing,
it's making space for
me to drop in the new spot.
Do you see that? I can still
drop drag over here but
now I'm dragging over here.
And it knows that, I might
be dropping there. And in fact
if I drop, it doesn't work
because I haven't implemented
perform drop. But you
could see the collectionView
is already knowing what I'm
doing. So
collectionView really cool for
doing drag and drop, it's so
powerful. We hardly do any,
we bring four lines of code,
to get this far in the drop.
So let's go back here and
do perform drop.
Well, our string of four lines
that go is going to end,
because perform drop is
a little bit more complicated,
not a lot. But when the
perform drop happens, we have
to update our model, which
is our list of emojis and
we have to update
the collectionView,
all right. Also there's two
different kinds of drops here,
there's the drop where it's
coming from my collectionView.
In which case, I have to
drop in the menu place, and
remove it from the old place
because I'm moving. And then,
there's a dropping it's
coming from some other app.
Which is allowed, watch this,
let's go over here and
select some text.
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Sorry you're not on the
screen? Yeah, thank you.
I will show you this, hide
others. Okay, so I can go over
here, and select this bee, and
drag and drop it over here.
And look, it's saying plus,
and it's making room for it,
and, I didn't do perform drop.
So I have those two cases
to do perform drop.
The local case and Mac case so
let's go do both those cases.
We'll do the local case first.
Now when we drop,
collectionView has
gives us this coordinator.
This coordinator,
I'm gonna make this a little
easier to read because it's so
long the name here, you can
see there's two arguments to
this thing. One, it's just the
collectionView is involved and
the one is this coordinator.
Now this coordinator is gonna
give us all the information we
need to know to do this drop.
The first thing
it's gonna tell us,
the most important thing is
the destinationIndexPath.
Okay, this is obviously
the IndexPath where we're
dropping. And
that = to the coordinator,
destinationIndexPath.
But that might be nil, because
you might be dragging it in
a part of the collectionView
that's not in between any of
the existing cell so
this could be nil. So if that
happens, I'm just gonna create
an IndexPath with item 0 and
section 0. Okay, I could pick
some other IndexPath but
that's what I'm using
my default. Okay, so
now we know where we are
dropping this drop. And now,
it's just a matter
of going through all
these items in
the coordinators items. These
items are UICollectionViewDrop
items and they have some very
interesting pieces
of information.
For example,
if I can let sourceIndexPath
= this item's sourceIndexPath,
then I know that this drag
is coming from myself, and
this is the sourceIndexPath
of it. So I don't even need
to look at the local context
in this case to know this is
coming from me, awesome.
And I know now the source and
the destination,
this is trivial. All I need
to do here is update my model
to have the source going
to the destination.
And then update
the collectionView to removed
the one from the source and
add it to the other one.
So, this is probably the
easiest case, this local case
so let's do it. First,
lets get the attributed string
that we need so I can say,
if I can let the attributed,
this is the attributed string
that we're dragging around.
And luckily, I stashed
it in that local object,
remember that? So I'm gonna
get the drag item, Item and
get it local object. Remember,
I can stashed it in local
object up here when I made the
drag item. I don't have to do
any of that provider stuff to
get it but I am going to have
to say as NSAttributed string
because its in any. So I will
get to the attributed string
which I'm going to be able to
cuz I know I set that. Then I
can put the attributed string
in the new place and move the
other one from the old place.
So here we go, I'm gonna say
emojis, this is my model,
remove at
the sourceIndexPath.item so
remove where the thing
came from. And emojis
insert this attributedString
that's being dragged around
at the destinationIndex
path.item. Voila, I've updated
my model. Okay, I moved b
from one place to the other.
Okay, destinationIndexPath,
Path.
This one probably also
up here, curly brace.
Okay, so now I have to update
the collectionView itself,
which is no,
that's not a curly brace.
What'd I do up there?
Item, yeah, thank you,
item. All right, so
now we've built the model.
Now we're gonna update
the collectionView.
So that's collectionView.
Now I could, one thing
I don't wanna do here,
very important to understand,
don't reload data here.
Do not reload data in the
middle of a drag, because it
resets the whole world, it's
bad, don't do it. So instead,
I gotta remove the rows and
insert the rows separately. So
I'm gonna delete the rows
at the sourceIndexPath. And
then I'm going to,
Insert rows,
InsertItems, sorry,
I keep saying rows,
use the table view at
the destinationIndexPath. Now,
This looks like it's.
Insert items. So this looks
like this would work fine but
actually this would probably
crash your program.
And the reason for that is
when you do multiple. This is
indexpath.string. When you
do multiple changes to your
collection view, each step
would normally have to have
your model completely in sync
which it wouldn't be because
until I do both of these,
the table won't be in
sync with the model. But
there's a really cool
way to get around that,
which is collectionView and
tableView have this method
called performBatchUpdates.
And performBatchUpdates just
has a closure. Inside that
closure, you can put any
number of these delete items,
insert items, move items,
whatever you wanna do. And
it will do them all
as one operation so
that it never gets out
of sync with your model.
See what's happening there?
It also has a nice completion
thing here which we
don't need in this case.
But when it's all done
with all the updates,
it'll call that
completion closer. So
don't forget to do batch
updates if you do multiple
adjustments to your tableView
or collectionView. And
then the last thing we need
to do is ask the coordinator
to do the drop. The reason
we need to do this is,
we need to animate the drop
happening, right there. So
we're gonna do the drop. The
dragItem is the item.dragItem.
And the ItemAt is
the destinationIndexPath. So
that's gonna actually
make the drop happen.
So this is going to animate
and move the bee over.
This is going to, at the same
time, be dropping the thing
that's on your finger is going
to disappear, and the plus
sign will go away, and all
that business. All right, so
let's take a look at this.
All right, here we go.
Now we've only done the local
case, but here it is, the bee,
moving it around and drop.
Woo-hoo, it worked, all right?
This over here, drop. Now this
one over here from outside
is still not gonna work.
Doesn't work because that's
not the local case, right?
So let's do the local case.
All right, so that's the else
of this right here. Yeah,
it's the else of,
not that one, the else of.
This one, the else of
this source index path.
So we don't have a source
index path, which means this
thing comes from somewhere
else, so how we do this?
Now this turns out to be quite
easy to do too amazingly,
but there's a little
problem here.
If you're dragging something
from outside and you drop it,
is that information
immediately available? No,
you have to asynchronously
go fetch it from that thing.
Well, what the heck are you
gonna do with your table
while you're off fetching it?
What if it takes ten seconds?
So
what you do is you put
a placeholder in your table.
And collection view manages
all of that for you, so that
all you have to do is when
the data finally does arrive.
You tell the placeholder,
context it's called.
Okay, I got the info.
Update your model, and
it'll automatically swap out
the placeholder cell for
one of your cells that matches
the kind of data you have. So
let's see how we do that.
We do this by creating
a placeholder context.
This is a thing that's gonna
manage that placeholder. And
placeholderContext, you
get from the coordinator,
oops, coordinator,
by asking it to drop the item
to a placeholder. You see
the second initializer there,
dropped item to a placeholder.
So I'm gonna do this one. So
the item I'm gonna drag
is the item.drag item.
Remember, we're still in this
for loop where we're dropping,
cuz we could be dropping
multiple items.
So we're dropping them one
by one. So that's what we're
dragging. And then here's
the placeholder right here.
So I gotta create
one of these.
Let me make this a little more
readable for you here. Okay,
let me put this on another
line. All right, so I've gotta
create a UIDropPlaceholder.
And to do that, I, it needs to
know where you're gonna
insert the placeholder. And
then it has a reuseIdentifier,
and I'm gonna talk about that
in a second. So let's put
the insertionPathIndex to be,
obviously the destination.
Okay. Where
we're putting this in. That's
this thing we calculated right
at the beginning up here.
That's the destination. And
look at this reuse identifier.
What the heck is that?
Well you get to decide
what kind of cell
is the placeholder. It doesn't
put some prepackaged one in.
You get to decide. So this
is asking you for the reuse
identifier in your storyboard
to use to create that thing.
So I'm gonna call mine
DropPlaceholderCell.
I can call it anything I want.
This is just the string that
I'm gonna use in my storyboard
to create this thing. Now
what's interesting also is you
can also include at the end of
this a closure. And in that
closure you can basically,
initialize this cell or do the
same kinda thing you would do,
where you do the
dequeueReusableCell, because
that dequeueReusableCell's
never gonna be called. This is
the placeholder cell, it's
not gonna call that thing. So
here you could do the same
kinda setup if you had outlets
in your cell, or whatever,
you could set them all up.
We're not gonna have
any outlets in our, so
we're not gonna do it, but
that's where you would do it.
So did I remember, so I just
wanna make sure we got this
all right, no errors. So let's
go back to our storyboard and
make that placeholder cell.
The way you make a cell
in a collection view,
you just select
the collection view and
go over to inspect it. And the
very first thing is the items,
and I want from one item
to two items. Okay, and
it makes a second item right
here. And I'm gonna go make
sure I say it's not an emoji
cell, it's a drop placeholder
cell. That's how I'm linking
it to that line of code I
just wrote. Its type doesn't
have to be emoji collection
view cell because it's not
gonna have the emoji in there.
So I'm gonna make it just be
a normal UI collection view
cell. Nothing special, and it
doesn't need this little label
on the inside because
it's a place holder for
the label, that information
hasn't arrived yet. So
instead I'm gonna put an
activity indicator in there.
So it's spinning there,
letting the user know I'm
waiting on some dropped data.
So I'm gonna put it in there.
Let's go ahead and center it.
And let's yeah,
that's probably good enough.
And let's make it so
it starts off animating. So,
I'm gonna click it right here.
So it starts off animate,
so I don't even have to tell
it to animate. All right,
all that. And
what are we using here? Emoji,
I thought I changed that,
I guess not. Yeah.
Didn't I change that already?
I did. Placeholder cell.
So now that we have this setup
for this placeholder cell,
we go back here to our Code.
No, not there. Down here.
Okay, and we've got this nice
placeholder ready to go.
All we need to do now
is go get the data.
And when it arrives, we just
tell the placeholder context,
here's the,
go swap them out and
here's my model change.
So, I'm gonna get the data
a little differently
than we got before.
Last time we used that
method's load objects,
plural, on session to load up
the objects, remember that?
When we dropped
the image in there.
This time I am just gonna grab
one thing, not load objects,
but grab one object
that was in my item.
So I'm gonna say here
item.dragItem.itemProvider.
So this is the item provider,
that thing that's provided
me the item, provides it
asynchronously because it's
outside of my app.
Load object,
I'm gonna say of class,
I want an NSAttributedString.
And it gives it back to
me asynchronously with
the provider. That's gonna be
the attributed string, and
also possibly and error, which
we're gonna ignore the error.
You can look at the
documentation to see what kind
of errors you can get.
But you can imagine right,
errors providing this data.
Now
this particular closure is not
executed on the main queue. So
this one we need
to unfortunately
say DispatchQueue.main.async
if we wanna do anything,
to our UI which we do.
What we're gonna do here,
is we are going to change our
model which are gonna cause
some UI stuff to happen.
Now, it could be actually that
the change in this would not
affect the UI directly cuz
we're only changing our model.
But the problem is we're gonna
do it in the context of asking
the placeholder to
replace that cell, and
that's certainly gonna cause
UI. So how do we do this?
We just say
placeholderContext.commitInse-
rtion of my data. And
this right here is
the insertionIndexPath,
and here is the code to fix
my model, and that's it.
This is all we need to do and
it will automatically
replace that placeholder with
a cell by calling your normal
self or item at methods.
Notice that this
insertionIndexPath might
be different than this
destinationIndexPath.
Why? Because this might have
taken ten seconds, not likely,
but it might have. So it might
have changed other things in
the collection view might
have been going on. Okay, and
new cells adding, other things
came faster whatever. So
always use the insertion index
here, and you're only using it
to update your model. So
how do I update my model here?
Well that's my emojis.insert
the thing that
came back which is this
provider as an attribute
of strings. So let's say if
we can let attributedString
= provider as
an NSAttributedString.
Okay, then we can do this.
So, insert that
attributedString at
the insertionIndexPath.item.
That updates our model,
this thing handles the rest.
You don't have to
do anything else,
you don't have to do
any inserting rows,
any of that business. Yeah,
this is attribution.string,
cuz we have just strings in
our model, not attributive
strings. And of course
we need you to do self.,
right here because we're
inside a closure. Now if for
some reason you couldn't get
that attributedString from
the provider,
maybe there's an error
instead. Then you wanna let
the placeholderContext know
to delete that placeholder.
Because you couldn't get
the other string after all, so
you go, and that's it. So
all you have to do to accept
stuff into a collectionView
from somewhere else. So
let's see this in action
right here. So we
haven't hopefully broken our
local. Nope, still working,
and hopefully where you can
get our bee and drop it in,
here we go. Woo-hoo,
we got a bee, now our font is
really big, so we can't see it
we'd probably wanna have our
font self-adjust or whatever.
But this is, you know, just
like anything from now we can
move this around, it's part of
our collectionView etc. So
that's collectionView drag and
drop start to finish not
really that complicated it's
actually they did a pretty
good job. Now the next thing
we wanna do is to drag these
things into our image, right?
We have our, oops let me go
back to in my images here,
and, where's my
favorite image?
And well, pick some
random image here we go.
All right, so
I have my image here, and
we want to be able to pick
up an apple and put it
under the tree. So how are we
gonna do that drag and drop?
Well, we just, all we need to
do is implement dropping of
NSAttributedStrings in our
EmojiArtView. That's all you
need to do and it's so simple
let's do that quickly here as
time is running out. So, let's
go to our emoji art view so
here's our EmojiArtView,
it kind of looks very
simplistic at this point.
And I'm going to add or
drop interaction to it,
init's initializers. So
I have this nice thing I type
which is the template for
having UI view initializers.
Remember you have to override
both these inits,
remember that? And
then I have this nice setup,
so in the setup right here,
I'm just going to add
interaction. And remember I'm
in the UI view now, so
I'm adding it to myself.
UIDropInteraction with
the delegate being myself,
now I'm
a UIDropInteractionDelegate.
I also have a nice
little thing here,
dropstubs that just
gives me the stubs for
the three methods canHandle,
didUpdate, performDrop,
you should be used to
this now. Same as we
had in the collection view but
these are the non-collection
versions. And
so what do I do in canHandle?
I just say whether I
can load the objects of
the right class in this case
attributedStrings. And what
do I do in sessionDidUpdate?
I have to return a drop
proposal, here I'm always
gonna allow dropping
an attributedString. And it's
always gonna be a copy because
I'm not gonna move things
inside myself with drag and
drop. I'm gonna move them
directly, so I'll always do
copy here, and then finally I
just have to load objects
of a certain class.
NSAttributed strings
of course, and
this is the list of attributed
strings, the item providers
are attributed strings. And
here I just need to add these
things to my view as sub
views add labels, sub view.
So, I'm gonna do this with
a little function here,
add label,
then I'm gonna write.
And it's going to get
the attributed strings so
let's get the attributedString
that we need out of here.
Actually I also need to
know where to drop it so
let's get the drop
point by saying Mr.
Session, drag session,
what is the location of this
drag in my coordinate system.
So I'm just finding out
where this thing is dropped
I obviously need to know,
where it's dropped to be able
to do it. So, then let's add
all the things that dropped by
doing a little for loop for
attributedString in
the providers as?,
an array of attributedString,
which it should be. But maybe
you didn't know you could
do this, but you can say as
an array right in the middle
of a four loop like this. And
in fact, you can even say if
that for some reason is nil,
cuz you can't as it,
then just use an empty array,
right here. Okay, that's kind
of a cool trick. All right,
so we're gonna add a label
with the attributedString,
we're doing this for each one.
And we're going to have it be
centered at the dropPoint,
So we
have write this method ourself
to do that private func, this
is an easy one, addLabel(with
attributedString:,
of type NSAttributedString,
centeredAt point: CGPoint).
I'm just gonna create
a UILabel. I'm
going to set its
backgroundColor to clear, =
clear, Cuz I want you know my
image to show through around
the edges of it I don't want
a big white background or
something. I"m gonna set the
attributedText obviously to
be this attributedString
that was passed in.
I'm going to size to fit it,
okay I don't want that label
to be some large random size.
I'm going to what else am
I gonna do? Yes I'm going
to position it, label.center
= drop point right there, and
of course I have to addSubView
to myself. That's it.
Let's do it. All right,
let's go get an image.
Did I lose my favorite image?
No, my favorite- there it is.
This is my favorite image
right here. Okay, so
I've got my image right here,
we can zoom in and out.
We can pick up a bee, and drop
the bee. Pick up another bee,
drop the bee. Maybe we'll put
an apple down here. Now of
course we want to be able
to resize these things, and
move them around, right? So,
I don't wanna waste your time.
That's just Jack doing
some gesture recognizers.
I have put those in
a little file right here.
So let's just throw those in.
And
you can go look at those
later at your leisure,
it's really, it's very simple.
Gesture recognizers tap and
pinch and pan, things like
that. And all we need do is to
turn that on, let's just go
down here and say addEmoji
GestureRecognizers to
that label, so
that just adds these
recognizers to the label.
Okay, so
let's see that in action.
Let's just get this out here,
drag this in. Now,
we drag a bee down here.
Drag another bee, this is
what I was doing at the very
beginning to demonstrate this.
And then we can tap on them
and make those bigger,
tap on them and
make them smaller.
We can even zoom way in,
before we make some really
small, take like apple put it
down here. Make it
very very small, right?
And then we zoom back out. It
will be a tiny little apple,
etc.. Now, I'm going
to back to the slides.
Like I say,
when I finish the slides,
we're not gonna be able to do
the text demo because we have
this midterm coming in. But
that's pretty much all we need
to do to make this collection
view, do full drag and
drop and all, so it's quite,
quite straightforward.
And hopefully
it'll make sense.
If you have any
questions about it,
Piazza is a great place
to ask. All right,
let's go back to our slides
and talk about UITextField.
All right, UITextField it's
a lot like UILabel and
you might just think,
it's just an editable UILabel.
It's a little more complicated
than that, but not much more.
One thing to really think
about conceptionally
UITextField is having editable
text fields, especially on
the iPhone, is not a very good
UI. And it's really easy to
fall in the trap of throwing
text fields into your UI and
thinking, well, this is
a great UI for doing this.
Because you're running
in the simulator and
you gotta keyboard.
You're just typing away
in those text fields,
hitting return, going to
the next section, whereas,
the poor user is like,
my thumb's like,
it's another dam text field,
I hate them. So it's not
a primary input source.
If you can find a way to let
them choose from a list or
otherwise input the data
without having to type things,
it's better.
Now on the iPad it's not so
bad, at least the keyboard
is quite large,
it's much more accessible,
people can put it down and
use two hands. So it's not
quite as bad on an iPad,
but on an iPhone,
don't get fooled.
And I see a lot of you doing
this in your final projects.
You submit these projects to
us that are just like, my god,
this is almost unusable.
Because we will be testing all
your final projects
on devices.
We won't be in the simulator
and be able to type away.
So think about that from your
users, whether a text field's
what you want. Once you've
decided you want a text field,
here's how it works. So a text
field is something that,
obviously, throws
a keyboard up and
lets you enter text. One thing
to notice about the keyboard,
is there's no keyboard
object or anything,
anywhere in iOS.
So the keyboard coming up
happens because an object
becomes the first responder.
So the first responder is the
thing that gets the keyboard
events from the keyboard. And
as soon as something becomes
first responder,
it starts getting keyboard and
the keyboard will appear, all
right? So becomeFirstResponder
is a message you can
send to text field and
it will cause it to be
the first responder,
which will cause
the keyboard to come up. And
similarly, if you send it
resignFirstResponder it will
stop being the first responder
and the keyboard will go away.
So that is how you make the
keyboard come and go in iOS,
is by making things become and
resignFirstResponder. So
that's important to
understand about keyboards.
One thing about text field
that's totally different than
the label,
is that it has a delegate.
And that its delegate is the
primary way you interact with
the text field.
As supposed to a label,
label don't even have
a delegate. You just ask for
its text and set its values
and that's it. Whereas since
a text field is editable, as
things are being edited like
a selections changing, or
someone types something new,
you can find out about all
of those things going on.
And another example is a lot
of times in the keyboard,
when the user hits the return
key in the keyboard,
you want the keyboard
to go away, right? So,
textFieldShouldReturn right
there, is a method that gets
called when the Return key is
pressed. And inside there,
you very likely wanna say,
resignFirstResponder, and that
will cause the keyboard to go
away. So that's an example of
what you can do with
the delegate. Another really
important delegate method
is textFieldDidEndEditing.
This gets called when it
resigns first responder.
So if someone is editing in
your text field and they touch
on another text field,
you'll resign first responder.
So if you wanna look at
the text at that point,
you're gonna wanna implement
this delegate method.
Now having said that,
text field is a UI control.
So it does have target
action and you can control,
drag it and have it send
certain target action messages
on certain activities
happening in the text field.
And some time people hook it
up that way without doing
the delegate thing.
But you kinda
need to know this delegate
because you need to know what
it's capable of doing. So
you'll definitely wanna look
up the UITextField Delegate
protocol, and see what are all
the things you can find out
about what's happening when
editing is happening in
a text field. All right,
the keyboard, so since there's
no keyboard object in iOS,
what if you want to
configure the keyboard like,
set what,
whether it does autocorrect.
Right, how it does all
that annoying autocorrect?
I didn't say annoying.
It does autocorrect and
you don't want it to do that
because it doesn't make sense
in your text field,
you can turn that off. But
you do all that by talking to
the text field, not by talking
to the keyboard. Anybody who
puts up a keyboard is going to
implement this protocol
called UITextInputTraits, and
it has all these
keyboard activities. And
it's that guy's responsibility
to get the keyboard to do
the right thing.
The keyboard also has in the
text input traits protocol, it
also has input accessory view
which lets you put a little
view on the keyboard, right at
the top of the keyboard. So if
you had some special buttons
or something you want, you can
put them in there, so that's
kinda cool, all right? Now,
one thing, I'm not gonna even
talk about this slide yet, but
later in the quarter, I will.
But I'm putting it up here for
reference, you can go back and
look at it. It's important to
understand that when
the keyboard comes up,
it covers up your views,
right? The keyboard does not
move things out of the way
normally, it comes up.
Now, there are some classes
like the UITableViewController
bundle, right, the thing that
you can drag out and get
a whole UITableViewController
with the table view,
that does. That will scroll
things up out of the way
of the keyboard. But normally,
the keyboard just comes up,
and your stuff is behind it.
And I'll tell you another huge
problem with final projects is
people who've only run them
in the simulator, and
when you run on a device and
you press on a text field,
the keyboard comes up and
covers that text field. And
so you can't even enter any
information in that text
field. That's extremely common
and we will, basically, not
be able to test certain parts
of your app because we can't
even type in, to a text field.
So it is your responsibility
to move things out of the way.
Now, when I talk
about NSNotification,
hopefully next week,
I will tell you how to find
out that the keyboard has
come up, where its come up.
And then you can
react by moving
your UI out of the way,
hopefully by scrolling it in
scroll view, but you might
have to do it some other way.
There's a lot of other stuff
in text field, you can look in
the documentation for. You've
already seen like the auto
shrink of UI label. Text
field has that as well and
you can control it like
setting the minimum font size,
and stuff like that. When
you click in the text field,
do you want it to clear out
the text that used to be in
there and start afresh?
Or do you want it
to leave the text that
used to be in there?
Those kinds of things, you
can do all that. It has some
little accessory views that
you can put on the left and
right. It is a pretty
powerful little object. So
coming up now is gonna be this
demo, but again we have to get
out of here because of
this mid-term coming.
So we'll be doing that, on
Monday, your homework five is
out, it's posted already. It's
essentially to do your own
collection view and
table view, all right?
With some drag and
drop, of course, and
with a little UI text field as
well. If you wanna wait until
I do the demo on Monday to
do the text field part,
it's a very minor part of the
assignment, you could do that.
You could just do the rest of
the assignment. I know you all
like to get started on your
assignments early. But if you
do your whole assignment
before Monday, except for
that, that's fine. And then
on Tuesday you could work on
the text field, it's not
a huge part of the assignment.
Again, no more Friday
sections. And then next week,
I'll be talking about the
final project requirements,
and we'll also be talking
about persistence.
We have this nice
emoji art thing, but
as soon as I quit my app and
start it again,
I lost all my work. So we're
gonna fix that next week and
learn how to make things
persist, between launching of
the app. And that's
a fairly small topic, so
we'll actually be doing some
other stuff as well next week.
And then your
final assignment,
assignment number six will
probably go out next Wednesday
and be due the next Wednesday.
And then no more
assignments the rest of the
quarter because you'll have
your final project. So your
final project is a three week
long thing, so you won't have
any homework during the time
you're working on your final
project. All right? That's it.
I will see you next Monday.
For
more, please visit
us at stanford.edu.