[MUSIC]
>> Stanford University.
>> All right, welcome to
lecture number 13 Stanford
CS193P fall of 2017 and
18. So we have a very which
demo today, I've actually kind
of compressed it ciz I really
need to get to the slides,
very important topic which
is persistance. And so
let me just dive
right into that demo,
and then we'll get to
persistence right after that.
So the demo here is I'm
gonna take our emoji art and
add a little way to make
a text field appear
up in our little collection
view that slides around, so
we can add more emoji to that
little sliding thing. So
how are we going to do that?
Well to make this go quicker,
here's our emoji as we
left it off last time. But
I've made a couple of little
changes here. I've added two
collection view cells.
You see them right here,
this one with the plus button.
This is just a UI button,
right here and then this one
has got a UI text field.
That's what this little,
I don't know if you can see
the light gray in there, but
this is a text
field inside here.
That's the only thing that's
in these new cells, and each
of these cells, of course,
I gave it an identifier.
This one's called
an AddEmojiButtonCell,
and this one's called
a EmojiInputCell.
This cell is just a standard
UI collection view cell.
So if I look at it right here,
you can see that its class is
just UI collection view cell.
But this one is a special
text field collection view
cell. A subclass of collection
view cell that handles this
text field a little bit.
And so we're gonna go take a
look at the code from that and
actually add a little bit of
extra code to that, cuz I want
to show you just a kind of
a trickier way to do things.
That's not tricky, but it's
a really valuable way that,
that's a little bit advanced,
so
I wanted to make sure you
learn that. All right, so
I have these two new cells.
Let's take a look at this code
for the text field, collection
view cell, that is right here,
it's a very very simple cell,
it just has an outlet
to that text field
you saw right there.
Now notice when
my outlet is set,
I immediately set that
outlet's delegate to my, me,
myself. And
I'm a UITextFieldDelegate.
Okay remember the slides
from last time. And
so I only implemented one
delegate method here which is
textfieldShouldReturn and
what it does, when you press
the return key on
the keyboard, it resigns first
responder, which means it
stops using the keyboard. And
the keyboard disappears. So if
you don't do this little thing
right here, then when you
press Return on the keyboard,
the keyboard stays up. Okay
and the cursor keeps blinking.
Here it caused it to go away.
And we're gonna add another
delicate method here
in a second. So now,
remember that I have these
two cells right here, right?
The emoji button one and then
the input cell right there. So
now, let's go back to our
emoji art controller code and
look how I dealt with this,
how I put this in the UI.
Well, first of all that
little plus button,
it uses target action to send
this message to my controller.
Now notice it's sending it
directly to the controller.
If I had multiple of
those plus buttons,
they'd all be sending
this message.
But luckily I only have one
so, this is perfectly fine.
Remember that a lot of times
if we have something in
a collection in
bureau table view and
it's sending target action,
we have it send it to a custom
cell, right? Because we want
each one to receive a special
thing, but, here we can have
things send it through the
controller. Now all of this
that plus button does is that
it turns this adding emoji on.
Because we're in the process
of addingEmoji after you press
that button. And
then it reloads section zero.
Now I have decided that I'm
gonna put that plus button and
the text field name in
a different section from all
the rest. Remember Collection
Views, like Table Views,
they have sections, so
I'm gonna have section zero is
gonna be the plus button or
the text field, depending on
whether I'm addingEmoji at
the time and then section
one is gonna be all mine.
Emoji as I'm used to it today.
So how do we implement that?
Well, we have to say we
have two sections now,
instead of just one section.
And when we get the number
of items in a section here,
we have to look at the section
and see if it's section 0,
then we have 1, either the
plus button or the text field,
or we have the number of
emojis if it's our old,
the old thing we used to have
where it's all those emojis
going across. Then we have to
change our cell for item at.
This is the thing that gets
a cell for a given thing.
So look at this
section as well. So
this is what this code used to
look like and I just put it in
an if the section is one then
do what we were doing before.
Otherwise if the section
is zero, then if I'm adding
emoji, I'm gonna put that
text field in there. And
if i'm not adding emoji, I'm
gonna put the button in there.
the text field are going to
be exchanging places right?
So the button and
You press the button,
it's going to change and
switch to the text field
because I'm gonna set this
adding emoji to true and then
I'm gonna reload my section.
And that's gonna cause all of
this to get called again and
it's gonna switch back and
forth. So I'm gonna have to
put some code in here, when
I switch to the text field
to get the text out, and we're
gonna talk about that. But
before that, let me show you
a couple other things I did.
One is I want the text field,
when it's there, to be very
wide. I don't want it to be
tiny like all the other cells.
I want it to be a wide cell,
so
I overrode this method here. A
collection view layout method
called size for
item at index path.
And you return a size for
an item at that path. Well,
if I'm adding emoji and we're
talking about section zero,
then I'm going for
wide buttons, otherwise,
I'm doing the standard size
I had before, and yes,
these are blue numbers, they
shouldn't be here. I should be
calculating this based on the
size of the font that the user
chose and the accessibility
slider, all that, but we don't
have time for all that so I'm
using blue numbers here. And
then another one I overrode
here is will display cell.
That's another cool
little delegate method
in collection view.
This is called right
before it displays a cell.
And here what I do is if I'm
displaying the input cell,
that little text field one,
I make it become the first
responder. That way when
the text field comes up,
the keyboard comes up.
See why I'm doing that? So
will display cell. Another
fun collection do you think?
I only had to do another
couple other small things.
I disabled dragging here
if we're editing the emoji.
If we're typing a new emoji, I
don't let the dragging happen
because it just
messes things up
to try to be swapping things
around at the same time.
That we're adding stuff, so
I took that out of there.
I also don't allow dropping,
where's my drop code here?
DropProposal, where is that?
I can't find any in here,
here it is. So I don't allow
when you're, repositioning
the collection items,
right, the little emojis.
I don't allow putting it
into section 0. That's where
the plus button is. I don't
wanna drop smiley face for
the bike into where the plus
button is, that section. So
I just say here that
if the index path
is section one, then I'll do
this thing where I'll copy or
move the emoji. Otherwise, I'm
gonna say the drop proposal is
cancelled, which means I
can't drop there. Everyone
cool with that? So that's all
the code that I did. Now,
the last thing, let's run and
see what this looks like here.
Here's our UI. So, here's our
thing that we have so I can
move things around. There's
the plus button on the left.
Oops. If I press that plus
button, you see it gets
replaced with the text field.
And I can bring up my
keyboard here and start typing
in, some, I don't know,
what do we got here some
shoes and hats and stuff.
And typing these things in.
Now if I press the return key,
my keyboard is gonna go away
cuz I implemented that one
text delegate method.
see how it went away? But it's
not adding the emoji, because
I have not put any code
in here that actually takes
what I typed in there. And
adds it to my scrolling list.
So how am I gonna do that?
Well that is the trick.
Let's go take a look.
And we want to essentially,
in our text field right here,
when the text field resigns
being first responder, right,
when it stops showing
the text field. Then we want
to put that in. So of course,
we're gonna use this
delegate method I talked about
called TextFieldDidEndEditing.
Editing, editing. There it is.
And when this happens,
I wanna talk back to my
collection view basically and
say add the emoji that
was in my text field. But
how do I talk back to my
collection view here?
The collection view cells
don't really have a pointer to
their collection view.
So, it's an interesting
problem to solve, and
I'm actually gonna solve it.
A lot of people would solve it
by trying to go find
the collection here and
talk to it or
something like that. But
an actually a much easier way
to do this with closures. So
I'm create a var, public var
in the cell called resignation
handler. And it's just going
to be a closure, a function
that takes no arguments and
returns no arguments.
In fact I'm even going to make
this an optional function so
that it can be nill,
doesn't have to be set.
And when text field editing
happens I'm just gonna
call this thing, resignation
handler. Might be nil so
I'll optional chain it and
call it. So I'm just calling
that function. Now, anyone who
is interested, when my text
fields resigns can just set
this closure to something. And
that's exactly what
we're gonna do back here
in our controller.
Where we load up our cell,
which is right here. If we're
doing the emoji input cell,
which is the thing
with the text fill.
I'm just gonna say if I can
let input cell equal this cell
as a text field collection
cell, which is collection view
cell which is that cell that
has that text field in it.
Then I'm gonna set the input
cells, resignation handler,
resignation handler.
Now, I'm just going to set it
to be some closure that does
what I want when that text
field resigns to the first
responder. Well, what do I
want to do? I want to take
the emoji out of it and
put into my list, of course.
So, let's just do that.
I'm gonna set my, well, first,
I'm going to say, if I can let
text equal the input cells
text fields text, so
if you can get some
text out of there.
Then I am just going
to have my emojis,
remember that's my model right
here? That's the thing that,
oops, where is it?
Shows all the emojis here,
I'm just going to add to that
thing I'm just gonna say my
emojis equals, that text
that was in the text field.
And I'm gonna map them, all
the characters in there to be
strings, so that I have an
array of strings, right? And
I'm gonna add that to
what's already there.
So that's emojis just are the
emojis we already have. And
I'm even going to do a little
trick where I'm going to
uniquify them, uniquified.
This is just a little thing
that I put in that utilities
thing which takes an array and
makes sure all
the items are unique.
Because I don't want to
have multiple smiley faces,
multiple bikes, whatever. Now
of course I get this of, hey
you are using self implicitly
here, you should put self dot.
And every time you do that,
you're gonna pause and
say hmm, does this
create a memory cycle or
is this perhaps causing
a multithreaded issue?
Well there's no multi
threading issue problem here.
Cuz we we don't have a problem
with cells being scrolled
off and scrolled back on like
you have in your homework. But
there is a memory cycle here.
You see how
there's a memory cycle because
self is the collection,
is our selfish
view-controller.
And we point to our
collection view.
Our collection view points to
its cells, of course. Its cell
points to this closure.
And this closure points back
to ourself. So it's going
around and round. So
we have to break this
with weak self. And
then make all our selfs
here be question mark.
This is a self also. It can be
self exclamation point because
we won't get there if this
is nil. So, that's good,
but there's actually
another one in here.
Sometimes, just because
it tells you about self,
doesn't mean there might
not be other ones in there.
And there is another one, it's
this. This var is the input
cell and I'm using it
inside this closure,
which will capture it.
And yet it is pointing
back to the closure through
its resignation handler,
so this has to be
broken as well.
Now this one we can broke,
break, with unowned because
we know we would never be in
this closure executing it,
if this were nil. Because by
definition, we're executing
its resignationHandler, so we
can use unowned, in this case,
to do that. And what else do
we need to do here? Well, we
just need to stop saying that
we are adding emoji, because
we're not, right, we've
finished adding emoji here.
And then, we're gonna have to
ask our emoji collection view
to reload data.
Why do we need to reload data?
Cuz we just added
emoji to our model and
anytime you change the model
you need to update your table.
So I'm gonna reload and
cause it to go back,
look at my new model,
call all those functions,
all these functions right
here, reload everything.
It's also gonna nicely
reload section zero and
put the button back because
I set this back to false. So
let's see all of
this in action.
Here we go. So,
we've got this, we can still
scroll around, normally. We
can reposition these things.
It won't let us put
it in section 0,
that's good. We hit plus It
brings up the text field.
It reloaded that section and
put the text field because we
are adding a module right now.
Can bring up my keyboard
down here, let's put some
sea creatures in here.
I'm just gonna do that. Now,
I'm gonna hit return which
gonna dismiss my keyboard
because of that resign first
responder that put in there.
And since that's
gonna end editing,
it's gonna add this emoji to
our list. See that? Their
they are at the beginning. And
we can do the same thing here.
Maybe I will add,
I don't know,
some farm animals here.
And this time I'm not
gonna return, I'm actually
going to dismiss my keyboard
by pressing the thing in
the lower right corner.
You see that thing, that says
keyboard go away. Ready,
boom and now it added those.
So that' it,
that's text field. Sorry we
had to rush, kinda rush that,
but we, again, we got a lot of
other stuff to cover. And I'll
be posting this code, so you
can look at it in detail and
see. I showed you all
the changes we made,
I just didn't
type them all in,
as we went along. All right,
back to the slides right here.
Let's get to our main topic
today, which is persistence.
By persistence, I mean making
things stick around, right?
The user inputs some stuff,
they create an emoji art
document or something like
that. And you, of course,
want those things to stay
around you don't want them to
disappear every time you run
the app. Which is the case in
your homework and the case
of emoji art right now,
which is kinda useless.
So there's a lot of ways to
make things persistent
as you can see so
let's dive right in and
talk about all of them.
Now,some of them I'm only
gonna cover a little bit and
some of them I'm gonna cover
in depth. The first one here
is UserDefault, now this
one is super duper simple,
it's kind like the dictionary
that persists, right?
You put things in this
dictionary with keys and
values and when you run
your app the next time,
they're still there. The only
restriction on that though,
is that the only things you
can put in this dictionary
thing is property lists.
Okay now a property
list is not a type, or
anything like that,
it's just a concept.
A property list is
any combination,
any data structure, that is
any combination of only array,
dictionary, string, date,
data or a number like bloat,
hint or double. Okay that's
what we call a property list.
And that's the only thing
you can put in this little
lightweight database called
UserDefaults, all right?
So what does the API look
like, to put things in there?
Very simple, it's got two
main methods here, set,
with a property list as
the argument for a key.
And then object for a key
that returns a property list.
The reason that's an NE right
there is that there's really
no other type that would
represent a Property List, and
this is an Objective-C API.
But that NE has to be a thing
that is a Property List. So
it could be an int. It could
be an array of strings.
It could be a dictionary
whose keys are strings and
whose values
are arrays of doubles.
Those would all be considered
property lists. But
an array of CG float?
Not a property list,
because a CG float is not
a property list. All right,
so how do you read and
write this stuff?
How do you access this? How do
you call those methods? Well,
we don't actually create a
different UserDefaults thing.
You can, but we don't usually
do that. We instead used
a shared one we get by saying
UserDefaults.standard.
Standard is a static bar in
the user's evolved class, and
it returns to this shared
UserDefaults thing. And
then we just set call set on
it to set values, and we can
call object uptight or forKey
rather, to get things back.
And so here's a bunch
of examples of sets.
Notice I can just set a float,
because that's
a property list.
I can set an array of ints,
that's a property list.
I can also set nil,
because it's an Any?, and
that means clear
out any value for
this key. And there's some
convenience methods for
getting things out, right,
cuz if you do object for
key, what type are you gonna
get back? An any, which means
you're gonna have to use as to
turn it into something. Well,
to save you that they
have some methods and
they're like double forKey,
array forKey and
those will return you that
type. Now, for example,
double forKey, if the thing
in there is not a double,
it's just gonna return 0.
Cuz it's not a question mark,
unfortunately, it's
just double. And
similarly, an array forKey,
if the thing in there,
if that key is not an array,
it's gonna return nil,
because that is an optional
array. So these little things,
these conveniences
try to help you but
they're only gonna help
you as much as they can.
If you put the wrong types
in there, obviously,
they can't do the right thing.
When am I ever gonna use this
thing?
This thing is really only for
lightweight stuff like
settings, preferences,
that kinda stuff. You
wouldn't store documents or
any kind of serious user data
in there with user defaults.
Now saving the database,
the database is autosaved for
you. So you really don't have
to save it. But sometimes you
want to, most notably when
you're in debugging and
you're hitting stop in
the debugger all the time.
Sometimes you'll stop it
before it gets a chance to
save. So
if you wanna explicitly save,
you can use this method
synchronize, which will save
it. It returns a bool whether
it was successful, although I
don't know what you're gonna
do if it wasn't successful.
I guess try again
in a little bit.
But we usually don't look at
the return value of this.
We just say synchronize. So
a lot of times people will put
synchronize in there because
they're doing the debugger,
and they're hitting
stop all the time,
and it didn't save them, and
then they run it again. So
you can feel free to
do that if you want.
It's pretty lightweight to do
synchronize. All right, so
that's the first one.
The second way to make
things persistent is called
archiving. So the problem with
user defaults, first of all,
only small things.
Second of all, has to be
property lists. What if I have
some data structure that I
wanna store, that's big and or
has things other than property
lists in it. And to do that
I'm gonna use archiving.
Now there's two mechanisms for
archiving, an old way,
and a new for iOS 11 way.
And of course, I'm gonna talk
in detail about the new for
iOS 11 way, because the old
way obviously wasn't good
enough. They came up
with a new one in iOS 11.
But they're very,
very similar in some ways.
It's just that the new way
is a lot more automatic, and
a lot less code to write.
So let's talk about these two
ways. The old way
is called NS Coder.
So NS Coder is a protocol. And
essentially NS Coder boils
down to having every single
object in the object graph
that you want to save, or
whatever, make persistent,
implement these two things.
A function called
encode with a coder.
So that NS coder kind of
like is a dictionary thing,
you can set values in there.
And then init from coder.
It's gonna potentially give
you that dictionary back and
you gotta initialize the
object. So it's very simple.
You're just gonna have encode
sent to every single object in
the object graph. And it's
gonna put itself like in a big
dictionary. And then when you
wanna bring it back to life,
you start telling init
with the coder and
they all have to
initialize themselves.
This is how storyboards
are saved. So view Controller,
UI View, UI Label Button,
all of them implement
both of these things in code
and init from coder. And
somebody went to a painstaking
amount of work to implement
that for every possible thing
that can be in a storyboard.
It's amazing how much work
that actually took. So
that's great, you have this
encoding, encoding and
decoding ability.
What do you do with it?
Well, what you almost always
do with it is you turn this
thing into a data. Remember
our friend data, bag of bits,
that little struct? You turn
into a data, and then you
can store a data
in a file system.
Cuz as you're gonna learn,
that's how we interact with
the file system. We store and
read datas. So how do you take
a big object graph, where
every single object in there
implements these two things,
and turn it into a data? You
do it with the class NS keyed
archiver. So NS keyed archiver
just takes an object that
it and everything it points to
implements these two things,
and it gives you back a data
that has taken the whole
object graph, and
collected it up into a data.
And similarly, if you give
it back a data like that,
to NS keyed unarchiver,
the unarchiver then it will
turn it back into the objects
by calling that init.
Is everyone cool with how we
do that? This is a lot of work
to make this mechanism work
because you've gotta implement
those two things for
every single object in there.
So
let's talk about the new way,
which is quite similar.
It's called Codable.
And Codable is a protocol,
it's actually two protocols,
D-Codable and N-Codable. And
it works the same kind of way.
You still have init and
you still have
an encode thing.
The difference is Swift and
the runtime, and, and
the foundation will implement
those two methods for you,
almost all the time. It just
kind of implements them for
free, so
you don't have to do anything.
So as long as you are using
kind of basic types in Swift,
including all the things
that you see on this slide,
it just all magically works.
So
I'm gonna show you both how we
then take an object graph and
turn it into a data
with this mechanism,
which is slightly different
than the key archiver thing.
And I'm also gonna show you
what it looks like to make
something Codable, cuz to make
it to do this, it has to be
Codable. It has to implement
Codable. So let's look at
those. First let's look at how
we turn it into a data. Here,
instead of turning it into
just an arbitrary blob of data
that we don't know what it is,
we actually encode it to
a known format like JSON.
Everyone know what JSON is?
It's essentially just
like this text format for
describing things on the
Internet, passing data around.
And so JSON is a well-known
format, and we can turn that
big object graph into
a description of it,
that is JSON, amazingly.
And there's another
encoder that can do this,
that does property list, so.
This whole thing I was telling
you about UserDefaults,
where everything's an array of
strings or dates or numbers,
you can also turn it
into something like that.
Those are the two encoders
that come with iOS. And
how do you do this? Well,
you just have your
object that's of mytype,
some type that you define.
That type has to be Codable.
And as long as it's Codable
and everything that it wants
to be archived inside of it is
Codable, then you can say JSON
data equals try to JSON
encode that object. And it's
gonna give you back a data
blob, and in that data blob
is a JSON representation of
your entire object graph,
which is pretty incredible.
Now notice this does throw,
it's unlikely to throw when
you're encoding, but it could
possibly have something where
first, I don't know why, but
it couldn't encode it,
it's possible it could throw.
By the way, if you have
a data Blob that's JSON,
you might wanna look at it
as a string. With JSON it's
always encoded as utf8. That's
the string encoding it uses.
So you can always just take
a data Blob like jsonData and
from that previous line there
and create a string with it.
And all that string needs to
know is what's the encoding?
You say it's .utf8. Which
is Unicode 8bit encoding.
All right, now, what if you
have a JSON representation of
your whole object graph and
you wanna create your
object graph out of it?
Well you just use a JSON
decoder and say decode.
Well then all you have to do
here is specify The class or
struct of the top level
thing in that JSON,
represented by that JSON. And
give it the JSON data blob and
it will decode it.
Now this also throws and
this is more likely to throw.
Maybe your JSON data is
corrupted or malformed or
something like that. And
it quite possible to make
this all work, where you're
using some standard JSON from
some website out there and
you're converting it to
objects in your code.
Where you make it do
a one to one mapping.
And so maybe the website you
went to had an error and
they generated bad JSON or
something, so this could throw
here. And let's talk, we'll
talk a little about that in
a second and what to do
with that thing throwing.
Notice that JSON is the
opposite of "strongly typed".
Like a date in JSON is just a
string in some format, right?
There's no such concept as
a date type in JSON. So this
decoder is quite configurable,
so you can specify things
like, what is the strategy to
decode what should be a date?
what format are dates stored
in in this JSON file? So you
In other words,
can specify those kinda things
to configure the decoder to be
able to figure out this JSON
representation. All right,
now I talked about throwing
errors. Here, for example,
I'm catching a error that
was thrown by this decoder.
And the reason I'm showing
this actually is not because
you're going to do this.
You're unlikely to actually
catch these decoding errors
and do anything about them.
Unless maybe you're debugging
your own JSON format,
you wanna see where you made
a mistake or something.
But I wanted to show you here
what it looks like to catch
an error that is thrown that's
an enum. Cuz remember that
anything can be thrown. You
can throw any kind of thing as
an error. All it has to do is
implement the protocol error,
which is really nothing,
so you can throw anything.
So a lot of times things will
throw an enum. And when they
throw the enum, you can do the
same thing we do with switch,
which is to grab
the associated values out.
So you see how that really
works great for errors, right?
So you're catching the key
not found error and
you're grabbing
the associated value,
which is, one of which is
the key that was not found. So
this is a common thing to do,
is to throw an enum and
then in your catch you
just catch the cases and
you're allowed to do this same
kind of grab the associated
value as you can do
with switch. All right,
so let's look at an example of
making something be codable.
So I've got my struct
MyType here. And
it's got a date in it,
a string, and
then it's got some other bar
which is some other type
not shown here.
And to make it codable,
all I have to do is say colon
codable. If I say that it's
codable, then it is codable.
Unless it or something inside
of it can't be coded
automatically by swift. So
it's not one of those things
that I showed you on the first
slide there. So here,
date is definitely codable,
string is codable,
and presumably,
some other type has made
itself codable as well. And
so, this thing is now codable,
and that's all I have to do.
A lot easier that implementing
init and encode for
every single object in there.
We just say it's codable, and
it is. And the JSON that would
be generated from using that
JSON encoder would look
something like this, right?
someDate, which is the same
name as the var, colon, and
then the date in some encoding
strategy that we decide.
And then "someString" :
"Hello", and then "other" :
<whatever SomeOtherType looks
like in JSON> looks like would
be embedded in there, you see?
And so it can be recursively
going down.
Now we might not want the JSON
to look exactly like this, so
can we tune this? Yeah we can,
look at this. In JSON, for
example, the keys usually
don't have camel case, you
know like some capital D data
like we do for our variables.
Usually the keys are,
the words are separate with
underbar like "som_date". So
we can easily change the keys
that are generated when we use
that JSON coder by adding a
private enum called CodingKeys
which is a string-type enum.
And
it has to implement
a protocol coding key. And
all it does is has a case,
it's an enum, right?
Has a case for every var
that we want encoded.
So if we have a var we
don't want encoded,
just don't put that
case there. And
if you have a var that
you do want encoded, but
you want it to change the key,
just say equals the key you
want. So here I've said case
someDate = "som_date", so
now in the JSON it's gonna say
som_date equals, instead of
someDate. And notice I didn't
put someString case in there
at all, so someString is not
even gonna be put in the JSON.
So this is a really cool,
simple way to
customize the JSON that you
generate from your type. Now,
I'm not even gonna really
talk about this, but
you can implement init from
decoder. The thing that
actually pulls the thing out
of the jJSON. If you want
to do some validation or some
kind of complicated thing, or
if for example you have a type
that swift can't encode.
Some new type that you
invented that's not made up of
other types that swift can
encode and you wanna do it,
you can do it. I just put
this here as kind of,
so you can look at it later
to see how you do it.
There's a container in
the decoder and you get it and
it's got keys and values that
looks like a dictionary. It's
not that hard. One thing is
when you're decoding a class,
you have to be here for
the call supe_init, right?
Cuz you're decoding,
you have to implement init.
So you gotta call supe_init.
But don't call supe_init
with the same decoder that was
sent to you. Decoder was sent
to you is for decoding your
vars. You want to send this
thing from the container
called superDecoder.
As the decoder of your
superclasses bars. And
then of course, you could also
implement encoding to encode
random types that aren't
part of the swifting.
Again, I'm not
gonna go over this.
You won't have to
do any of this for
your homework of course.
But for your final project
at least you know this can be
done, is to implement encode
and init for yourself.
All right, so that's it for
archiving. Archiving, the
whole point is we take some
object graphed of swift stuff
and we turn it into a data.
And the data is either
gonna be JSON or
property list format.
So we have a data,
now we wanna store that
data in the file system.
We're gonna put it in a file.
It's just a normal file.
Remember that iOS is Unix. And
so we have a unix filesystem
underneath of course and
starts at slash any other
of the unix file system and
all we need to do to store our
data blog is just write it
to a file. So how do we access
this unix file system in iOS?
Well, the most
important thing to
understand is that the only
part of Unix file system you
can access is your sand box.
Your sandbox is this little
enclosed space. It's the only
place you can write.
You can't write into any
system files anywhere.
other app's information.
You can only write in your
sandbox. Why does iOS
restrict you to a sandbox.
Well, three main reasons.
One, Security. Because we want
to make sure that no other
app can come along and break
your app somehow, make it so
that your app doesn't work.
Privacy,
you're collecting user
information, whatever,
you don't want other malicious
apps to be looking in there
and getting that information.
And an underrated one is
cleanup. You wanna be able to
clean up when the user says,
I don't want this app anymore.
If you have everything in
a sandbox, you can delete that
sandbox, and now everything
that app has ever done is
gone. So, there's the clean-up
part of it. So, Access in the
Unix file system is all about
finding a starting point in
this sandbox. And there's
a few starting points that
you can find. For example,
there is your application
directory in the sandbox.
This has your executable, all
your storyboards, JPEG files,
your image assets,
all those things.
This part of your sandbox,
you can get a Unix path to it.
But it's completely
not writeable.
You cannot write to any of
this. You can only read it.
If there was something you
needed to write in there,
like let's say you pass some
initial database or something,
you would have to
copy it out into
one of the other places
in your sandbox, and
edit it from there.
Another place in your sandbox,
really important,
is the Documents directory.
This is where you store stuff
that the user perceives
as their data in
document form.
And the reason it's important
that it be user-perceived
as a document is because this
directory, what's in there,
is gonna be visible in
the files app in iOS 11.
I don't know if you all have
seen iOS 11, played with it
much. There's a new app in
there, Files, and it shows
you all the files in all the
Document directories of all
the apps. So don't put things
in the Documents directory
unless they're perceived
as documents by the user.
There's also applications
support. That's where you can
put the stuff that the user
creates that's not a document,
because that's not gonna
show up in Files. And
then there's other
directories,
about a dozen other ones.
One of them, for example,
is Caches directory. That's
where you can put temporary
stuff that can be deleted at
any other time, at any time,
and recreated. For example, in
your homework for this week,
I'm gonna ask you to take
your image galleries and
cache those images. So that
when people drag stuff in and
then they start
scrolling around,
instead of constantly
going back and
fetching those
things all the time,
you cache them in
the file system. Well,
you're gonna wanna put that in
the Caches directory because
it won't count against your
app in terms of disk space
usage, and you can always just
re-fetch it again if you,
if the cache gets blown away.
All right, so, you need to get
paths to all these things.
So how do you get a path to
these special directories, and
then start building on it
to build your own paths.
Well the first thing to
understand is that all
the access to the file system
is gonna happen through
two classes, or two, two
objects. They're not classes,
they're struct.
But one is FileManager,
and the other one is URL. And
you've already learned about
URL because we've used URLs
to the network resources,
HTTP resources, and things
like that. Well, you can also
have URLs to local resources,
things on your disk.
And our URL is
essentially just a path,
a Unix path to the file.
So the,
what you're gonna do before
you do anything is find one
of these sandbox directories,
cuz you cannot only write and
read from those sandbox
directories. So
there's really two methods
to get a sandbox URL, and
I'm going to show you one of
them here, which is, I kind of
prefer. I'll actually show the
other one maybe in the demo.
It's a FileManager method, and
the FileManager is kind of
like user default in that
we use a shared one called
default. Although sometimes
we would actually wanna
create a different FileManager
by saying FileManager
open parentheses closed
parentheses, right? Just
calling its initializer, which
takes no argument, and I'll
talk about when we'd wanna do
that a little bit later here.
So this one is called URL for
directory in DomainMask,
appropriate for create. So
let's look at these arguments.
The for directory is the
sandbox directory you want.
Like the documentDirectory,
the cachesDirectory,
the
applicationSupportDirectory.
That's there and
it's specified via
an enum here. And
I show you some examples of
what they are at the bottom.
You can obviously go look
it up in the documentation,
what's available there.
In domainMask, is always
.userDomainMask on iOS because
we have the sandbox, and
we can only look
in the sandbox.
On MacOS it could be
a shared network domain.
It could be the systems
shared domain center, but
on iOS it's always
userDomainMask right there.
Appropriate for just, you're
always gonna set that to nil.
That's basically if you're
gonna replace a file,
you want to specify the URL of
what you're gonna replace so
you can make sure it's on
the same volume as the,
the URL you are getting.
Again, kind of not meaningful
in iOS most of the time, so
that's usually just nil. And
then create is
an important one.
That says whether you're
gonna create that sandbox,
special sandbox directory,
cuz not all of them exist
when your app is created.
Like applicationSupport does
not exist, so you'll have to
make sure you say create:
true, right there. Doesn't
hurt to say create: true,
I think documentDirectory
actually is already created
for you, but, can't hurt. So
this is how you get a URL, you
see the return value is a URL,
into the sandbox. Now that you
have a URL in the sandbox,
now you can start writing
files. And the way you do that
is by using the URL method
appendingPathComponent.
So adds a directory or
the name of a file
onto the end of that URL, you
can even add file extensions.
It's perfectly legal,
by the way,
to say appendingPathComponent
food.jpg, you don't have to
do the extension with
a separate call there.
But anyway, you're gonna use
that to build a URL that
extends past the sandbox, and
it can have directories and
stuff. You can,
once you have URL,
you can find out about things
like, is it a FileURL, or
is it an HTTP URL? You can get
things like the right date.
Is this a directory?
How big is this file?
From this method,
resourceValues in URL.
And resourceValues for keys
takes a bunch of keys, like
file size and stuff like that,
and goes and looks it up in
the file system and returns a
dictionary with those keys and
the value it found. That's why
the value is Any right there.
It could be a number, it could
be a string, things like that.
So you can find out a lot
about your files there.
How do you read and
write files?
We do that with data.
And you've already seen this,
actually. We used data to
read a file off the internet,
with an HTTP URL. Of course
you can do that with a FileURL
as well. We did not use
the options when we did it,
because we used
the default options,
which you mostly will. But
there are some read options
you can go look at.
And to write files,
you're going to send this
to data, write(to url.
And it also has options you
can look at as well. So that
is how we read and and write
to the file system. We have
a data, probably one we got by
archiving the thing to JSON or
whatever with their archiver,
and we just read and
write with these two methods
from the file system. So
you can see it's all about
just getting the right URL,
and then it's easy to read and
write. I want to talk
a little bit more about
FileManager. You can do a lot
of other things besides just
give you a URL of
something in the sandbox.
For example, it can tell you
whether a file exists, on,
in the file system.
It can move files, copy files,
create directories, enumerate
directories, delete files,
all that stuff,
all in FileManager.
FileManager has probably
a hundred methods in it for
doing all that. FileManager
also has a delegate. And
that delegate, almost all of
the methods are, should this.
Should I allow opening this
file? Should I allow you
to move this file. They're
kind of should things, so
a delegate can control whether
the FileManager is allowed to
do things. That and the fact
that FileManager is thread
safe, but only within one
instance of the FileManager.
So if you have a FileManager
on another thread besides
the main thread,
it's thread safe but
only if that FileManager
was created on that thread.
And the filemanager.default
that I showed you before,
that's the main thread one.
So you don't want to use
filemanager.default in any
of the thread, but the main
thread. And of course, if
you're gonna set a delegate on
the FileManager, you probably
don't want to set the delegate
of filemanager.default. That's
kind of a shared FileManager
everybody's using in
the main thread. So
you probably want to create
a FileManager in that case.
Multiple FileManagers know how
to not step on each others'
toes. All right? So we've
learned the simple little
database, which was
the user default thing
where we could store property
lists for, that's just for
settings and stuff like that.
Then we learned about how to
do archiving, much more
powerful. We can store other
things and Swift will mostly
just do the code for us,
but sometimes we can get
involved if we want. And
it generates datas, then we
learn how to take those datas,
with JSON or whatever in them,
and store them in the file
system, using FileManager and
URL. Now I'm gonna talk about
the next persistence thing
which is core data. So
core data is if you have
a large amount of data and
you need to search over it.
In other words,
you need a database.
So core data is essentially a
SQL database. With an objected
oriented API. So you
interact with this database.
It looks like Swift objects,
but behind the scene those
Swift objects are actually in
a database, a SQL database.
Now Core Data is
very powerful and
can actually have back ends
that are different than SQL,
but for the most part we use
SQL back end for Core Data. So
that's what Core Data is,
it's very efficient,
beautifully object oriented.
Now, I cannot,
I don't have time in this
quarter to talk about it, but
luckily, I spent a whole
week on it last quarter. So
you can go and look on iTunes
U and see two lectures on it,
it hasn't really
changed that much for
iOS 11, so it'll all be good.
This is a great
not covered in lecture feature
for your final project,
because I'm not really gonna
cover it in this lecture.
I'm gonna kinda give you
an overview of it. But
you can easily go back and
watch my last lecture and,
boom,
learn all about it and
be ready to go. So
all I'm gonna do here is
a brief overview of it.
If you want a detailed
of Core Data, and
it is a great feature to
do for your final project,
believe me. Go check
that iTunes U. All right,
so it's a way of having this
object-oriented programming
layer with the back end SQL.
How do we do that, how do we
match those two things up?
Well we actually have a tool
in Xcode which is a visual
mapper. You build all your
objects and all their vars
essentially in this mapper.
And the mapper is used to
figure out how to do that
mapping forward for you, and
it just happens automatically.
So if any of you who know
about databases, databases
have tables. They have rows in
the tables that are records,
they have columns
which are the fields.
That's still happening
behind the scenes, but
you don't see any of that
when you're programming,
because you're using
an object-oriented API.
So this is what the Visual
Mapper looks like, right,
it's in Xcode here. And here
I have a couple objects here,
a tweet and a twitter user.
And those are going to map
to objects in my code and
tables in the database. And
then we've got the fields like
the tweet's got
a created date,
a unique identifier of the
tweet, the text of the tweet.
And its even got a var which
is the tweeter which points
over to the twitter user and
on the twitter user side,
it's got a var called tweets.
Which is gonna point back,
which is actually a set
of tweet objects. So
this mapping is being used
by Core Data on both sides.
On the object side to make
all of these things
look like objects, and
on the other side to
build the tables and
rows in the database. So
let's at how we, what it kind
of looks like to do this
in code so you get an idea.
Again, I'm not trying to teach
you how to do Core Data here.
This is to kind of give you
an idea of what it looks like.
The most important thing about
core data to understand,
is that we access all
of it from a code using
an NSManagedObjectContext.
So this context is key and
there's two ways to
get this context. One,
you know how when we
created our project?
There was that little
switch there, that said,
use core data, you remember
that? So you can flip that on
and then you'll get a method
in your app delegate, which we
haven't talked about. We'll
talk about that next week,
that is giving
you the context.
It's actually a var that
gives you the context.
So that's one way, another
way is to create a subclass,
it's use a subclass of
UIDocument, which I'm gonna
talk about later today. Which
will give you the context,
and UIDocument is a way of
abstracting a document.
So that's a way of looking
at your entire database,
as just like one big document.
It could be a huge document
cuz those databases
can be big. But
those are the two ways
to get a context.
Once you have a two,
a context in your hand,
now you can start doing all
this access in the database
looking like an object. And
here's what this looks like.
So here, for example, I'm
creating a tweet. And the only
argument to the initializer
there is the context,
which tells, is basically
the database to put it in. But
then if I want to set
the text of the tweet,
I just say tweet.text,
it looks just like Swift,
tweet.created equals a date.
Yeah I can even create Joe,
a twitter user in the same
context as the tweet and
say tweet.tweeter = Joe. I can
even go tweet.tweeter.name =
"Joe Schmo" in other words
use Swift notation to go
through objects that
I'm linked to. So
it really looks just exactly
like Swift. And I can also
delete objects by just asking
the context to delete them.
Changes that I made
are actually autosaved if
I use that UIDocument approach
to getting the context.
But if I used the Use Core
Data switch to do it,
then I have to save it. The
only thing about the save is
it can throw.
As you can imagine,
if I'm saving this stuff
out to the SQL database,
I could get SQL errors or some
kind of file system full or
things like that. So I have to
catch the errors, if I'm not
gonna do the UIDocument based
auto-saving. Now how about
searching for objects, tweets
and twitter users in there.
So here I'm gonna search for
some twitter users that have
tweeted in the last 24 hours.
So first, I asked
the TwitterUser class for
a fetch request. You see
the first line there where I'm
saying
TwitterUser.fetchRequest?
Then this fetch request,
I set a predicate on it, see,
NSPredicate format?
And predicate is a way of
specifying the search you want
in text. It's not quite like
SQL, but it's very English
oriented. So here I want any
tweets that were created
after 24 hours ago. Okay
cuz yesterday is a var I made
on the previous line which
is timeIntervalSinceNow
minus 24 hours. So
I've described my
search that way.
I also can describe how I want
the result sorted. Here I'm
gonna sort them by the name
of the TwitterUser. And
then I just asked the context
please go fetch those things
that match that. And it gives
me back an array of those
things, as we might expect.
And if none, if nothing
matches then I'll get an empty
array. If there was an error,
like maybe my predicate
had a syntax error I said,
like any twoots got created
by, then this is gonna throw.
And I'll have to catch it and
figure that out.
But otherwise it returns
in array of objects.
So it's really easy to query
the database too, and it's
using SQL to do that search so
it's super efficient.
And it's, even large values
coming back, it's efficient
about that as well. I can't
talk about how it does that,
but it's also very efficient
even if huge things are,
are returned. And
Core Data can do so much more.
It has great support for
multithreading,
it has a very close
integration with UITableView,
as you can imagine.
You, you know, often might
want the information from
the database to appear in a
table. You can even set it up
so a table is always showing
the result of a fetch request,
even if the database
changes from underneath.
It just automatically
updates the table, and auto,
you don£t have to do
anything in your code.
Just say what fetch request
you want associated with
the table. It does
lots of good databasey,
things like optimistic locking
and rolling back changes.
You can do undo redo
really easily with this,
with the Core Data. And so I,
I can't cover any of that,
but I just wanted to give you
a kind of an idea of
what Core Data can do,
cuz it's a very powerful
framework in iOS. So check out
my last quarter's iTunes U to
figure out how to do that.
I do a full demo the whole
deal. All right, so
next topic is also something
I can't talk about this week.
But I also did a week on this
the quarter before that.
So if you go back
one more iTunes U,
instead of Core Data that
quarter I did Cloud Kit,
and instead of either of them
this quarter we'£e doing
the document browser. So
every quarter I like to spend
a week on persistence, and
I kind of do a different thing
each quarter. This quarter I'm
doing document, two quarters
ago I did Cloud Kit. So
what is Cloud Kit?
Cloud Kit is a database also,
in the same way that Core Data
is, but it's not a SQL
database. It's a very simple
database, it just has
kind of objects and the
properties in those objects.
And you can query on them, but
they're simple queries. And
relationships between things
have to be pretty simple and
straightforward. But
what's incredible about it is,
it's on the network. So
this is a network database, so
Core Data, you can have your
database file on the network.
But when you start accessing
it, it has to bring the file
down to your local machine
Cuz it's a local SQL.
Database thing
whereas Cloud Kit
actually when you make
a request to search for
something, it does it over
the Internet to iCloud and
says search that database and
send the results back. So
Cloud Kit's API is completely
asynchronous, right,
you make requests and then
you provide a closure, and
it calls you back later when
it's got the result. So
this requires a certain
thoughtfulness
in programming when
things can take a long
time like that, okay. You've
already seen this a little bit
with multi-threading in your
homework, hopefully, but
it's kinda amplified in
Cloud Kit. Now it's not,
it's not bad, it just requires
you to think in a certain way
as you're programming. So
the important components
of Cloud Kit,
you got record types,
that's kind of like classes.
You've got fields,
that's like a var in class,
record, that's an instance of
a class. A reference, that's
like a pointer to another
class, you got databases and
zones inside databases. You've
got containers that contain
databases. You've got queries,
that's like a fetch request,
a little bit in Core Data.
It's actually quite similar
to a fetch request
in Core Data. And
then you've got subscriptions
which are a fantastic feature.
That's, you make a query, and
you give it to the server, and
you say anytime
the database changes,
such that this
query would change,
send me a push notification.
Do you all know what a push...
who knows what a push
notification is? So
not everyone, but most people.
So a push notification is just
something that comes to your
app, and it'll even wake
your app up and say, whoa,
some information has arrived.
And that is one of the
coolest, if not the coolest,
feature in Cloud Kit,
is that you'll get notified
when the database changes in
a way that you care about.
Those are called
subscriptions. But
you're gonna see, I'm gonna
show you some code for
Cloud Kit. It's not like Core
Data in that it doesn't look
like Swift in the code. You've
got more function calls and
as much just
stuff. Now to use Cloud Kit,
you have to turn on iCloud.
And you do this, like a lot of
things you have to turn on,
like push notifications and
other things,
in the Capabilities section
of your project settings.
So you're gonna go there
to Capabilities, and
you're gonna flip this
switch for iCloud ON. And
then you're gonna turn on this
little Cloud Kit switch down
here, and that's gonna
enable that capability for
you to use Cloud Kit.
If you don't turn this on,
you won't be able to use it.
And when you do that,
there's gonna be this little
button down at the bottom
called Cloud Kit Dashboard.
This Cloud Kit Dashboard,
let's press it and
see what it looks like.
It's gonna go to this place on
the Web, where it's gonna show
you your database schema.
So all your record types,
and all the little fields
in it, not just that, but
the actual data. Which it's
not that useful once you ship
your app because you're gonna
have thousands of users
generating so much data
you can't even look at it.
But in development,
it's really great,
because you create a object
and you can go look at it and
make sure it got in there and
it's got the right data or
whatever. So this dashboard is
how you kind of work on your
schema. It's not quite
like the Core Data schema
editor thing. Because in Cloud
Kit, different than Core Data,
it builds the schema
as you go.
As soon as you, if you say
create an object of this name,
it'll just go create it. It's,
it's gonna do it on the fly,
you don't have to go and
pre-build your schema like you
do in Core Data. That's what
this is talking about, dynamic
schema creation. And this only
works during development,
obviously. Once you ship
it to your users, then
it's not gonna create classes
and fields on the fly as you
access them. But you're in
development, it's really nice,
it's really easy, to just
start writing code, and have
it start building the database
that would match that code.
All right, so here's what
the code looks like. You're
gonna see it doesn't look
like as nice as Core Data.
So you have to get a database,
so usually,
you're gonna use the public or
private cloud database.
Then to create a tweet, you
see you're gonna say CKRecord,
CK is Cloud Kit. CKRecord with
the name Tweet which would
automatically add that table
to the database if it didn't
exist. Then you're gonna
say tweet subquote
text = the text. And then to
have a tweeter you have to say
CKRecord TwitterUser. And
then say tweet sub tweeter =
CKReference to record tweeter
with the action delete this
thing if the thing it's in
gets deleted. So you see,
it's more verbose and not,
doesn't look like Swift, to
be doing all this stuff. And
of course things like saving
are asynchronous, right.
So here I wanna save this
tweet in the database.
Well, it's going to, I have
to provide this closure,
and it's gonna call me
back once it's finished or
if there were an error. Now
this networking programming,
always a lot of error
handling. And so
if you guys haven't done
networking programming,
get used to it, there are 29
different errors in Cloud Kit
error. And not all of them can
happen on every operation, but
a lot of them can. For
example, I've shown the error
here NotAuthenticated.
Because since it's Cloud Kit,
if the user's not logged in
to iCloud on their device,
then it's not going to
know who they are, so
it's not gonna work.
So you could get that error.
You can get network timeouts,
all kinds of stuff. So
that's just a different way of
program, you have to kind of
get used to it,
this asynchronous programming.
Here's what a query looks
like. This is the analog of
the fetch request.
You still use NSPredicate. So
like text contains
some searchString or
whatever. But the predicates
can't be quite as complicated
as in Core Data. They have
to be fairly straightforward
predicates. But
then you create a CKQuery,
which is a Cloud Kit query,
and then you say perform, and
of course it's asynchronous.
So you provide a closure, and
it calls you back with the
results of doing that query.
So that's what querying,
querying looks like.
Again, pretty simple,
but asynchronous and
not as powerful as Core Data.
Standing queries or
subscriptions, I can't really
show you what that code looks
like because I haven't taught
you push notifications.
Push notifications
are not that difficult.
There's a whole framework for
it called UserNotifications.
But it doesn't make sense for
me to show you what it
looks like when I
haven't taught you that.
So we'll put that off til
later. Maybe I'll try and show
an example of a Cloud Kit,
push notification happening,
when we cover that.
All right, now, next topic.
So this is the topic that I
am gonna spend this week on,
which is document-based apps.
So
this is persistence when the
thing that you're persisting
is perceived by
the user as a document.
For example, emoji art.
I create a beautiful emoji art
document, put my ghost and
my bike in there, my bees.
And then I wanted to save like
a document, and then the user
is gonna go create a different
one with some other image and
some other stuff in there.
And they wanna save that
as a different document.
So they, you see how they
viewed them as documents.
Same thing with your
image gallery homework.
You have a gallery of
images that you built, and
then maybe you wanna have
a different gallery of images
that are related in
some other way. Those
are perceived as documents. So
we're gonna talk about a
mechanism that iOS API has for
storing things of document
that is fantastic. It takes
care of absolutely everything
you wanna do with a document,
and you have to hard,
do hardly any work to make it
work. All you have to do is
actually convert your model
into a data and back.
And that's it, and it manages
absolutely everything else. So
when I say it manages
everything else,
what do I mean? Well, opening,
writing, reading, closing
document files asynchronously
is all handled by UIDocument.
Now why do I want my documents
opened, say, asynchronously?
Why do I care? My documents
aren't big, it's not gonna
take that much time to write
them to the file system,
who cares? Well, UIDocument
supports saving your files in
iCloud drive. On the network,
and that could be slower. So,
if you had to write the code
to save them to iCloud drive,
you'd be very sad indeed,
because you'd have to do all
that networking code to figure
out how did I get this thing
over the network? Did it fail?
Is it the network?
Whereas, this way
you use UIDocument,
you just say save. It'll just
call you back when it's done.
It's all asynchronous,
it's awesome.
It also will auto save
your document. And, again,
I told you one of the ways to
get a context for your core
data is to create a UI managed
documents, it's called,
which is a subclass UIDocument
for core data databases, and
it will autosave it. Well the
same thing happened for yours.
Your documents can just
be automatically saved,
you don't even have
to save them. And
the most important thing
about UIDocument is that
it integrates with iOS
11's Files app, and
the document browser.
And we're gonna see,
if we get to it today,
which hopefully we will,
what that means cuz it means
a lot, it's very powerful. So
what do you need to do
to make UIDocument work?
You want to have UIDocument.
Well I'm gonna assume you
already have an MVC that
displays your document and
that it has some var or vars
that are its model, right.
This is MVC,
of course it's got a model.
So like in emoji art we
don't have our model yet
in emoji art, but imagine I
had some var of type emoji
art, which was the model for
what I'm showing. It would
have the URL of the image, and
it would have all the emoji,
and where they were, and
the size they were, right?
That would be
the model of the thing.
So I'm gonna assume I start
there. So all you need to do
to turn your app into working
with UIDocument is to be able
to convert that model to a
data, and convert from a data
back to the model.
Well, earlier in this lecture,
didn't I just show you
exactly how to do that with
the archiver? Really easy.
So you could use JSON format
as the file format of
your document, and
just use the archiving to turn
your model back and forth
between the data, and that's
really all you have to do.
The only other thing
you might wanna do Is
tell the UIDocument whenever
your document changes,
like if you drag a new
emoji in or whatever, and
then it'll autosave.
Cuz you have to tell it that,
otherwise it doesn't
know when to autosave.
But that is literally
called one function,
my document changed, and it'll
figure it out from there.
That's it, that's all you have
to do to make UIDocument work.
Really implement two methods,
get and set my model as
a data. So how do we do that?
We subclass UIDocument and
we override two methods, the
one that creates the data and
one gets our model from the
data. Now we're almost always
going to want to add a var
in our UIDocument subclass,
which is the model. The model
that we're going to be
the converting to and
from a data. So,
here if I had
an EmojiArtDocument
subclassing UIdocument, I'm
adding a var called EmojiArt,
which is of type EmojiArt.
That's presumably the type
of the model that
I have in my EmojiArtDocument.
Now there are other methods
you can override in UIDocument
that do some things.
I'll even talk about one of
them towards the end. But
the main two things you
wanna do is the reading and
writing of the data. And the
only thing you have to do to
create the UIDocument is
specify the URL it's at.
So the only initializer
that exists for
UIDocument, it
takes one argument,
as you can see it in yellow
right there, fileURL, and
that is gonna be the URL
of the document. Now I'm
gonna show you later that this
URL might be given to you and
might be an iCloud drive,
and you might not even care.
But you also could, of course,
create a URL somewhere
presumably in the documents
directory of your sandbox, and
create your own document if
you want. But actually, in iOS
11, usually we let the files
app mechanism give us the URL.
The user goes to where they
want the file to be, and
they say create document,
and it gives us URL, and
we just call this to
create our UIDocument.
Now once we've created
our UIDocument,
we're gonna set that var
that I defined at the top of
the screen there. We're gonna
set that model in there and
then UIDocument's gonna
take it from there.
It's gonna read and
write the file and
everything. All right, so how
about doing this conversion
from emojiArt to data and
from data to emojiArt. So
here's the two methods. This
is the one that converts your
model into a data, it's called
contents for type, okay.
It does throw, You could
throw. If you have a problem
converting your emojiArt to
a Data, you could throw. And
I'll show you where that thing
gets thrown to. And notice it
returns an Any. You would
think that would return a Data
right there, but it returns an
Any because you can actually
also represent your document
as a directory full of files.
That's called a FileWrapper.
But
we're just gonna talk about
the Data way of doing it.
If you wanna do the
FileWrapper way, you'll have
to look up the documentation
for file wrappers.
It's not that hard,
but it's a little more
complicated than just turning
it into a Data blob. And
so how am I gonna
implement this method?
Real easy, I'm gonna use
that archiving stuff, and
use a JSON encoder or
something right here, and
create a Data object. And
I just return it, that's it.
So this often is a one liner,
this contents for type. Now
that type that you see right
there, yeah I already said you
could throw there. So the type
that's passed along there,
that's a UTI, a universal
type identifier. And
I'm gonna talk a little
bit about what that is
in a few slides.
This is not a type like .jpeg.
This is a type like
public.json, which would
be a JSON file, or public.img,
it's an image file. That's
the kind of thing that's
gonna be in that type name.
Usually you don't care because
usually your UIDocument only
opens one kind of file anyway,
like an emojiArt document, so
you don't even care what
that type is. But you might
be a UIDocument that can be
in different formats and then
maybe you care. Alright, how
about the other way around?
You've got a data,
that's handed to you,
you gotta turn
into your model.
Again you're probably going
to use that JSON Decoder, and
take the data and turn it back
into an emoji art. And again,
it's got the types there, load
from contents of type, that's
UTI. This one throws as well.
This one you're more likely to
throw, because here you're
being given a JSON thing or
a Data blob, and you're
turning into EmojiArt. It
might be corrupted, it might
not be in the right format,
something's wrong with it,
so you might throw here.
And, in fact, that's all you
need to do is implement those
two methods. And now you
can use all the methods in
UIDocument like open,
which opens your documents.
And it's asynchronous, so you
provide it a closure there,
and it even tells you whether
you successfully did it or
not. If it doesn't
successfully open it, you're
gonna be looking at this thing
called documentState, and
I'm gonna talk about that
in a second, all right.
So that's how you open
a document. And you do have to
open your UIDocument before
you can use it, of course,
because UIDocument wants
to go and get the file,
and get the data,
and stuff like that.
Call the method that converts
it into an emoji art or
whatever, but
you do have to open your file.
You can save your file
explicitly or you can just do
auto saving. If you do auto
saving, this is the method you
have to call to tell your
UIDocument I've changed.
UpdateChangeCount(.done).
Another way, by the way, to do
this is to use the undoManager
of UIDocument. Unfortunately,
I don't have time to teach
you about doing undo.
undoManager is a really
cool little class where every
time you do an operation,
like drag a new emoji in or
resize it,
you go to the undoManager and
say, I just did this operation
and here's a closure for
how to undo it. And then, it
automatically does Undo/Redo,
and just pulls those closures
out so you can undo and
then redo, go back and forth.
And of course, if you use
the UIDocument's undoManager
to do that, then it will know
that the document has changed
when you do these Undo and
Redo things. So that's another
way to use the undoManager.
If you wanna explicitly save,
there is a save.
The save one is not like open,
it actually has a couple
arguments here. The reason
you have save to URL is for
save as. Because of course
a document knows its own URL,
that was specified in
its initialize, or
the file URL. So save to URL
allows you to save it off to
another URL like save as.
And then that for
document save operation,
unfortunately when you save,
you have to know whether
this is the initial document
creation save Or whether
it's a subsequent safe.
You have to tell
the system that.
I'm not sure why it makes you
do that versus it going out
and figuring it out, I think
it's just for flexibility.
Cuz it can save into so many
different kinds of containers.
iCloud drive, your local file
system, it can even save into
things like Box. So maybe some
of them don't allow it to ask
the question of whether the
file exists or not, I'm not
exactly sure why it does that.
But when you say it,
you do have to know whether
you're creating it or not.
When you're done
with your document,
you're gonna want to close it.
Of course, the big thing this
does is save it, if it's got
any outstanding changes.
And again, if it fails closing
it, you're gonna have this
document state thing. So
what is, what I keep saying,
look at the document
state if things fail,
what is that about? Well,
let's look at the document
state, the document state
is a var in UIDocument.
You can look at it and
see how your document's doing.
Here's some of the values,
normal, that means your
document is ready to use. Just
do whatever you want with it,
that's the normal state.
There's also closed,
that means either you haven't
opened it or you tried to open
it and it failed, and it's
still in the closed state.
There's savingError, which
is you tried to save it and
it failed. There's also
editingDisabled, and that is
a method on UIDocument,
which is disable editing.
And why would you ever want
to disable editing? Well, for
example, the core data
document, UIManagedDocument.
It disables editing when
it's doing some sort of
a SQL operation to update
the database. Now it
only happens for a microsecond
that it's disabled.
But essentially when you set
editingDisabled as the state
of your document. You just
would not want to allow users
to drag new emoji in,
or resize anything.
Not really an issue in
something like emoji art,
where it's very simple. But
it can be an issue in the core
data, or some other more
complicated storage mechanism.
Then there's
the progressAvailable state.
That means you did
open on a document, and
the document is huge, and it's
downloading it from iCloud or
something. And this will
tell you that progress,
it will be the progress
bar in the UIDocument,
will tell you how
far along it is.
And it will stay in this state
until it's fully downloaded,
and then it will move to open,
or normal rather. And finally,
there's inConflict, which
is a very fascinating one.
Since the document can be
stored in a network container,
it might get saved somewhere
that had network access at
the time. And then start
editing in another place that
didn't have network access, or
vice versa. Resulting in two
versions of the app finally
getting saved up to iCloud.
And now you have two versions
that might be conflicting, and
that's what this is about.
Now, you're not gonna deal
with this in your app.
You're probably gonna take the
default behavior, which is,
it uses the one with
the most recent file date.
Whichever one was written
most recently, it uses. But
if you want to resolve the
difference, and you want to
notice this and resolve it,
you can use this NSFileVersion
static method here. And get
all the different versions,
and look at
the differences of them.
And maybe offer the user
some choices, whatever,
that'd be up to you.
But for things like emoji art,
you're probably fine with
just always taking the latest
version, whichever
one was saved latest.
DocumentState as var can also
be observed in the same way
that the keyboard observing
can happen. Remember, I told
you that there was a way you
could like tell the system,
hey, if the keyboard comes up,
tell me about it, right?
That's called a notification,
same thing here. You can say,
hey, if my document state
changes, tell me about it,
and it would tell you that.
I'm going to tell you how
to do this next week when we
talk about notifications,
and I'll mention document
state and keyboard. And show
you what a code looks like to
watch your document state.
Finally I'm gonna talk about
a cool little extra method you
can override in UIDocument
to put a thumbnail image.
Instead of your documents
icon. By default,
when you look at your
documents in the files app or
whatever, they'll have icons,
right? Whatever the file type
icon, the jpg file icon,
whatever that is. Or
if you have an emoji art type
of file, which we are gonna
talk about, on Wednesday,
it would show that icon.
But you can also say,
when the user sees my
file in the file system,
actually use this thumbnail
image of it as its icon.
This is a really powerful
way to make it easier for
users to find which
document they want.
Because imagine emoji art,
you do some nice art, and
it makes a little thumbnail of
it. So you can actually see
the document before you
open it in the file system,
it's like the icon of
the document. And to do that,
all you have to do is override
this UIDocument method,
called File Attributes
to Write to URL for
Operation. This is normally
just going to return
a dictionary of the file
attributes like, is this file
hidden? Things like that,
but you can override it,
get the super file attributes
it would normally return.
And then add this very special
dictionary item called
URLResourceKey.thumbnailDicti-
onaryKey. And the value of it
actually is another
dictionary. With the key being
ThumbnailDictionaryItem.NSThu-
mbnail1024x1024SizeKey. And
the value is a UIImage. So you
add this to the dictionary,
if you have a UIImage to be
the thumbnail, and return it.
Now, it says there
NSThumbnail1024x1024, but
it actually can be any size.
It seems to me that if
the size gets too small,
then it will start using
the icon for the file. So
it can't be too small, and I'm
not sure what too small is,
probably has something to do
with how big the icon image
is. Maybe if it gets smaller
than the icon image,
I'm really not sure
how it chooses.
But, as long as the image
is decent sized,
and I don't know if
there's a limit too
big. But you probably wouldn't
want to waste your time
creating anything
bigger than 1024x1024,
cuz it's gonna be a thumbnail.
It's gonna be small showing in
the files app or whatever,
you can return it, so
we'll do this in the demo
on Wednesday as well.
So there's some other
things in UIDocument,
like localizedName.
It will look at the URL, and
get the name at the end of
the URL, and things like that.
You can find out if you have
any unsaved changes currently,
you can get the date that
a file was last saved,
you can even do userActivity.
Which is this thing where
you start working on
something on one device and
then you go continue
on another.
And you'll be exactly where
you were before. So we're out
of time today, I did have one
more topic, which we'll start
off Wednesday. Which is the
UIDocumentBrowserViewControl-
ler. Which is an awesome way
to give a very powerful user
interface for your user inside
your own app. To create files,
move files, delete files,
put them in folders, you know,
drag them from iCloud drive
to your local hard disk.
All this stuff, you get this
powerful UI, very little work
on your part as long as you
have the UIDocument based app.
So, we'll start off Wednesday,
I'll tell you about that.
And then I'll dive into
converting emoji art to be
a UIDocument based app that
uses all of this cool UI and
all that stuff. Friday, no
more sections, so there's no
Friday section. Next week,
I'll be talking about, alerts,
notifications, I mentioned
that, applications lifecycle,
that app delegate thing.
And some more about segues,
more segues that we haven't
talked about as yet.
So that's all what we're
doing next time, all right?
I will see you then.
>> For more, please visit us,
at stanford.edu.