[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Welcome to lecture number
16 of Stanford CS193P,
fall of 2017 18.
We have one topic today but
it's a big one,
lots of different parts
of it which is segues.
This is the last important
thing you need to know
structurally to be able to
build complicated apps.
So we're gonna dive right
into the first one here,
which is modal Segues. You
actually already know about
Modal View Controllers because
in our emoji Art view and
in your homework, you actually
presented your document view
modally. So a Modal View
Controller is one that takes
over the whole screen, usually
it slides up from the bottom,
though not always.
And here I have an example of
some sort of contact keeping
app and it's got little +
button in the upper right and
when I press that it modesty
segues to or modally presents
another view controller so
a completely different
view controller. This is
not a navigation controller,
there's no back button instead
you can see there's
a Cancel button there. And
I can have presented this view
controller and then present
another view controller
if I want. For example,
this little add photo button
in this new contact MVC,
if you press it, it presents
another modal view controller
on top of the other one.
Again, no back button, this is
not a navigation controller.
We are just presenting
these thing modally.
We call it modally because
the app is now in a mode,
essentially, where it can only
do this MVC. So we get out of
this, of course, by having to
dismiss these view controllers
just like we did with our
document and Emoji Art.
So I'm gonna Cancel this one,
goes back to the previous one.
I Cancel this one, it's gonna
go back to its previous one,
and we're back to
where we started here.
So that's it modal view
controller's very simple.
Now, I wait to tell you
about modal view controllers
until really the end
of the quarter,
because this is really not
the primary way you wanna be
putting view controllers up.
Navigation controllers and
split view controllers are a
much better way to interact
with the user, it's because
of this mode business.
You don't really wanna put
your users in a situation
where they can only do what
you're telling them to do.
They like the flexibility
to navigate around,
change their mind,
go somewhere else. And
they can't do that if you
put them in this mode,
all they can do is cancel it
to get back to that world. So
I generally recommend thinking
of another way to put an MVC
up first before you resort
to modal. So how do we set
a modal segue? Exactly the
same as all our other segues,
we just control drag.
Of course we can present it
from code as well with perform
segue with identifier.
And we even learned,
in last lecture,
there how to present a view
controller, not with a segue,
in a modal fashion,
which is the present method
in view controller. That's how
we got our Emoji Art document
onscreen when it was chosen,
and so you know all of that.
But modal segues and modal
presentations kind of like
the basic segue. It's again
I'm only telling you at last
because you don't wanna use
it as your first resort. But
there's nothing simpler when
it comes to this kinda thing,
and so preparing for
a modal segue is, again,
exactly what you're used to,
nothing special whatsoever.
And one interesting thing
about modal is how do I
hear back from
a modal segue to MVC?
I put that contacts thing, I
added a contact, how do I get
the contact that I wanna add
back, to my contacts app. And
really, things fall into two
categories there for the most
part. One is you don't need
to give anything back, so
like in the contacts app maybe
that new contacts MVC just
puts it in a database and then
you just dismiss that thing.
And when you came back to the
other one it's just gonna be
showing it because it's
watching the database.
In other words they're sharing
a model for example. But there
is the case where you actually
have to communicate back.
So let's say we didn't have
that sort of design in our add
contact thing,
actually it wants to
give us our contact back.
In that sense you wanna think
about those modally presented
view controllers like
the add contacts MVC as part
of the view of the previous
one. Just like in a navigation
tool when we go to the next
card on the stack, we think of
that as a part of our view.
Kinda why I think of the same
thing here, so, that thing you
present can't really talk back
to the thing that presented
it. Really the thing that
presented it needs to talk to
it. And we have a mechanism
for doing that,
it's called unwind segue,
which I'm gonna talk about at
the end of today's lecture.
And that's really how we would
communicate things back and
still keep MVC intact there.
And how do we dismiss a view
controller? Again, you've
already learned this because
we dismissed our document
view controller.
Use this method dismiss but I
kinda mislead you in our demo
last time, and I'm gonna
straighten that out and
I kinda did it intentionally
so that you would see these
change that I'm
gonna make today.
And realize I see, and what I
mislead you about is that it
is really the presenting view
controller's responsibility to
dismiss not the presented.
And you notice that in our
Emoji Art app we had our close
button just say dismiss,
in other words it's saying
dismiss to the Emoji Art
document saying
dismiss yourself.
That's really not
the right way to do that,
now it works because
the dismiss method will
automatically forward that
to its presenting view
controller, if you've been
presented. But the reason we
don't like to rely on that's
probably in there for
some sort of historic reason.
But the reason we don't wanna
rely on it is because if we
had the line dismiss inside of
our code somewhere in a view
controller, it usually means
we're going to dismiss
something we presented,
cuz we're the presenting view
controller. So to make that
clear, when we're dismissing
ourself, we probably wanna
send that to our presenting
view controller.
And there's a var in
UIViewController called
presentingViewController.
That,
if you've been presented,
it will not be nil and
you can send it dismiss, and
that will dismiss yourself.
So we're gonna go back to our
demo today, and I'm gonna
change our call to dismiss to
say presentingViewController
optional chain .dismiss. Just
to make it clear that really
we should be asking
our present,
it's not necessarily wrong to
dismiss ourselves like that,
but it's confusing. Because
we're not sure whether that
dismiss means to dismiss
something I presented or
dismiss myself, so we're just
trying to clear that up.
Yeah, so like I say for
convenience it's forwarded but
we don't rely on it.
Now another thing of course is
this Unwind Segue I alluded to
where you gotta communicate
information back that
automatically dismisses. So
that's another way to dismiss,
and we'll see that when we
talk about unwind towards the
end here. You can also control
the presentation of the view
controller a little bit with
the modal presentation style
var in view controller. And
this only can have a little
bit of control, for example,
the default is .fullScreen,
the
modelPresentationStyle.fullSc-
reen.
That means slide up
from the bottom and
cover the whole screen, that's
what you've been seeing so
far, that's the default.
There's also overFullScreen
which is interesting, that
does the same thing except
for it lets the view
controller that's covering
up shine through. So that
if you're presenting a view
control that has a clear
background it'll show through.
Now we don't usually do that,
so
hide something with a clear
background. However, sometimes
we will slide something out
with a blurred background. And
I'm not gonna really talk
about visual effects,
look at UI visual effects if
you wanna learn more about it.
But you can make it so
that you have a nice
blurred background, and
that would be the time we'd
use overFullScreen. On iPad,
sometimes doing the full
screen approach is just too
much white space, the screen
is so big there's way too much
white space. So there's a
couple of ways to have an iPad
a little smaller area
come up and have your.
View Controller, and the one
is called pageSheet which
kinda does something the size
of a piece of paper.
It looks to be a piece of
paper. And then form sheet,
which is even a smaller
little white thing. And,
when these things show up, the
rest of the UI is grayed out.
It's kind of grayed out and
also completely inaccessible.
You can't touch it on,
you can't interact with it,
whatever. In horizontally
compact environment like
iPhone, Right or
iPhone plus in portrait,
the iOS will automatically
adapt form sheet and
page sheet styles to
be full screen because
there's just not enough room
to show a form sheet or a page
sheet on an iPhone and still
have the gray area around.
Everything would be
jammed too small.
So it'll automatically
adapt for you.
How about the animation of
the thing appearing on screen.
Well, by default it slides
up from the bottom,
that's called cover vertical,
but
it also has flipped horizontal
where you can flip it over.
Another one is cross-dissolve,
and, finally, there's partial
curl which looks like a piece
of paper flipping up off
the bottom, which in kinda
cool that one only works
with fullscreen modal, doesn't
work with the page sheet or
form sheet. Doesn't make sense
you can't really fold it
up from the bottom when
you're kinda got the excess
area around the edges. So we
don't really tend to use those
other ones that much, you know
you want to be careful UI
be too tricky. You want it to
feel like other UIs. We tend
to leave that one cover
vertical most of the time.
Both of these styles,
the presentation style and
the transition style can
be set in the story board.
You just inspect the segue you
created by control dragging
and in Inspector there you can
set these things. All right,
so, we're going to
do a demo here.
We're going to go
back to EmojiArt.
And what we're going to
do is add an inspector.
You know how you have
an inspector in XCode.
Well, we're going to have
an inspector of EmojiArt
documents and what it's going
to tell us about the EmojiArt
documents is the size in bytes
and when it was created. So
it's a simple inspector.
This is a demo after all.
I'll probably throw
the thumbnail image in,
into the inspector as well.
Just so I can show you
a little bit what we can do
with constraints in code,
because I have a little more
to show you about constraints.
So let's hop on over here.
Here is EmojiArt exactly as
we left it last time.
This is our EmojiArt document
view controller here,
EmojiArtViewControl And
what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
a little button right here.
I'm gonna call it
inspect I guess. And
when you click this button,
it's gonna bring a whole new
view controller up modally.
That inspects this document
that we're looking at.
So let's go ahead and create
that new view controller.
And just to review, we created
a new view controller just by
dragging it out. So
here I put a new view
controller in here.
Of course every view
controller needs it's own
view controller sub class,
to controller. So I'm gonna go
new file here, we're creating
a coco touch class, it's
a sub class of UIV controller.
I'm gonna call it my document
info view controller,
all right. Put it in the same
place we out all our other
files there. Here it is.
I'm gonna make sure that I
don't forget to go back here
and inspect with the identity
inspector up here and
change it to be a document
info view Controller
otherwise won't be able
to wire up my outlets and
actions and all that business.
Let's go ahead and
add this info button that
modally segues to that.
Search for button here. Of
course, I'm going to use a bar
button item because I'm
putting it in my bar up here.
I don't think there's any
predefined button type for
inspector info, so I'm going
to use a custom button this
time. The title, I'm going
to have it be Inspect. And
then I'm just gonna
control drag,
this is how you create a modal
segue, just control drag, and,
instead of picking Show or
Show Detail,
which is navigation controller
in split view controller,
we're gonna do
present modally. And
that creates this little segue
right here, we can look at it.
Of course, we're gonna
wanna prepare this MVC so
we will need an identifier.
I'm gonna call this segue
under identifier Show Document
info cuz that's what it does
right there and you can see
this presents Modally. Here's
where I was talking about you
can change how it presents
Page Sheet, Form Sheet.
And also how it
animates on screen,
right. I'm just inspecting
this little guy right here.
So now I need to
build my UI here for
my document. Info, so I'm
gonna have some labels here,
of course, for the size and
the creation date.
So I'm gonna bring that out,
actually I'm gonna create four
of these, four labels,
and zoom in so
you can see this a lot better,
right, just my four labels. So
I'm gonna have one label
that's gonna be size, and
the other one's gonna be
created, and then this is
going to be the actual size
which all have the 99 bytes so
we can tell it's successfully
showing the actual size.
And then the creation day
we'll say today is date
because we created a lot
of our documents earlier so
this is the 15th, 17th and
we do about 4:45 pm something
like that. So these two we're
gonna set from information in
our document obviously.
Let's use stack views to line
of this stuff up so l am gonna
hit this to a stack view and
their alignment trail which is
exactly what l want and these
right here, putting stock view
and their alignment leading
which is exactly what l want.
Then l am gonna take the two
at these and put them in this
stack view with some standards
spacing between,
now I have a nice little
space to show my size and
created here. One other thing
I'm gonna add is an image view
and I'm mostly adding this
because I wanna show you
something about constraints.
So here's an image view this
is a little big, you know I'll
try to pick a size that.
Kinda works for this text
that I have down here. Let's
go and put that in stack view,
and I'll put standard
spacing in there as well.
And we'll have the alignment
here be centered,
because we don't want that
to be necessarily have to be
the exact same width.
Now notice it's red here.
We've got red up here
because it says horizontal
ambiguous settings here. And
this is because the image view
if you'll remember has
an intrinsic size.
It depends on the image
in there and all that. So
I'm gonna do a couple of
things here. One, I don't want
this image view to actually
get much wider than this.
I wouldn't want it to be
like really, really wide and
make this text fill
really small. So
I'm gonna fix the width of
this actually right here
to whatever it is fine. And
then also not to worry about
the hight, so I'm gonna
also fix the aspect ratio.
However with this aspect
ratio, I'm going to set it
from code. Because I want the
aspect ratio of this image,
which is gonna be my thumbnail
of my document to be the right
aspect ratio for my image.
So we'll do that a little
constraint in code exercise,
you know, a little bit here.
So I'm gonna take this and
center it in the middle.
So let's go ahead and
I have it centered vertically
in place here. And
that eliminated all of my
auto lay out warnings and so
what it looks like now. Looks
a little lonely here in this
big white space, but
it's what it is. And now,
let's go ahead and create some
outlets to these things so
we can set these stuffs.
So I'm gonna go over here.
Go to my document info view
controller. Here it is.
Get rid of all the free
stuff it gave us and
let's start wiring
these things up.
So I'll zoom in again so
you can see it. Let's wire up
this image view that's gonna
be where my thumbnail goes so
I'm gonna call this my
thumbnailImageView. And then
little this label right here
that's where my size goes, so
I'm gonna put it over here and
call it this my sizeLabel and
this one right here is where
my created. Creation date,
stuff goes, I'm gonna call
that my created label. So
I've created a nice little.
Guy here to do some UI, and
I've wired him up to Info.
Let's go ahead and
run what we've got so
far here. Just to see what
it does, even though,
of course, we don't actually
set any of these values. But
we can at least make sure that
our UI is looking similar to
what we want.
Okay, here we are.
EmojiArt, let's bring up
apple, bees, here we go,
apples and bees. And here's
our inspect button up here,
now, watch,
I'm gonna to click this.
Slides up from the bottom. We
see 99 bytes in today's date,
because we haven't done
anything there, and,
of course,
there's no thumbnail image.
And we've got a big
problem here.
Yikes, I can't get
back to my app, right?
Because I presented this
modally, it took over,
now it's my responsibility
to provide some UI to get
the heck out of here.
So let's go do that,
I'm gonna do that really
simply by adding a button, so
I'm gonna go over here,
get a button. Here it is,
so we drag this button in
here, I'm just gonna put it at
the bottom here, and I'm gonna
call this button Return to
Document. And we'll just
Ctrl+drag from here.
And we'll call this done, cuz
we're done with this thing,
and it's gonna be an action,
and we don't need any
arguments to it or whatever.
So this one is nicely done and
what are we gonna do when
we're done? Well, we want to
dismiss ourselves, but
now here's where we're gonna
remember that, we could just
say dismiss. And that works
because of that automatic
forwarding, but really what we
want to do is ask our
presentingViewController,
if we have one, to please
dismiss us. And it's animated,
true. And
it has a completion handler,
we're not gonna use that, so
it's gonna dismiss us, so
let's take a look at this.
Make sure this is actually
dismissing us. Okay, here we
go. Up here, let's Inspect,
we have Return to Document.
Woo hoo! We're back.
So, that's good. Now,
we have a model that this,
this MVC has no model, so we
have a model to add here, so
that you can actually show
the document. Actually, before
that, let's go back and add
this presentingViewController
treatment to our
EmojiArtViewController.
Just so
you can see where that was.
So let's get back here,
and search for dismiss,
here's where we dismiss
ourselves in our close and
we just said, dismiss, but
we really should have said,
presentingViewController,
dismiss. Got that? So
the model of this guy right
here. What is the model?
Well, it's
a DocumentInfoViewController,
it looks at a document's info
like its size and created. So
it's var should probably be a
document that it inspects, and
we'll make that be
an EmojiArt document. So,
when we set this model,
we want to update our UI,
put the size in there,
put the create in there.
So I'm going to put a little
didSet in here, and
the didSet is just
gonna call some
updateUI method that I'm
gonna have to write.
And similarly when
viewDidLoad happens,
I'm also gonna update my UI.
Because here, I might be
updating my UI before my
outlets are set, for example,
some might be preparing me. So
here I want to make sure that
after my outlets are set which
is what viewDidLoad is all
about that I go back and
update my UI again.
So I need a private func
here called updateUI,
and in here, we're going to
update all of the fields.
All of our outlets, and stuff
like that, to match our model,
which is this document
up here. All right, so
what do we need to do this?
One thing we need to do is
to obviously be able to get
the URL for the document and
then go look at the URL to
find its file attributes.
Now I'm gonna show you how to
do that with File Manager,
it's very, very easy. I'm also
going to protect against my
outlets not being set yet.
Because that's often true in
an update UI method because
people set your model and
prepare, and so
your things aren't set.
So I'm gonna first check to
see that my sizeLabel does
not equal nil, and also that
my createdLabel does not equal
nil. And
if both of those are true,
then I'm gonna see if
I can let URL equal
the document's.fileURL.
Cuz I've got to have that URL
if I'm going to find
the size and the created and
then I'm gonna see if I can
get those attributes. So
I'm gonna say, if I can let
the attributes equal try,
to get to the FileManager, the
default, not manger, Manager.
The default one,
to get the attributesOfItem,
you see the very
first one there,
attributesOfItem.
And, of course, this is
the URLs path right here. And
if I'm able to do that.
If I can get the attributes,
then I can update those
labels. Make sense?
All right, so let's do that.
I have the attributes here,
presumably, if I got this far
with all of these, if lets and
stuff right here.
So let's do the sizeLabel,
that was an easy one,
sizeLabel.text, equals,
let's just put the attributes.
Now,
attributes, they come back
from attributes of item, this
attributes is a dictionary
if we look at it right here.
It's the dictionary of
FileAttributeKey and any.
So you can go look in
the documentation for
all the file attributes
that you can get, and
there's quite a few. Created
date, modified date, size,
all these things, so we're
gonna use one of them here,
which is .size. And
if that happens to be nil, for
some reason, we can't get the
size, which we should always
be able to, but if we can't,
then I'm gonna go ahead and
say zero bytes. Although maybe
I'd be better off saying
something like unknown size or
something like that here, but
I'll just say that for
demo purposes.
And then we've got created,
so here I'm gonna say,
I'm gonna try to get
the creation date by saying.
If I can let created
equal the attributes for
the creationDate. That's
another FileAttributeKey
right there and
this comes back as an Any, so
I want to say as a Date. So
I'm converting it to a Date,
hopefully you're getting used
to doing this, as, business to
cast things from Any. So
here I've got the created, and
what I really want to say is,
my createdLabel's.text.
Essentially equals
this created, but
unfortunately, this is a Date,
and I have to turn it into
a string to put it
into text right here.
So how do you turn
a Date into a string?
Well, yes, you can do
backslash open parentheses,
the date, and you'll get
some sort of date, but
really we want to use a class
in IOS called date formatter.
So date formatter will format
the date, not just to look how
you tell it to look, but
also for the local language.
Cuz some people, they put
the month before the day,
or the day before the month.
And, of course,
in other languages,
the dates are all
completely different. So,
l'm gonna create a little
date formatter here,
l'm gonna call it a,
it doesn't have to be a let,
even, a shortDateFormatter.
So this is going to be
a formatter that makes the
date as short as possible, so
it's going to be of
type DateFormatter.
I'm going to create it by
setting it equal to executing
a closure, surely you are all
familiar with that. And
I'll just create a formatter
here by saying DateFormatter,
and then I'm gonna
configure it a little.
I'm gonna tell it that I want
it to use for its dateStyle,
I want it to use the short
style, and also for
it's timeStyle,
I also want it to do short and
then I'm gonna return
this formatter.
You know, if you were
really doing an app,
you might actually want
this to be of more friendly
naming that you'd have to do
yourself. It can actually be
quite a bit of work to really
get it right in all languages.
But you might want to say,
like,
yesterday at 5 PM. That would
be nice, unfortunately,
there's no Date format
that friendly format you
have to do that yourself,
so l have my credit here so
l am gonna use my short
date formatter here, and
date format has a method
called string from date. And
it will convert it into
a string format. So
that's the label in the UI.
What about our thumbnail
right there? I'm gonna do
the same protection here and
say if my thumbnailImageView
is not nil not equal
nil. Then also if I
can get my thumbnail
from my document,
remember that we have this
var in emoji art document
called thumbnail, right?
This is our model up here,
emoji art document. So,
we have this thumbnail. So,
I can get the thumbnail and
my thumbnailImageView is not
nil. Then I can just say my
thumbnailImageView.image
equals that thumbnail.
Okay so now we've taught our
this MVC how to take it's
model and keep its UI up to
date with it. Now we have to
do is prepare this MVC as
part of that modal segway. So
you're all familiar
how to do prepare.
I'm gonna put my navigation
code right at the top here,
which you wouldn't
normally do but
just to make so it's easy for
us to find it as we go through
this demo. So I'm going to put
my navigation here, I'm just
gonna to do prepare for segue,
here it is. Nothing special in
this, I'm just gonna say if
my segue.identifier =="Show
Document Info", remember
that what I said as my segue
identifier in the story board.
Then I can sting in and say if
I can let the destination
equal my segue's destination.
And I'm also gonna say dot
content because I want it
to work even if it's wrapped
in a navigation controller.
Remember that trick that we
do. And here I'm gonna say
as of course, a document info
view controller cuz that's
what it should be if
the segue show document info,
it should be segue into this
thing right here. Then we can
set our destination.document
= document. And
you know what? I'm also going
to update my thumbnail here,
so I'm gust gonna have my
documents thumbnail updated to
be my emojiArtViews.snapshot.
Okay just because I
might not have made a snapshot
of my thumbnail since the last
time I closed or whatever.
I want it to be as up
to date as possible.
So that's it.
We prepared it. It's a proper
MVC with a model and
all that, so this should all
work. Let's take a look.
Okay here we are so apple bee
is right here. Here it is.
Let's inspect it. Looking
good. There's our thumbnail.
The size is not 99 so
it must have got that.
So it looks like we created
this last week sometime.
So that all looks good.
We can return to document, but
there's a little bit
of a problem here.
Let's go look at Space Dog.
We got Space dog right here,
let's inspect that. Space Dog
got smooshed, because we have
this fixed aspect ratio in our
storyboard, and we don't want
that, we want the aspect
ratio of this to be equal to
the aspect ratio of the image.
Now how are we gonna do that?
Well, we're gonna do something
very similar to what we did
when we had the size hooked
up, but unfortunately it's
a little more difficult with
aspect ratio so I'm gonna go
over here to our story board.
And I'm gonna bring out my
document outline and
then I'm gonna bring up my MVC
over here, and
I'm gonna create a outlet
to this thumbnail image
views constraint, which is
the aspect ratio here that we
put, so that I can control it,
but I'm gonna have to control
it a little differently, so
this is an outlet I'm gonna
call my thumbnailAspectRatio.
There it is. And
when we did the size and
width, if you'll remember, we
just took the constraint and
we set it to constant to be
different, right? That doesn't
work for aspect ratio, because
aspect ratio is a multiplier.
If we go look at aspect ratio
in inspector over here,
so i'm gonna select Aspect
Ratio, here's the constraint
in the Inspector. You'll see
that it's constant is actually
zero and it's Multiplier that
is causing the Aspect Ratio,
and in fact, a Aspect Ratio
Constraint is nothing more
than a relationship between
a view's width In its height
using this multiplier.
Its not a special constraint,
its just a normal constraint
that uses this multiplier to
relate the width and
height of the view.
The problem here is that
multiplier is read only.
It's not like like constant
where you can set it and
adjust to it versus read only.
So if we want to change this
we have to change the entire
constraint. We have to create
a new constraint with that
multiplier and replace it.
So this is a great
opportunity to show you
how to set constraints
on views, and
how to remove constraints
how to create constraints with
initializer all in one nice
little example here, so that's
what we're gonna do. Let's
go back to here, go back to
our document info here. This
is where I just added this
aspect ratio right here and
then here where I set the
thumbnail, I want this aspect
ratio to be replaced with
one that is correct for
this thumbnail. So, the first
thing I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna remove the existing
ones. So, I'm going to ask my
thumbnail image view to remove
the constraint on itself,
which is the thumbnail
aspect ratio. That's the one
from the storyboard. So remove
the one from the storyboard.
I better also check to make
sure that that is not nil.
Oops. Not equal nil,
just cuz I don't wanna crash
inside here. So that's good.
So that's the first step.
Remove the constraints. Now
let's create a new constraint
with the right aspect ratio.
So this is how you create
a constraint in the code.
There's actually two ways.
You can use this initializer.
Believe it or not,
there's another way where you
can specify using kind of
ASCII art. Where you
make these ASCII strings
that have some rules, and
you almost make it look like
your constraints Art, kind of
artistically presented.
I'm not gonna show that,
it's really cool, but I don't
have time to show it, but
it's something worth looking
at in the documentation where
you can do things like
pin things to the edges,
make things centered,
have things have relationships
to other boundaries,
all using this, these like
this really concise ASCII art.
But here we're gonna use the
constructor to create a new
thumbnail aspect ratio and the
constructor looks like this.
So it's NSLayoutConstraint,
that's the class of
a constraint. And here is it's
constructor right here, this
first one. I'm gonna, it's got
so many arguments, I'm gonna
do my trick here. So you can
see them all clearly. And
this all line up, you probably
already starting to recognize
them as you look at this.
These are all perfectly
lined up with,
back here in the storyboard
when we selected this and
inspected it. Look, see these
things? First item relation,
second item constant priority
multiplier. Those are exactly
the same things we are seeing
over here when we are creating
one. Items, second items,
relationships, multiplier,
the same things. So we're just
setting them in code here.
Now remember I said these
aspect ratio is a relationship
between the thumbnailing,
which fills width and
its height. Right?
So the two items involved are
both the thumbnail image view.
So that's that one and
the two item.
Thumbnail image view. But the
attributes of the first one
here is the width and we're
setting it actually to be
equal to the height with
this multiplier. So
it's equal as the relationship
between the two but
the multiplier gets the count
in there. And of course that's
related to the height. And the
here's the multiplier we want
which is just the
thumbnail.size.width divided
by the thumbnails.size.height.
And
constant as you remember from
the inspector in storyboard
is zero. We're not doing any
constant manipulation of it,
just this multiplier between
the width and height.
So this is what it looks like
to create a layout constraint.
And of course these don't
have to be the same view,
they could be relationship
between two same, two views.
We could make their widths
the same or whatever. So,
now that's we've created this
new constraint let's add it
to the thumbnail image
view as a constraint.
You add a constraint with
addConstraint. So that's it.
So let's go take a look and
see if that fixed our problem.
Here we go, let's go to
the space dog again cause
it is that have the problem
and we inspect and whoa, its
still width is limited, but
it got the right aspect ratio.
And it's got the size there,
661 and
all that. Now, one other thing
I want us to notice here is
this big white space doesn't
look that good on iPad. So
let's go do what I said over
here and use the presentation
style here.
Where's the thing here.
Let's go here to that.
I will zoom out for
you. Let's go select this
segue. I'll go over here and
change it to be presentation
style form sheet.
Okay And this is what is
kinda gonna look like.
One thing that's cool about
the story board is it
will preview a lot of
stuff that you pick.
So it's gonna be a little
better here cuz little less
white space going on. So we'll
see what that looks like.
So here we go, space dog here,
inspect. That looks a little
nicer. It's still not awesome.
It probably be better in a pop
over which we're gonna do
next. But, it's a little
nicer. Note that I can't click
on the background like a pop
over to get out of here.
I still need return
to document. And
also, while we're here,
let's take a look what this
looks like on an iPhone.
Because an iPhone we
can't do form sheet, but
I promised you that iOS would
automatically adapt and
it will. So here we go.
Let's bring up Space Dog here.
Here it is. Inspect and you
can see it adapted by doing
full screen instead.
All right.
Let's get back to our slides
and talk about Popover.
So popover is really just
another way of doing modal.
It just looks quite
different and
it has more configuration to
it. That's really all that's
going on with popover.
So here's a popover happening
right here. You can see
it's got this "Search for
Appointment" MVC that's
appearing there. And
that's an entirely different
MVC and it is actually being
shown modally cuz you can't do
anything else on this screen
right now, except for interact
without MVC. But you can
see that the rest of the UI
is just kinda grayed out, so
it doesn't cover it all up,
it just grades it out here.
Notice that the Popover has
a little arrow at the top,
a little triangle.
That thing is pointing to what
cause this Popover to come up.
The thing that segwayed that
caused the Segway to happen
there that often is bar button
item or button item but
it also can be any arbitrary
rectangle in any view. And
why would you want that?
Let's say you have a text
editor, you select a word, and
you do some UI that says, show
me the dictionary definition
of this, and you pop that up
in a popover. Well you would
want that popover's arrow
to point at the word.
Right, so you need to be able
to have arbitrary rectangles.
Now notice that the grayed
area in the background,
while you can't interact with
it, you can touch on it and
when you do,
that dismisses the popover.
So popovers do not have cancel
buttons. They don't need
cancel buttons cause you can
always just click on
the background to cancel them.
That's why we went to be very
careful to the alert and
action sheets to say
which of our action items
were cancel buttons basically
so they would know not to put
them in a view
control like this.
All right, so like I said,
popover is just the same as
modal, you create it
the same way as well.
You can ctrl-drag to hook it
up there. It's just that when
you connect it you say popover
instead of present modally.
There's things you need to do
or might want to do when you
prepare a popover however.
So, the popover has got little
arrow. You might wanna make it
point in the right direction.
You might wanna make a point
at a little rectangle in
a view. You got to say
where that is. You
might want to control how it
adapts on iPhone because it
does adapt.
Because normally you don't
have popovers on iPhones, but
you still want to have single
code like we showed with
alert and action sheet, that
does the popover stuff, and
it just adapts and does
full screen on the iPhone.
So you can control that with
the popover. And the way
you do all of these is through
a mechanism that's built in to
iOS called presentation
controllers. So, all segues
are managed what's called
a presentation controller,
which I'm not gonna talk
about at all. However,
popovers controller which you
call UIpopover presentation
controller is the place you
want to reach into when you're
preparing to do these things,
set the triangle, the little
arrow where it points,
do anything with the adapting
mechanism, etcetera. So
let's look what that looks
like. So here's a prepare for
segue, for a popover, and
everything's the same
on the green code, all the way
until the yellow line of code.
That's where things
get different. And
here what I'm doing is I'm
asking the view controller
that I'm presenting,
for it's popover presentation
controller. This will be nill,
if this is not a popover
presentation, but if it is
a popover presentation, then
I can configure the popover.
For example, saying the
permitted arrow direction or
saying, which rectangle
in the text I want.
Or, as you can see down here,
setting it's delegate. So
setting the delegate is how
we control adapting behavior.
How the io, how iOS adapts to
trying to present a popover
on an iPhone. So let's talk a
little bit about adapting and
how that works here. It's
really great because you can
then write your code to
just work with popovers and
it just automatically
work in iPhone,
you don't have to put a lot
of, if device idiom is iPad,
then do this. So it's really
nice for that. So what happens
here is that when the popover
is presented in a horizontally
compact environment you'll
know which one those are.
That's an iPhone basically in
either landscape or portrait.
iPhone+ in portrait.
In that kind of environment it
adapts by switching from
popover to full screen. But
you can stop that if you
want by setting the delegate
like I showed on previous
slide then implementing
this delegate method called
adapter presentation style for
controller trait collection
and its. Essentially asking
you, asking the delegate. I'm
about to present this thing
with this trade collection.
Like, horizontally compact,
right. And I, what modal
presentations that you would
like me to do? I'm by default,
I'll do popover on iPad or
a non-horizontally compact
Places and then I'll do
full screen, not over screen,
full screen on horizontally
compact, that's the default.
Well, you can intercede here,
say no, no, no I want you to
adapt to none. In other words,
don't adapt. When I say return
UIModalPresentationStyle.none,
it says do not
adapt in any place.
That means, put it as
a popover on the iPhone. So
this is how you can
make it not adapt, and
thus use a popover
on an iPhone.
Which you sometimes want if
the popover's kinda small, and
will fit nicely, you would
want this. As an alternative
to this, let's say you really,
the popover is big and
it won't fit, then you can
use this delegate method. And
what this delegate method
does, is allow you
to return a different
MVC to show an iPhone.
Now why would you want to
return a different MVC?
It's not because you want
a different content MVC.
I still want my document
info view controller.
I still want it to
be in there, but
maybe I wanna wrap it in
a navigation controller, so
I can put a Cancel button
on the top. Because when it
comes up full screen, I have
to be able to cancel it,
unlike in popover.
You see the difference? So
I can have exactly
the same view controller,
my document info view
controller. And here from this
method view controller for
adapter presentation style,
I'm gonna return a navigation
controller whose root view
controller is my document
view controller, and
I've added a Cancel
button to it. Make sense?
This is a way to go ahead and
let it adapt on iPhone, but
get involved a little bit and
control what, how the MVC is
presented.
Another important popover
issue is its size. By default,
the popover's gonna come over,
come up at a kind of fixed
size. It's about the width of
an iPhone, to maybe two-thirds
the height of most screens,
but it's almost never what you
want. You want the popover
to come up and be as
small as possible, right,
to fit your UI. And so
you do that with this var
in your view controller, the
one that's being presented,
called preferred content size.
And it just returns the size
that this view controller
likes to be. The size it wants
to be in a popover. And
I'm gonna show you in the demo
here how we can calculate
that minimum size using auto
layout. Cuz that's really
what we really wanna do.
We wanna fit the stuff that's
in our UI using auto layout.
So this is a very important
var to either set or override,
one or the other.
All right, so let's do that.
Let's go ahead and make a nice
little popover version.
I, what I'm going to do here
is go back to emoji art and do
the exact same thing that we
did before, with this little
Info button that appears,
whoops, over here. But I'm
gonna add another button that
does the same thing, same MVC,
but in a popover. So you can
see them side by side. And
I'm gonna use the exact same
MVC to do that. They're gonna
completely share the code. All
right, so how do we do this?
Really easily, I'm gonna go
get another var button item.
Put it up here next to the
inspect. We'll call this one
inspect, we'll call it pop.
Cuz it's gonna pop over and
I'm just gonna control drag
from it to this exact MVC
right here. And
instead of present modally,
I'm gonna do present is
popover. And here you can see
I can inspect this segue.
Here's the old segue,
show document info. Here's
the new one. You know what?
This popover, since I can tell
whether it's a popover and
prepare, I'm gonna have
the exact same identifier.
Show Document info, it's gonna
do the same preparation.
We'll just put a little bit
extra in there if we need
to control something that's
popover. And look, even some
of these things like which
arrow direction is allowed and
things like that can be set
right here in the storyboard.
You don't even need to do
it in your prepare. But
the delegate stuff
we're adapting,
that we will need to do, and
that I am going to show you.
So that did actually,
it's all we need to do.
We already have a fully
functioning MVC.
You can already see,
it's not gonna be very pretty.
Look how big this
popover is gonna be.
That's not gonna be nice.
But let's go take a look,
let's go run it on iPad,
see what we get.
All right, and
our Apple Bee is right here.
Here's our old inspector,
right?
Looking good, and here's our
popover. Not looking great,
but not looking that bad.
At least it's working, but
we don't want it to be
this big. We want it to be
just big enough to fit all
of this stuff, all right? So
to do that we obviously
need the preferred content,
set the preferred content
size, so let's do that.
Let's go to our document
infield controller, and
have it essentially set its
own preferred content size.
Now where is a good place to
set one's own content size?
One good place is in
viewDidLayoutSubviews
because remember
the viewDidLayoutSubviews
is a place where
we're sure that
geometry will work, right?
This is where I encourage you
to put all your
geometry-specific code.
So this is a pretty good
place to put it here.
Our preferred size probably
doesn't actually depend on our
geometry very much,
because we're just gonna do
auto layout on our stack views
and see how they fit.
But it can't hurt to put
stuff in here. It's as good
a place as any probably.
Now how am I gonna calculate
my preferred size?
Well, I'm actually going to go
back to my storyboard here.
And what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna take this top level
stack view right here. See
this stack view? And I'm going
to ask iOS, and I'm gonna show
you how to do that. What's
the smallest you can be and
still fit all these things,
and still obey all
the constraints?
So that's what I'm gonna do.
So to do that,
I actually need an outlet
to this top level view.
So let's go ahead and
create that outlet.
We'll just go down to our
outlets all right here,
Ctrl+drag, call this
our topLevelView. So
here's out topLevelView.
And all I'm gonna do here,
I have to make full
code size here. So
what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
use this really great UI view
method called size
that fits in size. So
this is the method that
you give it a size and
it will tell you what size
best fits in that size. And
then there are two
really cool sizes.
One is as small as possible
and the other one is as big as
possible. Those are the two
sizes you can give us.
So I'm gonna use the as small
as possible size to do this.
So here's how it works.
I'm gonna say if I can let
the fittedSize equal
my topLevelView,
that top level
stack view thing,
sizeThatFits and
the smallest possible
size is UI layout, whoa,
there, UILayout fitting size.
And you can see here
there are the two magic ones,
expanded size and
compressed size. So compressed
size is the one I want. And
this is essentially saying
go do auto layout and
see the smallest possible
sizes you can be. So if I'm
able to do that, which I'll be
able to do if this is not nil,
if my outlet has been set
here. Then l'm gonna set my
preferred content size equal
to a CG size which is width of
that fitted size plus a little
bit of padding. You know,
l want a little border.
I don't want my popover
to be jammed right up against
my UI. I want a little extra.
And of course there should be
a constant, but it's a demo so
we won't do that.
So here's the height is
the fittedSize.height plus
some padding as well.
So I just wanna
make a nice size.
So this is the size that I
prefer to be, that I will,
I feel like I will look
nice if I'm that size.
So let's see what happens
when we run that.
Here again. Ready, cuz
there's our normal one, right,
and now the popover one.
Woo hoo, it looks really,
really good. It's very nice,
much nicer than the one that
does the whole A document. And
in fact, let's go look.
This is popover looks great.
Let's go make it look,
see how it looks on the iPhone
just real quick. Make sure
it's doing adapting, I
told you that in horizontally
compact, it's gonna adapt.
So let's make it's doing
what it's suppose to do. So
here we go, Apple Bees. Here's
our Apple Bees. Let's go pop
over. It still worked. Looks
nice. Didn't break anything
that we changed the preferred
size or anything like that.
It's still working just great,
but
we do have a little
bit of a problem here.
All is not perfectly awesome
in the world here, which is,
let's take a look at
this on iPad again. And
we're gonna see that,
it actually while it looks
pretty, it's not really very
sensible, because why do I
have a thumbnail image, when I
can see the image right there.
It doesn't really make sense
to have thumbnail image here.
It made sense in this case
over here, all right,
it makes sense here, cuz
I'm blocking the image, and
so I wanna remind myself
which one this is. But here,
it doesn't sense out there, so
we shouldn't have that here.
Also, return to document.
Yeah, but how about
just click over here, so I
don't need return to document.
That's essentially a cancel
button for this thing,
so I don't need that as well.
And finally, I don't know if
you're able to see this
with the screen resolution,
but do you see my triangle
right up there? It's actually
a little bit see-through. It's
kinda blurring the background,
but then I have stark hard
white background here.
I wanna get rid of my hard
white background, and
I don't want that,
have the whole thing be
a little bit see-through.
It's a little softer,
looks a little nicer,
it's less harsh to do that. So
this background of this view
controller really should not
be wide, it should be clear,
and let the blur of the pop up
show behind. So I wanna make
these changes in my document
view controller here.
So I'm gonna do this at
the end of update UI.
I'm just gonna say here, if my
presentation controller that's
a ,nope presentation
controller,
that's the controller
that brought me up.
If it is a UI pop over
presentation controller,
then I'm gonna do some pop
over specific stuff here.
Like I'm gonna have the
thumbnail image view isHidden
= true. I'm gonna hide that
image, I don't want that, and
also I'm gonna hide
that return button.
So let's go back to our story
board here, and make yet
another outlet.
This outlet is going to be
to this return document button
right here. Control drag,
I'm gonna call that,
my returnToDocumentButton.
Back here. All right,
so I'm gonna have that
return to document button.
It is hidden also true, and
let's fix that background.
I'm gonna have my
view.backgroundColor = .clear.
So I get that nice popover
blur effect behind right
there, right? Let's see
if that fixed everything,
that sure seemed simple.
And this is kinda the wonder
of auto layout, is that we
just hide those things and
then the rest of the stuff
is just going to
form up around it, and use the
auto layout. So here we go,
pop, look at that. I don't
know if you can see the blur,
right there behind.
So the apple, and
if I change that to the bee,
you'll see it's a little
yellow there. So this is nice,
and also it's using
very little space and
also giving me the information
I need without any
stuff I don't need, like the
return to document button. And
let's go see what happened on
the iPhone, when we did that
though. Sometimes you got to
pay when you make a change.
Here we go.
All right, and pop.
That's not good.
Well, what's happening here?
Why is this completely black?
It is about the worst possible
thing that can happen,
especially in iPhone X,
because the whole screen is
black thing while it's white.
Okay so why is this happening?
Well, we changed
the background color of that
inventory to be clear. So
we are actually looking into
the void here. Be careful to
get not closer to our device,
it might suck us in there,
because this is absolute void,
there's nothing behind there.
So that's not good. So we've
kind of changed our popover.
Now, we could go and
do the adopting thing,
where we fix on that you
view controller up before
it presents, but
I'm gonna do something else.
I'm gonna fix the adapting, so
that it shows up popover on
iPhone, because now, that I've
made that popover nice and
small, it'll fit
beautifully on iPhone. So
let's go fix that.
Let's make this adapt, so
that on iPhone, it still shows
popover. So I'm gonna do that,
but going back here. This
is my preparer right here.
This is where I prepare for
both my segues,
both the popover segue and
the other segue. So here,
when I'm doing my preparer,
I just need to grab my popover
presentation controller, and
set myself as its delegate, so
I can get involved
in the adaptation.
So I'm gonna say, if I can
let my popover presentation
controller equal the
destination view controllers
popover presentation
controller and again,
this will be mill if we're not
popover. So it's not gonna
effect the molo one we have.
No effect. This if let won't
happen. Then I'm gonna set the
popover controllers delegate
equal to myself. And of
course as soon as I do that,
now I need to say, yes, I'm a
UIPopoverPresentationControll-
erDelegate. All the methods
in there are optional, so
I successfully implement
that protocol.
But I am gonna pick
one to implement,
which is gonna be talked
about in the slide,
which is the adaptive
presentation style for
controller, traitCollection.
So you can see it again right
here. So this again,
this is gonna be a popover
PresentationController.
It's seen in a given
TraitCollection.
Horizontally compact,
for example, whatever.
What modal presentation
style do you want me to use?
And the default is, for
compact width full screen,
that's the default.
So I'm gonna say, no,
I want you to do none.
Presentation style none,
which means don't adapt.
The adaptation style is none.
There is no adaptation style,
cuz I don't want you to adapt.
And that's gonna cause it to
just continue to use popover,
as it's presentation style.
So let's go and look, see if
that's fixed in on the iPhone.
There we go, and,
pop. All fixed.
And this looks nice,
even in landscape mode.
And none of this broke this
inspector. Even though it's
using the exact same code,
it's because there's no
popover presentation
controller involved there,
so none of that code had any
effect. All right, that's it.
Let's get back to our
slides here. The next segue
way we're gonna talk about
is unwind. The unwind segue.
This is the only segue in iOS
that does not create a new
MVC. I just want to remind you
that, all the empty segues
we've talked about before,
they always create a new MVC.
Even showed detail in
split view controller,
replaces the detail with
a new MVC. And certainly all
the other navigation
pushing on the stack.
Modally, obviously create
one and puts it up, but
unwind does not, it's the only
one that does that. And
that's because,
where unwind segues to,
it segues to an existing
view controller,
that presented the current
or indirectly presented it by
presenting some other view
controller that presented this
one.. So what's this thing
good for? Well, two things
really. One, it's good for
jumping back more than
one step in a navigation
controller. So you've got
a navigation controller,
you've pushed a bunch
of cards on the stack,
now you want to go back three
or four cards in one jump.
This is good for that. Another
thing that's really good for
or the other thing which
is really good for
is, what we talked about
in the first slide
today which is communicating
back to its presenting view
controller. Because by
segueing back to its
presenting view controller
versus just dismissing itself,
it's giving that view
controller a chance
to interact with it. All
right. So how does this whole
thing work? Instead of control
dragging to create this MVC
by control dragging to
the MVC you wanna go back
to. Instead you're gonna Ctrl
Drag to this little red button
at the top of the MVC you've
probably seen this before,
you've probably
seen this before,
this little right button,
you probably wondered what
the heck is that thing?
And when you connect to that
you're gonna get some choices.
These choices are going to be
a list of special methods that
Xcode has found in
your entire app.
So it looks in your
entire app and looks for
these special methods and
it lists them all here. And
we're gonna talk about what
makes that special and how you
specify this special thing.
So, that's how you set up
an online segue. So, how does
it do when it does from there?
Ctrl Drag into there, and
choosing a method there means,
go Segue to some MVC that
presented me or that presented
someone who presented me, or
all the way up this chain, who
implements that method. IOS
is gonna look at every single
person, every single MVC they
have presented you, until
it finds one that implements
the method you chose when you
control dragged to that exit.
If it doesn't find one,
it won't Segue. And that's it,
that's how Unwind Segue works.
So let's look at
the methods involved here.
Here's the special method.
That it looks for
it to put in that menu. It has
to have two things about it.
One, at-time IBAction,
if you don't put at-time
IBAction in front of it,
it won't work.
Won't appear in the list,
the little exit button. And
number two, it has to
have one, and only one,
argument which has to be
of type UIStoryboardSegue.
So UIStoryboardSegue is the
exact same type as the first
argument to prepare for segue.
And it has the destination
View Controller. It also has
the source View Controller
in an unwind case. So it knows
where you're unwinding from,
that's the source and
where you're unwinding to,
that's the destination.
So that's the only argument.
So if you create that method,
it will, in any VC, anywhere
in your app, it will show up
in the exit menu there. Now,
let's talk about these two
methods in the code there.
You do get to prepare for an
Unwind Segue. You do actually
get prepare for segue called,
for you, and you would be,
maybe thinking that you would
want to, get the destination,
like you usually do, and
call it public, API. But
I actually recommend
against this. And
why is that?
Because MVC's that you present
are essentially part
of your view, and
you don't really want to know
about them by name. Which you
have to have here, because
you have to say destination,
as some MVC. So I kind of
recommend against this,
it a little bit violates MVC.
So how do you have
the unwinding segue talk to
the MVC that presented it?
Well, what you do is you have
the one that presented it talk
to it. And you can do that
through that special method.
Here's the special method.
Go back, takes the segue as
the argument. Has IB action.
And in here,
I'm looking at the source
segue which is where
we're unwinding from and
getting something out
of this public API.
So in case of the contacts
example, this would be asking
the add contact MVC, okay what
contact did you get? Which
perfectly obeys MVC because
when you present something,
you're certainly allowed to
talk to what you present. So
that's how it works. Notice
that when the unwind happens,
the presented one
gets dismissed.
And will presently
leave the heap.
After this special method
finishes. All right? So
let's go and get demo of that.
What are we gonna do for this?
I'm gonna add a close document
button to our inspectors.
So all right, so we're
inspecting the document, and
what if I just wanna
close it right away?
Right now, I have to return to
document and then hit done.
But it'd be cool if I could
just in the inspector say, eh,
close this document, go right
back to the document user.
So that's what we're gonna do,
I'm gonna go to my storyboard
right here.
And I'm just gonna,
just to kind of give you an
idea of what I'm doing here,
I'm taking a button, I'm
gonna put it right in here.
This button is gonna be
called close document.
I'm gonna make it red, so
it's clear that it somewhat
destructive to doing this. And
what I want this one to do,
is close the document.
Well, how am I gonna do that?
Well, I'm gonna do
it with unwind, so
that means I wanna Ctrl Drag
up to this little exit button
up here. But if I Ctrl Drag to
it now, in fact, let's do it
you'll see that there's no
choices. Look, Ctrl Drag and
it won't even let me do it
because there's nothing there.
That's because I haven't
created any of these special
methods anywhere. So
let's go over to our
EmojiArtViewController and
create one of those special
methods here. I'm gonna call
it, @IBaction gotta have that
piece of it. I'm gonna call
it, close(bySegue, is what's
it's gonna be called and
it's got to have the
UIStoryboardSeque) as its only
argument right here.
This is the special method and
it's a func. And what I'm
gonna do inside here is,
close. Close myself. Now, I
could do other things in here,
I could get the seg,
this bySegue.source.
This is the MVC that
I'm unwinding from.
I could go talk to it,
whatever.
I don't need to here,
because I'm just gonna close,
like just click. And of
course, close is this method
down here. It takes a bar
button item as the argument.
I'm gonna do the trick of
making that optional and
having it default to nil. That
way I can say close(), and
this will work. Now that I've
created this special method.
Now if I go back to
my story board. And
Ctrl Drag from this document
button. Up to here.
Woo hoo,
there it is closeBySegue.
Notice it kinda mangles
the name a little bit.
But there it is closeBySegue.
I'm gonna click it. And now,
when I click close button it's
gonna search up the people who
presented me looking for
that. In this case,
it's gonna find something
because of course, our emoji
art document is the one that
presents this inspector.
So here we go.
We got apple bees. Right?
So right now if we wanted
to close the document.
Right here. We have to click
back here. Then click done.
Bring it back. But now, we can
just say, close this document.
And it unwound to
the emoji view controller,
which closed itself. Same
thing that at work in here,
right? Unwind and notice that
the unwind works both in
popovers and it also works
from modal presentation.
All right?
That's it for unwind,
it's a really easy one.
Let's go back to our slides.
All right, the last Segue
we're gonna talk about is,
Embed Segue, alright?
So an Embed Segue is
really cool Segue. It allows
you to take the self.view,
the top of a view in a view
controller, and put it
inside the view hierarchy
of another view controller.
So it's essentially embedding
one view controller, inside
another. Okay, which is really
a powerful encapsulation
technique to be able to do
that, because you could have
a very complicated view
inside your view controller,
completely controlled by
a full view controller suite,
right? It has a model,
it knows how to update its UI,
it has outlets, everything.
It's all over there
controlling this view that's
embedded in another view
controller's view hierarchy.
So it's super powerful.
Xcode makes this super easy
to do. You just go down to
your utilities window. Same
place you drag out a button or
whatever, you drag out what's
called a container view.
So just search for
container and
you'll find it. You drag
that out, and when you do,
it's gonna automatically
create this embed segue.
You see how it made the little
S-shaped segue right there,
to another view controller.
And
then you can do whatever you
want in that view controller.
Set its identity to
whatever put UI in there,
hook up outlets, do whatever.
It's completely its own view
controller. Now it works just
like other segues in that you
get to prepare for it, right?
So you're gonna get
prepare for segue, and
you're gonna set the segue
identifier right there.
However, one thing to consider
about embed segues is
the timing there. Just like
other segues, the outlets of
the thing that you're
connecting to are not set. So
you can't really
update it there. So
a lot of times when we segue
to an embed segue, what we do
in the prepare is we grab a
hold of the embedded segue, or
embedded MVC. We grab ahold of
that view controller so we can
talk to it later because we
might need to update it or
set something about this model
or whatever as time goes on.
So we actually usually have
a var and we grab on to it,
and we talk to it later.
And that what's I'm gonna
do in our demo here. And
after the demo, we're done for
this week and actually done
for quite a while cuz we've
got Thanksgiving next week.
But what we're gonna do in
this demo is I'm gonna take
the inspector stuff that
we did and I'm gonna embed
it as a little overlay in my
EmojiArt document.
So I'm gonna be able to see
the size and creation date
of my document at all times.
I won't have to click
either of those buttons,
Pop or Inspect, to do it. I'll
just be able to always see it
in the bottom. And now,
to do that, of course,
I'm gonna have to update it
every time my document saves,
right? Because it shows
the size of the document.
And when it auto saves,
woot, that's gonna change.
So I have to be
able to change it.
So I'm gonna have to grab
onto this embedded thing and
update its model,
as my model changes basically.
All right, so let's hop
back in here and do this.
So what do we need to do this?
Well, we're just gonna
grab that container view.
Let's go do it, container
view. Here it is, right?
And I'm gonna drag it in here.
Now this is kinda difficult
to drag where you want.
I'm gonna put it over, well,
let's scroll this over so
you can see it better. It's
a little hard to drag this in
here because when I try and
drop this,
look, it's always trying to
drop it in my drop zone or
in the scroll view.
See how it's saying drop zone,
scroll view? It's trying
to drop it in there. And
there's just no way to drop
it. I don't want it in either
of those. I want it to be at
the same level as all these
other views, and overlaying
everything. So all right,
I'm gonna give up and just
drop it in here. At least it
put it in there. And you can
see here is the little view
controller that it created for
me. So here's where I'm gonna
do all my, I'm gonna basically
do this stuff in here.
But let's fix the fact
that this got added,
looks like to my drop zone or
something. And we are gonna do
that with a document outline.
And I've kind of reminded you
of this before that document
outlining is a great place to
fix problems like this. So
you can see it actually added
it as something, as a subview
of my scroll view. But I want
it to be up at the same level
as the drop zone and
the emoji collection views.
So I'm just gonna drag it out,
stop being a subview there.
Now, drop zone, emoji, and
container view are all at
the same level. Now we need to
do some constraints because
I don't want this thing
sitting in the middle here.
I actually want it down
in the bottom edge.
So I'm gonna do that.
I'm gonna set constraints 00.
And I'm gonna hope my nearest
neighbor is the safe area,
let's hope. Maybe it was,
maybe it wasn't, we'll see.
Now it wants to know
about width and
height. This thing needs to
know width and height. So
I'm going to have my width and
height set to the preferred
content size of my view,
of course, right,
same size that the popover is.
But to do that I'm gonna
have to set a width and
height here and
have outlets to them like we
saw before. And look at that?
It jumped and it looks like it
did the safe area. Let's look.
It is, safe area right there
and fixed width and height.
Well, of course we don't
want fixed width and height.
We want to have
outlets to these, so
let's add outlets for these
things. Put it right here.
We'll control drag, oops,
not from there, from here.
This is our embedded,
embeddedDockInfoHeight. And
this one is our
embeddedDocInfoWidth.
So we're gonna have
to set this width and
height to be the preferred
content size of our doc info.
So let's go back to our view,
or to our storyboard here, and
do our UI. We've got this UI
here. First of all, we have to
set its identity to be a
DocInfoViewController. This is
the great thing about embedded
is we're gonna get all
the benefit of the code we
wrote to do the size and
the created by, and
all that stuff.
We're gonna get all that
benefit here essentially for
free. Now, here, embedded,
I don't need, obviously, this
view. And I don't need closed
document or return document.
So I'm gonna do another
kind of tricky thing,
which I'm gonna grab this
whole Stack view here,
which is this one, I think,
yes. I'm gonna drag this over
here and copy it and
paste it down here. Then I'm
gonna center it in the middle.
So that it's centered.
I'm going to, of course,
wire up my outlets to it.
So let's do that.
Let's go over here.
Go down here to where our
outlets are. Here they are.
So let's, this is our,
let's zoom in a little so
you can see better here.
So here's our size label,
let's drag it in there. Here's
our created label, right here.
And our top level view is
actually now this stack view.
So let's do that one to
toplevelView. So we've wired
up our UI. All this other code
is just going to work because
we set this thing to be
a doc.info view controller.
So now let's go back to our
EmojiArtViewController, and
we need to prepare it.
So it's gonna need its
own identifier cuz
we want a little bit different
preparation for this embed
one. So I'm gonna click on
this, and inspect it. And
the only thing I can inspect
here is its identifier.
So I'm gonna call this my
Embed Document Info Segue.
Let's go back here.
Now I'm gonna say,
my segue else if it is
the Embed Document Info segue,
then all I'm gonna do
here if that segue,
is I'm gonna grab on to that
document MVC. So I'm gonna
create a local var here, which
I'm gonna call private var.
I'm gonna call it,
what did I call it here?
I called it my embedded
document info,
embeddedDocInfo, we'll
call it. And
it's of type
DocumentInfoViewController. So
here I'm just gonna say
that my embeddedDoc,
DocInfo =
segue.destination.contents
probably as a doc You
meant InfoViewController.
Cuz if it's not a document
info controller,
I don't even wanna set this
bar. Then all I need to do is,
every time my
document auto saves,
I need to update this thing.
So let's go down here to where
we know where auto saving is.
It's right here where
we're observing.
Here's where we're observing
the document state,
state, state change. So,
every time the document
state changes to normal,
I'm going to update it. Cuz we
know that when it auto saves,
it goes to progress available
and then back to normal, and
it'll also work when I
first open the document. So
I'm just gonna say
here if self.document,
.documentState, State
== normal,
then I'm gonna let docInfoVC
= my self.embeddedDocInfo,
embeddedDocInfo.
So I got that. Then, I'm gonna
set my docInfoVC's model to
be myself, in case it's not
already set there. This will
also cause it to update.
Then I'm also gonna set
the width and height of that
embedded document based on
those constraints, all right?
So, that was
the self.embeddedDocInfoWidth
is .constant = the docInfoVC's
.preferredContentSize.width.
And the same thing here,
this will have
embeddedDocInfoHeight.constant
= the
docInfoVC.preferredContentSiz-
e.height. The crowd's
outside the door here,
so let me show you
this real quick.
Here we are, Apple Bees,
and there it is.
Now it doesn't quite look
right. It got the size right,
but it's got this
white background.
Also watch this, if I move
this apple down here and
then I try to pick
the apple up,
no, I can't pick it up.
So even if it were clear,
this would be a problem. So I
need two things I need to fix.
I don't want this white,
and I want it not to
grab any gestures. So let's
look and see how we do that,
we go to our story board right
here. We're gonna make it
clear by just having this view
controller right here have
a clear background. So that's
gonna make it clear. And
then we're gonna make it
not intercept gestures by
clicking this button here off.
See it says user interaction
enabled in this embedded view?
I'm gonna turn that off. And
that's gonna make it so
that it doesn't have any user
interaction, so of course it
won't grab any of the gesture
stuff. Here we go, look,
it's clear. It's not going to,
let's put an apple over there.
I can pick the apple up even
if it's right on top of it, so
that's good.
So that's all fixed.
It works beautifully here
on iPad. If we change
something, which we did, we
moved the apple, but let's add
something that's gonna change
the size. So we go here,
I'll put this in.
We have to wait a little
bit for it to autosave, and
then hopefully this 718 bytes
will change to something else,
Before the hoards come in.
There it is,
760 bytes. And also, last
thing, it works on iPhone.
This all works on iPhone as
well because the embed segue
completely independent of
the platform that it's on.
There it is there. Also, this
stuff is all still working.
Close document, select work,
Space Dog, Pop Over,
all still working.
That's segues. So hope,
you'll be using segues all
over in your final project.
So good luck with that.
And I will see you all in
a couple of weeks.
>> For more,
please visit us
at stanford.edu.