[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Well,
welcome to lecture number
17 of Stanford CS193P,
this is a fall of 2017. Today
we're gonna talk about some
hardware specific APIs,
specifically Core Motion,
which is the position of the
device in space, basically,
as it moves around.
And then the camera, so
we can capture images with
the camera. Now Core Motion
is really a whole set of
APIs that go together.
The primary inputs to Core
Motion are the accelerometer,
almost all devices have
an accelerometer. The gyro,
most newer devices have
a gyro. And the magnetometer,
kind of similar to the gyro,
newer devices have all that.
And you're gonna see a part
of the API we're really gonna
wanna check and make sure
that the device we're on has
the hardware we want before we
do it. Now the primary API to
get at all this is this class
called CMMotionManager.
There's some other classes
we're gonna talk about,
but this is the primary one.
Now, you can create multiple
instances of this thing,
but in a sense,
there's only set of hardware.
So usually in your app,
you're gonna have one
shared CMMotionManager to
collect all the information
from these devices.
Now, the way the API works,
basically, is first you're
gonna check to see what
hardware is available,
all right,
that's a very important check.
Then you can either start
sampling, okay, just
asking the CMMotionManager
what's the current state of
the accelerometer? What's
the current state of gyro?
What's the current state
of magnetometer? Or
you can register a closure,
and a certain refresh rate,
and it will execute your
closure at that refresh rate,
as best it can anyway, and
tell you what the state is.
So it's kind of like you can
either pull the data out
of it, or it can push the data
to you. Really either
model, and it kinda depends on
how your app works as to which
of those is appropriate. So
I'm gonna talk about the API's
for both of those things.
So let's do number one here,
which checking the
availability of the sensors.
Really, where you're
simply are just gonna get
your CMMotionManager and then
you gonna ask questions like,
accelerometer available,
is gyro available,
magnetometer available? And
this is gonna return yes or
no whether these
things are available.
Notice that there's something
there called device motion,
you see accelerometer,
gyro, magnetometer, and
deviceMotion. So we're gonna
talk all about deviceMotion.
It's essentially a combination
of all the other devices, and
it allows us to get much
more accurate readings,
more interesting readings, by
combining the accelerometer,
gyro, and magnetometer. So the
way where you're going to pull
the information, okay, not
gonna register a closure but
you're just gonna ask for
as you need it.
You do that by calling start
accelerometer updates, or
start gyro updates and that's
gonna tell the hardware,
tell iOS, hey,
l wanna get this information.
So, if that particular piece
of hardware has to be powered
up or something like that,
then iOS is gonna do that so
that you can start
asking the value of it.
So that's all you have to do
to start pulling the data.
You can also find out if
the hardware is on and
collecting data with
accelerometer active or
gyro active VAR in
the CMMotionManager.
Now a really important thing
to do when you're accessing
this data from these hardware
devices is to turn it off,
okay? The reason you
wanna turn it off is,
it requires battery, okay?
Who knows how much, it depends
on the piece of hardware, to
do this, and you don't wanna
waste the user's battery.
All right, so we definitely
wanna turn if off anytime
we're not using it. Not like
just when our app quits or
something, but actually any
time we are not actually gonna
use the information, let's
turn that thing off, right,
save some battery. All right,
so now let's talk a little
bit about that pull interface
where you're just gonna
ask for the current state
of this thing all the time.
And the API is
very similar for
all the devices, gyro,
accelerometer, and
magnetometer, and for this
combined device motion thing.
So, here's what
it looks like for
accelerometer, it's just a VAR
in CMMotionManager called
accelerometer data.
Gives you back a struct,
it looks like this, x, y, and
z. That is the acceleration
of the device in x, y, and z.
So x is the axis that goes
across the device, okay, so
if you're looking at the
device and the home button at
the bottom and you're looking
at it. Then across is x,
y is up and down through
the home button essentially,
or you have an iPhone 10,
through where the home
button used to be. And
then z is down through
back of the device device.
Okay, so if you had a device
sitting on a table flat,
then z would be 1.0 here,
because this is in g, and
the only acceleration that the
device would be experiencing
is the acceleration
due to gravity, okay?
Don't forget about
that acceleration,
right, 9.8 meters per second
squared towards the center of
the earth,
that's always happening. So
if you then pick the device
up and kinda set it down so
that the home button is on
the bottom, right, then your
y would be experiencing 1 g,
and z and x would be 0,
okay, cuz nothing would
be moving it. Now,
if you took the device and you
shake it all around like this,
then x, y, and z are gonna be
all kinds of random numbers.
Could be much greater than
1 if you really jerk it,
much faster acceleration and
the acceleration due to
gravity, you could get
all kinds of numbers.
All right, so this'll give
me the raw acceleration
of the device in space,
including gravity.
All right, the gyro,
so the gyro, we're
almost never gonna ask for the
gyro information directly like
this as you're gonna see in
a motion. But if you did, it's
essentially gonna tell you
the rotation rate around those
three axes I talk about in
radians per second. Okay, so
it's basically how fast it's
rotating in these devices.
Now the problem is,
is the gyro on its own can get
bias introduced to it. It can
kind of drift a little bit,
so the gyro works a lot
better in concert with
the accelerometer,
as you'll see in a moment,
and similarly with
magnetometer. Yeah, you can
find out the magnetic field
around you but, you'd like to
know what, how much of that
is earth's magnetic field,
so you can find out where the
north is, versus how much is
just local interference
from devices. And so,
we don't usually access the
magnetometer directly either.
Instead, in both cases,
we access this pseudo device
called deviceMotion. Okay, and
so, it's similar to the other
ones, it has var, this one's
called deviceMotion, and
it gives you back this
deviceMotion struct. Now,
the deviceMotion
struct is giving you
a lot of the same
information that you're
getting from these
other devices, but
it's combining the devices to
give you better information.
For example, let's look
at acceleration. So,
when you have a device and
you're looking at
the accelerometer, you don't
really know how much of that
is due to the acceleration
due to gravity, and
how much is because the user
is moving the device around.
Right, well, but if you have
the gyro, now you do know
how much the user is moving
the device around, okay.
So, if you combine the two,
you can factor
out the acceleration
that's due to gravity and
the acceleration that's the
actual user moving the device.
So in CMMotion,
you have the gravity which
is a CM acceleration, and you
also have user acceleration,
and they're separated out.
Okay, so
you see how it's used the gyro
to give you more information
about acceleration, and
similarly for the gyro, okay?
If you have this gyro, you can
remove the bias that happens
with the gyro because you have
the accelerometer information
that tells you where
this thing is being
moved around as it's being
rotated. So, there you can
get rotation rate in the same
way as you got before, but
you can also get much more
interesting in things like
roll, pitch, and yaw, okay?
So if you know anything about
flying, if you have an
airplane that's flying along,
the roll is when the airplane
tilts it's wings side to side,
right, that's the roll. Pitch
is when the pitches is nose
up or down, right, that's
the pitch. And the yaw is when
it kinda turns into the wind
in the same plane parallel
to the ground, right. So you
can get that same roll, pitch,
and yaw in your device, which
is really kind of a cool way
to think about your devices,
what your device is doing. You
can also get heading, okay,
now it needs the magnetometer
for that, obviously,
to do the heading. And this is
gonna give you the heading.
And heading is sometimes
interesting to
have if you have, for example,
an, augmented reality app, or
something like that, where you
wanna know the gyro position
as you're moving
this thing around.
But you also know where
you are in the world.
Are you facing north?
Where are you facing?
So, we can give you that
information, as well.
So, CMDeviceMotion is probably
the primary way we get
information out of core
motion, when we want gyro,
accelerometer, magnetometer,
because it combines them
very intelligently.
Okay, now when you're getting
device motion you can actually
control, which of the devices,
accelerometer, gyro and
magnetometer are used,
specifically the magnetometer,
okay? There's a couple of
reference frames and reference
frame is just an argument when
you start getting the updates,
from the device motion. So,
there's two reference frames
called xArbitraryZVertical and
xArbitraryCorrected ZVertical
which either don't use
the magnetometer, or
can work without the,
magnetometer,
I believe they can do.
And so, they're not,
they're really not used for
a reference frame when,
when you wanna know where
your device is in the world,
okay? So, there's two other
ones. xMagnetic/TrueNorth and
xMagneticTrue NorthZVertical.
And
those use the magnetometer.
Now, those actually will
require the magnetometer
to be calibrated,
and, and ready to use, so,
you know, you don't wanna
use these reference frames
lightly, but if you need to
know where you are then you
need this. Obviously, for
true north it not only needs
to know all the information
that we talked about so far,
but it also needs to know your
location, where you
are on the planet.
So, it can tell the difference
between magnetic north,
which is the only thing it can
measure, and true north, okay?
And that just depends where
you are on Earth. Now,
if you want the heading
VAR that I talked about on
the last device motion you'll
need to have the reference
either be magnetic, or
true north. All right? Now,
always check to make sure that
whatever reference frame you
want to use, especially if
it's going to be the magnetic,
or true north ones is
available. And you can do that
with the availableAttitude
ReferenceFrames, function and
it'll return one of these
frames above, and you can
kinda, it's a bit masked and
you can look in there and
see if yours is available.
All right, so
we talked about how to just
grab the information whether
it's accelerometer data, or
this device motion data, grab
it from CM motion manager.
And how about the thing
of registering a closure.
So, that API looks like this.
For accelerometer,
for example you're gonna say,
startAccelerometer
UpdatesToQueue,
that's the queue that your
closure is gonna be executed
on. That's almost always gonna
be the main queue, so you're
gonna say .main there usually.
With a handler, and a handler
is just a look closure.
It takes two arguments,
one is the accelerometer data
that it's giving you in its
updates, and the other
one is a possible error.
And one of these is always
nill, okay? Either it,
it got the data, or it didn't.
It's as simple as that, okay?
So, you're just gonna get
called this closure is gonna
get called repeatedly with the
state of the accelerometer.
Similar for the gyro, similar
for the magnetometer, and
similar for device motion,
okay? Notice, that device
motion also has this extra
argument at the beginning,
which is that reference frame
I talked about, okay? Now,
what about the errors that
can come back here, okay?
Well, a lot depends on what
your asking for, especially in
device motion world. If you're
asking for something like true
north reference frame, you're
trying to get the heading,
you might get the error True
North Not Available. Maybe,
because it doesn't know where
you are on the Earth, okay?
Because it can't see any cell
sites, or Wi-Fi, uh,GPS, or
anything like that, so
it doesn't where you are. Also
you can get NotAuthorized and
NotAvailable, and we're gonna
talk about that in a second.
Where, the user might have
said, I don't want this app to
be able to get this
information from me, okay?
That's from a privacy
standpoint. Okay, so
you want to look in
the documentation and
see what the errors you can
get are and handle them.
I, core motion same thing
with the core location and
the map kit it's a place where
you really want to
handle the errors.
You don't want to
blindly ignore errors,
because these errors
do come up. Okay?
We're talking about physical
devices here. Real world,
it's variable, okay? So, how
often does your closure get
called? Well, you get to
determine that by setting one
of these vars, the
accelerometer UpdateInterval,
or the deviceMotion
UpdateInterval.
This is a TimeInterval, so
that's number of seconds. And
usually you're gonna set it
to maybe a 10th of a second,
or 30th of a second. Maybe you
could do 60th of a session,
but you're really
pushing it by then.
And remember, that it's gonna
be calling your closure, so
unless your closure's
really lightweight,
you don't wanna call
it too much. So,
how do you decide what
to set this to? Well,
it totally depends on what's
happening in your app, okay?
You're gonna see the demo
I'm gonna do day,
today I'm gonna use
the accelerometer.
Eh, it's not that important
to see really quick changes
in the accelerometer, so
I'm gonna go fairly low rate.
But I might have something
that's very detailed
thing where I'm looking
at accelerometer, and
I wanna know exactly
what's happening and
the users using it,
moving it tiny little amounts.
Then I might want to be
updating very quickly, okay?
So there is a limit of course.
The hardware can only
deliver certain limit,
I'm not sure what those limits
are. Probably around a 60th of
a second kind of thing but
that's something you have to
tune to make your app work
well. It is okay, by the way,
to register multiple closures,
okay, inside your app.
Have two different things,
although they're all going to
want to be updating at
the same rate, okay?
And if they're all registered
with the same motion manager,
they will all be updating
at the same rate.
Okay, it's not really
recommended to have two core
motion managers with
different rates and
different closures. Cuz you
could get a performance issue
there when it's trying to
service both of those rates
and it's having to call them a
lot, so be careful with that.
All right, so
we understand then
how to get the accelerometer
data, the instantaneous value
of the accelerometer.
But really accelerometer data
sometimes make a lot more
sense over time, okay? Like,
what's the average amount of
movement in the last minute?
Or something like that.
Maybe you're trying to see
what the user is up to.
What they're doing. Kinda
how they're moving around,
or they're walking around or
what,
they're doing. So, this is
another class is slow motion
called CMSensorRecorder.
And it can record at 50 hertz.
What's going on now.
Only newer devices.
I think iPhone 7 and
later can do this.
So, you definitely want to say
is accelerometer recording
available? This is also
something on the Apple Watch,
which is very useful for that.
Then once you do it,
you just say to
the CMSensorRecorder.
Record accelerometer for
some duration,
and it will start
recording it, okay, and
you can say whatever
the duration is.
Now, I recommend keeping that
duration as short as makes
sense for your app, okay,
[LAUGH] whatever is going on.
It's expensive to turn that
accelerometer on and record.
However, this is
really in a way,
less expensive than doing some
other things, because this,
most iOS devices, in fact,
probably all of them that can
implement this, they know
how to go to sleep, right?
The screen turns black,
they're asleep,
the processor's not
really running.
But that thing is still
collecting accelerometer data.
So, they've separated out the
accelerometer hardware into
a separate little chip that
knows how to collect data, and
then report it back when
the system wakes back up. So,
it is possible if you
want to go for a run, and
your app wants to measure the
person's acce- acceleration in
three dimensions while
they are running, or
they put it on their arm, or
in their pocket, or whatever.
And it goes to sleep, because
it's not running your app.
They run for one hour and
when they come back, and
then the data can all be
there without the app having
to constantly run and ask for
it, okay. There is a lot of
fitness API that I'm not
talking about here [LAUGH] in
core motion that in that is
same vein where you gonna ask
the system please record this
things for me. And then,
if you get them later, you ask
for them later. For example,
this quarter I didn't get to
talk about core location.
Okay, core location is
something I highly recommend
you look into, possibly for
your final project. And
it core location can
record your GPS,
or otherwise location, and
it can do it in a way that
doesn't cause the phone to
have to be awake all of
the time. All right, so
once you start a recording,
then you can go back and
get the recorded data.
It only keeps a recorded data
I think for three days, so
you wanna be asking for
it in a time,
reasonably timely manner but
you can ask for
the accelerometer data
during a certain time.
And it's gonna come back as
the CMSensorDataList which
you just basically for in to
get CM recorded accelerometer,
this would just could be that
XYZ of all that stuff you can
look through there. And
usually you gonna take that
list and average it or
something like that to trying
to figure what's going on.
Now if what you're doing is
looking at accelerometer
data because you want to try
to figure out if these are
running or staying still or
walking. Or
are they in their car?
Then you don't wanna use that,
you wanna use this API, okay?
There's an API called Activity
Monitoring that will use
a different object, here, it's
not the CM Motion Manager,
it's CMMotionActivityManager,
and it's very similar API.
You stay startActivityUpdates
and you have a closure.
And it will call that
periodically, telling you what
the user's doing.
Are they standing still?
Are they walking, running, are
they in their car, cycling?
This is a really powerful API,
it's using a lot of input
to try and figure out
what's going on here.
It's been very finely tuned,
especially for
driving because of this new Do
Not Disturb feature in IOS 11.
So this is how you
would want to try and
figure out what the user
is doing rather than
trying to look at their
accelerometer data and
figure it out, okay? This
data is stored, I think for
a little longer, maybe like
seven days, I am not sure.
But you can go back and look
at this data with a from and
to, and again it's gonna call
you with the information, and
you can get all that. Now in
addition to that, you can also
get pedometer information. So
steps, user is walking around,
what are they doing.
Similar API, Start update,
you get a closure,
it calls you back. Pedometer
information really only
makes sense overtime, right?
You're not gonna ask like how
many steps are you seeing
right now? Okay, you are in
the middle of a step.
No, it's like how many did
you take in the last hour,
have you taken the last minute
or whatever? So when you call
this you get back a struct
that has a start date and
an end date of the recording
that it made and it'll tell
you how many steps were taken,
how far they walked. How many
floors they went up and
down, stuff like that, okay?
So pedometer, if you're doing
some kind of fitness app or
something like that, a
pedometer is a cool thing for
that. You can also find out
Altimeter, okay? Now this is
relative Altimeter, it can't
tell you exactly what your
altitude is, because
really it's just measuring
the barometric pressure around
you. But as you go up and
down, of course that pressure
is going to change and so
it can give you a relative
altitude change. Okay, now,
let me talk a little bit
about authorization for
all this stuff. Some of
the information here that we
talking about is considered
private to the user.
Like their steps information
and what they are doing,
standing still, driving,
that's private information.
So if you wanna get that
information the system is
going to ask the user is it
okay to share this information
with this app? And they're
gonna say yes or no. So you if
you are gonna use this private
information you need to check
the AuthorizationStatus
before you go and try and
access this data. Otherwise
it's just gonna fail and
give you an error that
explains it, but this way you
can avoid even wasting your
time calling that. And
here's the authorization
statuses you can get.
You can have notDetermined,
the user hasn't been asked
yet, okay? So we don't know
what it is. Restricted means
the user can't be asked,
okay, about this.
Maybe because they've just
turned off fitness tracking in
their phone in their Privacy
Settings so they're not gonna
have you ask because this
user just told me no.
No apps can do any of
this fitness data.
Or it's either Denied or
Authorized if they've been
asked okay what their answer
is. And of course they can go
back and change this in
their settings, right?
So if you have an app and
it depends on this,
and you can check this,
it says Denied, you can put up
an alert that says, you denied
me the access to do this,
so I can't do this feature.
If you wanna re-enable it,
go to Settings and do it,
all right? Okay, so the demo
I'm gonna do is a super little
simple one. I'm not even gonna
use device motion, I'm just
gonna use the accelerometer.
We're gonna take our
Playing Card app,
if you remember that app
from many weeks ago.
And remember it has
the cards flying around?
Here, let's actually go and
run it, here it is,
I'm gonna run it on my iPad
over here. So here it is,
remember this app right here?
I got the cards here and
I got my iPad here, tapping on
it. I've got match in the very
first cards. So what we're
gonna do is make it so
that these cards are affected
by gravity, real gravity okay?
We're gonna make it so
that the cards go towards the
center of the earth basically.
And we're gonna do that
with the accelerometer and
measure the acceleration
due to gravity.
Now, again, I'm not gonna
use device motion so
if I shake my, my iPad around,
it's, they're gonna
start flying around.
And not too fast, because it's
just acceleration. It's not
actual motion. But so, we're
not gonna worry about that,
okay? If I didn't want that,
which I probably wouldn't,
then we'd use devi-,
device motion. But
we're trying to save time, cuz
we got a lot to demo today.
So we're just gonna use
accelerometer. So let's jump
back here into Playing Card,
you all remember it here.
We got this pile of
Playing Card here.
So how are we gonna do this?
How are we gonna be make our
cards be affected by gravity?
Well, it turns out that
there's a behavior.
One of the animation behaviors
is gravity behavior and
you can specify the magnitude
and the direction that
the gravity is coming from,
okay? And so what I'm gonna do
is as my device tilts around,
I'm gonna change where
gravity is so that it goes
towards of the center of
the Earth. And that's really
easy to do in Playing Card
because we already have
this card behavior, right?
Remember this sub class
of UIDynamicBehavior
that handles our collisions
like do we allow rotation,
when we push an item, etc.,
and we just added those things
as our child behavior. So I'm
gonna do exact same thing for
gravity. So I'm gonna create a
new behavior, gonna call it my
gravityBehavior, it's gonna
be a UIGravityBehavior. And
I'm actually gonna initialize
it in exactly the same way
that I did these other ones up
here we just use a closure,
right? I'm gonna execute
a closure to initialize them.
So here I'm gonna let behavior
equal a UIGravityBehavior.
Now the only initialization
I'm gonna do at the start here
is to set the magnitude of
the gravity to 0, okay?
Now you can even control what
the magnitude of the gravity,
and remember this is not,
we're not talking about real
gravity here. We're talking
about the gravity that affects
the animation of these items,
right? So you can set that
to anything you want, okay?
Whatever gravity you want.
So I'm gonna set it to 0, and
the reason for that is
remember I said that we don't
want to turn the accelerometer
on until we're on screen.
And as soon as we go off
screen we're going to turn it
off, cuz we don't want
the accelerometer on. So
until I turn the accelerometer
on, I want no gravity to be
affecting my cards. So they'll
just do what they normally do
until I turn, until I hook
it up to the accelerometer.
All right? So there's our
behavior. Now, anytime we have
a child behavior like this,
we're gonna wanna make sure
that new items that we add to
it are added so that gravity
effects them. And of course
if when we remove an item,
we want the gravity to
stop affecting them. Oops!
And we always need to add any
of these behaviors as a child
behavior like this. Okay,
so now, our cardBehavior,
up here, That we defined
up here. Now, in addition
to doing collisions and having
this other item behavior,
and being able to be pushed
and all that, it's also
affected by gravity which
starts out zero. Okay, so
now that we can do that, let's
go back to our controller,
this is our viewController
where we make all the cards
and all that stuff. And it
knows about the card behavior.
And I'm going to turn on the
accelerometer when we appear,
and I'm gonna turn it off
when we disappear. And
when I turn it on, all I'm
gonna do is register a closure
that takes
the accelerometer's data and
puts it into that
cardBehavior's data, right?
So let's do that. I'm just
gonna first do viewDidAppear,
okay? super.viewDidAppear,
animated, all right?
And so, in viewDidAppear,
the very first thing I'm gonna
do is figure out how to get
my, motion manager going on
here. And the way that I'm
going to do that,
is by creating a shared one,
because really I can only
have one, as we talked about,
motion manager per app.
It only makes sense to do one.
So I'm gonna do that
actually in another file and
I want to show you a little
bit how what kind of what the,
conventions we might use
are to create something on
the file. Now, what I'm gonna
create here is an extension to
CMMotionManager to
add a static var,
which is the shared one, okay?
And so that's what help
people get it. So usually,
we call files that have
an extension like that.
The same, the name of the
class that we're extending and
then plus sign, and
then the description of what's
in there. In this case, it's
gonna be shared. A shared one,
so I'm gonna call it shared.
So it's called
CMMotionManager+shared.
It doesn't wanna the import
Foundation instead it
wants to import CoreMotion,
okay?
Anytime you do anything with
CoreMotion you need to import
CoreMotion. So I'm just
gonna have an extension
to CMMotionManager and it's
just gonna be a static var.
So a class var, right,
called shared which is,
is an instance of
CMMotionManager. So now,
anyone who wants to use a
MotionManager can use this one
right here and they'll
all be sharing the same.
Now, of course,
our simple app,
we're only using it
in one place, but
I just wanna to show you, this
is how you could do shared,
data if you wanted
to in your app.
All right, so viewDidAppear is
happening here, we wanna turn
on the accelerometer. First
thing we always do is what?
Check to make sure
we can do it.
Okay, so let's do that and say
if the CMMotionManager, and
now, I'm not getting
escape completion,
that's because I need to
import CoreMotion in here
as well. If I'm gonna use
CoreMotion I need to do it.
And now,
it's figuring it out for me.
And I'm gonna do shared and
I'm gonna
call the method there to check
if to see if my accelerometer
is available called
isAccelerometer Available. And
if it is available here, then
the first thing I'm gonna do
is take, tell my cardBehavior
to have it's gravityBehavior
turn it it magnitude
back to 1.0.
So we're gonna turn on the
gravity in our cardBehavior.
Then we wanna register
a closure with
the MotionManager to call us
with accelerometer updates.
And we do that by saying
CMMotionManager.shared
.startAccelerometerUpdates.
And you can see here the one
where you pull and here is the
one where we get the closure.
So we want the one
with the closure here.
We're gonna do it on
the main queue, okay?
And the handler, we'll just
double-click. And you can see
that handler has the argument
here which is the data.
That's the AccelerometerData
and it has a possible error,
which could be null,
to use the closing trailer,
the trailing closure syntax
here. Make that work.
So this is all we need to
do to get these updates.
Now, how often are we
gonna get these updates?
Well, we get to say.
We get to say CMMotionManager
.accelerometer, accelerometer
UpdateInterval,
meterUpdateInterval. What is
it called? I can't type here,
called acc, let's just go
updateinterval. No? Sorry,
.shared.accelerometer
UpdateInterval.
And, okay, think about what's
happening with these cards,
right? They're being pulled by
gravity going on. They don't
need to know instantly what
the gravity is. In fact,
probably once every half
second would be enough, but
to be sure, I'll go maybe once
every tenth of a second, okay?
It doesn't, I don't really
do much in the closure, so
it's really not a performance
hit to change that too much.
So we'll go about every tenth,
we could go fifth, and
we could kinda tune this, we
might find that once a second
is enough to get
the behavior we want.
In which case, we should
use once per second, so
this is something we have to
tune. All right, now, we wanna
get AccelerometerData,
where is it? It's in here,
this is that struck that has
the acceleration x, y, and z.
So I'm gonna say if I can
let x, which is gonna be my
acceleration in x, equal
that data? If we have it,
if it wasn't an error,
acceleration.x.
And I'm gonna let y =
the data?.acceleration.y.
So if I'm able to get
the information, if I can't,
I'll just ignore this,
I'm gonna ignore errors.
I should handle them
if I need to here, but
I'm gonna ignore errors.
So if that comes through, now,
I need to set the gravity
vector, okay, the direction of
gravity, in my CardBehavior's
GravityBehavior. Okay, now,
this is an interesting
thing here to wanna do,
because the AccelerometerData
is in with respect to
the device, okay? If I hold
this device up right here,
okay?
Here's the home button, down.
That means in the y direction
this is gravity 1.0, okay? And
this will be if it is going up
it will be negative gravity
right here. And this is the x
direction and this is the z
direction back behind, okay?
So that's different then
possibly, my reference frame
of my animation because for
example, I might be rotated,
okay?
So if I'm rotated, maybe my
app does autorotation, and so
up is actually the x location.
Do you see what I'm saying?
So the hardware and the view
are not quiet the same. Now,
before we try and
deal with that,
let's just try saying
that the CardBehaviors's,
GravityBehavior's direction,
gravityDirection is called,
which is a CGVector, which
just means x and y extent,
right? We'll just try
setting it to the x and
y of the accelerometer. Let's
just see what happens when we
do that, okay? Because that
kinda should work. Let's,
let's run and see what happens
here, though. All right,
so, so
you can see what's going
on here on this screen, okay?
I'll have to tell you what I'm
doing. So here, I'm holding my
device now straight up, okay?
And you can actually see,
look.
All my cards are actually
going up. If I turn it upside
down, now, they'll fall down.
Back to the right side,
woo hoo, they all go back up.
So gravity is working,
but it's kind of anti-grav,
okay? It's working
opposite direction. Now, can
anyone think why it's going in
the opposite direction and
why? Okay, where is our origin
in, in our drawing thing?
It's in the upper left, right?
So if we have gravity which
is down, where is down in
a coordinate system where the
upper left is 0, 0? It's up,
right? So up towards zero,
zero. So that's the problem.
So we need to, to kind of
reverse y because the device's
gravity down is different than
our coordinate system. And
actually, it could work,
it works. Right now I have my
orientation locked so
as I rotate my device
it's not autorotating. But if
I auto rotate it, then my view
would constantly be changing.
So how are we gonna fix that?
Let's go back to our code over
here. And what we're gonna do
is change this x and y from
hardware coordinate system to
our view coordinate system and
we're gonna do this,
I'm gonna have a little thing
to type it fast here. We're
gonna do this depending on
the orientation of the device.
So I'm switching on
the device's orientation. So
remember we used UIDevice to
see if it was an iPad. Well,
we can also use UIDevice to
find out what the orientation
is, either portrait,
portrait upside down,
that means portrait with
the home button up on the top,
or landscape left or right.
Landscape left is the home
button on the left,
landscape mode. And of course,
these need to be VAR's and by
the way, yes, you can say if
VAR x and have this be a VAR,
that is legal. Probably,
maybe didn't get that when you
read your homework part of it
early in the quarter, but you
can. So,uh, if I'm in portrait
mode, then we've already
seen that Y needs to be -1,
right? Because up is down and
down is up. If we're in
portraitUpsideDown, they
actually match up.
Okay, in portraitUpsideDown,
the home button is
at the top and so
is our coordinate system. So
we're all in good shape. And
landscapeLeft and
right, actually x and
y have been swapped.
Okay, cuz in landscape,
it's the x part of the device
that is now the vertical, so
we'll have to swap them.
And in landscapeLeft,
we swapped them and
it's upside down as well. So
let's go see this in action.
And we're currently locked to
portrait. Okay, first of all,
now I have my device on me,
this up here.
So now my device is flat,
okay, so acceleration is in
the z direction, so x and
y are 0. So you can see it's
just doing it's normal,
floating around business.
Now what I'm gonna do
is I'm gonna tilt it up so
the home button is down. And
sure enough, gravity pulls
them all down to the bottom.
Now I'm gonna turn it
upside down, okay?
Now gravity is pulling it
all to the other side.
If you're watching on the
screen, if you can't really,
understand what I'm doing,
maybe. But now let's go to
landscape right, right? And
over to landscape left, okay?
So it's working, gravity
is pulling on these and
they're still bouncing
off each other and
have those forces as well.
But they're doing that.
Now I'm gonna unlock my,
rotation here,
I'm gonna go swipe, turn this
lock off and go back. Now
it's gonna auto rotate. Okay,
so here we're in portrait
mode and these all go to the
bottom and now if I go flat,
for example, in all my. So
let's actually go here and get
these things loading a little
bit. And if I go to landscape,
you can see that they
stay at the bottom, okay.
So they're staying
down at the bottom,
no matter which way I go.
So even though my coordinate
system is changing here
because I'm auto-rotating,
it's always knowing
which way is down. Okay,
makes sense? All right, go
back go back to blocked here.
Here we go, so now we can see
it going in other directions.
All right, now, one other
thing we have to do here
back in our code is turn
off accelerometer updates,
okay? Cuz we always want,
every time we turn it on,
think of somewhere where it
makes sense to turn it off.
In our case, it's really
easy where that is.
That's going to be in
viewWillDisappear. So
let's go to viewWillDisappear.
Super, whoops,
super.viewWillDisappear.
And here,
we're gonna do two things,
I'm going to tell my card
behaviors gravity behavior to
set it's magnitude to 0, okay?
So stop doing gravity,
and I'm also going to
tell my CMMotionManager,
the shared one, to stop
accelerometer updates. Okay,
so you see how I've paired
starting it with stopping it.
Always start and stop.
Okay, that is it.
Let's go back to our
slides here, And
talk about our next topic
which is the camera and
the photo library
actually as well.
And this API for doing this
is actually very simple.
Its just a modal view control
that you get from iOS and you
present it modaly that's as
simple as that. The usage here
is that you're gonna create
it, kinda configure it, set it
to delegate because it won't
work without the delegate,
that's how it tells you what
the photo it took was. And
then you present it and then
listen to the delegate methods
that get's sent to you.
So, it's actually very simple,
to use the camera.
What the user can do,
by the way,
with the camera depends on
the platform, all right.
Newer devices have really
awesome cameras, both front
and back, for example, with
flash and all these things but
older devices don't. So
just like we did when we did
Core Motion, we're gonna wanna
ask what's available? Now,
what's interesting is with
the same view controller,
you can ask for
a picture from the camera but
you can also ask for a picture
from the user's photo library
or from their camera roll,
right.
The camera roll is where kinda
of recently taken photos,
get dropped in. So the same
view control can kind of
do those different things but
they are different.
Okay, the UIs of them are, are
quite different actually and
we'll talk about
that in a second. So
not every particular, camera
can do every type of media.
So, not every camera for
example can do video.
Not every camera can do live
photo. Everyone know live
photo is? That's like where
you take a burst of images,
around the time you, you say
picture. So you kinda have to
ask, is this media type
available for this source,
usually the camera.
Okay, and you do that here.
Now these media types
are really unfortunately
this weird type here kUTType
something which is not even
a string. It's a cfstring
it turns out and
that does not automatically
bridge like a nsstring does.
And they're defined in
MobileCoreServices which means
to use camera you have to
import MobileCoreServices. And
you have to use these and cast
them to a string, okay? So,
sorry about that.
I didn't write this API,
so we'll see, hope they
fix that in the future,
but it's a little annoying.
You can also find out things
about, particular camera
devices like, do they have
flash and things like that,
that's all part of
the UIImagePickerController.
Notice that all these
methods are static funks.
You don't even have to create
a UIImagePickerController to
do it, you can just ask
the UIImagePickerClass
about these things. So here's
kinda collecting all that
into some code that would put
up a picker to capture video.
All right, so the first thing
we're gonna do there is create
an ImagePickerController
called picker, okay.
Then I'm gonna set the type
that I want to be movie.
I'm gonna create a little
local variable media type
movie which is that weird
kuTTypeMovie thing as
a string, okay.
Now I'm gonna set myself
to be the picker delegate.
If I don't do that, I'll never
find out what photo was taken.
So I have to do that,
it's an absolute requirement.
Then I'm gonna ask you why
ImagePickerController,
by the way I say UIIPC because
it just won't fit on the slide
someplace. So imagine that
says UIImagePickerController.
That is source type available,
camera.
So I'm gonna see is there
a camera available on this
device, which for
most things there is a camera.
The simulator however,
will not have a camera so
this is a good way to
test this line of code.
Then I'm gonna set, if it does
have a camera, I'm gonna set
the source type of the picker
to be the camera. Okay,
don't forget to set the source
type where you wanna do it.
Now, this source type is where
you would say photo library if
you wanted to let the user
choose a photo from the photo
library instead, okay,
or the camera roll. So
then we're gonna say, tell me
the available media types for
that source, camera or
whatever source type that I'm
using. And I'm gonna look in
the array that comes back and
see if movies, kUTType movie,
is in there. And if it is,
I'm ready to go. I'm gonna set
my media types to be movie and
then we're gonna put
the picker up. So
this is how you put a picker
on the screen. All right?
Now when I, I told you earlier
that you can configure this
picker, okay, to, when
you're putting it on screen.
What are some of
the things you can do?
Well, you can just say
that it allows editing.
So, in that sense the user
can take a photo and
then even before it
comes back to you,
they can zoom in on it
a little, move around. Video,
they can even edit the video
before it returns to you. So
you're basically has in place
editing right in the UI,
the UIImagePickerController,
puts up, which is kinda cool.
You can, if you're doing
video, you can limit the video
capture to a certain number
of minutes or to a certain
quality using these VARs right
here. To present the picker,
all you do is use the same
present modally that we did to
do a UI alert controller, or
the same thing we did to put
our document up in Emoji art.
And here's where you want
to think a little bit about
the platform you're on.
Because an iPad, if you're
gonna put the camera up, it
needs to be full screen modal.
You cannot put it in a popover
if it's the camera, okay?
Don't put it in a form sheet,
don't put it in a page sheet,
full screen modal, okay?
That's actually on
both iPad and iPhone.
On the iPad for the photo
library, or the photos app,
you want to put in a popover,
okay? And then on the iPhone,
it's gonna be full screen
always on the iPhone, okay? So
just clear about, I just want
to take a moment to make sure
that sinks in. On iPad, full
screen for the camera, popover
for the photo library, okay?
So if you had an app where you
could pick your image either
from a camera or from a photo
library on the iPad, you'd
have to have two buttons.
One that brought
up the camera and
one that brings up the photo
library in a popover. Okay,
once the thing has
been presented and
the user picks and possibly
edits their photo then
the delegate method
will be called,
saying that it did finish
picking media with info, okay?
And this info is a dictionary,
and inside that dictionary is
all the information about
what was picked. Okay, and
we're gonna talk about what
all that is on the next slide
but this is how you get
the information. Now,
once you've got all
the information,
you're going to dismiss
your view controller, okay?
This is actually
old slide here,
that's just called dismiss
not dismiss view controller
animated [LAUGH] right there.
And so similarly,
if the user went to
take a picture and
said cancel, then you're
gonna get the dele method,
delegate method, imagePicture
ControllerDidCancel.
And you're gonna do
picker.presentingView
Controller?.dismiss, okay?
So let's look
at that dictionary, that info
dictionary that comes along
with didFinishPicking
MediaWithInfo and
see what we can get from this
UI image picker UI that lets
the user take a picture with
the camera or do the photo
library. So you're gonna find,
there's one thing that
tells you what was chosen,
image or a movie.
Then if it's an image, you're
gonna have both the original
image that was taken and
also the edited image if they
edited it. And those are just
UI images, all right,
then there's Image URL,
that's the URL for the image.
By the way, that is in
a temporary location,
make sure you move it to
somewhere, you know, in your
sandbox that's more permanent
if you want to keep it.
CropRect will tell you what
rectangle the user cropped it
to, if you allow editing,
they can crop it
to a certain rectangle, you
can find that out. You can get
some metadata about
the media that was chosen,
maybe the GPS location
that you're at,
if the user allows that to be
captured, things like that.
If it was a live photo that
they took, then you get
a PHLivePhoto object in there.
I'm not gonna talk about
the photo library framework
which is PH stuff but
you can get that. Also PHAsset
which is just a struct
that kind of describes the
photo, but it doesn't actually
have the image.
You can then use it with
the photo library to
get the image data.
And if you have video,
then you get a MediaURL,
which is just a URL to a file
in your sandbox that contains
the video that was captured,
all right? So
that's what you get back from
the UIImagePickerController.
Now when you get
this image back,
if you get an image not
a video, if you get an image,
you might want to save it to
the camera roll. Okay, now it
totally depends on why you're
asking them for an image.
If it's purely for your app's
purposes, maybe not but
if it's something where it's,
you're like a camera app of
some sort. And you want, it's
a photo that they might be
interested in using in other
circumstances then you can
save it using this write
image write to save photo,
so unfortunately,
this is asynchronous.
Unfortunately, it doesn't
use a closure API, instead,
it has a kind of target and
selector, right?
So the callback is a target
and a selector but
it's essentially, you can kind
of imagine what this would be
like if it had a nice
closure that called you back.
asynchronous is the image
might be quite large. In fact,
And the reason it's
some of the cameras have very
good cameras that are very
large, intra, you, you know,
megabyte sized, images.
And then you talk
about a live photo,
you're talking about really
large images. Now, when you're
talking about saving photos,
if you're really an app that
deals with photos.
Maybe you manipulate them and
you have filters and things
like that, really you're,
this is only just the lightest
weight API for doing image
picking by the user. There's
a whole other framework called
PHPhotoLibrary which
basically is an API for
accessing the photos app,
the photos that are in
the photos app on your phone.
Super powerful,
very highly efficient API, you
definitely wanna check that
out if you're doing,
really doing photo stuff.
You could of course save
the image to your sandbox,
if you're just using
the image in your own app.
Okay, that's perfectly legal
as well. In addition to
PhPhotoLibrary as a place to
do really cool media stuff,
there's also AVCaptureDevice.
That's a whole API for
doing much more sophisticated
image capture, image capture,
right? That you're gonna
see when we do the demo,
the ImagePickerController has
a very simple kind of camera
to it. So AV capture device
let's you control a lot more
of the aspects of
the photo being taken. Now,
what else can you do
with the ImagePickerView?
It allows you to actually
provide your own UI, even for
the button that
says Take a Photo.
Okay, so you get this default
UI that is very simple,
it lets you take a photo and
cancel and all that.
But you can actually put
your own view on there, and
your view can even replace
the existing camera controls.
If you say,
Show Camera Controls is false,
then yours will be the only
UI that lays on top. The kind
of, what do you call it? The
coordinate system that your
frame of your view is gonna
be in is the UIScreen.main's
bounds, okay? So we haven't
really talked about UIScreen,
it's just an object,
it happens to have, a static
VAR called main. And you can
get the bounds of that and
that'll tell you the bounds of
the camera, so that you know
where to put your UI on top
of that. You can also zoom or
translate the image that
you£re capturing, okay, but
with an app line transform. So
maybe you wanna scale it up so
that it is zoomed in or
something like that,
you can do that. Once you
get the image back from
the PickerController, you
might want to process it, and
there's quite a lot of
[LAUGH] API in iOS for
processing images. Most of
it is in a framework called
Core Image, which I strongly
recommend you take a look at.
It has literally a couple of
hundred different filters for
doing blur,
changing the colors,
you know, doing sepia tones,
smoothing edges.
Just about everything you
could possibly imagine doing
to manipulate your image,
this Core Image will do.
There's also as part of
the whole machine learning
stuff that came out in iOS,
is that, I think it's iOS 11
or iOS 10, I guess iOS 11.
There's a whole framework
called the Vision Framework,
and Vision can look at
an image and recognize things
like faces, bar codes, things
like that. You can even,
with machine learning, teach
it to recognize, you know, is
that a hat, okay? So [LAUGH]
you can even do that as well.
So if you're doing
sophisticated image stuff,
again, I don't have time
to cover any of this but
just know that it's there.
All right, so that's it for
today except for the demo.
I'm going to do a demo and
what we're going to do is
we're going to make it so
that an emoji art, we can
set our background image
with the camera. It's obvious
thing to want to do instead
of having to drag and
drop from another app, and
our next lecture is our
last lecture, okay?
It's on accessibility. And, of
course, one week from today,
you're going to have
your final presentations.
Be ready to go on that. We're
about halfway through your
final projects. Hopefully
you're halfway done? I hope,
anyway. So, that's about it.
So let's dive right into
the demo, unless there's any
questions about that? Okay,
let's get rid of that and lets
get rid of playing card here.
And here we are with emoji
art. All right, so hopefully
all of you remember emoji
art from the last lecture,
the last lecture was
a quite a while ago,
from Thanksgiving,
but here we are.
Remember last time we did
all these various segues and
stuff. But, what I'm gonna do,
in terms of UI for
this camera thing is, I'm just
gonna add a button right here,
okay, which is going to
bring up the camera.
And then, when you take
a picture, it's gonna use that
picture as the background,
couldn't be simpler.
So, let's go add that button,
and go down here, and say, bar
button item, of course. Drag
it out here. I believe yes,
there is a system one here for
a camera. There it is,
looks just like a camera. Now,
I'm going to connect this up
to my code both with
an action and with an outlet.
And the reason I'm
going to do that,
is I'm going to check to see
if my device has a camera, and
if it doesn't, I'm going to
disable this button. Okay? And
I told you, you always have
to check for the device,
and that's how I'm going
to check. So let's do that,
let's go over here.
Nice and wide,
let's put all our camera
stuff at the top. Mark
camera. Alright, so
let's go over here,
I'm just going to control
drag. Do the outlet first.
We'll call this my
camera button. And then,
let's do our action.
And of course, it's
gonna be BarButtonItem type.
And we're gonna call this,
how about we'll call this take
background photo, cuz that's
what this button does it takes
the photo and this is going to
be the background. All right,
that's it for our UI,
we don't have to do anything
more there, so let's implement
this stuff, let's start right
off with the camera button.
I'm going to write when its
set, I'm going to enable it or
disable it depending on
whether I have a camera.
So I'm just gonna say that
my camera Button.isEnabled
equals my
UIImagePickerController
.isSourceTypeAvailable.camera
okay? Here is why I
told you gotta test it I'm
testing it right here okay? So
these are not gonna be able to
get into this code down here
if we don't have a camera.
All right, take a photo really
easy, we just create a picker
UImagePickerController.
We're gonna configure it to
have the right sourceType.
We want the camera. Now again,
we could do photo library and
stuff here, if we did
Photo Library though,
that little camera button
would be bring up or
pop over. Okay, but here we're
gonna do camera, so it's gonna
be full screen presentation.
We want an image here, so
I'm gonna say the mediaTypes
equals an array that has
kUTTypeImage, okay.
And this is not turning purple
because it's not recognized
cuz I have to go up here and
say import MobileCoreServices,
only just to get that one
symbol. That's the only
reason I had to do that. And
now it's complaining
that it's a CFString. So
I'm gonna say as string, okay?
So that's the types I want.
I just want images,
I don't want video.
Just want images in this case.
And sure, we'll allow editing,
allows editing, true, why not?
Most importantly,
we gotta set the delegate
to ourself or
we'll never find out about
anything the camera did and
then we can just present
this picker animated true of
course. Now we are getting an
error here of course because
we are say delegating=self but
we don't say that we
are a UIImagePicker
ControllerDelegate.
And you'd think that
would be enough to,
when we compile get rid of
the error but it says cannot
assign value to UIImagePicker
ControllerDelegate and
UINavigation
ControllerDelegate what?
Why is it saying that?
Well unfortunately the
UIPickerController I believe
it's a subclass of
UINavigationController so
you have to,
be its delegate as well.
So we just have to
say UINavigate, and
this is the case by the way
where the fix it down here,
you do not want this fix it,
this fix it is to cast self,
to be these things,
which it£s not. So
be carefull of fix its, it£s
always the right thing. So
here I£m gonna be UINavigation
ControllerDelegate as well.
Luckily, neither of these
have any required methods,
although, in
UIImagePickerController,
they should be required.
Because, you can£t really do
anything without them. And
let's jump right to
those delegate methods.
There's only two of them.
So image picker. There's this
one, which is cancel. And then
there's this one, other one,
imagePickerController.
Which is the didFinish
PickingMediaWithInfo. And
in both of them, I'm gonna say
the picker.presenting
ViewController dismiss,
okay anyone it's time to
go animated true. Now,
who is the pickers presenting
the view controller? It's us.
Cuz we're presenting it. So,
I could actually just get rid
of this right?
This would actually be okay.
But I kinda like to do
this explicitly. Just,
I don't know, for some reason
it just, you know, because
that dismiss has that weird
thing where it'll look and
see if you're presented by,
a person and... I like to have
it explicit to be the pickers
presenting the viewController.
What if I put up another view
controller that presented
the pet camera and then it
was unwinding back to here or
something like that. I don't
know, so. I like to do that,
and I wanna do this in
both places, both when,
if it's canceled or
whether it successfully
picks some media here.
All right, so now we have this
ImagePickerController and
it successfully picks some,
some image or whatever that we
want to use. How do we get
that image out of there?
Well it comes out of this
dictionary right here.
So we're going to look
in that dictionary and
say if I can let the image
equal that info dictionary and
I'm going to look at the key
UIImagePickerController.
Edited image. Okay?
I allow editing, so
I'm going to do this.
Now, notice that the type in
the dictionary is any because
that might be UI image,
it might be URL, okay? It
could be a PH live photo, so
it's any- so we are required
here to say as a UIImage.
Okay. So this gets the image.
Now, I'm going to do two other
small things here. One is,
I'm gonna actually say if this
is nill, because maybe I went
back and changed this to false
in the future, then I'm going
to also back up by grabbing
the UIImagePicker
OriginalImage,
okay? So basically I'm just,
if I ever change this,
I want the rest of the code to
still work. So I'm just kinda,
if this is nil then I'm
gonna grab this one
instead. The other thing I
wanna do here is shrinks this
image down a little bit.
Because, some of these cameras
are huge. I£m, this image
would be four megabytes in
size. And in emoji art,
you know, usually they don£t
want the emojis to be these
tiny little dots in a gigantic
image, right? So
meaning the emoji only has so
much resolution.
So I'm gonna shrink this down.
And I'm gonna do that with a
little function that I have in
my utilities called scaled by.
And scaled by is the world's
cheapest little image scaler.
It actually scales it, not
even by the area of the image,
but it scales
the edges by that much
which is kinda
freaky way to do it.
But it's simple code and
you can go look at it,
it's in the utilities .swift
that I provide with EmojiArt.
Okay, so now I've got
the image I want, hopefully,
right? if let, so
hopefully, I got the image.
Now I need to set this as my
EmojiArt's background, right?
Well, because we wrote
our code so nicely,
we can just say,
emojiArtBackgroundImage =.
Now I wanna say image, but
do you remember what this
argument is? It's a tuple,
remember that, we changed
[LAUGH] that to a tuple?
What am I gonna put as
the URL here? Because I got
that image directly from the
camera and I don't have a URL.
So I'm gonna have to, for now
anyway, and if I have time,
I'll show you a better way I'm
gonna have to create a URL for
this thing, okay?
And I'm gonna create a URL in
my sandbox, okay, that stores
this image. I actually have
a little utility function
to do that as well. You can go
look at that in the code. So
I'm gonna say so
I'm gonna create that.
Also, and the other thing
we wanna do, by the way,
is note that our document
has changed here, right?
If we set our background
image, then our document
has definitely changed. So I'm
going to create this little
URL, let url =, take my image,
and I, the function I have
is called storeLocallyAsJPEG
with a name.
So that's what this does.
It store, takes a UIImage,
all right, this is a UIImage
extension method, and
it stores it as a name.
Now, I need a unique name for
this thing. A really great
unique name is the current
date as seconds since
January 1st, 1970, okay?
Turns out the easy
way to get that,
which is Date.timeInterval
SinceReferenceDate, okay?
Of course, this is going to be
seconds so that's a double.
So I'm going to turn it into a
string by just stringifying it
here. And now I have
a nice unique name for
this JPEG. Now, I hate
this because I just took
a picture with the camera and
I'm having to create this
random file in my file system.
When am I gonna clean this
thing up? Okay, I'm gonna have
to find out when my document
was deleted somehow or and
what about on iCloud? This
is not gonna work on iCloud.
If I open this on another
device, it can't see my
sandbox on this other device.
So this is terrible, okay?
Now, we're gonna be close on
time here so I don't know if
I'm gonna be able to
show you how to fix this.
But I don't like this, but
we're gonna do this just so
that we can see
this all working so
you can see the Camera API
working, etc., okay?
So let's do that.
Let's take a look at this.
Let's go to our iPad here. So
here's EmojiArt, let's
create a new document here.
I just created, I pressed
Create New Document. And
you can see we got our camera
up there in the upper right.
And notice that it's also
enabled, that's good.
That means we have a camera
on this device. So
I'm gonna click that camera.
Okay,
it's gonna load up the camera,
bring up this, here it is.
We're gonna do a blast from
the past right here and
go picture our picture
from our concentration.
This is kind of
nostalgia day here,
kinda going back to playing
card in this. So here,
let's try and take a picture
without that shadow in there.
There we go. And here's
what I was talking about,
where I can zoom in on this,
or
change the cropping rectangle
cuz we allow editing. So
we'll do that. And
I'm gonna hit Use Photo and
we're gonna see if
this is gonna work.
And it doesn't work.
Now, why this doesn't work?
You're like, no,
now I've gotta go debug this.
This couldn't
possibly not work.
This is one of those cases
where you look at our code.
It's so simple here,
it couldn't work well actually
this doesn't work, believe it
or not because of the view
controller life cycle. When we
press that camera button and
bring up the camera
it actually covers up
our view controller entirely.
And then when it goes away,
"view will appear" gets called
on our view controller. Do
you see why? Because it just
appeared. It was covered up
and the camera went away and
now it appeared.
Well let's a look at our
viewWillAppear down here.
Here's our viewWillAppear.
What do we do in
viewWillAppear?
We open our document, okay?
And we open it no matter what.
So if it's already open,
we open it again. We go back
to disk and get it again.
That's what's happening here,
it actually was working. It
put that image in there, but
then it reopened the document
and went back to blank, cuz it
was an untitled document. So
this is a simple fix here.
We're just gonna say,
if our document state is not,
Normal.
Then, we'll open our
document here. Okay?
But that's kind of a tricky
bug, when I went to prepare,
add this before class. I was
like why doesn't that work?
And so this is a little bit
of a tricky one there, but
this will fix it.
So let's go back up there and
get this code on screen for
our camera here and
run again. To bring our
untitled document up again,
oops. That one screen so
you can see it.
All right, so
gather untitled documents.
So I'm gonna hit the camera
button again. Go up here,
let's take a photo and
get in focus right there.
Cute little guy there, okay?
So this now I'm gonna say
use photo and sure enough,
here it is, okay?
Here's our photo and
we can add apples or whatever,
maybe like a bee caught in the
web up there, make sense. And
we're done. Hopefully we'll
get a thumbnail there.
We even get a thumbnail,
that's great. Okay. Now,
let's talk a little bit about
what I was talking about where
this is bad because it creates
a little local file for this.
How are we gonna fix that?
Well I'm gonna fix that at
light speed here because we
have ten minutes left.
The way I'm gonna do it is
I'm actually gonna store
the camera's image in my
emoji art document, okay.
So I'm not gonna store it
as a URL, a separate thing.
I'm actually gonna store the
data embedded in my document.
Okay, that way it'll work in
icloud and all the stuff and
I won't have to create the URL
it's going to be great.
Now I'm not gonna do that for
documents that do have a URL
because I don't want my
to duplicate that image,
no need to do that we just
go out on the internet and
get it. But for cases where I
don't have the URL I'm going
to do that. So let's again at
light speed I'm going to limit
the explanation here because
time constraint but I'll.
I think you'll learn something
from doing it, let's go do it.
Now the first thing I
need to do is go back to
my EmojiArt model and make it
capable of having the image,
cuz right now it has
to have a URL. So
I'm gonna make having
URL be optional and
have a new one called
ImageData which is just a data
object. Notice this is not
a UI image cuz this is
not a UI thing because this is
my model. And since I can now
have either URL or image data
I'm gonna go down to here and
have a different
initializer or
another initializer actually
that let's me initialize
an image data based.
Oops, not image data,
data. This is imageData
= imageData. Okay so
now I can create my emoji art
with either URL or image data.
Now, what about Codeable, what
about turning this to .json,
is this all just going to
work? Well yeah, no errors
right? And in fact it is gonna
work because Codeable knows
how to deal with optionals, it
knows how to write out datas,
so this is all perfectly fine,
it's all just gonna work. So
that was easy, let's go back.
To our emoji art view
controller. Now what's
the problem here? Well,
the real problem over here is
this method right down here.
Okay, this is the core of the
problem, right here [LAUGH]
okay? This is our
emojiArtBackgroundImage,
which is that tuple.
Remember the tuple we had?
Okay, well, that tuple
has a URL in the image.
But now it might be image
data in the image. Okay, so
we have to fix this. This
can no longer be this tuple.
It has to be some other
type that's either a URL or
it's the image data. Now what
kind of data structure we
use when something is either
one thing or another?
What do we use? What?
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Any, we could use any, but
that's not very Swifty.
>> A enum?
>> enum, absolutely.
Let's use an enum here.
I'm gonna say
enum ImageSource,
I'm gonna call it.
And it's gonna have the remote
case which has a URL and
the UIImage. Okay, and it's
going to have the local case
where it's an image data and a
UIImage. Now for convenience,
I'm gonna create a var.
Notice they both have UIImage.
So I'm gonna create
a var called image here,
which returns to that UIImage.
And I'm just gonna do that
by switching on myself. And
in the case of a remote, then
I don't care what the URL is.
But I'm gonna get the image
back here and return it.
Okay, and in the case of
local, I don't care what
the data is. I'm just gonna
get the image and return that
image, okay? So this is just
a nice little convenience var,
so I can get the image,
no matter which one it is.
All right, so
now I'm gonna change this.
I'm gonna change this tuple
to be an ImageSource which
has to be optional because we
might have a blank document.
It has no background. So we'll
have to leave it optional. And
I'm not gonna have it be
a computed var anymore.
I'm gonna have it be stored.
And I'm gonna use didSet to do
all this stuff down here. And
I don't have to keep the URL
separately anymore, cuz it's
built into the ImageSource.
And everywhere where
I did newValue,
well in the computed sense,
is now this thing,
okay? Which, is optional, so
it might be optional there.
So this is also optional. And,
the image, which is this var
I just created right there,
is not optional, so
we'll take that away. So this
is great! I just fixed it!
Okay, the moment you
heard background image.
Now of course we need to go
all the places we set and
get this, okay, to fix it to
work. Well, let's start with
our camera, where we set the
camera. That's right up here.
This is the code right here
where we say url image. Well,
I don't wanna do url anymore
so I'm gonna get rid of that.
So that clearly makes this be
the local case where I'm gonna
have imageData and the image
that was passed in. So
where do I get the imageData?
Well, we know how to do that.
I'm gonna say if
I can let the imageData equal
the UI JPEG thing, this thing
right here, UIImageJPEG
Representation, of the image,
will have a lossless
compression right there.
And as long as we are able to
do that, then we will do this.
Otherwise, I probably have
a to do here to go and
put up an alert, alert user of
bad camera input or something,
okay? Cuz I wasn't able to
turn the thing from the camera
into a JPEG, for some reason.
I don't know why that
would ever happen but
I should probably put
up an alert here.
Okay, so we fixed that one.
Where else do we do this?
Well, we do it when we drop,
okay, right?
When we drop an image in,
drag and drop a background,
of course we do it there. Now
here, look at all this stuff
we did last lecture to go
put up an alert if the thing
we dropped in we couldn't
get the image. Actually, we
don't have to do that anymore.
Because now if someone drags
in a bad URL we can use the
image, use its image data. So
I'm actually gonna
get rid of all of
this stuff that we did last
time. What a waste of time
last lecture was. And instead
I'm gonna go back to exactly
what we had before which is
use the image fetcher. Okay,
but what I'm gonna do here is
well, first we gotta update
this, right, to the background
image in the ImageFetcher
world. So this is remote
with the URL and the image.
However, what if we had to
resort to our backup image?
Because then it's not really
remote. Now it's become local.
So I'm going to say
here if the image was
the imageFetcher's
backup image
then I'm going to do
one thing, else, oops.
Else I'm gonna do another. So
the else is to do the normal
remote case cuz I didn't
use the backup image. But
if I do use the backup image
here, this becomes local and
we have to have the image
data here, Data. So
I need to get the image data
here too. So I'm going to say
if I can let imageData equal
that UI JPEG thing. There it
is. Image compression,
lossless. Just go in here, and
I'm gonna do this.
What am I'm gonna do if not?
If I wasn't doing,
you want I'm gonna do?
I'm going to present
that warning thing.
What was the name of that
thing? Bad URL warning,
bad URL? There it is,
presentBadURLWarning for
that URL. That same alert
that we were doing before,
I'm just gonna present that
if I wasn't able to take
the image that was dragged and
get it to imageData.
Again, I don't know why it
would ever not be able to.
But yeah, let's make our code.
Okay, good, woohoo.
Now every single place where
we set the background image,
both the camera and
the other one is now setting
it to this nice enum here.
What about where we use it?
Okay, well the primary place
where we use it is right here
where all this red is, which
is our model, right? Because
someone sets an emojiArt model
and we have to obviously get
the right data out of there
somehow or they're asking for
it. And we're gonna give it
back to them depending on
the two different cases. So
let's do the get case first,
it's quite simple. Where,
instead of looking at the URL
now I just need to look
at this image source thing,
emojiArtBackgroundImage.
Get the image source.
I still want to do this,
which is to get all
the emojis. But I'm only gonna
call this URL one here if this
imageSource is the remote ca-,
case. So I'm gonna switch
on this imageSource. And
if it's the remote case, where
I'm gonna grab the URL, and
I don't care about the image
in this case, then I'm gonna
do this. All right, and
what if it's the local case,
okay, where we got this
imageData? Well, then I'm just
going to return an EmojiArt
that takes imageData instead.
[SOUND] All right, that's it.
So that was easy.
The get case of that was, was
really easy to do and obvious,
what we're doing there.
What about the set case?
Little more complicated.
First of all, we don't
do the tuple (nil, nil).
We just say nil cuz it's
an optional image source right
there. Still wanna do this.
Still wanna check and
see if there's a URL and
try to go fetch it if we can.
And if we can successfully
fetch it, then we do wanna do
remote url kinda image
just like we did before.
Now, I'm gonna do the same
thing here that I did
with drop, which is I'm gonna
use any image data I can find
in the emoji art that you're
setting on me and use it as
the backup image. Okay, so
let's take this down here and
say, imageFetch.backup = the
image that's in the EmojiArt
that you're passing me, so I
better create a var for that.
So I'll get the imageData
out of the newValue. And
then I'll get the oops, I'll
get the image by saying well,
if the imageData is
not nil then I'm gonna
return a UIImage from
that data. Otherwise,
I'll just return nil. In other
words, there is no image data
in that EmojiArt so I can't
use it as a backup. Okay,
in that case I'm not going
to be able to load this,
which is fine. That's no
different than it was before.
All right, so there's
our imageFetcher backup.
So now we'll just
say imageFetcher,
fetch that URL. Now,
when that comes back, okay?
We have to use the same exact
thing we did down with drop,
is check and see if we
used the backup image.
Cuz if we used
the backup image,
we're in the local case.
So again, I'm gonna say, if
the image that we used equals
our imagefetcher.backup, then,
I'm gonna use the local
case with imageData,
right? This is the image
data from up here
which we know this is going to
not be nil because we wouldn't
have gotten this to be not
nil if this weren't nil.
So fine, now what if the thing
has no URL, URL at all?
What if we have an emoji
art and it has no URL?
It's just image data only, so
we'd better handle that case
as well. So here I'm gonna
say, where's the other side
of that if, here it is.
I'm gonna say, else if
the image does not equal nil,
in other words it has no URL
but it does have an image,
them I'm just going to use the
information here that we have.
I don't think I have to say
self there, otherwise image,
else, where are we here?
Else if,
sorry, so
here I can do this, set this
emojiArtBackgroundImage stuff
using the stuff we have
directly from the emoji art
image that came through.
So we just here set our
emojiArtBackgroundImage here
to be the local case
with the imageData and
the image, all right?
Unfortunately, I also need
to do this right here,
do I have time? No, I don't,
this really [LAUGH] wants to
be put in to another function,
right? You never want to copy
and paste code like that,
but we have 30 seconds left so
I'm going to leave that. So,
hopefully I did all this and
it's gonna work, let's try,
it's the world's fastest
demo here. Okay, so
I'm gonna make a new document
since the other document
is with the old style.
So, let's go ahead and
use our camera, oops, sorry.
Cancel, all right, so
I'm gonna use the camera here,
let's get our fun guy
again here, oops.
There we go, zoom in on him
a bit, we'll use that photo.
So we have this photo here,
let's put, again, a bee up
here flying near the web. So
now when we close this here,
hopefully we can see
this on other devices, so
lets go over and
run this on the simulator.
All right here we go, we're on
our simulator right here, so
totally different device
than our iPad. In fact,
I'm gonna get them both on
screen at the same time here,
let's make this a little
bit smaller. So
we've got these two different
devices and we can see that
we're on iCloud drive, that
this document that we created
right here has appeared.
So let's open it up, and
sure enough, we can see it
with the background image,
because it's not referencing
it by the URL anymore.
It actually brought the image
that we dragged in, or in this
case that we've selected with
the camera, into our document.
And we could,
put a little apple on here.
And that'll save it up to
iCloud Drive, you can see
right here that it's in the
process of uploading it. Over
here, in my device, you saw
it just download there, so,
if we below here, hopefully,
well, there we go, we have our
apple, okay? So that way we're
able to share our document
across iCloud Drive, even
though the background image
was something we captured with
a camera on a specific device.
All right, so that is it for
today, and
we'll see you next time for
our very last lecture, which
is gonna be on accessibility.
>> For more,
please visit us
at stanford.edu.