[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Okay, well,
welcome to Lecture 9 of
Stanford CS193P, fall of 2017.
So we have two
major topics today.
We're gonna talk about
the view controller lifecycle,
which is when your
MVC comes alive and
does all the things it's gonna
do and then dies eventually.
And then we're also gonna talk
about a UIView called scroll
view which allows you to look
at large UIViews by panning
around on them, zooming in
on them, etc., all right.
View controller lifecycle.
So the view controllers
have a lifecycle.
It's essentially marked by
a sequence of messages.
Methods that are invoked
on the UIView Controller.
Why do we care about this at
all? Because at the various
stages of the lifecycle of
the view controller we might
wanna get involved, right,
and do certain things. So
this lifecycle starts with
the creation of your UIView
controller. For your view
controllers that you write,
this is almost always
coming out of a storyboard,
right? You drag something into
storyboard, you put your views
in there. That's how you
know how to create an MVC.
So your lifecycle is gonna
be when your app runs and
you've segued to something or
it's your first view
controller in your storyboard
or what whatever. Now iOS
also has some API which we
haven't learned about yet
that can hand you a view
controller, that you can
then segue to or whatever.
For example, there's a view
controller that lets you take
a picture with the camera.
So, it can come from code as
well, it's not only out of
the storyboard.
But once it's created,
what happens to it? And you've
already actually learned a lot
about the lifecycle
of a view controller.
Of course, the first thing
happens after it's created is
that it gets prepared to be
segued to, right? So if it's
being put on screen because of
segue, the preparation
part happens.
Then after that importantly,
the outlets get set, or
your UI buttons and whatever
those connections get made.
Then your view
controller appears and
possibly disappears on screen,
right? Imagine a split view in
portrait mode, the master
disappears. And then you can
slide it out and then slide
it away so it's appearing and
disappearing, for example.
Also, along the way, as all of
this is happening you might
have geometry changes.
Most notably,
you rotate your device, and
you go from having this tall,
thin rectangle to a shorter,
wider rectangle. So
geometry changes can happen.
They can happen for
other reasons, as well.
Again, in a split view,
you know, your master,
sometimes it's in the little
tall thing on the left.
Sometimes there's a shorter
thing on the left and
the one thing on the right,
it sometimes fills
the whole screen.
Or, when it's in landscape,
it fills just a part
of the screen.
So the geometry is changing,
depending on the situation
of your view controller.
And then lastly, and
by far least importantly,
in a low-memory situations,
you might have your view
controller asked to free up
some memory, we'll talk
about that in a second.
All right, so let's talk about
all the methods that get sent
to your view controller when
all these things happen.
Now, you already know
the first one, viewDidLoad, I
mentioned it in your homework.
It's a really powerful place
to do initialization, because
you're already prepared and
all your outlets are set, so
now you really can go to town.
So it's great for that and
we usually put most
of our initialization in
viewDidLoad with one huge
exception. And it's in red so
don't miss it geometry.
When viewDidLoad runs, your
bounds have not been set yet,
so do not put things in here
that have to do with the size
you are on screen. Because
you have not been fitted to
whatever device you're on,
okay, it's very important.
Very common mistake to put
stuff in here and then you
just wonder why, when you run
it on a different device, your
code doesn't work anymore.
So do not put geometry.
I'm gonna show you where
to put your geometry
changes in a moment here.
So that's viewDidLoad,
a great one. The next
one is viewWillAppear.
Now by the way, notice in all
of these I'm calling super
viewWillAppear or super
viewDidLoad in all of them,
you always do that,
do not forget to do that.
In fact in a demo the other
day, I noticed I forgot to do
it and so we'll fix
that in today's demo.
But, and
I noticed in your homework,
many of you did not call super
viewDidLoad. Now of course,
we didn't talk about
view control lifecycle so
I don't blame you for that.
But from now on,
don't forget to do super,
give your super class a chance
to find out it's appearing or
that it got loaded or
whatever. So viewWillAppear,
what do you do in
viewWillAppear?
viewWillAppear is exactly
what it sounds like,
your view controller's view
is about to appear on screen.
So this is where you can catch
up with stuff that might've
gone on in the world while
you were not on screen. Or
if this is the first time
your coming on screen,
catch up with the state
of the world. So
this is really a place to kind
of load up your view with all
the information from your
model, especially if your
model can change like let's
say your model is a network
database. Other people are
editing it, so it can change.
So here's where you wanna get
up to date, because when your
view is not on screen,
you don't want your view
controller to be doing much
work. It just wants to kinda
sit there quietly, and then
when it's time to come back,
then it does its
little setup in here.
One thing to notice about
viewWillAppear of course,
it can be called repeatedly,
because your view controller
can go away and come back,
and go away and come back.
But viewDidLoad is only ever
called once in the lifetime
of your view controller. It's
just called once after you're
prepared and your outlets
are setup, it gets called
once and that's it. But
viewWillAppear obviously can
be called every time you're
gonna come back on screen. Now
there's also a viewDidAppear.
This is called to you after
you have come on screen.
Now, what would
you wanna do here?
It's a little late to
do things like update
your view from your model here
because these things are on
screen. You don't want things
to come on screen wrong and
then view did appear and
now you've clean them up. But
this is a great place to do
things like start an animation
cuz you can't do that
in viewWillAppear.
You're not on screen,
yeah, right. Start a timer
that does something on screen.
Start observing something in
the world like a GPS locations
or maybe the gyro position
of your phone. Okay, those
are all things you can do once
you're on screen. Okay, so
that's what viewDidAppear
is really good for.
One other thing that you can
do viewDidAppear is maybe
kick off a very expensive
thing. Something you
don't want to kick off
in viewDidLoad because,
when viewDidLoad happens,
your view controller may not
actually appear on screen.
Okay, there's no guarantee
that anyone's ever gonna
actually put you on screen.
So viewDidLoad is not a great,
even veiwWillAppear,
surprisingly, might get
called on you, and then,
you don't actually appear on
screen. So viewDidAppear,
you know you're on screen. So
it's worth it to do something
expensive. Now what would
be something expensive?
Let's say you wanna fetch
a huge image off the network,
okay, almost anytime you're
gonna do something on
the network, it's pretty
expensive. Because on a phone,
maybe you only have a cellular
connection, it's a bad
connection, you're out in
a country road somewhere,
it's barely getting any.
So it could be really quite
expensive. For the same
reason, these expensive
things, we almost always do
them in the background. And
on Wednesday, I'm gonna talk
all about how to put things in
the background. That's because
it is absolutely primary goal,
primary thing you
must do with any
iOS app is you never block
the user interface experience.
Users always have to be
able to touch on things,
swipe things around.
If they swipe or touch and
your app is frozen, they will
not use your app, believe me.
Okay, so that is of primary
importance. And the way we do
that is by putting things that
would block, like waiting for
something on the network, off
the main queue, we call it,
off the main thread into
these background processes.
So we'll talk all about
that on Wednesday, but
viewDidAppear is a great place
to kick those things off.
Because you don't wanna waste
their cellular data usage
fetching an image if you're
not actually gonna appear.
Now what this means though is
since you're kicking this off
in the background, when you've
already appeared on screen,
you have to design your UIs So
that they always work even if
the expensive thing has not
come back yet. Do you see why
that is? That expensive thing
might take ten minutes or
might never come back because
of bad network, for example.
So you have to put place
holders or spinning wheels or
loading, dot, dot, dot or
some animation to shows the
user, yeah, I'm fetching your
thing. I'm working on it. But
your UI still has to be fully
responsive. If they're
in a navigation control,
they have to be able to hit
back and give up. Okay, or
they have to hit a tab at the
bottom and go to a different
tab or whatever they wanna do.
So designing UIs,
they're like that, take
a little bit of adjustment.
So far, you haven't had
to do that probably. So
you're mostly
thinking linearly.
Okay, I am going to put
this image on screen, so
I will go get the image.
Then I will put it on screen.
Well, you can't think like
that. You have to think,
I wanna put this on screen, so
I will put an image displaying
thing on screen that is not
loaded, with a little spinner.
And then, later, and the user
can do whatever they want.
And then later when
the picture arrives,
now I will update my UI to
show that image. Okay, so
it's a little bit kind
of thinking with that
other dimension,
that dimension of time.
Okay, all right, so there's
also view will disappear.
You get this right
before you go away.
This is a great place
to undo what you did
when view did appear.
So if you started a timer or
start some animation or
started watching GPS, or
something like that, this is a
good place to stop doing that.
Because you now know that
you're going to disappear. And
then when you reappear,
you'll turn it back on and
view did appear. So they kinda
work together, these two. And
then there's viewDidDisappear.
Okay, this one gets sent to
you after you've
completely disappeared.
Usually, we don't
do much here.
But you could imagine maybe
cleaning up your MVC here,
possibly saving some state or
something. But this one is
rarely used. All right,
I said that in viewDidLoad,
you cannot do geometry.
So where do you do geometry?
Well, you might think,
I can do it in viewWillAppear.
Cuz I'm just about to appear,
and so my geometry will
be right, no. You would think
that, but that would be wrong.
You obviously can't do
it in view did appear,
because now you're
already on screen.
It's too late, okay,
to do anything about geometry.
So the place you do geometry
is in these two methods,
viewWillLayoutSubviews() and
viewDidLayoutSubviews().
These two methods are sent to
your controller when its view,
the self.view, the top level
view of the controller,
that bar, view. When that
view, just before and
just after, that view is sent,
layoutSubviews.
So why would that top level
view be sent layoutSubviews?
Same reason any other view.
Maybe subviews came and
went out of it.
That's a common one.
Or its bounds changed. So this
is why this is a good place to
put geometry changes. Because
here, this is always gonna
happen when the bounds of
your top level view change.
Now usually, you don't need to
implement these methods, why?
Because you use an auto
layout, right? All that Ctrl
+ dragging, pinning things
to the edges, keeping things
in the center, fixing aspect
ratios, all that business,
you're doing that. And that is
automatically being evoked in
the layoutSubviews of
your top level view. So
you don't actually need to do
anything in your controller.
Okay, but if you do feel like
you need to do something to
your controller, this is
definitely the place to do it.
Now one thing about these two
methods you have to be aware
of, they could be
called quite often. And
at times you might be
surprised like, whoa,
nothing changed. The bounds
didn't change, nothing
changed with the subviews,
why did this get called?
Well, the system is allowed to
layout the subviews, ensure
the layout of the subviews of
any view at any time. Maybe it
wants to do an animation and
it's laying out the beginning
and end stage that it's going
to do a flip between or
something. And the bounds
have not changed but it wants
to make sure the views
are laid out. Or
it's laying them out in
the destination, the end of
the animation etc. So
it doesn't really matter why,
but the system is allowed to
call it anytime it wants.
And so since it can call
layoutSubviews anytime,
these could also
be called anytime.
So you wanna make sure this,
if you do something as
a reaction to your bounce
changing, you wanna make sure
these methods properly and
efficiently work even
if they're repeatedly called.
They might be called twice in
a row with the exact
same bounds, for example.
So you wouldn't wanna, if
you had to do something very
complicated and expensive,
you certainly wouldn't do
it twice in a row. Okay, so
that's geometry. Now there's a
special case of your geometry
changing, which is
autorotation. So
this is you turn your device
from landscape to portrait or
back and forth. And when this
happens, of course, you get
that layoutSubviews thing,
because your view's bounds
change until you get
viewWill/DidLayoutSubviews.
But you also have this
animation that's free
going on. So iOS automatically
animates the moving of all
your subviews from
the portrait layoutSubviews
to the landscape
layoutSubviews positions.
It does that for you.
Now that's great, that saves
you a lot of work. But if for
some reason you wanna
participate in that animation.
Now why would that be?
I don't know if you, have you
guys ever looked at the
calculator app on the iPhone?
When it's in portrait,
the buttons are really big and
there's not very many
calculation buttons like
times, plus, minus, equals.
That's about it, right? But
when you switch to landscape
now the buttons get small and
there is a whole bunch.
Square root, algorithms,
all kinds of things.
Okay, well,
when this rotating happens,
the calculator app wants to
get involved, cuz it wants to
animate those extra buttons
appearing on screen, maybe.
Okay, and also the layout
changes from being kinda big
buttons in the middle to those
buttons being on the side and
new buttons appearing.
So that's where you might
wanna participate. So
how do you use this method?
Well, view will transition to
size with coordinator to do
that. Well, the coordinator
that's passed you is
the animation coordinator.
It has a method in it called
animate alongside transition.
And in there, you can
provide an animation block,
a closure and do your
animation. And that animation
will be performed alongside
the animation that the system
does when it rotates. Okay,
and I'm not gonna talk anymore
about it than that. It's
just so you know it's there.
90% of the time, you don't
need to do that. Now,
in your current assignment,
assignment three, or
assignment four, you probably,
if you're far along on it, or
if you're not,
you'll notice eventually,
that you've got animation,
like cards being dealt out.
Well, what happens if you
start dealing out a card,
it starts flying
across the screen,
and then you rotate. Rotate
your device. Well, what's
gonna happen is this is going
to try and do some animation.
Now, I specifically put in the
assignment, don't worry about
that. You don't have to worry
about that case this week. But
you might ask,
what do I do there?
Well, you have to understand
that that might happen and
deal with it. Because when
you're throwing a card out
across the screen there, and
this thing starts to animate
that same properties
of that same view,
it's going to put it
possibly in the wrong place.
Cuz it's gonna move
it to a new place.
It probably does animation
begin from current state. And
so you could end up with views
totally in the wrong place. So
you need to be able to
setup your animations so
that if they get taken over
by someone else, all right,
that they end up in the right
place at the end. Okay, and so
that can require a little
bit of tuning, like I said,
this animation
tuning business.
That might require some of
that. But not required for
assignment four. It's a little
bit of an advanced animation,
so you have to deal with that.
All right, this last one and
definitely the least
is low memory.
This would only be, you would
have only any interest in this
if your app had large memory
items like videos. Images,
huge sound files. Very high
resolution big sound files for
example. And you know it is
possible that an iOS device
that had many apps that were
doing a lot of big photo
manipulation or something.
That it could possibly
run low on memory.
Most new ones have so
much memory this doesn't
ever happen. But
maybe if you had an app that
had a memory leak that was
leaking big images in memory
then it could happen. But
anyway, you'll be sent
this when that happens.
And all this is asking your
view controller here is
please release anything from
the heap that you can recreate
fairly easily later, or
when you need it. And so
it's kind of a memory
cleanup kind of thing.
One thing I will say is
if your app is leaking
in the heap and you are
getting larger and larger, and
it sends this to you, and
you have bad code and
you don't know how to clean it
up and you continue to leak,
iOS can kill you. Okay, so, if
you are a big memory hog and
you keep leaking, you can be
killed. So, just. It's kind
of the dangers of being
a bad programmer I guess.
I can get killed. Almost never
happens though. All right.
The last thing is actually
back to the beginning ,which
is waking up from a story
board. This is not strictly
part of the view controller
life cycle. But I put it in
here because any object that
comes out of a story board,
all your UI views, and
your view controller,
get sent awakeFromNib.
This is sent very early,
right after initialization,
before preparation,
before your outlets are set. I
tend to stay away from trying
to use this unless I really
do need something set early.
Now we used this in the demo
the other day cuz I wanted my
master of my split view to be
the delegate of the split view
really early before the split
view started collapsing things
on top of other things.
I wanted to get myself in
there as the delegate.
But normally you don't put
things in awake from NIB.
And I would say try to put it
one of the other ones first,
and if you really need it this
early, then, you can go and
do it in a way from nib.
Of course, this is only gonna
work for MVCs that come out
of storyboards, but again,
that's almost always yours.
Your ones always come out of
storyboards.
It's only the system ones,
like the camera one, that
you get Get from code,, so
here is a summary of
View Controller lifecycle,
you're instantiated,
usually from a storyboard,
but sometimes you
can ask IOS for
a View Controller.
Then you get awake from Nib,
if you're coming out
of a storyboard.
Then Segue preparation
happens, in case some other
MVC prepares you, note that
your outlets are not set yet.
Then your outlets get set.
Get wired up by iOS. Then,
viewDidLoad gets called,
all right? Then you appear and
disappear off screen, and
you get those viewWill and
did disappear, appear and
disappear, back and forth.
At any point along here,
your geometry might change,
causing vewWillLayoutSubviews
and viewDidLayoutSubviews to
get called. Probably with auto
layout happening in between
those two calls because
LayoutSubViews will cause auto
layout to happened and
if at any time you start
using a lot of memory or
even just the whole device.
Use a lot of memory you might
get didReceiveMemoryWarning
which you can hopefully
clean up something to but
often you can't because you
don't have anything big.
All right, so that is
the View Controller Lifecycle.
Now I have a little demo here,
I'm not gonna spend too much
time on this demo because we
got scrollView to demo here,
but, what I'm gonna do is show
you a little piece of code,
that you can drop
into your app.
It's a sub class of
UI view controller,
and you can just change all
of your view controllers to
inherit from this instead
of UI view controller, and
it will essentially just put
a print statement of all of
the view controller
life cycle methods.
So you can look in
your console and
see what's happening in the
view controller life cycle.
I;m gonna do it a little bit
today just to show you kind of
a couple of interesting
things about that.
So I'm gonna do this to
concentration, okay,
here's our concentration,
by the way,
this is where we left off last
time. Here's awakeFromNib,
oops, super.awakeFromNib.
AwakeFromNib you also wanna
call super even though, again,
it's not strictly if you
control the life cycle method.
You still wanna give you super
class the chance to do it. So
how does this code that
I wrote work? Okay,
here it is right here. Where
is it? Somewhere over here.
I'll get these things
out of the way.
There it is! Okay,
here it is right here.
Let's drag it in and
take a look at it.
I'm going to copy it in, so
what this thing look like is
exactly what you would think.
It's a subclass of UI
view controller. And
it just has prints for all you
did load view load appear did
receive that morning layout
subviews will transition even.
It just prints them out on
the screen when it happens.
It also has kind of a cool
little var, this thing,
vclLoggingName. When it logs
it on the console it will
use this string to identify
your viewController. Or
if you don't subclass this
it will just use the name
of the class.
which is the name
of the struct or
class you are in. String
describing type of self.
That's how you do that. So,
I'm going to make my two view
controllers in concentration,
right? I've got the theme
one and the game one.
So here's the game one.
Instead of having it inherit
from UI view controller, I'm
going to have it inherit from
VCL logging view controller.
So now it inherits ability to
print out all of those view
controller life cycle methods.
And I'm going to
override this,
what did I call it,
VCL logging name.
And I am going to return Game,
just because it will make our
console output
a little clearer,
which view controllers
are which. When it's logged
in. So this is gonna be called
game instead of calling it
ConcentrationViewController,
which is kinda long and
very similar to
ConcentrationThemeChooser or
whatever it is, view
controller. And I'm gonna do
the same thing with my
themed view controller here,
I'm gonna have it inherit from
VCLLoginViewController and
I'm gonna change its name
You see a log in name to be
TeamChooser. So,
that's only you need to do,
in fact you don't even need to
do this part if you just make
your, your controller in here
from this cell log in detail,
it will log. So let's going to
run, let's run this on iPad,
see what happens. Let's go
bring our console up here so
we can see what's going on,
all right?
So here is our concentration
game, showing up in landscape.
And you can see right away
look at this init from
coder, this init from coder is
when something comes out of
a storyboard. So
both of these are initialized.
Both of them awake from Nib,
you see?
Both of them have their
outlets and everything set.
And then viewDidLoad
happens on both of them.
They both are told
that they will appear.
They get their sub views laid
out a few times. Look at this,
viewDidLayoutSubviews.
This one gets laid out twice
even though their bounds
have not changed.
Then the theme chooser
gets a viewDidAppear and
the game gets a viewDidAppear
and they appear on screen Now
what happens if I rotate this
to portrait. Now when I go to
portrait, I get theme chooser,
the master will disappear,
because it disappeared, right?
It's no longer here,
it no longer showing. And I
also get this whole transition
to with coordinator,
because it was a rotation,
so we have an opportunity to
participate in the animation
if we want. The game,
of course, got a new size.
See, it's 768 by 1024, so we
got LayoutSubviews sent to it.
And then the ThemeChooser also
got its size laid out, for
some reason. And
then it disappeared. Now,
if I drag it out,
let's see what happens.
Now I get the subviews layed
out and view will appear and
view did appear for
the theme chooser.
You see what's going on here?
So as this is happening,
it's telling us exactly what's
going on. Now I'm gonna show
you one other thing about this
which is kind of interesting.
Let's go to our
Concentration theme choose.
We were already there,
theme chooser view controller.
I'm gonna make it, we put
a lot of code in here so
that it wouldn't segue if it
could. So I'm gonna make it so
it always segue just by
commenting this out.
So by doing that, I've
made is so that every time
we choose a game theme,
it always segues. And
I do that because I wanna show
you, let's even go over and
do this on iPhone just to
see what's going on there.
I'll show what happens in the
view controller lifecycle when
you are segueing, cuz it's
important to understand that.
Okay, so lets bring this up,
and then,
sorry. See this happen here
from the start? Okay, so
this is an interesting, a very
interesting start right here
because we see that we
created them, we wait for
a viewDidLoad them, we got
the game view well up here,
but it never did appear,
did it, right? Because
we did that thing where we
stop the collapse, remember
the stopping the collapse and
the swiving controller,
it never appears. So
it got view will up here but
never viewDidAppear cuz it
didn't actually appear.
Just another reason we wanna
wait 'till viewDidAppear,
sometimes to kick off
something expensive,
all right? And when they
both got laid out, and
the chooser did appear.
Now when I click on one,
here it creates a second,
a new, game MVC,
you see that? It's new, this
2 means it's a new instance.
So this is the instance
number of it. And notice,
look what happened
to the first one,
the one that never appeared,
it left the heap. And
that's what happens
when you segue.
You get a new one and the old
one leaves the heap. So
the new one gets viewDidLoad,
viewWillAppear, viewDidAppear.
If I go back,
I get some viewDidAppear and
disappear cuz this
one appeared and
the other one disappeared.
And if I segue again,
now I get a third MVC, and the
second one leaves the heap.
So this is what I was saying
about, when you do segues,
a new one is always created,
and
the old one gets thrown out of
the navigation controller and
leaves the heap. Everybody
got that? Okay, that's
all I wanted to show you. This
is more just code that you can
use to kind of figure out
what's going on in your own
app, if things are not working
the way you expect. Okay,
let's head back over here,
continue our slides and
talk about ScrollView.
Okay, so ScrollView,
you know what a ScrollView is,
right? You have a little area
on screen, and you want
to look at something big,
so you gotta ScrollView. You
can scroll around with your
finger and pinch in and
out to zoom in on it.
I just wanted to make sure you
understand the ScrollView is
a very powerful UIView.
Okay, and it works
really like a UIView in pretty
much all circumstances.
Here's my favorite
little demo, a little,
what do you call it recording
this show in this class.
Because this I believe is an
iPhone one that you're seeing
up here, but
even back from the iPhone
one ScrollView did this.
Now watch what happens here
when I start this thing going.
You can see that I've got a
ScrollView, a horizontal one,
that I can scroll between, and
inside it are vertical ones.
So it is perfectly fine to
have ScrollViews
inside ScrollViews.
Here's another one, okay,
where we're scrolling
horizontally between these
stock quote views or whatever.
And then we get there, we can
scroll up and down. Okay, so
ScrollView knows how to
live within itself and
knows how to live in
virtually every environment,
ScrollView is really
amazing little class. So
let's talk about how
ScrollView works,
it's actually very
simple to use as well.
You already know how to add
subviews to a regular UIView,
so I have regular UIView here.
I just create a view,
set its frame, and add it as
a subview, it appears, right.
Surely the same three, you are
intimately familiar with doing
this. So how does it differ if
it's a ScrollView? Okay, well
in the ScrollView, there's
one kind of huge difference,
which is that we create
what's called a contentSize.
When we specify this
contentSize, we're specifying
the size of the area that
the ScrollView is gonna scroll
around. Okay, so this is the
big thing that the ScrollView,
which is little, is going
to look around in. And
it is only a size, it's origin
is always 00, this little
content area right here, so we
always just specify the size.
So this var, contentSize,
that you see right there
in ScrollView is crucial.
It's the most important var
maybe on any class,
anywhere. It's the thing
that tells the ScrollView
how big the space is. But
after that, adding subviews
looks just like another view.
Now I can create a frame, add
a subview to the ScrollView,
and instead of putting it
in the black square over
there on the left, it puts it
in that content area instead.
Same frame, but
it puts it, you know,
still uses the frame to place
it. But it's doing it in
the content area. And I can
put other things in there,
you know, multiple subviews
as many as I want, so
here's two of them. And now
the ScrollView, what it does,
it just lets you have a little
window that is scrolling
around as the user pans around
here, and of course they can
zoom as well. Now you can
reposition the subviews in
that content area just
like you can in a regular
view subview, right?
So I just new frame, set that
thing to have a new frame,
it repositions. I set the logo
to have a different frame,
it repositions. Now I have all
this white space on the edges,
I don't want it anymore, so
I can just reset my content
size to fit the aerial frame,
right? Now when I scroll
around, I'm just looking in
this new content area. Got it?
So that's it, so just that
content size is the the key.
Now, because of this magic,
there's a couple other
interesting things about
Scroll View like it has
a var called content offset.
Content offset is just
the x and y position
of the upper-left corner of
the, what's the ScrollView
is currently showing in that
content areas coordinate
system. So it's just kind of
exactly what it sounds like,
the offset of the content that
is being shown right there.
And you also, might be zoomed
though. And if you're zoomed,
you're probably much
more interested in,
what is the rectangle in the
content area coordinate system
that I'm looking at?
Cuz maybe I'm zoomed
the way in on one of the
windows there in the quad, and
I wanna know that window. Well
that's gonna be a very small
rectangle, that window,
cuz I'm zoomed way in on it.
And the way we do that is
using the same methods that
you probably use or you might
have used in your assignment.
Which is UIViews methods
convert from and convert to
points and rectangles, those
all work in UIScrollView.
So if you say convert from
the ScrollView to this aerial
views, you will get the bounds
of the ScrollView in
that view's coordinate system.
So that's how you can find out
that rec in the aerial view's
coordinate system. Just normal
convert, nothing special
there. Okay, so how do
you create a ScrollView?
Well, you can drag one out,
of course, out of the little
object palettes. You can
also select a view in your
storyboard and go to the embed
menu as simple as you say,
embed in navigation
controller. And say,
embed in ScrollView and it
will wrap a ScrollView around.
Unfortunately, it puts
about a 20 pixel 20 point
border around it which I don't
really like but it does.
I'll show you that in
the demo today and
how we got rid of that. So you
kinda do that either way or
you can obviously create them
in code, right? It's just
a UIView so it has the init
with frame initializer to do
that as well. So once you've
created your ScrollView or
put it in your storyboard and
created an outlet to it,
then you just say addSubview
to add your subviews to it.
But this will do nothing,
nothing will appear
screen until you set your
contentSize. If you don't set
that contentSize,
then the ScrollView
will be scrolling over a
little zero width zero height
rectangle in the corner. And
your, if you put a Subview in
there, it probably will spill
over and show but there will
be no scrolling. So if you use
a ScrollView, and your image
appears, or your views appear,
but then you can't pan or
pinch, it's probably because
your contentSize is zero.
The panning and pinching is
only happening in the content
area, all right? You can
scroll programmatically,
of course the user can
scroll with their finger.
But you can do it in code by
saying scrollRecToVisible,
you just specify a rectangle
in the content area and
it will slide over to
show that rectangle.
You can control a lot of
other things that I don't
have time to cover
in scroll view.
For example, when a scroll
view first appears on screen,
it can flash its
ScrollIndicators. Okay,
the two things that kinda
show you where you scrolled
on the edges. They can flash
that's the default in fact.
But there's this bar flash
scrolling indication you can
turn it to false if you don't
want it to do that etc. Also,
scroll view is super
smart about safe areas.
Okay, remember we talked about
safe areas like the place at
the top of the iPhone 10? Or
you're in a navigation control
in the title, or
a tab bar at the bottom, or
it's like not like safe to
draw there? Well scroll view,
even if you make the scroll
view underneath those safe
areas, it will let you scroll
your content into the safe
areas. But if you scroll
all the way down,
or all the way over, then it
will make sure your content is
not obscured by the safe area.
You'll see this in the demo.
So scroll view, really super
smart about safe areas.
Because it is often the case,
that when we have scroll view,
we might wanna go full screen
to get as much of our image on
screen as we can. But, you
know, if we got some pixels
in the upper left corner,
we don't want them to be,
you know, underneath
the little black bar at top
of the iPhone 10. So we want
to be able to make sure we
scroll down to that far.
Now what about zooming?
So far we've only
talked about panning,
moving the scroll view around.
What if we want to zoom in
on what we're looking at and
see it larger? Now, one thing
when you zoom in by the way,
be careful. That's obviously
gonna affect your contentSize.
If I zoom in to make what
I'm looking at bigger,
the content area has to
get bigger as well. So
sometimes that happens and
then people are expecting
their content area to be the
same old size and it's not.
Okay, now scroll view
automatically sizes it for
you so you don't have
to worry about it.
But, it's just if you ever
look at your contentSize,
while you're zoomed in, it's
going to be larger, or smaller
if you zoom out. And take
note of the contentOffset,
obviously. All right, so
how do you make zooming work?
Well, you have to do two
things. And don't forget these
two things. It will not work
without these two things.
The first one is to set the
zoom scale min and max. Okay,
so this is just saying how
much do you allow to zoom in
and how much do you allow to
zoom out. By default, these
are both 1.0 which means you
can't zoom in or zoom out.
It has to be the identity size
right there. Now, zooming and
scrollView works by modifying
the transform, right?
We know what
the transform is right?
The thing you can rotate,
scale or translate.
Well, it is using the scale
part of a transform to scale
one of the subviews, we'll
talk about which one that is,
up and down. Okay, that is
how a scrollView works.
That is all it does by
the way. Okay, when you
zoom in and out, it's not
doing anything else except for
transforming the view
that you specify. So
this tells it how much it can
modify that transform. So
if it's 1.0, the transform is
always the identity matrix and
so It's never gonna zoom in or
out. So you have to set these,
at least one of these two, or
you won't be able to zoom.
The second thing is
to specify that view
that gets transformed. Because
remember that the scroll view,
that content area is allowed
to have multiple subviews.
Like we had the logo, we had
the aerial view. Okay, so
which, when I pinch,
which of those gets zoomed.
So, you have to actually
implement a delegate method
in scroll view.
Yes, that's right, if you want
to zoom on a scroll view,
you have to implement
this delegate method. And
that delegate method is called
viewForZooming in scrollView,
and it just returns which of
the subviews to zoom. Now,
to be honest, normally,
If we had multiple subviews,
we'd put them inside of
a view, a top level view, and
that's the view where
we would zoom on.
And of course when we
transform that view,
all the subviews will
get zoomed as well.
We wouldn't usually have
two different views that
are subviews in the content
area of the scroll view and
they're not sub views of some
common view. But it's possible
to do, but we don't usually
do. Okay, you can also zoom
programatically. In addition
to pinching to zoom,
you can set the zoom scale and
also zoom to a rect.
And here's what that looks
like. So here I, my zoom scale
is set to 1.2. That's 20%
larger than the identity
matrix. Here I've gone back
to identity matrix. See how
that zoomed out a little?
Now we'll go back to 1.2.
See, it's 20% larger, right?
Even this would not work by
the way if I don't set my
minimum and maximum zoom scale
to allow this. Now the rect is
even cooler, so if I had this
yellow rectangle and I said
zoom to rect it will zoom
the whole thing up so that
the rect just barely fits. Or
if I had a rect that was much
bigger, then it would zoom it
down to fit, so zoom to rect
is a cool way to zoom in and
out. All right, so ScrollView
has a lot of delegate methods,
like 12 or 15, somewhere in
there. I'm not gonna talk to
you about all of them.
You already met one of them.
That's view for zooming and
ScrollView, but
here's another one, just give
you an example. This one's
called ScrollViewDidEndZooming
with view atScale. And
this gets sent to you
when the user pinches and
then lifts the fingers up. Now
remember, as they're pinching,
all that's being changed is
the transform of the view for
zooming, that's it,
nothing else is
happening in there. And
when you let go, what if your
view, if you are capable of
drawing your view,
much higher resolution when
it is zoomed in. For example,
let's say your view draws an
arc with core graphics. Draws
an arc, you know an arc is
just a bunch of little pixels,
right, coming around here.
If you zoom way in,
it's gonna look like little
blocks. Kind of jaggedy,
right? Well, here when you get
this DidEndZooming atScale,
you could set your transform
back to the identity matrix.
And draw your,
draw a rect bigger. So
that you're using that arc and
now you get a nice smooth arc.
You see how this would work?
So this is a good way to draw
with higher resolution after
you pinch in. You're still
going to be doing transform
while it's pinching, which is
good. High performance, and
all that, but then when
you let go, it redraws,
kinda sharp. Okay so,
I'm gonna do a demo here of
ScrollView. Hopefully I
should have time to do,
show you all these stuff that
I just talked about. And
then on Wednesday, we will
learn about multithreading,
okay, putting things
in the background. And
we'll update the app
that I'm writing today to
do its image loading and
all that stuff in
the background.
Now I'm going to do that
kind of background stuff by
doing it over the network.
Which I was going to show you
a little bit of today but
my network doesn't work
on my new laptop. So,
I'll just be using local image
file today, which is fine, but
on Wednesday, I'll get my
laptop working. And we'll be
able to do networking, because
when we load images over
network, they're slow. And you
can see it's called Cassini,
that's because the images
we're gonna load up are from
the Cassini probe that
was sent out to Saturn and
they're big. Big and very,
very high resolution. And
then even on Stanford's fast
network, they take
a few seconds to load.
And that, we can't have our UI
blocked by that. Wednesday,
I'll also talk about
text field, and
maybe I'll fit in one
other little UI element,
time permitting. We do have
a Friday section this week,
it's on this app called
Instruments, which is used
to analyze the performance of
your apps. So don't miss that.
And then next week we'll dive
into probably table view and
collection view, drag and
drop kind of more powerful,
more sophisticated things that
I haven't been able
to teach you yet,
because you really needed to
understand delegation and
things like that before we
dive into those. All right,
let's do Cassini here.
Oops, I quit,
I didn't wanna quit it.
Okay, I'll start it back. So
we're gonna create a new
project here for Cassini and
it's gonna be single view app.
I'm gonna call it Cassini.
Not gonna do anything special
here. We're not gonna do,
you've all learned about
source code control now, but
we're not gonna do that here.
Okay, here's our Cassini.
I'm gonna do what I usually do
here, but take the assets and
the app delegate and
the launch screen, and
kinda move them out of the way
into supporting files so
we don't get confused by
seeing them repeatedly. And
I'm also gonna do something
interesting here as well.
We get, when we create
that single view app,
we get this little view
controller for free and
this is its controlling view.
And a lot of times, or
only thing we've done so
far, is rename this to be
a concentration
view controller, or
you probably had set view
controller in yours as well.
But there's another way
to do this as well,
which is I can just take
this and delete it.
So now I have a completely
empty storyboard.
There's nothing in here.
I can delete this, too.
Let's just delete that,
get that out of here,
move it to the trash. So now
my app is completely empty.
The only thing I have is this
supporting files here, but
there's basically nothing. So,
there's nothing going on here.
So, that's perfectly allowed.
Now if we do that,
how do I build it back up?
Well, I'm going to build an
app here, Cassini. Initially,
it's not going to have nothing
to do anything with Cassini,
it's just going to have
an image in a scroll view.
That's going to allow you
to choose an image and
put it in a scroll view.
So I wanna create my own view
controller that shows an image
and I'm going to create a new
view controller to do that
called image view controller.
So I'm going to go here.
Yes, it's a view controller.
I'm going to call it
image view controller,
cuz that's what it does,
it shows an image.
I'm gonna create it,
I'm gonna make sure I put it
in the right place here. And
here's our image
view controller.
I'm going to delete all of
the code out of it, just so
it's clear what code I'm
adding. I'm gonna go back to
my storyboard, which is
completely empty, and drag out
a new view controller, and go
to the identity inspector over
here, and change it to be
an image view controller.
Now, I haven't done one thing
that's very important that is
causing this warning.
You see this warning up here?
It says image view
controller is unreachable.
That's because there's no
arrow, you see? Remember
the arrow that I moved over in
split view controller demo?
There's no arrow.
So how do I put the arrow?
There's no arrow. How do I get
it? Well, you can do this by
inspecting a view controller
in the normal inspector, and
look at this
button right here,
is initial view controller,
boom. Okay, now it'll
come in and this will be our
view controller. Okay, so
let's start here by just not
having a scroll view and
just having an image view.
I'm just gonna take
an image view out of here.
Here's one, we put in image.
Here's an image view.
So image view, like I said, is
kind like UI label, except for
it's for images.
And I'm gonna put it in here,
and go edge to edge, right
there. Let's actually see what
this looks like on an iPhone
10, because of course we have
safe area issues there. Zoom
in a little. So I'm gonna move
the size of this actually so
that it covers the safe areas.
See how that's in the safe
areas right there?
Now, what I wanna do,
and let's go ahead and
while we're here let's go
get our view controller and
create an outlet to
this image view,
cuz we're going to
want to talk to this.
So I'm just going to
control drag into my class.
I'm going to call this image
view. So I'm not lit there.
Now, I want this big image
view right here to go all
the way to the edges. I don't
really want it to respect
the safe area for now. We're
going to have scroll view and
it will help us
with that later.
But I want it all the way out.
It looks cool.
I don't mind if a little
bit is covered by this and
a little bit is covered
by that. It's fine by me,
I think it's my image will
look cooler to do that.
Now how do I control drag
to the edges here? Okay,
I can't get to any
of the edges, right?
Because it's right on
the edges, so I can't pick it.
Well, we're gonna use, again,
I'm trying to show you auto
layout a little bit at a time,
one drip at a time.
So we're gonna start using
these little things in
the corner here. You see in
the lower right-hand corner?
We already know about
this one right here,
embed in stack view. We're
not going to use that. And
we actually have
seen this one,
I think, which just let's you
clear all your constraints, or
reset to the blue line
suggested constraints, etc.
But we're actually going
to use a different one,
which this one right here. It
just says add new constraints.
Look what happens if I select
the image view and click this.
It offers to let me set
some of its constraints.
Now, some of these like width
and height and aspect ratio,
we know we can get by control
dragging to itself. But
look at these ones up here.
This is essentially pin,
pin to the edges. So this is,
these little I beams,
if you turn them on,
will add constraints.
You see, add four constraints.
Add three constraints. It'll
add constraints that pin them
to what's called the nearest
neighbor. You see the nearest
neighbor? So it's gonna look
at that edge, and say what's
the nearest neighbor there?
Maybe it's the other edge of
a nearby view, maybe it's
the edge of your superview,
maybe it's the safe area. So
let's see what happens when we
add these four constraints to
our image view. We'll find
out what the four nearest
neighbors were to its four
edges. So here we go. Add four
constraints. Now I'm going
to bring up the inspector,
go to the size inspector
to look at my constraints.
Remember, that's how you
look at the constraints on
a view when you
select a view and
go to the size inspector
up here. You get to see it.
And look, the bottom and top,
it's thought the nearest
neighbor was super view,
self.view. My view
controller's top level view,
right? But look, on the sides
it thought it was the safe
area. That's because the safe
area here, on this iPhone 10,
goes across here. It doesn't
include that thing, so
it goes across here down this
edge. And then across here,
not including that little
thing right there and
back up this edge. That's the
safe area. Well, obviously,
the two sides are just as
close to the safe area
as they are to the edges
of the superview.
And always, interface builder
will prefer the safe area
over the superview's edges,
if they're the same. But
up here, this is nowhere near
the safe area this is right on
the superview's edge, but it's
nowhere near the safe area. So
that's why it shows superview.
See why it did that? Okay,
now, I don't want the safe
area though here.
I always want this at the
edges. So how do I fix this to
not be doing safe area?
I want that to say superview.
So how do I do that? Well, I
need to edit this constraint.
But no, how do I pick that
constraint? I can't even,
I can't see it, where is it?
Well, I'm gonna introduce to
you the way we almost always
actually access constraints,
which is with the document
outline. Okay, remember this
little button over here, and I
said in previous lectures and
demos, hey, don't worry
about this for now?
Well, we're gonna start
worrying about this cuz this
is showing the everything
that's over here in my view.
In outline form,
including the constraints.
See those constraints right
there, they look familiar? And
these are the constraints
between this
view and its superview. So
here's the two that
are hooked to the Safe Area.
Here's the two that are hooked
directly to the superview.
So let's click on one, and
go to the normal inspector or
the size inspector, either one
for constraints, and we can
edit this stuff. And we've
already seen in previous demos
how we edit the constant here,
or the multiplier or whatever.
Now we're gonna see how we
edit the actual connectivity.
So this constraint is from the
images, image view's leading
edge setting that equal to
the Safe Area's leading edge.
Well, I just want this
to be the same, but
I don't want to be
the Safe Area's leading edge,
I want it to be the
Superviews. So you can change
from Safe Area to Superview
just by editing the constraint
and changing the item that
is sent, connected to.
Same thing here, I'm gonna
change the Safe Area Trailing
to be the Superview Trailing.
Now, if I select this and
look in the size inspector,
you see that all of my
constraints are to the
Superview. So now my view's
gonna fill my entire space,
forgetting about any space.
I don't care if I have title
bar for navigation control, or
tab bars. It's all gonna be
filling the entire screen
behind those things.
Or if things, this is like
a physical thing, this is not
gonna be able to draw there.
But that's kinda what I want
in this case. Well we're gonna
see more from this document
outlined in a moment here. But
this is a great way to access
everything in your view.
It's very easy to get at
stuff. All right, so let's go
back to our code over here.
And we want to write some
code that makes this view
controller do what it does.
Well, this is
a controller of an MVC.
What is the model of this MVC?
Well I'm gonna make the model
of this be an imageURL.
It's gonna be of type,
this class in iOS, called URL.
A URL just represents a URL.
It could be a local file URL,
or it could be an Internet
URL. And this is my model.
And so it's my job
to take that model,
turn it into an image and
present it in my view,
which my view right now
is just this ImageView
right here. So I'm going to
do that right away by saying,
that if someone sets my model
right here, I'm gonna set my
ImageView's Image to nil.
Okay, because I'm changing
it to a new thing. And then
I'm gonna go fetch that image.
Now the reason I'm making this
another little function here,
some private func fetch image,
is because this thing
might be over the network.
And eventually on Wednesday,
we're gonna make fetch image
work in a background task,
obviously, because you could
get blocked by the network. So
I'm kinda thinking
ahead a little bit and
putting this in a separate
function as opposed to just
dropping it right in here. So
someone set a new image URL.
We clear out whatever
image we have, if any.
Image is just a bar in our
imageView that says the image.
And then we're gonna go
fetch a new image over here.
Now one thing, since we just
learned about View controller
life cycle. I told you that
you don't really wanna do
something like this fetch
image unless you have to. So
I'm gonna do something here,
which is I'm only gonna
fetch this image if someone
sets my model and I'm on
screen. If someone sets my
model and I'm off screen,
I am not gonna go fetch
that image yet. I'm gonna wait
until I know I'm on screen.
Now how can you tell if you're
on screen? How do you know if
your MVC's on screen? Well
here is a cool way to do it.
I'm just gonna check to see
if my view has a window
that's not nil. So we didn't
really talk about window and
i kinda told you to ignore it
at the beginning of class, and
you mostly can,
except for that a view,
if it's onscreen,
we'll have a window bar, which
is the window that it's in,
which is usually just this one
window. So this is a kind of
a cool, simple little way to
check am I onscreen, and if
I am onscreen, then I'm gonna
go ahead and fetch this image.
But what if I'm not onscreen?
Eventually I need to fetch
the image. So when is a good
time to do that? Anyone have
an idea on that? Yeah,
view did appear. Exactly,
let's do it, viewDidAppear.
Okay, super.viewDidAppear.
At this point, I know that
I'm on screen, so now
inside of my viewDidAppear,
I can just check to see if my
image views image.
Oops, image is still nil,
then let's fetch it.
See how I use the view
controller lifecycle there to
keep myself from doing any
unnecessary work? Now, of
course, if my fetchImage truly
does work in the background,
I have more work to do here,
which is I've gotta give
some indication to the user
I'm working on it. Okay, cuz
otherwise they're gonna say,
where's my image.
Went to this view control,
I don't see any image up here.
So I have to give some
feedback. But since right
now it's gonna block
the user interface, until it
gets the image cuz we're not
doing the multithreading,
we'll just leave it like it
is. But we're gonna see it,
when we do it we're gonna put
something in there to do that.
All right, so fetchImage,
how do we implement fetchImage
right here? Well,
this is actually pretty easy.
We're just gonna see if
our URL, our model here,
is non nil, cuz if it's nil,
we don't have to do anything.
Because whenever someone sets
a new image, we set it to nil
and whether we fetch it here
or here, if there's no,
if that image URL is nil,
we just, we leave it blank.
Nothing in our image view. But
if I have it, then I need to
go out in the Internet and
get the data at that URL and
turn it into an image. So how
do we go out on the Internet,
and get data from URL? We do
that with the data objects.
Remember the data
object I talked about,
it's just as bag
of bits thing.
Well, it has an initial,
an initializer, which is
give me a URL, and I'll go get
the bag of bits from that URL.
So we can set a little
local variable,
which I'm gonna call my URL
contents, equal to data.
Now, let's look at the various
initializers for a data, and
it has a lot of them
because it's a bag of bits.
So we can convert to a lot
of different data types,
right, bags of bytes and
all kinds of things here. But
one of them has, is this one
right here, content of URL.
What's that word after
contentsOf : URL? Throws.
So why can this throw?
Well, it's going
out on the network maybe,
lots of reasons it can throw.
Network connection is bad, the
server rejected the request.
There's probably 20 different
things it could throw here.
Now it turns out we don't care
about any of them. If we did,
let's go ahead and put
contentsOf: URL in here. And
the URL is url.
If we did, since this throws,
what do we have to say in
front of it? Try, yeah,
we have to try it
because it might fail.
And we could wrap a little
do catch let error here and
do this thing, catch the error
and then process the error.
It was a server time out,
network unavailable all these
things. But we don't really
care about any of that stuff.
We're just a lowly image view
controller, we just wanna put
our image up or not. So we
don't care about the error, so
we're not gonna do it with
a do try, do catch thing here.
Instead, we're gonna use
this ver, okay, right now,
this urlContents right
here would be a type data.
But I'm gonna change
this to try?,
which says try this thing and
if it fails, just return nil.
So that makes this now we have
type Data?, right? Optional
data, because the try might
fail. So I've got this content
right here. Now I'm just gonna
say if I can let my image data
that I got from that URL
equal the urlContents.
Then I can create my image
from that data. So that image
data is probably JPEG data or
something like that. So
I'm gonna say here that my
image views image equals
UIImage. Now UIImage, we've
seen UIImage named, right?
That's the one we've used.
There's another UIImage one
called UIImage with data. And
you give it Image data
which is data object.
And it will look in there,
that bag of bits, and
see if it recognizes anything
that looks like an image,
like a JPEG file or
something like that. So
that's kinda cool,
all right? So that's it.
That's all we need to do to
show an image here. I'm gonna
do one other thing just for
demo purposes here, which is,
in my viewed load, I'll just
do super here. I'm gonna say,
if by the time I load
my image URL is nil,
then let's load up kind
of a sample image, and
I have a sample image
here in a file, a URL for
sample image. Let's go here,
I'm gonna drag this in,
demo URLs right here. Again,
let me show you this demo URL,
what this looks like.
So the demo URL's that I have,
I have this Stanford one right
here. Which is a big picture
of the oval, and then I have
these NASA ones right here for
Wednesday's demo. Now again,
I don't have any network,
so I can't actually do this
one over the network, so
I'm gonna do a local one.
Using this bundle main.url.
So this gives me a local one.
So I have a local version of
the oval here. I'll just
drag it in, copy that in.
I can show you what this
looks like over here, right.
So it's just a big thing
of the oval there,
very high resolution.
Notice I click this button
over here target membership
to make sure that this oval
when I install my app on
the device gets included.
Because I'm looking
at locally, but
I'm just gonna get a URL to
it. It just happens to be
a URL to a local file as
opposed to URL for network,
which doesn't matter cuz we're
not doing multi-threading yet,
so it's perfectly fine.
Okay, so
that here I'm just gonna
set my model equal to my
DemoURLs.Stanford. So that's
just that URL for the local
guy. All right, so let's run
to see what this does for
us. Actually I'm gonna,
we're gonna re-run this and
do it with iPhone 10.
But here it is. Now it
showed the image but that
really long image got smashed.
And if I go this way, it's
doing a good job of sticking
to the edges. But of course,
it's kind of smashed as this
is not Stanford in
all its glory here.
So we need to fix that, and
how do we fix that? Of course,
with ScrollView, right? If we
put a ScrollView in there,
it can be its normal size and
we can scroll around on it.
Zoom in and out and
look at it. So that's perfect
opportunity here, to fix our
little app with ScrollView.
Now, I'm gonna show you
both ways to do ScrollView.
Scroll view done from a
storyboard and ScrollView done
in code. So that you both see
how to do it in storyboard,
because it can be a little
bit tricky there, and so
you can see what's going on
with the contents size and
all that stuff in the code.
All right, so let's go to our
storyboard right here.
And here is our ImageView.
Now I am going to add this
ScrollView. Again, I could
go over here, and if you
go down here and search for
ScrollView you'll see you can
drag out a scroll view and
then just drag
sub-views into it.
By the way, when you are
interacting with the sub-views
of ScrollView and Interface
Builder, it's talking about
the content area. So the
Interface Builder doesn't even
know anything about ScrollView
sub-views except for
that they're in
the content area. So
for example we're gonna
create some constraints here
between the image view and
the ScrollView.
That's gonna be constraints
between the image view and
the content area, that big
white area of the ScrollView.
So that's important to
understand when you're working
in Interface Builder. But I'm
not gonna do it by dragging
it out down here. Instead, I'm
gonna use that embed thing,
right? So I have my
Image View selected here.
I'm gonna go Embed In,
Scroll View, and it does it.
Now like I said, it puts this
little 20-pixel border around
it, which I don't really want,
so I'm going to resize
this to be perfectly hooked
up to my edges right here.
Notice that now the ImageView
still got the 20 pixels, so
I'm gonna move it. So I've
kind of put these two things
where I want. Now, it really
doesn't matter actually where
I put the image view in terms
of it's size and angle.
What's important here is that
that ImageView be tied to
the edges of the content area.
And why is that important?
Not, so that the ImageView is
the right size, but so that
the content area is the right
size. If I tie the ImageView's
edges to the content area, and
the ImageView changes size,
the content area will change
size. And I have to have that
content area always matching
the size of the ImageView if I
wanna be able to scroll over
the entire image, right?
So, when you do this in
Interface Builder as opposed
to in code, you do this
with constraint by hooking
the ImageView to be tied to
the ScrollView. Which in fact,
it already is, because when
I did embed in ScrollView,
the ImageView was already tied
to its super view, so it kept
it it's just that it got these
little extra 20 points in
there which I don't like.
Now the thing here is this
ScrollView itself is not tied
to its edges. I resized it but
it's there's no constraint. So
I'm gonna tie it to the edges
in the same way that
I did the other one.
How do I choose the ScrollView
though? When I click here,
dang it, I keep getting the
ImageView. Can anyone think of
a way we could choose this?
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> The document outline,
absolutely. Let's go over here
to Document Outline, right?
And here's the ScrollView
right here,
I just selected it. So it's
really easy in the document
outline to pick what
you actually want. So
I can pick my ScrollView here,
and once I have my ScrollView
here, I can pick,
go down here to
this thing we had
with the edges and
just hook it to edges up to
its nearest neighbors. Same
exact thing we did with the
ImageView, it does it here.
It had the same problem where
it put the trailing and
leading to the safe area.
Now in the document outline
when you're looking for
constraints, be careful
about the indentation.
These constraints go
to the ImageView.
to the ScrollView.
You see, how the indentation
matters there? So
here I'm gonna change the safe
area of this to be SuperView
also. SuperView.
Okay, we got that.
And then the last thing I
wanna do here is fix all this
all these 20 points thing that
it gave me when I embedded,
20 points,
cuz I don't want that.
I can edit that right in here,
right in my size inspector
here. So I'm just gonna say,
edit, make that zero.
Edit this, make that zero.
Edit this and make that zero.
So now I've got good-looking
constraints right here.
See, the ScrollView is
hooked up to its SuperView.
You can see that the ImageView
is hooked up to its SuperView,
which in Interface Builder
means the content area
of the ScrollView.
I can't emphasize that enough.
When you have this view,
let's say sub-view, see how
the ImageView is a sub-view
of the ScrollView is indented
right there? That means that
the ImageView, when the
ScrollView is your SuperView,
you're talking about the
content area. Now, why is this
still red? Okay, it seems to
me like I've specified all my
constraints between these
views. Why is this red?
Well let's go look up here and
see what it says.
It says scrollable content
size is ambiguous for
ScrollView. So it's talking
about that content area,
it's saying how big is that
thing? Well the answer is,
it's as big as the image view,
because the edges of those two
things are tied together. But
Interface Builder does not
know how big the image view
is. Why? Because it has
no image. Okay, this
image view is empty, it has no
image so Interface Builder is
like I don't know how
big that thing is, so
I don't know how big the
scrollable content area is for
the scroll view. Now,
this is an unsolvable problem,
because we don't set the image
until our code runs.
So how do we deal with
this in Interface Builder?
Well, Interface Builder has
a really cool little feature,
if you inspect the image
view right here and
go down to the bottom, you see
this thing intrinsic size?
The intrinsic size of
something is the size that it
wants to be to fit its
content. So for a label,
an intrinsic size of a label
is however small it can be and
still fit all of
the text in there.
For an image view of
the intrinsic size,
how it can be with
the natural aspect ratio and
size of the image, so that's
its intrinsic size. Well
its intrinsic size, it's right
now set to be the default, but
you can actually set it
to be a placeholder.
This placeholder, which I'm
gonna set, is just any random
size you want, and it'll only
use this in Interface Builder.
It's just holding this place
in Interface Builder, right?
In code we're going to set it.
So look, that got rid of
my red complaint. Because now
the imageView has a size, and
so the content area's
gonna be 8375 by 812, but
only in Interface Builder.
Once it runs,
it's going to be whatever
the size the imageView is,
which is gonna depend
on what image we set.
Everybody got all that?
So this is kind of the,
you can see what I
was saying about it.
It's a little bit tricky
with the scroll view.
It takes a little bit getting
used to understand that when
you are setting constraints
between the image view and
the scroll view,
you're talking about
the content area.
And that's controlling
the size of the content area.
So let's run,
that's all we have to do,
we don't have to do anything
in the code here cuz we set
all these constraints.
So let's go ahead and
run this thing,
I keep forgetting
to do this on iPhone 10 which
is a little more interesting.
In fact, let's do it on iPhone
10 and stop here. iPhone 10,
iPhone 10's a little more
interesting, because it has
that safe area built into it
whereas the other one doesn't.
Okay, so look.
Here's our image.
You see how this blue
sky of our image is
up here where the time is and
all that? And if I scroll,
woo hoo, it's showing, okay,
our tree up here. That's cool.
You can scroll all around.
Notice that if I scroll down
it'll reveal the safe area,
right? It'll make this be
lower than the safe area.
So that's the scrollView being
smart about the safe area.
Even though we tied it to its
super views edges it still
knows there's a safe area.
And it goes all the way down,
and the same will be true down
at the other side. So here
we're scrolling through. We
can go landscape for example,
and just scroll around.
Find the stuff we want,
there's the dish right there.
And so that's it.
That's all that's required for
scrollView. Works super easy.
Now what about doing this in
code? So in code, in some ways
it's almost a little easier
than doing it. Because
you don't have the 20 pixel
thing and all that stuff.
So I'm gonna do the exact
same thing here in, in code.
So I'm gonna take my
imageView and delete it.
So I just deleted
my imageView.
I'm gonna leave my scrollView
in there, though. Because I
need to talk to the scroll
view to set its content size,
so I'm gonna leave that in
there. Let's go over here and
get our code up
at the same time.
I'm going to create an outlet
to this scrollView right here,
so that I can again talk to
it. I don't need my image view
outlet anymore, because I'm
going to create it in code.
In fact, let's just
create it right here.
I'm going to save my
ImageView = a new ImageView,
I'm just gonna create
the ImageView.
It's sub zero size, but that's
okay. Whenever I set an image,
I'll resize it. And then
let's Control+Drag to hook
up to our scrollView. Call
this scrollView. Now we have
a connection to both. Here
we just want the imageView
to be in the content area of
the scrollView. So as soon as
the scrollView gets hooked up
by Interface Builder I'm going
to ask the scrollView to
add the scrollView to add
as a subview by imageView.
So it added it. That's nice.
Again the content area is size
zero and so is my imageView at
this point, so it's going
to be completely blank.
Any time I set image
like I do it here and
actually I do it
up here as well.
I need to tell the imageView
to size itself to fit.
So size to fit means make
yourself your intrinsic size,
right? The size that will
fit this image the best and
now the UIimage use
frame has been set, but
if I don't do this,
scrollView.contentSize =.
Equals the
imageView.frame.size.
If I don't do that then it's
not going to scroll at all.
You see why? Okay, otherwise
the content are would be 00
size. I got this big image and
I'm trying to scroll and
this 00 size rect
does nothing.
Okay, now I actually have to
do this same thing up here
when I set the image
up here back to nil.
I want to resize my content
size back down to zero.
Now normally I would say,
copy and
pasting code like that
that's bad. Don't do it.
But this is a demo.
I don't have time to fix it.
But actually I'm going to
take the time to fix it,
because I'm going to fix it
in a way which I think will
be kind of interesting.
Which is I'm going to make
a var, actually a private var,
called image which is going
to be a type UIImage, and
every, it's going
to be computed,
every time I want to set
my image or get my image,
I'm just going to get it from
imageView. So I'm gonna say
get, return the imageView's
image, and set, it's
going to set the imageView's
image to the new value. So
this is just a normal computed
property right here. But
the cool thing is now,
I can put this in here. So
that every time
I set my image,
I resize my imageView and
my scrollView. And so
up here I can just say,
image = nil, and down here,
I can just say, image = the
new image, and I don't have to
have this code copied in
two different places.
So here's an example where
you can use a computed Var,
because conceptually
this is my image,
it happens to be stored
in the imageView,
I don't need to
duplicate it from there,
I'm just gonna return it,
and set it in there. But
I can also do my nice little
setting on the side there.
Okay, that's it.
So it's easy in code as well.
Okay this is a big file so
even locally it takes awhile
to load. But here it is. So
we got the exact same
thing we had before,
we can still find the addition
here, we can rotate. But
it would be really cool if we
could see the whole picture.
It's a little annoying,
we can see just
two little parts of it.
It's kind of cool, actually,
to be able to look
at parts of it. But
we'd like to be able to zoom
out and see the whole thing.
So now we need zooming.
So what are the two things
we need to do zooming? Set the
minimum, maximum's zoom scale.
Provided delegate says
which view to zoom.
Now it's obvious which view we
want the transform to work on
here, it's our ImageView. So
let's go do that, and I'm just
going to do that, I'll set
those things right here. Okay,
here is where my scrollView is
set by iOS so let's just have
the scrollView's minimum
zoom scale, we'll go 1/25,
okay, 1/25. So
we'll allow it to zoom out, so
that the image is
1/25 its normal size.
And then maybe for the maximum
zoom scale, I'll say 1.0.
Why would I say 1.0?
Well, maybe because I don't
want you to zoom in so that
the bits look kinda, you know,
pixellated, so I'm not gonna
let you zoom in anymore than
1.0. So you can zoom into 1.0,
but no closer, and we'll let
you zoom all out to 1/25,
so that's part one, part two
is scrollView.delegate. Equals
what? Self, yeah. I'm gonna
be the scrollView's delegate.
Now, this is going to
generate an error right here,
because self is not a UI
scrollView delegate.
That's easily fixed,
we go up here and
say yes, I am a UI
scroll view delegate,
thank you very much. And since
all those methods are optional
Objective-C methods, all
my errors go away. However,
scrolling not gonna work
unless I implement that view
for scrolling method. So let's
do that. It's called view for
scrolling there it is,
viewForZoomingIn I mean, and
we just need to return our
image view, because that is
the view, the sub view in the
content area, that we want to
be transformed when we pitch
all right? So let's try it.
Okay, here we go.
We can still pan around.
But now, we can zoom. Remember
remember how to pinch?
Hold down the option key
right here. Got low battery.
Hold down the option right
here, and pinch. And
we can zoom out here.
Okay, all the way out to here.
Maybe look better if we do
this, there we go. Like that,
okay, zoom in, real easy.
So hopefully, that gives you
the full tour of scrollView
in terms of adding subviews,
managing its content size,
doing zooming, all this stuff,
very straightforward,
easy to use. Next time
what we're gonna do is the
images that we're gonna get
are gonna be these huge
images over the network.
Hopefully, I can get my Mac
to work on the network, and
that's going to be slow. And
we are not gonna want our UI
to be blocked waiting for
that to happen.
We want it still to be
highly interactive. And
so to do that, we need to do
multithreading. So that'll be
our primary topic at the start
of Wednesday's lecture.
And I will see you all then.
>> For
more, please visit
us at stanford.edu.