[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Welcome everyone to
our Friday section of CS193P.
I'm Junjie, one of your TAs.
And today, I'm gonna
talk about the GitHub and
the source control
workflow in Xcode 9. So,
what is source control?
Like have you used like
some source control
systems like GitHub?
Yeah, so as a software
developer, you will like,
almost like it's
a necessary skill set for
you to learn how to use
source control systems.
Like big companies like
Facebook and Google,
they all have their own
source control systems. And
it's very important for you to
master those skills before you
really go into the industry.
So what is source control?
Why should we matter?
Why should we care about it?
It allows you to track your
code changes over time.
You can revert your files
back to a previous state.
You can compare different
versions of code side by side.
And it also makes
it a lot easier for
you to work with
other teammates. And
like when bugs happen, it's
much easier to take it down.
Today, our topic is one of the
biggest source control system
in the world, and
it's built right into Xcode 9.
Xcode 9 has done a lot of
great things to integrate
GitHub to make it
very easy to use. So
I'm gonna try to demo you some
of the basics in Xcode 9,
how to use GitHub. Before
that, you should register
an account in github.com.
The repository,
the public repository or
a repo, is free. And, a repo
is just like a code directory
for you to store the code.
And if you register using
your Stanford email account,
you can get the private
repository for free. I highly,
highly encourage you to use
a private repo to manage
all your assignments,
all your cost projects.
And it's much easier for
you to collaborate with your
teammates, and in-
>> Remind people not to make
it public, though.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> [CROSSTALK] the public
to private.
>> So
that's why you wanna register
using your Stanford email.
You would never like up,
upload
your assignments onto GitHub
using a public repository cuz
like you don't know who will
just download all the code and
copy, copy out of no place.
So last Friday's session,
Jason also mentioned that
there's a Pro Git ebook.
That's really great for you to
learn some of the basics of
GitHub and the source control,
some of the concepts.
It's a really good
starting point for
you to learn those skills.
I post a link here and
you can like check it out if
you want. So there are three
main components in like Xcode
9 Source Control Workflow, and
I will go through
each of them briefly.
The first one is pulling and
pushing. For pulling and
pushing is like dealing
with your local changes and
the changes in the remote
repository. So, for
clone and pull,
you can download all the code
from the remote repository to
your own laptop. Xcode 9
actually make it really,
really easy to download
a repository. You just click
the Clone and Download button
and then open it in Xcode.
And Xcode will download
all the changes for
you. It's really nice. And
I will show you how to do that
in a demo. And another way to
do it is to copy out this
GitHub repository address.
And I will also show you how
to do that in a demo. For
the push, it's like you
make some local changes,
you, and you want to push to
the remote so that you can
edit it in another machine or
share it to your friends.
So, every batch of code
changes is called a commit.
The commit it's like
a snapshot of all the code
changes and
also the description message.
It has the author, description
message, and also the time.
I highly encourage you to
make small commits instead of
making a really big commit,
like only one commit for
the repository. That's
like the final finish one.
Because making small commits
makes it much easier to debug.
The rule of thumb is one
feature at a time, and
each commit should
be self-contained.
When bugs happen, you can
easily revert to the previous
state without affecting
the other files. So
here's what the commit panel
looks like in Xcode 9.
You get the commit message
here and also the author,
the branches,
the tags and remotes.
We will go through these
concepts in a demo. And
here's the identifier,
it is the SHA identifier for
this commit. The last
concept I'm introducing
today is the branching. So
each little commits, one after
one, is called a code branch.
In the GitHub repo,
repository,
the most important one is the
master branch. You would wanna
always keep your master
branch clean, bug-free and
stable. And when you want
to work on new features,
you would like to branch
from the master. So
Xcode 9 is really easy for
you to just right-click and
create a new branch. The new
branch will have the same
code as the master. But when
you keep developing your code,
it won't affect the master
branch. And after you finish
developing all your features,
you've unit tested your code,
you can merge it back
to master branch.
I will show you how to do the
branching in this demo. So,
any questions so far? No,
so let's go into the demo.
So let's pull out Xcode.
So before we do the fancy
things in Xcode,
we would like to set up the
GitHub account in Xcode. So
the way to do it as click
on Xcode > Preferences
> Accounts. When you
select the Add button,
you can add GitHub Enterprise.
Enterprise is like,
when you work for a company,
they will have the company
GitHub account. So
I'm gonna select the GitHub.
And I'm using my Stanford
email address. So
we've already signed in. And
before we jump into the code,
we would wanna make sure the
Source Control is setting up
correctly. So, these options
is like, whether you
want Xcode to download
the remote changes for you.
So that you won't need to pull
the changes in command line.
And when you click on the Git
button here, you can set up
some global ignored files. If
you have used GitHub before,
you know that there's
a gitignore file so
that your files won't be
checked by the GitHub system.
So you can set up some global
ignored files here. That means
like .D_Store files won't
be checked by the GitHub. So
let's start by creating
a new Xcode product.
Let's do Single View,
and then GitTutorial.
And it's basically the same
thing as we are doing when
creating the new project for
our homework,
but the difference is that we
wanna select this button. So
this is the mysterious
Source Control button we never
talk about in class.
And this means that Xcode will
initialize a Git repository
for you. So we would select
this button for this section.
Hit Create, and
then we would have
a Git repository, and
we can inspect the Source
Control panel over here.
It's on the top left,
and the second button.
It shows that we are currently
at the master branch. And
the initial commit is just
some free code given by Xcode
that create, initialize,
and then push the code for
you. So,
let's make some change.
Maybe I will delete
this free code. And
then add a print line.
And once I've saved the file,
there's an M appeared here.
That M stands for modified.
Basically, it means that your
local repository have some
uncommitted changes. And
that's also modified in
storyboard. I want to drag our
button. And
put it in the middle. Okay,
let's save the change. So
now I have made some change.
So we wanna commit
those changes.
It's like clicking
the Source Control here, and
then hit Commit. Then
a Version Editor will appear.
And it's really nice because
you can see your change
side by side by clicking the
filename. And it shows that
you've added one line and
you've deleted some code.
And if you click on
the button in the middle,
you can actually don't
commit this specific line or
discards the change. So, let's
also look at the storyboard.
Maybe it's your first time
looking the storyboard.
At this level, we generally
don't like added the file in,
in this level.
It's a XML file, so
it's super complicated. After
you've confirmed that this is
the change you want, you would
enter the commit message here.
Added a button and
a print. Notice that
there's also a Push to remote
button here. But we don't
have a remote now because the
repository only lives locally.
We don't have a remote
repository in the GitHub.
If we have the remote origin,
we can push also to remote.
And I will show you how to add
the remote origin in a second.
So now let's just
commit the files. So
once I do that,
the M disappeared. And
let's go back to
the Source Control Panel.
Look, here's the commit I just
made. And you can inspect
it by clicking it and then
select the button here. And
it shows the author,
the date, the branches,
and also the files. If you
want to inspect the changes,
you can actually click
on the Assistant Editor.
I want my Assistant Editor
on the bottom. And
then when I click the file,
it actually
displays the changes side by
side. You can easily see what
files you've changed in
this specific commit.
And let's make more
changes here, like print,
hello CS193p.
And over to Source Control
button here, I can actually
discard all the changes
in my current repository.
That basically roll back
to the latest commit. But
I will show you how to revert
to several commits ago.
So let's add this
commit first.
Add an, another print.
But we should have
successfully committed because
there's no M over the
ViewController. And say, for
this specific file, I want to
roll back to two commits ago.
I can open this
Source Control button.
And then it's a side by side
comparison between your
local revision and
your commits. So
if I select the commit,
two commits ago,
I can see all my changes.
And I can click on the button
here, if I want to
discard all the changes.
Revert, so
now my local repository
have reverted those changes.
That's commit. Revert.
Like I just mentioned,
all the code now lives
in my local repository,
so there's no way I can share
it to my teammate or work
on the other workstation. And
also if I just lost my laptop,
everything will be gone.
You certainly don't want that.
So let's see like how to
add a remote. Origin for
this GitTutorial repo.
And it's super simple here,
you just click on the Remote,
and right-click.
There's a Create GitTutorial
Remote on GitHub.
And it allows you
to select public or
private repository. So since
I'm using my Stanford account,
I can get the free
private repo.
Okay, now we have
a remote origin, and
let's take a look. So
here's my
Stanford GitHub account.
And there's a GitTutorial
repository we just created.
And it has all the files
we've modified.
And if you want to work
in the other workstation,
you can just clone or download
and open in Xcode and/or copy
the address. So before I
show you how to clone,
let me show you how to add
the collaborator. It's super
useful if you want to work
with the other teammate. So
for this specific repository,
you go to Setting,
and hit Collaborators.
And basically, you need to
know your friend's GitHub ID,
and you just type it here.
For demonstration,
I will add my personal
account here. And
GitHub will you send an email
to your friend and, or
you can just share
this invite link.
Let me copy it here, and then
sign into my personal account.
So I click on this link And
it says that you are invited
to collaborate. So
I can accept the invitation.
Now,
I have the push access to
this private repository.
So another way to create
the repo is by cloning
the existing repo
from the GitHub. Say,
I have a Concentration
private repo here.
And I want to download
it to my local machine.
I can just hit Open in Xcode,
and Yes.
So all the code were
downloaded by Xcode. And
the other way to do it
is save this address.
And then,
in our Xcode welcome page,
you can select this Clone
an existing project.
You can paste in the address,
and then just clone.
So Xcode will do
the exact same thing.
It's just copying all
the files from remote.
The good thing is that in
the source control panel here,
you can actually get all
the code changes for
the repository. And
you can also like inspect all
the changes you've made.
So for
this specific repo, actually,
the master is a fully
functional version. The, I
want to like work on the other
new features that may be,
I think, is a little risky. So
I, I can branch from master
by right-click here.
And I will call my new branch
test because I don't have
better names.
So my current epository is set
to test. Now, it has the same
copy of code as the master.
Let's work on some
risky new features.
So that's to change the color
of the button. Maybe I
think blue is too ugly.
I want to change it to red.
And I commit this change.
Notice that because we
have a remote origin,
we can actually select
Push to remote. And
because the test branch only
lives locally in my machine,
actually Xcode can create
that remote origin test for
you. So
we can commit and push.
So in my current test branch,
I have this changed. But
my master branch
is not affected.
So, if you want to switch
back to the master,
you can right-click on
master and select Checkout.
Now my current branch
is master. And when
I go back to the storyboard,
the button is still blue.
Now say, you've fully tested
your code, and you're saying
that the button should be red
instead of blue in the master.
You can right-click here, and
then select Merge
test into master.
The version editor is like for
you to see whether this merge
is what you want.
Another thing is that,
because the storyboard is the
XML file, you would never want
to merge the same storyboard
with the other teammates.
You can work on different
storyboards, but
you would never like want
to merge the change in
the same storyboard, because
that's really, really painful.
Now we are at the master,
and we also have the Changed
button color here. And when
I go back to the storyboard,
The button is now red.
So we've successfully merged
the change. And
notice that our current
master is ahead
of the original master.
So another way to push to
the origin is to click
Source Control > Push.
Now all my notes are at
the same snapshot.
Another cool thing I
want to show you is that,
they make it really easy
if you want to inspect your
commits. Like I have
some commit for button.
It will show all the commit
message that should,
has button in it. And
you can also filter by author,
like author is junjie. And
you can also search last
24 hours, last 30 days.
It's really helpful if you
want to search your change.
So that's basically all for
our demo.
Do you have any questions? No,
okay, so that's it for today.
Thank you for coming, and
good luck on your assignments.
>> For more,
please visit us
at stanford.edu.