[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> All right welcome class,
everybody, to iPhone
section about instruments.
We're gonna learn today about
instruments which is a tool
that helps you with figuring
how to profile your code, and
profiling means a few
different things. So we'll get
started with a little bit of
background on what it means to
even profile code in the first
place cuz that may not be
something you've done before.
Even outside of Xcode in
general with your programming
career. So, I want you to
rewind back to kinda when
people were building OS' back
in the day and people had all
kinds of questions that they
wanted to ask about their code
as it was running in their OS.
And those questions would
range across things from like
the hard disk to main memory
to the CPU and just to try to
figure out like how the OS was
allocating various resources.
For the disk you might
ask something like, what,
what processes are asking for
a given resource right now and
which command requested that
resource from the OS so
you could figure out whether
there are some bug or
what was going on.
You might have a problem in
memory like there's a leak or
something like that and
you wanna figure out how you
can trace down that leak.
And then very importantly you
might wanna figure out how
long certain processes are
taking on the CPU compared to
other processes or how long a
process is taking in general.
Or, when it spikes to 100%
usage or something like
that so, these are all
really important questions.
But, in order to figure it
out, you'd have to go in and
manually write a bunch of
code, and that's not very fun.
So if somebody came along
around the early 2000s, and
said hey, there must
be a better way. And
so I believe at
Sun Microsystems,
they created this thing called
DTrace, which is a little
lightweight scripting language
that looks kind of like C, so
it fit right in with your
operating systems code.
And DTrace would do is like
you would place this little
things called probes which are
little of code inside your,
inside your bigger system.
And then they would trigger
output about how long it was
taking to run various things
and you could figure how
much memory was being used by
given resource and what not.
And what is great is really,
really expressive which meant
that you could do a lot of
different things with it,
by writing very little code
and you could deploy it to
production no problem because
when it was running in
production mode. It wouldn't
take any hit on the CPU, so
you can just leave
your code in there,
in the live production system.
So, that's a super great step
in the right direction, but I
had a little bit of a problem,
which is that,
for example here,
when you see this one that
compares process times,
you see this one in
the center here is,
is outputting a distributing
of processes as Atsy text. So
it's showing you these little
at signs to say that that,
that process in the center is
taking up half of the overall
time and the other ones
are taking up the rest,
it's not the best GUI. So
you end up with this non-ideal
situation where you kinda got
all this console of output and
we really didn't want that
with Apple when we were
creating, you know Xcode and
IOS because in most cases,
people who are using it
are maybe programming for
the first time. They've
never made apps before and
this is just something that
you don't wanna have to go and
deal with. So, This is kind
of the vision in my head
of DTrace, it's like this very
powerful machine that has way
too many knobs and, and
buttons to get
used to easily and
you have to kinda learn it up
front to be able to use it.
And the solution instead, is
to have something happier and
friendlier like our
friend Eve here,
or Eva,
I forget how you say it. And
the solution is called
Instruments, Instruments,
Instruments. And so what
Instruments is, is it's a GUI,
and it sits on top of DTrace,
that same little programming
language, scripting language
that we just talked about.
And it's built right into
Xcode and so it, it kinda
democratized this idea that
you could do CPU analysis or
memory analysis or
disc analysis and
things like these. And one of
the interesting differences
between instruments and using
something like DTrace is that.
Since it's a GUI we now
can't do all of these,
all of the D Trace tasks that
we would wanna do within one
single window because there're
just too many of them. So
what instruments does instead,
is it splits off
all of all of the thing that
you'd possibly wanna do with
an iOS app with profiling into
lots of different flavors.
So, you see that we have these
things like the activity
monitor, which is, you may be
used to from your actual OS,
which shows you how
much stuff different,
processes are taking up,
how many different resources.
And you might have this thing
called the time profiler,
which tells you how long
it takes for a given
CPU process to do a certain
task or something like that.
But, you can't have all of
them within one window, or
it would just be too much
clutter and too much stuff.
So, the way an instruments
works from a high level is,
you're gonna launch a specific
subpar, sub module like this.
And then you're going to
focus on only that for
the duration of your app, and
that way you get this nice
GUI, that's not cluttered up.
And in particular with these
instruments what we'll focus
on today are the ones that are
most useful for probably 95%
of the use cases that you'd
ever use instruments for
you'll be using these
four instruments.
So you'll notice that four of
them are blue because they
have more to do with CPU
stuff. And then two of them
are orange because they have
more to do with RAM stuff
with memory. So, we'll go
through these four today
starting with the two CPU ones
and then we'll end up talking
about memory stuff with
allocations and leaks. And
the one big takeaway
from today, that I want
you to have is that
instruments is not
some kind of like, nice to
have optional thing that
sometimes people go off and
use if they have a problem.
It's actually very critical,
even if you think you've
created your app properly and
you don't have any problems or
memory leaks or anything
like that. Going through and
profiling it before you deploy
a real production app and
making sure that it's using
memory properly and that it's
not taking too much CPU time
when it shouldn't be and
things like that
that really matters.
So, Instruments is
something that's
a necessary thing to learn if
you're trying to become a real
iOS programmer. So don't
consider this as like this
optional thing that you
may not need some day. So
we're gonna go into right
into a demo here and
we're gonna show a little app,
a little mobile app and it's
gonna have a few, few issues
with it that we're gonna track
down like little detectives
inside of Instruments and
it'll illustrate
how those four
flavors of Instruments work
that I was speaking about. So,
The first thing I'll do
is I'll run this app in
the most basic version of
Instruments and we'll kinda
just give you a little tour of
what this app is doing. And
the idea with Instruments
is that you go up to this
Product menu and
you click on Profile,
which you can access with Cmd
+ I. And then when you run
Profile it builds a version
of your app with certain
debugging stuff built in and
pops up in the same so
many flavors thing that I
showed you from earlier.
And then we'll select
the Activity Monitor,
which just as it says
monitor CPU memory disk and
network usage statistics for
processes and the file system.
So just general statistics
about stuff going
on on your system, and
in this case we click Choose.
This is the instruments GUI
that pops up that's gonna show
us all of our statistics.
And in order to run your app
while recording all of these
statistics, you click the
Record button. It's kind of
like using iTunes or something
but for debugging information,
and then we'll pop open
our simulator here. And
first thing I'll do is explain
what this app is just briefly,
the idea is that we're
number theorists here.
And we've got some big prime
number that you see right here
at the top, and we want to
figure out what its prime
factors are.
So since the number's so
big that's gonna take a lot
of CPU time to compute so
let's see what happens when we
try to compute it. And I also
have two options here for
how we're gonna factor this,
one is to do it
the main thread, and
the other one is to do it
on the background thread.
Now the first thing we'll
experience is what Paul talked
about in lecture this
week which is that when you do
things on the main thread, and
they're really CPU intensive,
you actually block the main
thread. So when we click on
this button here, We notice
that the UI is completely
blocked I can't click anywhere
else, because it's off
factoring this number,
figuring out the prime
factors on the main thread.
You'll also notice over here,
we have a list of all
of the processes running
on my machine right now.
Since we're in the simulator
this is my actual Mac Book all
of the processes and
the name of this app
as you can see up here
is instruments demo. So
one of the first things we can
do is instruments demo here is
taking up a lot of
the CPU time in fact,
Twice as much as the total
percentage, because it's off
finding the prime factors
of this large number. And
if we want we can even filter
to get rid of all the noise,
by typing in the name of the
process we want to inspect.
You'll also notice
that there's other
information displayed here
in the activity monitor
like the number of threads
that are currently running.
So since I have this. Forking
on a background thread options
down here at the bottom.
To solve this problem,
I'll go ahead and
click on this a few times,
fork up a bunch of threads.
And
you can see I hover over
here inside instruments for
seeing the number of threads
pop up. Now we have a bunch of
different threads all going
off in the background to try
to figure out these prime
factors all on their own.
And then they're gonna report
back when done. And we'll see
these number of threads
go down when they finish.
So this just kind of gives
you a general sense of what
instruments is like. The
activity monitor you can see,
doesn't give you superfine
grained information.
It kinda just gives you
the high level, like. You know
what the name of the process
is and how much CPU time and
the number of threads and the
memory, just basic stats, but
it doesn't allow you to
dig deeper. To do that,
you have to as I said earlier
you have to go back and
run instruments with
a different flavor,
so that you can inspect
that particular thing.
So, let's do that.
We'll stop this
here. And
you can actually save
off what's called the trace.
So the actual record of what
happened with that
run of instrument.
So you can maybe compare
across multiple runs. Or
do additional analysis later.
And we will
go back to profile. And the
next time we want to profile
on what's actually taking so
long to factor this prime
number? Maybe there's some way
we can optimize this algorithm
to make it faster for example
and we've looked at our code
a bunch. They aren't quite
sure what's going on.
Why is it taking so long to
factor this prime number?
And so we don't have a theory
we're not sure why but
we know figure on
the time profiler.
Maybe it will help us dig in
to exactly what's taken so
much time on the CPU. And like
of us more algorithmic insight
into what we're doing wrong,
with our, with our
factorization methods. So
we'll run the time profiler.
Okay, so here we are in
the time profiler, and
we can see we have this nice
graph at the top that says,
CPU usage, and
it's also showing
us how much usage in
the main thread, versus this
dispatch worker thread that's
running in the background and
these other threads. And like
earlier, we'll notice that
when we click do it on
the main thread, and we block
the UI here, we see that the
CP usage skyrockets. So you'll
got this long running process.
And if we wait long enough,
eventually we should see
the factorization complete.
And that CP usage should
drop back down to zero.
So this is the general idea
behind the time profiler.
Also at the bottom
while this is going on,
you'll see that we have this
sort of call trace here.
This call stack, which is
actually it's a tree of calls.
And it shows you what's going
on nested inside all of
this apps different threads.
So if you'll notice we're
done factoring here.
We've found all the prime
factors of this number. And
it took a 99% of the CPU time
within the main thread and
99.3 within the start method.
And then so on and so forth.
And so it's showing us the
percentage of total CPU time,
that's happening within
all this different stuff.
this is not a very fun process
to dig through all these
But obviously,
system methods right,
because we didn't even
write these methods.
We're just, we're just
curious about our code.
All we care about is
the app what I wrote.
Where is all the information
for that stuff? So
there's a nice set of options
down here inside this call
tree menu, so
if I click on this,
you'll notice there's already
this option checked by default
to separate things by thread
as we've seen up at the top.
But another thing we can do
is hide system libraries. So
the moment that we click,
hide system libraries, you'll
notice that it collapsed all
of that junk that we were just
look at into just the stuff
inside of our application.
So we see stuff inside of
our view controller for
example, like factor on mean
thread which is the method
that went off to do factoring
of this prime number on
the mean thread as opposed to
on the background thread. And
then inside of there,
there was part of it that
was taking a lot of time. So
we'll go dig into our methods
and we see this prime factors
method that we've written
apparently is taking up a lot
of time. And then there is
what some method in there
taking up a quarter of the
time that's testing a divisor.
So at some point we we we're
down to a part of the code
that seems more granular and
this is where the actual
problem is happening.
And we can actually go into
code level detail from
instruments by double
clicking on that method. So
the moment I click on that, or
thrown into our code base, and
we look at this, we have
on the right side here,
we have different percentages
of what lines were taking so
long to run. So if we're
looking at our algorithm here
for factoring prime numbers,
this is the overall function
that computes it.
We pass in some big integer,
and or a long long in this
case just because it's so
large and then we have
an enter function here
called test which is gonna
test a given divisor.
To see is that large number
divisible by this divisor? And
since that divisor can be
a divisor multiple times of of
a given number maybe,
you know,
the number 31 that actually is
2 times 31 times 31, right?
So we have this while loop
here which checks that same
number multiple times, and
then appends it to a result
array which is that thing that
we were outputting in the app
earlier. And then what we do
to figure out the overall
total set of prime factors
here in this algorithm is we
go from i b 2 up by ones
all the way up to N,
which is the number. So we're
checking every number from 2,
3, 4, 5, 6 all the way up
to this large number N.
And we're testing each of them
to see whether it's a divisor
of that number. And what our
instruments demo here is
saying is that 43.5%
of it is taken up,
I think this line
should actually
be referring to the line
immediately following it, so
the line that's actually doing
the stride. So just doing this
many iterations of a loop is
taking a lot of time. And
then inside of here, we're
doing, we're spending a lot of
time iterating on these loops.
So it's just as
if the total number of
loops that we're doing
is just too many. So that
might give us the insight.
Maybe we're just trying to
divide too many numbers,
right. Which of course we are,
because we're going all
the way from two to
the actual number and itself,
which is kind of crazy
if you think about it.
Because first off,
if we were to go over
n divided by 2, that's already
kind of crazy because we
already tried all the numbers
that were less than that.
So we would have found them
already by that point. And
if you think it a little
bit harder actually,
the more standard mathematical
way to solve this problem
would actually be to only
go up the square root of N.
You can think about that from
a math perspective with like
a proof by contradiction where
you you assume that if there
were some. Prime factor of
a number that were larger
than the square root of n
that that number in order for
it to be multiplied by another
number to reach that number
would need to be larger than
the square root of n which,
is a contradiction so
it doesn't make sense. So
anyway we have that already
typed down here for
you so. I will prove that
instruments has done it's task
correctly by, instead of
iterating over every number,
doing it by starting
with the divisor two,
because that's our
first prime number, and
testing two. And then
starting at the number three,
because only odd numbers can
be prime numbers after two.
And then going up to
the square root of n by 2, so
we're gonna try 3 5 7 all the
way up to the square root of n
which should be a much
smaller number.
And then when we go off and
we profile this.
We'll notice that,
when we click on factor
on the main thread
we're done immediately, yay.
So instruments did its job,
the time profiler's very
useful, and it can help you
find what's taking up
a lot of your CPU time,
it's about that simple. You
can bumble around in all these
other options inside here to
see what they afford you.
But the main ones are the ones
that I just showed you. So
let's switch gears for a
moment. I've shown you kind of
the two first instruments that
have to do with CPU time and
what we'll do instead is start
looking more into memory. So
processes. And
like I mentioned earlier, the
two that are most useful for
this are going to be
allocations and leaks. So
the simpler of the two
would be allocations.
We're just gonna see how much
memory is getting allocated at
various times in the program.
And we will hit Choose and
Run. We will go over to this
classroom section here. And
the first thing that we'll
notice about allocations,
which is showing us
the memory that's being used,
is that when we
go off to a new
view controller, the number,
the amount of memory being
used currently sky rockets up
because we have a stack of
navigation controllers.
We have the one that's still
allocated that's still on
the stack and
then we have this new one.
So we should see this go up.
And likewise, when we go back
we should see it go down
a little bit. And it does.
So that's great. As we go to
the classroom controller and
from it we see allocations
going up and down.
Sometimes if you have some
kind of bug in your app
you might have it that when
you go back from a view
controller. All of a sudden
you don't see the allocations
go down, which would be a bug.
So that's something that
you might wanna check for.
And what we'll do
here in this case is,
is explain what's going on in
this tab of the app. And then
we'll kind of look for, for
any possible errors. So when
we click this little button
here, we will show a hint. And
the hint is that Jack, this
friendly student here who is
an image we fetched
from online,
is asking what tips can we use
to speed up prime fact-finding
prime factors? Paul says, have
you considered the domain or
possible factors?
Maybe you're trying too many,
which is the exact bug that we
went and fixed earlier with
the time profiling so. We
noticed that when we clicked
on Show Hint, this really
skyrocketed up a lot because
here we are loading
an image into the app and
that contains a lot of data.
So
what we might do is just play
around with all the operations
we can do inside the app. And
just see what's going on here.
And we immediately
find something kind of
suspicious which is that every
time I click Show Hint, we see
our memory usage is going up,
but when we unclick it and
click it again, it doesn't go
back down. So that seems like
we've got some kind of problem
here, seems kinda strange.
Why would it be going up each
time you click Show Hint?
All that happens each time is
we display an image on the
screen, and then we put these
two labels on the screen.
So why would there not be
memory being, being freed?
In this case it's not like,
not like necessary that
we have a leak, but
we're just using too much
memory for some reason. And so
let's go off into
the code here. And
we're inside this
ClassroomViewController,
which I will kinda show how
it works at the high level.
It's pretty simple. We have
this UI switch, which is that
button at the top that appears
next to the show hint text.
And when we tap on it and it's
on, we fetch this hint. So
the idea is we're simulating
doing a number of requests and
getting this data back for
this particular
hint from online.
And then we're displaying
it on the screen and
otherwise we're going to null
out this stuff that existed.
So when we call fetch hint,
what we do is we
allocate this thing called
the factorization question,
which is this class down here
at the bottom. And we allocate
a factorization answer which
is this other class down here
at the bottom, which has
text for the answers.
So these two labels being
displayed at the bottom. And
then on the answer itself,
we give a handle back
to the question.
And then inside of
the question itself,
we also have an array, which
is trying to store references
off to all the answers for
that particular question.
In this case, there's just
one. But we can imagine a data
structure needing
many answers,
because we might have many
answers to a given question.
So that's what's
going on there.
And then we have this thing
called the askerImgUrl,
which is the, the image that's
gonna get displayed for
the person asking the current
question. And that is the URL
of some image from the web.
And so once we fetch the hint,
and we update the UI,
we go off and
we set off all the text on
those labels. We set that
the whole bottom section on
the screen should be mapped to
whether that's reach up the
top is enabled or disabled.
And then, if it has just
been turn on we go often and
fetch this image online.
So, that's what this code is
doing here and when we're
done way inside here and
may have the data from this
image, we're making image for
you. And we set it off
as an image with data,
like Paul did in lecture. And
then we set its contentMode,
and we add a subview. So every
time that the hintSwitch gets
turns on, we go off and fetch
the image from online, and
we add a subview to
the screen. So, of course,
we have a problem here,
which is that if you keep
adding successive subviews,
you are adding memory to
your app, repeatedly.
That's why we saw the blue
line going up and up and
up and up and up, right?
So that kinda tipped us off,
since it's going up and
up we should go look
inside the code and see if
there is any reason why we
would just be repeatedly
allocating memory without
ever freeing it. And
here is our answer right here,
its this highlighted
line of code. So it's
kind of how the allocation
still works, it's for kind of
generally figuring out where
memory is being allocated.
But it doesn't actually
go that much deeper into
figuring out did you leak
memory or anything like that.
So that's what the next and
final instrument that we're
going to show today is for,
which is the lease instrument.
So let's pop open
instruments again,
stop our previous run.
And we will click on the next
and final leaks tool.
And then we will head on over
to the classroom again and
we'll notice that at
the bottom here we have this
kind of like, periodic little
green check mark saying,
you have no memory leaks,
good job. So far for this,
one of the instrument's trees
we haven't detected any leaked
memory and you can see
it's still green and
that's great. So
what you might do in this case
is just go off through normal
use cases of your app and
just try things out and
see if you have any problems.
So we might, like, show this
hint, unshow this hint, and
the moment that we do that we
actually see that we already
have a red x here which means
that the leak checker has
detected we have a memory leak
somehow. That's no good. So
if we want to figure out more
details about what's going
on let's say that we go onto
one of these x's where it says
look there are twenty new
leaks. And we click on it and
wow look at all these
leaks that are happening,
and how could so many leaks
be happening within a single
simple application? But
it turns out that these leaks
are all happening very under
the hood like malic this malic
leak to this leak. So those
might be caused by one general
greater leak inside of our
app which is things like
question and answer which were
those classes that we created.
You can see them here inside
that view controller. So
these are the things that are
the root cause of these leaks.
But still looking at this
trace right here it's not
exactly obvious
why that leak happened. And so
we might want to go into
a little bit more detail,
and figure out, what the heck,
why, where is this thing
coming from and what's going
on here. And if you'll notice
up here on this tab, which
exists in all the instruments,
we can actually select the way
that we want it to display
this data. So right here we
just have this kind of big,
set of all the information,
but we can also do this thing
called cycles and routes,
inside the leak checker.
So when we go inside here,
we see that we have some
kind of MallocBlock
right here that is referencing
something else that was
referenced up here earlier.
And that there is overall some
circular reference of memory,
some circular dependency. And
so maybe when we're freeing
memory from one thing,
it's not actually freeing
everything because things
still have references to
things that don't exist in
memory. So we're actually
getting rid of all of our
references. And sometimes when
you run instruments it won't
actually symbolicate your, the
names of your code classes,
or objects in memory,
into the cycle checker,
and sometimes it will
properly do that. So,
if I run it again here We'll
start, we'll restart the app,
maybe we'll get
luckier this time. And
when we show a hint, And
then we unshow a hint.
We'll see that there's a leak
here. Oops, I guess we
have the same problem. So,
first lesson of instruments is
that sometimes in the leaks
checker you'll notice that it
doesn't actually symbolicate
this. In some use cases of
this you might see it show
that the questions arrayed
down here in the answers
array are up at the top and
that they have a circular
reference to each other.
It might actually show that if
it symbolicates the debugging
information. But you're not
guaranteed to have that. But
in any case, we know that
we have a cycle here.
So what we can do now is
go off knowing that we have
a memory cycle somehow, and
look at our code and go hm,
something about questions and
answers has a memory cycle.
And so I, you can see I have
these helpful comments here
after each line like the
factorization reference count
is 1. So
when we allocate when we
allocate a question to set off
to this instance variable,
which is the optional question
here, factorization question,
then there's also an answer.
We're making one here and
one here, which means
the reference count is one for
each of them because
these are classes,
which means they're reference
types, so they're allocated
with reference counting. And
then you see down here when we
set off the factorization
answers question property,
now factorization question has
a reference count of 2 because
we actually stored it off on
the answer. And then the same
thing is true for
setting off on the answers.
So in theory, it makes sense
we could have a cycle here
because we have the answer
referencing the question and
the question referencing
the answers. So
there is circularity going on.
And of course, we do because
we are never actually, when we
uncheck the hint switch up at
the top, that's this else case
right here, we're nilling
out the factorization answer
optional and
the question optional. But
the reference counts were two,
not one, because we internally
set references to each of
them off on each other. So
we never actually get the
reference counts down to zero,
which would cause them
to be fully deallocated,
which is why we have a memory
leak popping up due to what's
called a complex cycle. That's
what instruments was telling
us. So now our question
becomes, how on earth do we
solve this problem? And there
are lots of ways that we could
solve this problem. One of
the ways is we could say,
the problem has to do with
reference counts. What we
really need to do is get these
reference counts down to zero.
So manually we can go in
like it's 1995 and say
factorizationAnswer.question =
nil,
which will cause the reference
count to actually be zero.
And then that will cause the
reference count to hit zero.
And then it will get
deallocated properly. But
imagine if every time you ever
wrote a code that used classes
and allocated things on the
heap, you had to manually go
make sure your reference
counts were zero,
that would be really gross.
And it would be nice if
the programming language
itself gave you constructs to
avoid this problem in the
first place. And of course,
Swift does. It affords you
many. So the first and
simplest way that Paul has
gone over in lecture with
regard to closures is to use
this keyword called weak. So
if we store off the reference
to the question inside answer
as a weak variable, then it
doesn't actually increment
that reference count.
And there's actually no reason
that why when the answer
itself is set to nil,
it won't go down to zero and
get deallocated properly.
So all we really need to do
is add weak in order to get
the same behavior as manually
going off and
So that's a nice thing that
Swift provides you to solve
a reference counting
problem like that. But
there's one more way that
Swift gives you to solve this
problem up front in the very
first place. Which is to say,
you know, we have this
distinction between
classes and structs, reference
types and value types. And why
on earth are we using classes
here to increment reference
types when a struct would have
done just the same. This is,
there's no reason that this
needs to be a class. We don't
need a handle on it anywhere
else in the application.
We don't need a pointer to it.
We don't need to worry about
the fact that making many
of them is going to cause
way too much memory to happen
cuz they're just questions and
answers which are tiny amounts
of data. So what the heck?
Why are these classes in the
first place? All righty, so
since we've changed these two
structs now, we should have no
more reference kind of going
on anywhere with questions and
answers. Which means that
value typing has solved our
whole allocation leak
problem outright,
which is a great feature
of the Swift language
in the first place. So
that's actually kind of the,
the nuclear bomb and
great solution to,
to this problem which is
that you should just use,
you should use value types
when, when possible, and
when it makes sense to. If you
don't need a reference type,
then you should use
the value type. And
that's kind of the end of
the leaks demonstration here.
So as you can, as you can see,
we've been through these four
main types of instruments
here, the activity monitor,
the time profiler,
allocations, and leaks.
And you've gotten
a kind of taste
of how they work.
If you wanna go off and
learn how more of them work,
maybe you're going off,
you wanna figure out what's
going over the network.
You can learn more about the
Network tab on your own time,
or you're making some kind
of graphics application,
you might use these purple
colored ones, like scene kit,
or metal system trace,
or core animation.
So there's lots more that
you can do with instruments.
And it's very fun to
go off and use it.
So I encourage you to go off
and try all of them out and
figure out how you
can Introduce it
into your debugging process so
that you're not sitting there
really confused by your most
complex bugs. And instead,
you're going off and just
getting more data and figuring
out what's true and not true
about your application.
So that's it for the
instruments demo for today.
I hope this has been useful,
and we'll see you in class on
Monday.
>> For
more, please visit
us at stanford.edu.