[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Alrighty, well,
hi everybody.
My name is Jason.
I'm one of your two TAs.
Junjie is the other one.
She is not here today and
we are gonna go over today
kinda two different things.
One is just a whirlwind tour
of Xcode just to make your
life a lot simpler for
the entire quarter and
the rest of your life to make
it more familiar to you.
And the other thing is how to
use the debugger within Xcode
in particular.
than most sections just cuz
there's not that much material
to get through, so we'll
be out of here a bit early.
But um, there is also,
there is also no slides or
anything like that,
there is no lecture to give,
it's just I'm gonna hop
right into the demo.
And feel free to stop me
at any point, just shout,
raise your hand if something
is not clear if you wanna,
you wanna learn more about
something or whatever, and
I'll stop to do that.
I know we're going through
a giant list of key commands.
It's not like the most
engaging lecture, so
I'll try to be as
engaging as possible, but
uh, it is actually
super useful.
So if, if I want you to have
like one take away from,
from this whole talk, it's
that, if you wanna get good at
using Xcode and you wanna feel
fluent when you're using it,
you actually need to know
a lot of key commands.
It will really help you a lot.
Xcode from Paul in lectures
but actually learning all the
shortcuts for everything will
make your life way simpler.
And I hope I can kinda
convince you today that all
this stuff is actually
pretty intuitive.
It's not just like memorizing
a bunch of random things, but
it's all laid out by Apple
in a very nice and, and
orderly way.
So let's just dive right in.
I'm gonna pop up an Xcode here
and I have Concentration open,
which is the end of
Wednesday's lecture,
we had this code working.
The catch here though is that
this version of Concentration
that I'm using right now, I've
deemed it sad Concentration.
You can see right
here on this folder,
we're gonna investigate
that using the debugger.
But before we do that,
I am gonna hop in and
give you a tour of Xcode using
key commands and what not.
So you remember things from
lecture where you've seen for
example, you can navigate
around all the panes
by clicking these various
buttons, but it's gonna
get really old really
fast when you're coding.
If you're also
You can get like five
times faster if you just
learn how things are laid
out in some various things.
So the first thing,
I'll just kinda go,
go through Xcode in order,
kinda from the top left.
The first thing is, all this
stuff up here at the top left,
you can actually do
automated by key commands.
So instead of going up and
clicking Run and what not,
you can do Cmd+R,
and that will run.
So there,
there are key commands for
controlling everything about
running and, and stopping and
all that stuff.
Um, the next thing I wanna
talk about is more important
which is just how you actually
navigate around all of Xcode.
And so there are key commands
for doing things like, if you
watch the screen right now,
I can do this, this, this.
You get really fast
at this stuff.
We're, were opening up
a second editor right now.
Right, so
how you can like quickly
get your way around Xcode.
So when I close everything
that I just did.
Suppose that were at a full
main screen like this,
the way that everything is
laid out is very logical,
where the left-most pane,
which is called the Navigator,
is controlled by Cmd+0.
That's what shows it.
And then the right-most pane
is showed using Cmd+Option+0.
That's what shows and
hides the op, right-most pane.
And then within each pane,
so if I'm on the left pane,
if I do Cmd+1,2,3,4,5 you see
how up on the top left here
we're going through
these tabs?
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, right?
And then if I do Cmd+Option+0,
and
I look at these tabs up here,
I just do Cmd+Option+1, 2 and
I can go through
all those tabs.
So it's actually pretty
nicely laid out like that.
You just remember that, Cmd+0
is for showing and hiding and
then the numbers are for
tabbing.
And then if you add in Option,
it does the right side.
So it's pretty simple.
If you just do Cmd+Shift+y,
it toggles the console and
the debugger at the bottom
which we'll be working with
more later today.
And those commands alone are
enough to just kind of like
constantly manage
your window size,
especially if you're
programming on a laptop where
you only have like limited
screen real estate.
It's actually really nice to
be able to use those commands
to quickly navigate around.
The next thing I'll point out
is that, you know from lecture
that Xcode has uh,
two different editors.
It has the um, the main editor
that we' re in right here, and
it has also this thing
called the assistant editor.
So if we do
a Cmd+Option+Enter.
It pops up in this second
pane over here, and
then we can do Cmd+Enter to
go back to just one pane, so
this is super useful.
The one thing that I'll point
out about this is that,
if you go to your,
your Xcode preferences window,
we have all these things that
we can, that we can toggle and
we won't go through all
You can go around and
change your font colors and
all that good stuff.
recommend that you utilize,
which is in Navigation here.
There's this little check box
that says, Navigation uses
the primary editor, versus
using the focused editor, and
by default, this is set to
using the primary editor.
And that's going to probably
torture you if you use certain
other key commands.
Let me give you an example.
One of the key commands is for
opening certain files without
having to navigate
there in the,
in the file
navigator over here.
So let's say that I,
we all know that there's
a file called Card.swift and
we wanna open it, all I
have to do is Cmd+Shift+O for
open, type card, and
then there's Card.swift,
and that will open it up.
Now what if I wanted
So right here,
I am zooming around in the,
in the right pane and I have
the right pane selected.
If I do Cmd+Shift+O and
I go back to ViewController,
it still opens in
the left pane.
So if you don't have this use
focused editor option selected
it's always going to
use the left editor or
the prime editor for
those key commands.
So that's why you wanna have
this box checked, so that now
when we go over here and
we have the right one selected
and we do card, it opens
it over on the right pan.
Makes sense?
Cool, so I highly
recommend that you do that.
Okay, the next thing,
we're gonna do is actually
talk about text editing within
each window really briefly.
One thing that I wanna point
out is, you haven't dealt with
this problem yet because your
Xcode projects haven't gotten
very large, but
they will get very large.
There will be lots
of code files and
eventually you'll have
hundreds of files in a single
project when you're making
a big Xcode project.
And one of the things that
will help you navigate that is
to help yourself by
leaving Navigation,
like Navigation helper things
throughout your files and
one way to do that is this
comment right here that is
prefixed with comment mark.
excuse me.
below this line.
this notification in
this window up here.
That's where card
touch behavior is and
it will jump to that
point of the file.
And so you can imagine in big
files, using these marks is
actually super helpful
when they're really long,
something to navigate around.
The next thing that I'll point
out about text editing is,
it's very useful just to know
basic text editing commands.
Like for example, if you
have many lines selected and
you want to comment them
out all of a sudden,
just Cmd+/ will comment
things out like that and
then Cmd+/ again
will undo them.
Another maybe even more useful
thing is when you get yourself
into a,
a nasty state like this.
Just mess some stuff up for
no reason.
And you can tell that it's
really not formatted.
We can select everything
that we want and
do Ctrl+I, I for
indent and it will just
magically put everything
exactly like we wanted.
So that'll save you a lot
of time and headache,
if things are not, if you,
if you can't tell things that
are nicely indented or not.
And I'll list these all
online on Piazza by the way,
so it's not like you need
to know down what they are.
I just kinda want
to give you the,
give you the lay
of the land here.
So hopefully we're through
the, the fast sorta boring
part of the lecture where it's
just all of the key commands.
But I highly recommend that
you learn all this stuff and
start getting it into
your muscle memory so
that when you're
navigating on Xcode,
you're not torturing yourself
for having to click around
everywhere and
do everything manually.
The next thing to do is
to actually start using
the debugger.
we're not actually using
the version of concentration
directly from the end
of Wednesday's lecture.
We're actually using a
slightly broken version of it,
and so let's see what happens
when we actually run this one.
I'm gonna run it on
the iPhone X simulator using
our trusty Cmd+R key command,
and let's see what happens.
So I've crashed, it doesn't
even work right from
the start, and we're thrown
to the app delegate,
which is the main file.
It's crashing on the main
method it says, but
that's not very helpful.
So the way that we first
get more insight into this,
is to look into
the actual stack trace,
which shows up in
the console log down here.
And you just see this
huge stack trace,
which goes all the way
into the internals of iOS,
all the way down
through UI kit,
and core foundation,
and all this stuff, and
it's not very helpful to see
all these memory addresses.
But if you scroll up to the
top in almost every case you
will see what
the actual reason for
terminating the app was.
And in this case it tells
us that there's an uncaught
exception called
UnknownKeyException,
which we may might not
know what that is.
It tells us that the reason
for the crash was, oops,
sorry.
The reason for
so it already tells us what
file something is happening
in, has some error on
setValue:forUndefinedKey.
Unclear exactly what that is,
cuz we didn't write that
method, and then this class is
not key value coding-compliant
for the key flipCountLabel.
So that gives us even more
insight, is something is wrong
with flipCountLabel, and so
if we go into view controller,
and we go check out
flipCountLabel,
we actually see flipCountLabel
abbreviated to LBL here,
which is not what it
says in the debugger.
Can anyone figure out what's
actually going on here?
How does it know to print
out flipCountLabel?
Any ideas?
If we've named
it flipCountLbl,
then why is it printing
out flipCountLabel?
Can anyone think of why?
No?
Yeah, in the back.
Yeah, exactly.
So that's what I named it.
What he said was,
So if we go over to
the storyboard over here,
actually let's just open up
both side-by-side using all of
our happy new key commands.
So we got the storyboard
open over here.
I'm gonna make this
fullscreen for a moment,
cuz it's easier to
see what's going on.
If we look inside here,
Now this right here,
that I've selected,
is not actually the official
name of the object.
If I open up our assistant
editor over here, and
I go over to the view
controller, and
I look at its rightmost pane,
this is where we see all of
the things that
we've connected, and
on the storyboard what they're
actually connected to.
Here's where you see
that we have this outlet.
The name of the outlet is
Flip Count Label, and it's
connected to flipCountLabel,
but if you zoom in here,
you'll notice that there's
a little exclamation point or
an empty thing,
as compared to the normal dot.
So that's it telling you that
this thing actually can't
find what it's
actually connected to.
So if we go back over
into our View Controller,
in this editor, and
And then we go back to
the storyboard editor,
we should see that, that
error is no longer there, and
we actually have
Flip Count Label connected.
So this is a bug that you'll
probably see often at first,
as you're not quite, I mean,
it's just hard to keep your
storyboard in sync with
your code sometimes.
So just know that there's this
error about key value coding
compliance and
that's what it means.
That you should go
check this right most
pane with your
View Controller selected, and
that will help you get
rid of these errors.
Cool, so
we're gonna save that, and
then we're gonna run it.
Okay great, so
it's actually running now.
So if you click around
to play the game.
Oops, it crashed, and so if I
look down inside the console
here, I don't actually
have any logs.
It didn't actually show me in
the console why it crashed.
In fact,
I have no info anywhere.
Let's try and run it again and
see if we can figure out
what causes it to crash.
It looked like that
time it crashed when
I clicked on a card.
Okay, that time, it let me
click on one of the cards, but
it still crashed, so
let's try it again.
Let's see if we can figure
out some sort of pattern for
what's going on.
That time it crashed
after four cards.
So does anyone have an idea
for how we can actually start
figuring out how
to debug this?
Like how on Earth are we
It seems to be crashing
randomly after some number
of cards, and
Anyone have an idea?
Even if you think it's silly,
just say something.
Say one way we can do this.
Print statements?
Yeah, print statements.
frustrating if you were in
a really big app though.
But you already see
the problem with print
statements is, if we're
gonna use print statements,
what the heck are we gonna do,
go inside every method, and
type print at every
point in the method,
and figure out where,
and what's going on?
We have to inspect
our entire app,
imagine we had like a 100,000
lines of code that'd be really
frustrating.
think about when the actual
app is crashing.
At what point is it crashing?
When you flip a card.
When I flip a card.
Can you use a break
point somewhere?
Bingo, so you say,
just using a break point,
because it's definitely
crashing when we flip a card.
So that's a new idea.
inside that method.
And then that will help
us hopefully figure out,
when the crashing happens
we'll be able to step through,
and hopefully figure
out what's going on.
So the way break
points work in Xcode,
and if you haven't used break
points before it's a way
for your debugger to pause
execution of your program on
a certain line of code.
So if we go inside
the touchCard method,
which is we know,
the first thing that
happens directly when
we click on a card.
We can click over here on the
left pane on the line of code,
and it pops up this
little blue arrow, and
that's what a break point is.
And that instructs the
debugger to please stop there
when we get there.
in the left down here, and
you can see that it has this
little blue arrow that looks
just like this one, and
when I click on it
it turns into grey,
which means break
points are disabled.
All break points in the entire
program are disabled, so
if you want break points to be
enabled you have to activate
them this way.
There's also a pane, up inside
the navigator over here,
that looks the same way, and
it'll show you a list of all
your break points throughout
your entire Xcode project.
So, you can also go
up here to this pane.
do with break points
than just this.
You can also go to this little
plus at the bottom left of
this pane, and you can set
certain special break points.
So for example, there's one
called an exception break
point, so if I add that,
what this does is,
anytime an exception
is thrown,
if you throw an exception
in your app,
instead of just throwing the
exception to the console, or
crashing, or what not, it'll
actually always, by default,
open the debugger and
pause on that line of code.
So if you just always
have this all exceptions
break point running
that will actually help
you in your developing for
example, so
you can actually customize
break points here that way.
You can also disable
individual break points from
this pane.
the one that we just
set right here, but
this one that I just mentioned
about exceptions causing
break points to happen,
this one is disabled.
So you can selectively
go enable and
disable break points all
across every file off on this
one pane, which is nice.
But oftentimes all
that you need to do,
I'm gonna disable
the exceptions one.
Oftentimes all that you need
to do is actually within
an individual file, set the
break point in that one file.
So okay if we run
the program now.
When I click on a card we'll
see that what happens is we
end up on this line of code.
So the program is paused at
this line where we're
setting off the card number.
And the first thing to point
out is that you'll notice
in the debugger itself we
actually have a trace of
everything that's stored off
in memory at this point.
So self would refer to the
view controller in this case.
And you can see if I zoom in,
you can see
that it says concentration
view controller and
this is the memory address
of the view controller, but
it not only gives you that,
it gives you a drop down menu
with all of the things that
are instance variables
stored off on that
instance of that class.
So things like we have the
instance of the actual game
of concentration and that has
lots of properties itself.
If it has the array of cards
and then it also has that
variable index of the one and
only face up card, and we can
expand cards and we can look
into each card and then we can
find out that the identifier
for that card is five.
So you can actually see all of
the things that are stored off
right here,
inside of the debugger, so
that's super nice, and we can
do that, use that to confirm
something like maybe we
want to make sure that.
The identifiers that we've set
actually have an equal
number of pairs of options.
So, if we go through,we
see that the first one is
identifier five, the second
one has identifier three,
third one has four.
Four, okay great,
here's a pair.
We shouldn't see another four,
right?
There's a one and
we should see,
we should see one through six,
correct?
And we should see
each one twice, so
anyway, that'll be like a way
to figure that out quickly
without having go manually and
print everything out.
Another thing that we can do
at any given point is over
inside the console, LLDB,
stands for your debugger,
the DB part stands for
debugger.
We can actually print out any
object that we want to be able
to inspect it.
So if I do a PO,
Give it a moment.
And you notice it prints out
this optional concentration,
because concentration
is of type optional.
In this case, it's what's
called an implicitly
unwrapped optional.
In other words, it's not nil.
The other value in the enum
for an optional is sum.
So we know that
concentration is set here.
Another thing we can do is
actually we can print out by
just typing p for print so
it just works magic
abilities to figure how to
format the thing that we need
to print out in the way they
think is the best readable.
So if I print out game,
prints out cards, all twelve
values and then all the info
that we were just looking
at inside the debugger.
But it does it all there
formatted very nicely.
And then we know that
index of one and
only face up card is nil so
We can also do that for
any other object.
So I print out flipCountLabel,
it prints out that its
a UI label optional.
It's a UI view,
which has a UI responder.
And anyway the point is p is
very nice it's very helpful
for printing anything
out whatsoever.
So, I'm back to our actual
bug, at this point.
We have this problem we're
clicking on, we click
on a card and we're stopped
at this break point and
we wanna figure out why
this thing is crashing.
So the first thing
that we might do
to figure out what line we're
crashing on in this case,
since we're not getting
an exception and
we have no idea what's going
on, is we might go use these
navigation options inside
the actual debugger here.
So if you look in right here,
we have a few different
options right here.
One of them is continue
program execution and
what that means is okay we're
paused at a break point.
Just continue running the
program until we hit the next
break point, or
if there are no breakpoints,
just continue
running the program.
So let's try that right now,
let's click, let's click
on continue running.
Okay, in this case
we didn't crash,
that time that we
tapped on touch card,
so it's just continuing
the program.
We're not on a break point
right now, so we click again.
Okay, we're back at
the same break point, and
we can continue again.
Oh, and that time
the program crashed, and
we're not sure
what's going on.
But we know that it definitely
happened right after
this first line of touchCard.
So let's see how we can go
into a little bit more detail.
>> Okay, so
we click on the card again.
Rather than continuing
the execution, instead,
we can pick the second option
here which is step over.
Oops, saw the little
help dialog pop up for
a second there.
I wanna get that pop
up on the screen.
So you can step over
an instruction.
Let's maybe do the next
line of code and
we can keep going like this
hoping that this is the time
where the crush
actually happens.
And it's not, unfortunately.
So actually it doesn't
help us with our problem.
Does anyone have
any other ideas?
How do you think we can
go further to figure
out what the problem
actually is?
Take a look at, take a look
at this method here.
Well actually,
it didn't crash that time,
so that was kind
of a bad exercise.
But I'm just saying,
in general,
once we hit the time that it
does crash, what's something
else that we could do
to actually go further?
Any ideas?
>> Set a break point.
>> There we go.
So she just,
inside concentration.
we're also calling other
methods inside of touchCard.
And then there's another
method after that.
There's also
updateViewFromModel,
so actually,
Which means, it can be
crashing anywhere inside
the chooseCard, or any where
inside updateViewFromModel.
So one thing that we could
do is we could go to
both of these methods
like updateViewFromModel,
and we can set
a break point there.
And then we could pop open a,
let's pop open card over here,
and we'll go to chooseCard,
oh excuse me
we're go to concentration over
here and we'll put a break
point inside choose card and
now we have three different
break points set as you can
see in the break point pane.
And that'll make it stop at
all the places where it could
possibly be at the start
of the method.
But another, I'm not gonna do
that right now, another way of
doing that actually is to use
the The next option inside
the debugger pane.
So if you click on something
Let me get back to
one window here.
Once we get to a method,
Like chooseCard,
we can see this next option
here is step into and
that's how we get inside
the actual method, so
if I click step into, now we
are at the top of chooseCard.
And now if we want we can
step over each line inside of
chooseCard.
And we can inspect
the code if we want,
we can read it to make
sure everything's okay.
We could put extra break
points inside here if we see
something that might
be suspicious.
Notice that if we're
inside a four loop,
that's a lot of iterations,
it would take forever to
step over the whole time.
So you can get yourself
in trouble real fast
if you're stepping
into methods that
have a lot of
behavior going on.
But that aren't relevant to
actually what's going on.
But you get the idea.
So let's continue,
Let's, this time let's step
inside updateViewFromModel.
So that's the method that's
right beneath this one.
And let's step over this.
We're gonna go through all the
indices inside cardButtons,
which is kind of a pain
because we have to go
through this big for loop and
see if anyone sees anything
suspicious in this method.
Just point it out,
point it out if you see it.
If something weird
is going on.
Anybody?
It's the world's worst
line of code of all time.
What is this?
Who put this here?
it's information this way
to exit your app, right?
So we're just actually
exiting with negative 1.
It turns out we're exiting a
flipCount, which that thing we
keep in track of at the bottom
of that is greater than some
random number that's
generated between this.
What the heck?
This line couldn't just make
any sense, right?
debugger because it's like
it's giving us no information
in the console so
Anyway, so obviously this is
the problem, if we get rid
of this completely
pointless in same line of
code that I put in there,
then we run the program again
We're gonna stop at that
break point, so maybe we'll,
we'll disable it this time,
cuz we're not sure if we
fixed all of the problems.
So we'll keep that break
point there just in case, but
we'll disable it and
hit continue.
And then we'll try to
play concentration,
See if anything
strange is going on.
It actually seems like it's
working more this time.
Also, I'm not actually
playing right now.
I promise I'm not this
bad at this game.
But it looks like we
fixed the problem.
And we know we have fixed one
problem because there's not
an exit in our code which
is kinda ridiculous.
Are there any questions about
using the actual debugger?
Are you done here?
Everyone understand kind
of the general idea?
It's actually pretty simple,
for
navigating around
the memory hierarchy and
then using these commands
to step through your code.
That's all make sense?
Okay cool, one thing I
wanna show you is that
the debugger is not quite as
simple as everything that just
appears the pane right here.
It turns out that there's
something inside of Xcode's
preferences called behaviors,
and this is an Xcode
wide thing, it's actually
really useful and cool.
And what behaviors is for
various parts of running your
app, and
actually gives you the ability
to make custom configurations
for when certain events occur.
You can say if this
thing happens,
then do this thing to x code.
So for example, right now
when we pause inside,
when the app is running,
whenever we pause,
we have this option here that
says, show the navigator.
We have that checked.
So if we change this to hide,
for example,
then when the app pauses,
watch what happens.
So you're gonna
touch on the card.
Did you notice that
the navigator pane on the left
disappeared when
that happened?
So that's interesting.
we're debugging, we might want
Xcode to just, by default,
just go to a certain state cuz
we don't know whenever we're
running the app what state our
Xcode is currently in, but
we know that when we're
debugging we want it to be
in particular state.
So you can actually go
customize all that stuff
inside behaviors.
In the interests of time and
sanity, I won't go through
every single little option,
like we could play
a sound when certain
things happen or whatever.
You can actually go through
the Behaviors pane and
kinda check and see everything
that it can do for you.
So it's actually
pretty useful.
Any questions about behaviors?
Does that make sense?
Okay, great.
a little bit about what
actually the Xcode file itself
contains, because it's kind of
opaqued people the first time
they have used Xcode.
So this is your
actual project file.
It has all these different
tabs inside of it, and
there's just a lot
going on inside here.
In general, I am not going to
go through every little point,
but in general, what I would
encourage you to do is
understand the difference
between build settings and
what goes on inside of build
settings, and build phases,
and what that means.
like figure out what version
of our programming language
that we're running with.
That's something
that's going to go
into your build settings.
So we can either scroll down
and look for that option like,
here we find Swift language
version set to Swift 4.0 or
you can actually use this
handy thing coz this menu
can get kind of large, and
type something like language,
and then, okay, great.
I was just filtering to
just Swift language.
So I would encourage you to
go through build settings,
and just see what things that
there are to change and what
not, and you'll see this, can
get actually kind of large,
the more complex your
Xcode product is.
Both phases is
separate from that.
And the thing that I would
point you towards here is,
this is where you see
all the source files
that are used inside your app.
Then there's the second
section called link
binary with libraries.
So that's if you wanna
actually add a library
to use to your project which
we are gonna get into later
in this quarter.
besides just putting
a label or a button or
any of the stuff that
comes stock in UI kit.
Say that we wanted to put like
a map because we are making
an app like map something
like that what we will do is
add a new library to our
app and type in map, and
we find this thing called map
kit, and then you type add and
that's where all you're adding
for frameworks happens.
And then we see it created
this new Frameworks folder
over here,
it has a MapKit inside of it.
And now we can go inside any
file, like ViewController.
We can go to the top of that
file and say import MapKit and
it's there.
Make sense?
the Xcode file for now.
The one caveat I'll talk
about with the Xcode file is
if you're using Git or
any kind of source control,
you will actually be
committing the Xcode project
file itself to the repository
and imagine that you're
working on source control
with other people online.
If two different people have
a merged conflict within
the actual Xcode
project file itself,
that's just a big file that
stores off a bunch of data by
your Xcode project, that can
be kind of nasty to learn how
to merge those conflicts.
So that means,
code it might be worth looking
up online ways to help manage
the Xcode project file itself
inside source control.
Cuz it's not as simple as
doing source control inside
an actual code file.
project file that you'll wanna
learn about what it actually
looks like internally.
So that's all that
I have planned for
today does anyone
have any questions or
anything that we went over.
Does all make sense?
key commands in the debugger,
yeah sure.
>> Is it possible to do some
sort of version control?
>> Or right sure, so
So I was just sort of alluding
to that when I was talking
about the Xcode
project file itself.
The answer is yes,
you can use source control.
Most people, pretty much
everybody these days uses GIT.
So highly recommend
you go learn GIT.
If you dont know GIT,
you can go online and quickly,
I would recommend, there's
something called PRO GIT.
And that's a free book
that you can learn online.
Learn from online.
Okay, great, so here's
this book called Pro Git.
And if you haven't
used Git before,
I highly recommend that
you don't just go off and
try to use Git.
I highly recommend
that you go off and
you read something
like Pro Git first.
So that you actually learn
what's going on with Git and
how it represents source
control under the hood.
It'll really help you because
one of the big pain points for
people, when they are first
learning source control is you
learn a few commands for
how to commit code online and
how to send it
to other people.
But then, when you run into
a problem, of some sort, and
you don't know how to
undo that problem,
It's really hard to figure out
what's going on if you don't
know how to Git
actually stores things.
So it's really necessary
to go through and
read something like this book
to understand how Git works.
And then if you don't
have a GitHub account,
go to github.com and
immediately create
an account and
start creating your repository
and learning all the commands
that are better explained
to you inside this book.
I highly recommend that.
in particular,
So I'll do file, new project,
I'll create a single view
app,I'll call it test, And
then you'll see that when I'm
actually creating the project,
I'll put in my desktop here.
It actually has a source
control option for
creating a Git repository.
So actually, when you check
this it'll, it'll put your
project with a .git file
in the actual directory.
And then you can push
that online to GitHub.
So it'll do that
automatically so
you don't need to
do it manually.
Any other questions?
No.
talk to me afterwards.
Thank you all.
>> For more please visit
us at stanford.edu.